埃莉诺小姐的斗篷

大约在一百二十年前，舒特上校就任马萨诸塞湾政府总督之后不久，一位既有地位又很富有的年轻小姐从英格兰来到此地，要求他做她的保护人。他只是她的远亲，但又是她渐趋灭绝的家族中尚在人世的最近亲属；因此，对于富有而出身高贵的埃莉诺·罗彻克利夫小姐来说，再也找不到比大西洋彼岸殖民地这个行省的政府更适宜的庇护所了。此外，舒特总督的夫人自埃莉诺小姐幼小时起对她就像母亲一样，如今也正急切地想要接纳她，希望美丽年轻的小姐生活在新英格兰的纯朴社会里，不会像置身于宫廷的阴谋诡计和腐化堕落中那么危险。假如总督或者他的夫人对他们自己的舒适安乐加以特别考虑的话，大概会想办法将这份责任推到别人手里去；因为埃莉诺小姐尽管具有某些高贵而杰出的品德，却以粗暴苛刻和孤高自傲而著称，自恃血统与个人的优越而目空一切，这使得她行事几乎肆无忌惮。根据许多逸闻传言来判断，她这种怪僻性格差不多达到了偏执狂的程度；或者说，假如她的性格所导致的种种行为出自一个心智健全者，那么如此罪孽深重的骄傲按照天意是该招致严酷报应的。许许多多半被遗忘的传说故事就笼罩着这种奇异色彩，而埃莉诺·罗彻克利夫的怪异故事大概也是因此而平添了几分疯狂的野性。

埃莉诺小姐搭乘的船抵达了新港，她再从那里坐总督的马车到波士顿，沿途有一小队骑马的绅士护送。笨重的车身由四匹黑马拉着，隆隆驶过康希尔时十分引人注目，前后簇拥着五六个骑士，胯下的骏马昂首阔步；刀剑在马镫上摇晃，手枪插在皮套子里。队伍奔驶而过的时候，人们能够透过车厢宽大的玻璃窗看见埃莉诺小姐的身影，在她身上妙龄女子的优雅美丽竟与女王般的庄严高贵奇妙地融为一体。一种古怪谣言已经在当地上层妇女中间传开来，说是她们的这位漂亮对手那种无法抵御的魅力大大得益于一件服装——一件绣花斗篷——它出自伦敦最高明的艺匠之手，具有增添美色的魔力。不过，现在她的魅力却丝毫没有借助于这件斗篷的魔法，她身上穿的是一件天鹅绒骑装，别的任何人穿上都只会显得既呆板又粗俗。

车夫勒住他的四匹黑马，整支队伍停在了州府门前，有一道弯曲铁条做成的栏杆把州府和公用街道隔开来。这时发生了一件令人尴尬的事，老南方教堂的钟声正好敲响了一场葬礼的丧钟；结果，埃莉诺小姐没有受到按惯例宣告贵宾到来的喜庆钟声的迎接，却被一阵哀伤的当啷声所导引，仿佛灾难就蕴藏在她那娇美的身影中。

“这是大大的失敬！”兰福德上尉叫道，他是一位英国军官，新近给舒特总督送来了公文急件。“葬礼应该推迟举行才是，免得埃莉诺小姐被这种倒霉的迎接方式弄得心情不快。”

“请原谅，先生。”克拉克博士回答说，他是一位医生，也是民众拥戴的著名斗士。“不论预兆是什么，一个死去的乞丐应该优先于一个活着的女王。死亡之神赐予了至高无上的特权。”

他们一边交谈，一边等着人群让出一条路；州府门前每个方向上都聚满了人，只留出一条通向州府门厅的通道。一个穿着号衣的黑奴从马车背后跳出来，打开了车门；与此同时，舒特总督走下了府邸的台阶，准备扶埃莉诺小姐下车。然而总督庄严的进程却被人抢了先，弄得所有的人都目瞪口呆。有一个面色苍白的年轻人，满头黑发蓬乱不堪，竟然从人堆中冲出来，匍匐在马车旁边，把自己的身体奉献给埃莉诺·罗彻克利夫小姐做下车的踏脚凳。她踌躇了片刻，不过那表情仿佛在疑惑这个年轻人是否配承负她脚步的重量，而并非是不愿意接受一个同类如此可怕的敬意。

“起来，先生。”总督厉声喝道，对着这个莽撞之徒举起了他的手杖，“这狂徒疯疯癫癫的想干什么？”

“不，”埃莉诺小姐调皮地回答说，不过在她的语气中嘲讽多于怜悯，“阁下不要打他。既然有人只想自讨践踏，不给他这种举足之劳的恩惠就太可惜了——况且他也受之无愧呀！”

接着，她就一脚踏上了那个瑟瑟战抖的身体，尽管脚步轻盈得像一道阳光照射在云朵上，同时伸出手来握住了总督的手。埃莉诺小姐保持着这种姿态的时间只有短短一瞬，然而确凿无疑，贵族与世袭骄傲对于人类同情心和天然亲情的践踏，再找不到比这两个人此刻的形象更加适宜的象征了。可是围观者如此为她的美丽所倾倒，而且骄傲对于这样的美人又是如此必不可少，所以他们同时发出了一片热烈的喝彩声。

“这个莽撞无礼的年轻人是谁？”兰福德上尉问道，他这时仍然站在克拉克医生旁边。“要是他神志正常，这么鲁莽就该挨一顿棍子打脚底。如果他是个疯子，就该关起来，免得埃莉诺小姐再遇到麻烦。”

“他叫杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯，”克拉克医生回答说，“一个没有门第和财富，也没有其他优势的年轻人，只有大自然赋予他的头脑和灵魂；他是我们殖民地派驻伦敦代办的秘书，不幸遇见了这位埃莉诺·罗彻克利夫小姐。他爱上了她——她的轻蔑弄得他疯疯癫癫。”

“这么异想天开真是疯了。”英国军官评论道。

“也许是如此。”克拉克医生说，一边皱起了眉头，“不过我告诉你，先生，要是这位趾高气扬地跨进那边府第的小姐不蒙羞受辱的话，我简直要怀疑上天还有没有正义了。她竟然将自己凌驾于人类与生俱来的共有怜悯天性之上。等着瞧吧，看天道会不会以某种方式对她进行惩罚，把她拉到与最卑贱者同等的地位！”

“绝不会！”兰福德上尉愤慨地喊道——“不论她活着还是与祖先同眠，都绝对不会！”

过后没有几天，总督为欢迎埃莉诺·罗彻克利夫小姐而举行舞会。殖民地的首要士绅都受到了邀请，无论远近都是由骑马的信使将请柬送上门，请柬上带有与正式官方公文快件一样的信函封印。大家应邀而至，拥有地位、财富和美貌的来宾济济一堂；州府的大门很少接纳过像埃莉诺小姐的舞会这么众多和显贵的来宾。无须堆砌溢美之词，整个场面可以称之为“壮丽辉煌”；因为依照当年时尚，女士们浑身绫罗绸缎，光彩照人，裙环撑得长裙下摆远远展开；男士们的上衣和马甲都是紫色、猩红色或者天蓝色的天鹅绒，缀着重重叠叠的金钱刺绣，闪闪发光。一套服装中马甲是至关重要的，因为它把一个人包装到接近膝盖，上面绣满了金色的鲜花和叶簇，或许会耗费掉主人整整一年的进项。如今人们的品味已经有所改变——这种品味象征着整个社会制度的深刻变化——所以今天会认为这些豪华艳丽的装束无不滑稽可笑；可是那天晚上客人们都在拼命寻找自己在大穿衣镜里的影像，瞥见自己在闪闪发光的人群中闪闪发光就欣喜若狂。这些贵重的大镜子没有一块保留下了当时场景的一个画面，真是太可惜了，否则那些稍纵即逝的景象本该教给我们多少值得了解和记忆的东西啊！

至少，倘若有位画家或者有块镜子能让我们知道一点儿故事中提到过的那件衣服——埃莉诺小姐的绣花斗篷——那就好了！流言蜚语已经赋予它许多神秘特性，说是她每次只要披上它就会增添一种新的、人们未曾领略过的优美。这固然是毫无根据的奇思异想，但这件神秘的斗篷却给她在我心目中的形象笼罩上了一层凛然可畏的色彩，部分原因在于它传说中的种种价值，部分原因则在于它出自一位垂死的女人之手，说不定那构思的怪异魅力还要归功于死亡来临之际的精神狂乱呢。

在进行过礼节性问候之后，埃莉诺·罗彻克利夫小姐便离开了众宾客，只待在一个小小的显贵人士的圈子中，她对这个小圈子里的人要比对一般人更亲切热情。蜡制火炬的光线明亮地投射到场中，以强烈的对照衬托出光彩夺目的人物与衣饰；但她只是漫不经心地注视着这一切，不时流露出厌烦与轻蔑的神情，其中糅合着她那种女性的优雅，使得听她说话的人难以觉察出这种神情所表明的道德缺陷。她并不是以粗俗的讥嘲态度来看待这个场景，不屑于欣赏小地方对宫廷庆典的拙劣模仿，而是怀着一种更深的轻蔑，因自己精神上的优越而不愿屈尊参加到别人的欢乐中去。不论当晚见过她的人对这场舞会的回忆是否受到后来与她有关的奇异事件的影响，总之他们以后一想起她来就觉得她特别骄狂和做作——尽管当时大家都悄声赞叹她美貌无双，以及那件斗篷给她带来的无法形容的魅力。某些做过近距离观察的人还确实发现，她的脸色随着情绪的高低起落时而像热病似的殷红，时而又转为苍白，有一两次还痛苦而无奈地流露出疲乏无力，仿佛马上就要瘫倒在地上。接着她又神经质地浑身一颤，似乎强打起精神，在谈话中插进几句欢快俏皮却又半带恶意的嘲讽。她的举止与情绪显得如此奇怪，使每一个听她讲话的心智健全的人都感到诧异；再观察她的脸色，那种潜藏不明和不可思议的目光与微笑更是使人困惑，简直令人怀疑她的态度是否认真和神志是否清醒。渐渐地，埃莉诺小姐身边的圈子越来越小，最后只留下了四位先生。其中有兰福德上尉，即前面提到过的那位英国军官；有一位弗吉尼亚的种植园主，他是到马萨诸塞来完成某项政治使命的；有一位年轻的圣公会牧师，他是一位英国伯爵的孙子；最后还有舒特总督的私人秘书，他的讨好献媚已经多少博得了埃莉诺小姐的默认。

在晚会的不同时间，都有身穿号衣的州府仆从穿行于宾客之间，手里托着放有各种点心和法国与西班牙葡萄酒的大托盘。埃莉诺·罗彻克利夫小姐拒绝让香槟酒的哪怕一点泡沫来沾湿她那美丽的嘴唇，她深深坐进一把大马士革缎面的大扶手椅里，显然对这种场面的骚乱刺激或者单调乏味感到厌烦透顶。有那么一刻，她对四周的谈话、笑声和音乐都丧失了知觉，就在此时，一个年轻人悄悄走上前来，跪在她的脚下。他手里端着一只托盘，盘里放着一只雕花银质高脚杯，杯中满满盛着酒。他就像对一位加冕的女王那样恭敬地献上这杯酒，或者说像是一位牧师无限虔诚地向他的偶像奉上祭祀品。埃莉诺小姐察觉到有人碰了碰她的裙子，不禁吃了一惊，她睁开眼睛，看见了杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯那苍白而狂乱的面容和蓬乱的头发。

“你为什么老这样缠着我？”她用没精打采的声音说，不过比她平日准许自己使用的语气要和气一些，“人家告诉我说我曾经伤害过你。”

“上天知道是不是这样。”年轻人庄严地回答说，“不过，埃莉诺小姐，为了报偿那种伤害，如果说有过伤害的话，也为了你的现世与来生的福祉，我请求你喝一口这神圣之酒，再把酒杯传给客人们。这将作为一种象征，表明你不愿脱离人类同情心的环链——无论谁想摆脱这个环链，都必将与堕落的天使为伍。”

“这个疯子是从哪里偷来那只圣杯的呀？”圣公会牧师惊呼道。

这一问把宾客们的注意力都吸引到那只银杯上来，大家认出这正是放在老南方教堂圣盘上的那只杯子，或许杯里满盛着的就是圣酒呢。

“说不定里面下了毒药。”总督秘书半似耳语地说。

“把它灌进这个浑蛋的喉咙！”弗吉尼亚人恶狠狠地喊道。

“把他赶出去！”兰福德上尉叫嚷着，同时粗暴地抓住杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯的肩膀，结果打翻了圣杯，杯里的东西全洒在了埃莉诺小姐的斗篷上。“不管这个家伙是恶棍、傻瓜还是疯子，总之不能容他逍遥自在！”

“先生们，请不要伤害我可怜的崇拜者。”埃莉诺小姐说，脸上浮现出淡淡的、厌倦的微笑，“把他从我眼前弄走，假如你们乐意的话；因为我在心中除了对他的嘲笑以外就什么也找不到了。不过，出于礼仪和良心，我还是该为自己造成的伤害哭泣才合适！”

可是当旁观者试图把那个不幸的年轻人带走的时候，他却挣脱开来，以狂乱而激动的恳切态度向埃莉诺小姐提出一个新的、同样古怪的请求。这个请求不是别的，而是要她脱掉那件斗篷；刚才他要求她啜取银杯中的酒时，她用那件斗篷紧紧地裹住身体，几乎把自己完全包了起来。

“把它从你身上扯掉！”杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯喊道，绞紧双手痛苦地恳求着，“现在也许还不算太晚！把这该诅咒的衣服丢进火里烧了！”

然而，埃莉诺小姐却轻蔑地大笑一声，把褶皱重叠的绣花斗篷一直拉到头顶，这种穿着式样又给她美丽的脸庞赋予了一种全新的容貌，她的脸半遮半掩——似乎属于某个具有神秘性格和意图的生灵。

“再见了，杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯！”她说，“把我的形象保留在你的记忆里，记住你现在看到的这副模样。”

“唉，小姐！”他回答道，语气不再那么狂乱，而是哀伤得像丧钟一样，“我们很快就会再见面的，那时你的脸会另换一副模样——那才是应该藏在我心中的形象。”

他不再抗拒宾客与仆人的暴力行为，他们几乎是把他硬拖出房间，粗暴地把他推出了州府的大铁门。兰福德上尉在这件事上一直非常卖力，就在他返回埃莉诺小姐身边时，遇上了那位医生克拉克博士，他们二人曾在小姐到达之日做过随意交谈。医生远远站在一边，与埃莉诺小姐隔着整个房间的距离，但一直在以敏锐而精明的目光注视着她，兰福德上尉不由得认为他一定发现了什么深藏的秘密。

“看来你到底被这位女王似的小姐的魅力打垮啦。”他说，希望借此引出医生的心里话。

“上帝保佑不是如此！”克拉克医生回答道，庄重地笑了笑，“假如你还明智的话，也会为自己做同样的祈祷。那些拜倒在美丽的埃莉诺小姐面前的人要倒大霉了！不过总督就站在那边——我有些话要同他私下谈谈。晚安！”

于是他朝舒特总督走去，低声对他讲了几句话，声音小得让旁边任何一个人也没有听到一个字，不过总督一直很欢悦的脸色突然一变，表明谈话的内容绝不愉快。片刻之后他就向宾客宣布，由于某种未曾预料到的情况，必须提前结束这场晚会。

接下来的几天里，州府这场舞会为整个殖民地首府提供了一个谈话题材，它本来可能成为持续更久的普遍话题，只是因为发生了一件与所有人利害攸关的事情，才一度将这个话题逐出了公众记忆。那就是出现了一种可怕的传染病，它在当时以及前后很长的时间里常常会杀死大西洋两岸成百上千的人。在我们这个故事发生之时，这种病以一种特殊毒性而著称，其严重性足以在这个国家的历史上留下它的痕迹——用贴切的说法，就是刻下天花疤痕——所以这种病灾的猖獗使得举国上下惊惶不堪。

一开始，这种病并不像其通常的传播方式，似乎只限于上流社会，专门从那些傲慢自大、出身名门、拥有财富的人当中挑选牺牲品，坦然自若地侵入堂皇华贵的卧室，与睡在锦缎卧榻上的人同眠共枕。州府晚会上一些最显贵的客人——甚至包括傲慢的埃莉诺小姐认为不屑一顾的那些人——受到了这种致命疾病的打击。人们怀着有失宽厚的嘲讽情绪注意到那四位绅士——弗吉尼亚种植园主、英国军官、年轻牧师和总督的私人秘书——在舞会之夜对埃莉诺最为殷勤的四个人，最先受到瘟疫的袭击。然而，这场瘟疫继续蔓延开来，很快就不只是贵族阶级独享的特权了。它那通红的烙印不再像一颗贵族饰星或者一枚骑士勋章。它曲曲折折地穿过狭窄而弯曲的街道，钻入低矮、简陋、昏黑的住所，把死亡之手伸向了城镇里的水手、工匠和劳动阶层。它迫使富人和穷人感觉到相互之间的同胞情谊；它在三山之间纵横肆虐，那种凶猛劲简直是一场新的鼠疫。那个威力强大的征服者来啦——那种袭击我们祖先的灾难和恐怖来啦——天花！即使把这场可怕瘟疫看作今天的无牙妖魔，也难以恰当估量它在当时所造成的恐慌。

我们一定记得，我们曾怎样满怀敬畏地目睹亚洲霍乱横行无忌，大步践踏大西洋的一段又一段海岸，像厄运降临在遥远的城市之上，逃窜的居民撇下的只是半座空城。再没有什么比这种恐惧更可怕更残忍了，它使人竟然因担心空气有毒而害怕呼吸，竟然因担心传染疾病而害怕紧握兄弟或朋友的手。紧随着这次瘟疫而产生的正是这种沮丧情绪，它甚至在瘟疫未来到之前就已传遍了全城。人们匆忙地挖掘出坟墓，慌乱地掩埋掉病死者的遗体，因为死者就是活人的仇敌，仿佛死者要拼命将活人拽进自己阴森的墓坑。公众会议都暂时停止，似乎人类智慧最好放弃它的谋略手段，既然超自然的篡位者已经在宫廷官府里登堂入室。假如敌人的舰队正在海岸线上游弋，或者敌军的铁蹄正在践踏着我们的国土，人们大概也会将守土之责托付给祸害了他们的那同一位可怕的征服者，而不允许对他的统治稍加干预。这位征服者拥有一种胜利的标志，那就是一面血红的旗帜，它飘扬在病毒污染的空气中，飘扬在天花瘟疫侵入的每一家的门上。

这样一面旗帜早就招展在州府的大门上方了，因为追溯灾难的起源，这场可怕的瘟疫显然就是从这里开始传播的。进而可以一直追溯到一位小姐的豪华闺房——追溯到傲慢者中的最傲慢者——追溯到那个无比娇美、自以为是天仙胚子的女人——追溯到那个目空一切、竟敢用脚践踏人类同情心的人——追溯到埃莉诺小姐！毫无疑问，传染病毒就潜藏在那件华丽的斗篷中，在舞会上它曾给埃莉诺小姐增添了如此奇异的魅力。它那怪异的光彩是一个垂死女人的谵妄头脑孕育出来的，是她的僵硬手指茹苦含辛的最后遗作，因此那些金线中便织进了厄运与苦难。

这个阴森的传说开始只是悄悄流传，现在则已广为人知。人们激烈地斥责埃莉诺小姐，大声宣称正是她的骄傲与轻蔑召来了魔鬼，正是她与魔鬼共谋带来了这场怪异的灾难。有时候，人们的愤怒与绝望会以苦涩欢乐的面貌出现，只要那面标志瘟疫的红旗在一家又一家的门前升起，大家就会到街头去拍着巴掌高声喊叫，辛辣地嘲讽道：“看哪，埃莉诺小姐又胜利啦！”

就在这些阴郁的日子里，有一天，一个模样狂野的人走近了州府大门；他环抱双臂，站在那儿注视着那面猩红色的旗帜，一阵微风将它突然吹动，仿佛要将它所象征的疾病抛向四方。最后，他攀着铁栏杆爬上了柱子，摘下那面旗帜后便走进了州府，同时举起旗帜在头顶挥舞着。在台阶脚下他遇见了总督，总督穿带着马刺的靴子，斗篷紧裹着全身，显然正要出门旅行。

“讨厌的疯子，你来这儿想找什么？”舒特总督喝道，伸出手杖来护卫自己免受接触，“这儿除了死神什么也没有。回去——不然你会碰上它的！”

“死神是不会碰我的，我是瘟疫的旗手！”杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯喊叫道，一面把红色旗帜高高举起摇动着，“今天晚上，死神和瘟疫会以埃莉诺小姐的模样走遍大街小巷，我必须举着这面旗帜在前面开路！”

“我何必对这个家伙白费唇舌呢？”总督咕哝道，把斗篷拉过来掩住自己的嘴，“他这条贱命何足轻重？反正我们谁也不清楚自己能否再活十二个小时。朝前走吧，傻瓜，走向你自己的毁灭吧。”

他给杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯让开道，后者立刻登上了台阶，可是刚走到第一段楼梯平台，他的肩膀就被一只手紧紧抓住。他气势汹汹地抬头观看，疯狂的冲动使他想要跟对手拼斗并挣扎开来，但在一道平静而严厉的眼光俯视之下他顿感软弱无力，那道眼光具有平息极度狂暴的神奇力量。他所面对的是那位医生，克拉克博士，令人悲哀的职责把他引到州府里来了，而在升平昌盛之时他倒并非是这里的常客。

“年轻人，你来干什么？”他问道。

“我找埃莉诺小姐。”杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯柔顺地回答。

“所有的人都从她身边逃离了。”医生说，“你为什么现在还来找她呢？告诉你，年轻人，连她的看护都在那间致命的闺房门槛边倒毙了。难道你不知道，我们的海岸上从来没有降临过像可爱的埃莉诺小姐这样的灾星？你不知道正是她的呼吸使空气中充满了毒素？你不知道撒播在这块土地上的瘟疫与死亡，正是从她那件该诅咒的斗篷的褶皱里抖落出来的？”

“让我看她一眼！”疯狂的年轻人回答说，神情更加狂乱，“让我看看她，看看她那令人敬畏的美貌，穿着那件撒播瘟疫的华贵服装！她和死神并坐在宝座上。让我跪倒在他们脚下！”

“可怜的年轻人啊！”克拉克博士说，对人性弱点的深刻意识令他动情，甚至此时他的唇边也泛出了一丝讥讽的笑容，“难道你仍然崇拜这个毁灭者，她所制造的邪恶越多，你反而越要用更壮丽的幻想来包裹她的形象吗？人类对压迫自己的暴君历来就是这样。那么，进去吧！我已经注意到了，疯狂具有一种良好的功效，它会保护你免受传染——说不定在那间闺房里还能找到治疗疯狂的药方呢。”

他登上另一段阶梯，推开了一道门，示意杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯进屋去。这个可怜的疯子，大概心中怀着虚妄的幻想，以为他那位高傲的女王正庄严端坐，尽管她像使用妖术似的在自己周围撒播了瘟疫，她本人却丝毫不受影响。毫无疑问，他梦想着她的美丽非但不会有丝毫减色，反倒会增添超凡的光彩。他心中怀着期望，虔敬地轻轻走向医生所站的门边，但一到门槛前又停住脚步，疑惧重重地探视着昏黑的房间里那一片阴暗。

“埃莉诺小姐在哪儿？”他悄声问道。

“叫她一声。”医生回答说。

“埃莉诺小姐！公主殿下！死神王后！”杰瓦斯喊道，朝卧室里前进了三步，“她不在这儿！那儿，那边的桌子上，我看见她曾经戴在胸前的那颗钻石在闪光。那儿——”他打了个冷战——“那儿挂着她的斗篷，一个死去的女人绣进了具有可怕威力的诅咒。可是埃莉诺小姐在哪儿呢？”

在一张支着华盖的卧榻的锦缎帐幔后面，有什么东西动了动；同时还传出低低的一声呻吟。杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯仔细一听，分辨出这是一个女人的声音，正在哀伤地抱怨说口渴。他想自己认识这声调。

“我的喉咙！我的喉咙像火在烧，”那声音咕哝着说，“给我一点水！”

“你是谁？”头脑被击蒙了的年轻人问道，一面走近床边猛地拉开帐幔，“你这些抱怨和哀求是偷了谁的声音，就好像埃莉诺小姐竟然会感知到凡人的病痛？呸！你这病得要死的破烂货，为什么藏在我的小姐的闺房里？”

“啊，杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯，”那个声音说道——在发出声音的时候，那个人形不停扭动，挣扎着要藏起她毁损了的脸孔——“如今别看你曾经爱过的女人！上天的诅咒已经打垮了我，因为我不肯把男人称作兄弟，把女人称作姐妹。我用骄傲包裹起自己，就像披上斗篷一样，藐视人类天生的同情心；因此天道才把我弄成这副惨相，成为可怕的怜悯对象。你报了仇——大家都报了仇——天道也报了仇——因为我就是埃莉诺·罗彻克利夫！”

尽管因为生命横遭摧残毁灭，杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯已陷于疯狂，但精神疾病所产生的恶意，心底潜藏的痛苦，以及遭受冷酷蔑视的爱情，此时都在他的胸中苏醒过来。他对着悲惨的姑娘挥动战抖的手指，爆发出一阵疯狂的欢笑，卧房里激起回响，床上的帐幔也随之震动。

“埃莉诺小姐又胜利啦！”他大叫道，“一切都是她的牺牲品！谁能像她自己那样配做最后的牺牲品呢？”

在自己疯狂心智的某个新狂想的驱使下，他一把扯下那件致命的斗篷，冲出了房间和州府。那天晚上，一支游行队伍高举火把走过街头，队列中段抬着一个女人的塑像，裹着一件华丽的绣花斗篷。杰瓦斯·赫尔威斯昂首阔步走在队列的前头，手里挥舞着那面象征瘟疫的红旗。到达州府对面，众人烧掉了那个模拟像，一阵狂风吹来，刮走了灰烬。

据说从那一刻起，瘟疫就销声匿迹了，仿佛从瘟疫初始到结束，它的威力都与埃莉诺小姐那件斗篷有着某种神秘的关系。至于那位不幸小姐的最后命运，则始终笼罩着一片疑云。不过，有人相信在州府的某个房间里，不时能朦胧觉察到一个女子的身影，龟缩在最黑暗的角落里，用一件绣花斗篷捂住她的面孔。假如此项传说事属真实，这个人除了昔日那位高傲的埃莉诺小姐又能是谁呢？

罗杰·麦尔文的葬礼

在印第安战争的几次事件中，1725年保卫边疆的那次远征自然是最富于传奇色彩的，它给人们留下了“洛弗尔之战”的深刻记忆。人们的想象力对于其他某些情况总是低调处理，从而证明那一支小部队战士的英雄主义精神值得大加赞美，他们在敌国领土的心脏地带，与两倍于己的敌人交战。双方所展示的英勇气概都符合文明的英雄主义观念；有几个人的行为，即使是由中世纪骑士传奇加以记载也当之无愧。这一仗尽管对于参战者来说是毁灭性的，其结果对于国家来说却不失为幸事，因为它削弱了一个印第安部落的力量，导致了此后维持了数年之久的和平。历史与传说对这次战斗做了不同寻常的详细记叙；领导由参战边民组成的侦察部队的首脑，也获得了像率领成千上万士兵的胜利领袖那样的军事声誉。下面讲述的事情将告诉你在“洛弗尔之战”结束后实行撤退的几个战士的命运，虽然替换上了虚构的姓名，它们来自人们耳熟能详的老人们的口头传说。

清晨的阳光在树顶欢快地闪耀着，两个疲惫和负伤的士兵就在树下摊开四肢过了一夜。他们那张用干枯的橡树叶铺成的睡床，散落在一块巨石脚下的一小块平地上。这块巨石矗立在平缓起伏的山脉中的一座岗顶附近，而这派山脉使得整个乡间景色变得多姿多彩。这块花岗岩的光滑平整的表面高过两人的头顶十五到二十英尺，颇像一块巨大的墓石。石头的纹理看上去就像是用人类遗忘了的字符刻下的一段碑文。这块巨石周围几英亩土地上全是橡树和其他各种硬木林，它们取代了这个地区常见的松树；紧靠这两位行路人身边，还长着一棵生机勃勃的小橡树苗。

年纪较长的那个人身负重伤，大概使他通夜未能入睡；因为当头一缕阳光刚刚照到最高的树梢时，他就痛苦地爬起来，挺直身体坐着。他脸上很深的皱纹和头上间杂的白发说明他已人过中年；但他那副肌肉强健的身躯要是没有受伤的话，肯定还像青春蓬勃时期一样能吃苦耐劳。现在，只有疲惫和衰竭留驻在他憔悴的脸上；他投向树林深处的绝望目光，也证明他断定自己的生命已经走到了尽头。他接着又把目光转向躺在身边的伙伴。那是个年轻人——才刚刚届于成年——他头枕胳膊，睡得很不安稳，他的伤口所激起的剧痛似乎每一刻都会打破他的睡眠。他的右手紧握着一支滑膛枪；从他脸上的强烈表情来判断，他在睡梦中又返回了激战的情景，他正是那场战斗的少数几个幸存者之一。忽然他发出一声呐喊——他在梦中觉得喊得深沉而响亮——到唇边却化为了含糊不清的咕哝声；即使自己发出的这种微小声音也使他猛然一惊，他突然醒了过来。在意识清醒之后，他做的第一件事就是关切地询问受伤的同伴情况怎样。后者摇了摇头。

“鲁本，我的孩子，”他说，“我们头上的这块岩石满可以给老猎手做块墓碑咧。我们前面还有漫长的狂啸怒吼的荒野；就算我家的烟囱就在这片山地的另一边冒烟，对我来说也没用了。印第安人的子弹真是比我想的更厉害啊。”

“我们赶了三天路，您太累啦，”年轻人回答道，“再稍微歇息一会儿您就会有精神了。您就坐着吧，我到树林里去找些树根、草叶来充饥；吃过东西以后，您靠在我身上，我们一起朝回家的方向走。我相信，有我帮着您，您一定能支持到有一座边疆要塞的地方。”

“我活不了两天了，鲁本，”长者平静地说，“我不想再无益地拖累你，况且你自己也很难支撑得住。你的伤很深，力气也很快会耗尽的；但如果你单独地往前赶路，可能还能保住一条命。我已经没指望了，就留在这儿等死吧。”

“要真是这样的话，我也留下来守着您好了。”鲁本语气坚定地说。

“不，我的孩子，不。”他的同伴回答，“希望你听从一个垂死的人的意愿；你伸手让我握一握，随后就走吧。你以为我在断气的时候想到我也会把你拖死，心里能好受吗？我一直像父亲一样地爱你，鲁本；到了眼下这个时刻，我也应该有点儿父亲的权威才是。我命令你离开，这样我才能死得安宁。”

“难道因为您像父亲一样待我，我就应该留下您独自死去、抛尸荒野吗？”年轻人叫道，“不；万一您的生命真的走到了尽头，我就守在您身边，听您的临终嘱咐。我要在这块巨石边挖个坟坑，如果我也支撑不下去了，我们就埋在一起；如果上天赐给我力量，我再寻路回家。”

“人们无论住在城里还是别的什么地方，”长者说，“总要把死者埋进土里；那是为了避免尸体让活人看到。可是在这里，也许上百年也没有人来过，难道我不可以安息在苍天之下，让秋风刮落下的橡树叶掩盖我的尸体吗？再说还有这块灰白的岩石做我的墓碑，我可以用我垂死的余力在上面刻下罗杰·麦尔文的名字；将来有路人经过，就会知道这里长眠着一个猎手、一个勇士。别再抱着这样的傻念头，白白耽误时间啦，快走吧，就算不为你自己，也该为孤苦伶仃的她着想啊。”

麦尔文在说最后几句话时声音战抖，看得出他的同伴也受到了强烈的震动。这番话使他想到自己除了以无益的死来与同伴共命运之外，还有另一份更不容推卸的责任。我们也不能断言说，鲁本心中这时绝对没有自私之念在侵袭，尽管意识到这一点只会使他更加热切地抵制同伴的恳求。

“在这荒山野岭里慢慢等死多可怕啊！”他叫道，“勇士在战斗中是绝不畏缩的；只要有亲友守在床边，甚至女人也能镇静自若地去死；可是这儿——”

“即使在这儿我也不会畏缩，鲁本·伯恩。”麦尔文打断了他的话，“我绝不是个胆小的人；况且，即使我会害怕，也有比人世亲友更可信赖的上帝来给我勇气。你还年轻，生命对于你来说是宝贵的。你在最后时刻将比我更需要慰藉；等你把我埋进土里，只剩孤单一人，夜幕又降临在树林里的时候，你就该感受到死亡的全部痛苦了，而你现在却是可以逃脱的。你天性慷慨，我不愿怀着自私的动机怂恿你留下来。为了我的意愿而离开我吧，我在为你的平安而祈祷之后，再从容地了此一生，免却人世忧伤的折磨。”

“可是您的女儿——我怎么去面对她的目光呢？”鲁本喊叫道，“她会询问她父亲的命运，而我曾发誓要用自己的生命保护您的生命啊。难道我该告诉她，您和我撤出战场后赶了三天路，然后被我扔在荒野里独自死去吗？在您身边躺下来一起死，不是比安全脱身后对多卡丝说这番话更好吗？”

“告诉我的女儿，”罗杰·麦尔文说，“尽管你自己伤势严重，既虚弱又疲乏，还是领着我踉踉跄跄地走了很多里路，只是在我的恳求下才离开我的，因为我不愿意让自己的灵魂染上你的鲜血。告诉她，在痛苦和危险中你一直忠心耿耿，要是你的生命能够挽救我的话，你是会为我流尽最后一滴血的。告诉她，对于她来说你要比一个父亲更宝贵，我为你们两人祝福，我在临死的时候会看到你们将一起走上一条漫长而幸福的人生道路。”

麦尔文说这番话的时候，几乎从地面上撑起他的身子，他突然迸发的力量和结尾的话语仿佛让荒凉而孤寂的森林也弥漫着幸福的憧憬。可是，等他精疲力竭地瘫倒在橡树叶铺成的床上时，刚才在鲁本眼中燃烧着的火光也随即熄灭了。他感到在这种时刻还想到自己的幸福既是罪过，也很荒唐。他的同伴观察到他神情的变化，便善意地设法哄他离开自己。

“或许我说自己活不了多久只是在欺骗自己，”他接着说，“或许只要得到迅速的救援，我的伤还有可能治好。跑在最前面的人一定把我们打了败仗的消息带到了边境上，搜索队会出发来营救像我们这样的伤员。要是你碰上他们，就带着他们到这儿来，谁能说我就不能再坐到自家的炉火边呢？”

这个垂死的人在设法编造毫无根据的希望时，脸上掠过了一抹哀伤的微笑；不过这番话对鲁本却并非没有产生影响。单单是自私的动机，甚至于多卡丝所面临的孤苦处境，都不足以说服他在这种时刻扔下同伴不管——然而麦尔文的生命或许有救的想法唤起了他的希望，他那乐观的天性振奋起来，几乎认定获得救助的渺茫可能性是确定无疑的了。

“您这话的确有道理，很有道理，希望朋友们离我们不远。”他提高了些声音说，“战斗才刚刚开始，有个胆小鬼连汗毛都没伤着就逃了，他大概一路都在飞跑。听到他带去的消息，边境上每个真正的男子汉都会扛起他的滑膛枪。虽然搜索队不会巡逻到树林里这么远的地方来，但我走上一天也许会碰上他们的。您对我说句真话，”他对自己的动机有所怀疑，便转向麦尔文问道，“假如我是您这种处境，您会不会把我活活扔下不管？”

“已经是二十年前的事啦。”罗杰·麦尔文回答说，他长叹了一声，心中暗自承认这两件事是迥然不同的。——“那是二十年前，我同一个好朋友一道从蒙特利尔附近印第安人的监禁下逃了出来。我们穿越树林跑了好几天，最后被饥饿和疲乏压倒，我的朋友躺倒在地上，恳求我扔下他自己走；因为他知道，要是我留下来，我们两个都必死无疑。我怀着找到救兵的一线希望，用枯叶给他堆了个枕头，然后独自往前赶路。”

“你及时回去救他了吗？”鲁本渴望知道麦尔文下面的话，仿佛这将预示自己是否会成功。

“去了。”麦尔文回答说，“当天日落之前，我就发现了一队猎人的营地。我把他们带到了同伴等死的地方；如今他老当益壮，在远离边境的内地经营着自己的农场，而我却重伤在身，躺在这荒野深处。”

这个事例对鲁本的决定产生了重大影响，此外他还受到自己未能意识到的其他种种动机的潜在驱动。罗杰·麦尔文感到胜利在望。

“好啦，走吧，我的孩子，愿上天保佑你！”他说，“你碰上朋友之后别跟他们一起回来，免得伤势和疲乏弄垮了你；只要能抽出两三个人到这里来找我就行啦。相信我的话，鲁本，你往家里每走一步，我的心就会轻松一分。”然而就在他这样说着的时候，脸色和声音似乎都发生了某种变化；因为说到底，被孤零零地抛在荒野里等死毕竟是件恐怖的事。

鲁本·伯恩对自己的行为是否正当半信半疑，最后还是从地上爬了起来，准备独自上路。首先，尽管这违背了麦尔文的意愿，他采集了一大把草根、树叶，在过去两天里他们就是靠这些东西果腹的。他把这些无济于事的东西放到濒死的人伸手可及的地方，再扫拢干枯的橡树叶堆成一张新的床。接着他又从巨石粗糙破碎的一面爬上它的顶部，把那棵小橡树弯下来，把自己的手巾绑在树顶的枝丫上。这一个谨慎办法倒是颇有必要的，可以指引到这里来的人寻找到麦尔文；因为那块岩石除了它宽大而平滑的正面之外，其他部分都被浓密的矮树遮住了，稍微离远一点就看不见。那条手巾原来是包裹着鲁本手臂上一处伤口的绷带；他在把手巾绑在小树上的时候，心里暗暗以上面沾染的血迹发誓自己一定要回来，不管是来挽救同伴的生命，还是来安葬他的遗体。随后他爬下岩石站立着，低垂着目光，接受罗杰·麦尔文的临别嘱托。

长者凭着自己的经验，详尽地指点年轻人如何穿越茫无路径的森林。他在交代这些事时语气十分平静恳切，就好像在送鲁本去打仗或者参加追猎，自己则平平安安地待在家里，而并非在与此生只能见最后一面的人做最后诀别。可是，在说最后一番话之前，他的坚毅也有所动摇了。

“把我的祝福带给多卡丝，告诉她我最后的祈祷将是为她和你而做的。叫她不要因为你把我扔在这儿而心怀怨愤，”——鲁本的心猛地一跳——“因为假如牺牲你的生命能对我有益的话，你是会将它看得无足轻重的。她在为父亲哀伤一阵之后就会嫁给你；愿上天保佑你们长寿和幸福，愿你们孩子的孩子能守护在你们临终的床头！还有，鲁本，”他又补充道，临终时的软弱终于袭上了他的心头，“等你的伤痊愈了，体力恢复了，要回来一趟——回到这块巨石前，把我的尸骨埋进坟墓，并在墓前做一次祈祷。”

边疆居民对墓葬仪式抱有一种近乎迷信的敬重，这大概来源于印第安人的习俗，他们跟活人和死人都要同样交战。为了安葬那些被“荒野之剑”砍倒的人们，在许多情况下又得牺牲更多生命。因此，在鲁本庄严地许诺将回来完成罗杰·麦尔文的葬礼时，他深深感到这个诺言的重要意义。很明显，麦尔文既然在临别嘱托中说出了他的肺腑之言，也就不再竭力劝服年轻人，不再说只要尽快获得救援就可能保住他的性命了。鲁本心里也十分清楚，他再也见不到麦尔文活着的面孔了。他出于仁厚的天性本来是很乐意留下来的，不管要冒多大的危险，直到死亡的一幕结束为止；然而对生命的欲求和对幸福的希望已经在他心中占了上风，他实在难以抵御。

“行啦。”罗杰·麦尔文听过鲁本的诺言之后说，“走吧。愿上帝保佑你成功！”

年轻人默默地紧握拳头，转过身去，准备离开。他迈开缓慢而蹒跚的步子还没有走出几步，又听见麦尔文的声音在呼唤他。

“鲁本，鲁本。”麦尔文虚弱无力地说；鲁本折回身来，跪倒在垂死者身旁。

“把我扶起来，让我靠在这块岩石上，”他最后这样要求说，“我的脸要朝着家的方向，在你穿越树林的时候也可以多看你一会儿。”

鲁本照同伴的希望改变了他坐的姿势，然后重新开始他孤独的行程。他一开始走得很快，与他的体能并不相符合；因为人们的行为有时候虽然很合乎情理，却也会受到某种内疚感的折磨，正是这种心情使他想尽快躲开麦尔文的目光。可是，他在脚踏林中沙沙作响的落叶走出很远之后，又在狂乱而痛苦的好奇心逼迫下悄悄溜了回来，躲在一棵被连根拔起的大树沾满泥土的树根后面，急切地凝望那个孤独的人。早晨的阳光清朗明亮，大树灌木都呼吸着五月甜美的空气；然而大自然似乎笼罩着一层愁容，好像在对人类的痛苦和哀伤表示同情。罗杰·麦尔文高举双手在热忱地祈祷，一些话语透过树林的寂静一直潜进了鲁本的心房，以难以言说的剧痛折磨着他。那断断续续的语句表明麦尔文正在为他和多卡丝祈求幸福。年轻人倾听着，他的良心或者类似的感情强烈地要求他转身回去，到巨石边去重新躺下。他感到，这个慈爱仁厚却又被自己抛弃在绝境中的人将遭遇多么残酷的命运啊！死神会像一具僵尸那样缓缓逼来，穿越森林渐渐潜到他身边，将它那张苍白的、呆滞的脸孔从树后探出来，一棵又一棵，越来越近。可是假如鲁本再耽搁到日落，他也会遭到同样的命运；况且他要是逃避了这种无谓的牺牲，谁又能责怪他呢？就在他投去临别最后一道目光时，一阵轻风吹动了绑在小橡树上的手巾，提醒鲁本要记住自己的誓言。

重重困难阻碍着负伤的行路人的回家之途。第二天，空中阴云密集，使他无法根据太阳的位置来调整自己的路线；他不知道，自己每次耗费所余无几的体力的结果，都只是离家更遥远了。他那少得可怜的食物来自森林中的浆果和其他野生植物。是的，一群群野鹿不时跃过他身边，山鸡也时时被他的脚步惊得呼地飞起，可是他的弹药已在战斗中耗尽，没有办法去猎杀它们。他为求一线生机而奋力赶路，伤口受到刺激便发炎疼痛，渐渐耗尽了他的体力，并使他的意识也时不时地发生混乱。不过，即使是在神志恍惚之中，鲁本那颗年轻的心仍然顽强地执着于生命，直到他最后完全无法走动了，才最终倒在一棵树下，无可奈何地等待着死亡。

就是在这种境况下，他被一支搜索队发现了，这些人是在最初获得战斗情报后被派出来救援幸存者的。他们把鲁本抬到最近的拓居地，碰巧他自己的家正在这里。

多卡丝怀着古昔时代的纯朴情感守护在受伤情人的床前，以女性心灵和双手所独有的温情抚慰来悉心照料他。在开头几天里，鲁本的记忆昏沉沉地迷失在他所经历过的千难万险中，对于人们向他急切询问的那些不胜其烦的问题，他都无法做出明确的回答。战斗的真实细节尚未传播开来；母亲、妻子和孩子们都无从知晓自己的心爱者是做了俘虏还是被更强大的死神的锁链拘押。多卡丝在沉默中忍受着忧虑的煎熬，直到一天下午鲁本从烦乱不安的睡梦中醒来，似乎比前几次醒来时更清楚地辨认出了她。她看到他的神志已经恢复清醒了，再也克制不了自己关切父亲的焦急心情。

“我的父亲呢，鲁本？”她一开口就问道；可是她的情人脸色的突变却使她打住了话头。

年轻人仿佛因为剧痛而猛地一缩，一阵红潮即刻涌上了他那苍白憔悴的脸颊。他的第一个冲动是想掩住自己的脸，但接着又不顾一切地奋力挣扎着抬起上半身，激烈地说起话来，面对想象中的指控为自己辩护。

“你父亲在战斗中受了重伤，多卡丝；他叫我不要为了他而拖累自己，只是要我把他弄到湖边，他好解解渴然后死去。不过我并没有在绝境中抛下老人，尽管我自己也流着血，仍然搀扶着他；我把一半体力都花在他身上，领着他一道走。我们在一起走了三天，你父亲居然出乎我的意料挺了过来；可是到第四天早上醒来的时候，我发现他非常虚弱、精疲力竭，一步也走不动了；他的生命很快就耗尽了；后来——”

“他死啦！”多卡丝用微弱的声音喊叫道。

鲁本感到自己无法承认，由于对生命的自私爱恋，他实际上没等她父亲断气就匆匆离开了。他不再说话，只是低垂着头；他在羞愧和衰竭的夹击下又倒在病床上，用枕头掩着自己的脸。多卡丝的担心得到了证实，她流下了泪水；不过因为这个打击早在意料之中，所以还不是那么沉重猛烈。

“你在荒野里挖坟埋葬了我可怜的父亲吗，鲁本？”她的这个询问表明了一片至诚的孝心。

“我双手虚弱无力，但还是尽力而为，”年轻人用压抑的声音回答道，“他头顶上有一块高高的墓碑；上天做证，我真愿意像他那样永远安息！”

多卡丝听出他最后的话显得很狂乱，此时也就不再多问；她想到罗杰·麦尔文到底获得了当时情况所允许的适当葬礼，心里也感到好受多了。鲁本的勇敢和孝敬，她都毫无遗漏地对她的朋友们做了讲述；当可怜的年轻人脚步蹒跚地走出病房享受阳光和空气时，人人都在赞美他，他受之有愧，深受痛苦和羞辱的折磨。乡亲们公认说他完全有资格向美丽的姑娘求婚，因为他对她的父亲“至死不渝”；既然这个故事跟爱情无关，我们只需交代一句就够了：几个月之后，鲁本就成了多卡丝·麦尔文的丈夫。在婚礼上，新娘满面娇羞，新郎却脸色苍白。

现在，鲁本·伯恩心中怀着一种难以告人的思绪——这桩心事他不得不小心翼翼地瞒着自己最心爱最信任的妻子。他充满深深的、痛苦的懊悔，当他想要向多卡丝坦露真相的时候，道德上的怯懦又让他不敢开口。自尊心，担心失去妻子的爱，惧怕受到世人谴责，使他无法变更自己的谎言。他觉得自己不该因为抛下罗杰·麦尔文而受谴责。他如果守在那里，无谓地牺牲自己的生命，只会给死者的临终时刻再增加一份毫无必要的痛苦；可是隐瞒事实真相却给原本正当的行为蒙上了一层浓重的罪孽。虽然理性告诉鲁本说他做得不错，但他仍然深深体验到一种巨大的精神恐惧，那正是对犯下隐秘罪行的人所给予的惩罚。他心里会发生某种联想，有时觉得自己简直就是一个杀人犯。许多年里，还有一个念头时时出现在他心中，虽然他明白这个念头纯属胡思乱想，却又无力将它从心头驱赶出去。那是一种像鬼魂作祟般的折磨人的幻象——他的岳父仍然坐在那块巨石下，坐在林中枯叶上面，依然活着，正等待着他去实现自己的诺言。这种心理错觉出现之后又会消失，他也从来没有把它们错当成真实情况；但每当心境宁静清晰之时，他仍然感到自己还有个庄严誓言不曾履行，荒野中还有一具未曾掩埋的尸体在召唤着他。然而，他总是找借口来遮掩推诿，结果始终不能让自己去服从那种召唤。现在再请求罗杰·麦尔文的朋友帮忙去实施拖延日久的葬礼已经太晚了；边疆拓居者特别易于沾染上的那种迷信恐惧，又阻止鲁本单独前往。他也不知道在荒无道路、广袤无际的森林中，到哪儿才能找到那块光滑的、似乎刻有字迹的巨石，下面躺着那具尸体？当时从那里走回来的路，他连一段也记不清了，最后一段路更是完全没有印象。然而，他心中始终有一种冲动，有一种只有自己才听得见的声音，在命令他到那儿去，去履行自己的誓言；他也有一种奇怪的想法，觉得只要自己去试一试，就会被笔直引到麦尔文的遗骨所在的地方。可是年复一年，他并没有服从那个他虽听不见却感觉得到的召唤。难言之隐变成了一条锁链，束缚着他的精神，像毒蛇一样咬噬着他的身心；他变成了一个忧伤、抑郁却又暴躁易怒的人。

在婚后几年的光景里，鲁本和多卡丝那外表看来很兴旺的家境开始出现了一些变化。鲁本仅有的财富是他那颗勇敢的心和两条强壮的胳膊；而多卡丝作为父亲的唯一继承人，则让丈夫做了农场的主人。在往日的耕作方式下，这片农场比边疆大多数农场都更大，收成也更好。然而鲁本却是个管理粗疏的庄稼汉，别的拓居者的田地一年比一年收成多，他的田地的情况却一年比一年糟。同印第安人的休战使人们对农业的兴趣不再那么低落了，而在战争期间人们要一手扶犁一手拿枪，冒险劳作的成果不论长在田里还是收进谷仓，只要不被野蛮的敌人毁掉就算幸运。可是鲁本却没有从条件的改善中受益；无可否认的是，即使他也间或辛勤照料自己的农事，但收成总是很糟糕。他近年来出了名的暴躁性格则是导致家道中落的另一个原因，在与邻居发生不可避免的交往中，他的坏脾气总是经常引发争吵。结果是招来无数的官司；因为新英格兰人在最早的定居阶段，在国家尚处于蛮荒状态下，只要有可能就要采取法律手段来解决彼此的争端。总而言之，鲁本在这世上总是不走运；婚后没过多少年，他终于成了个破产的人，要对抗穷追不舍的厄运只剩下一条路，那就是钻进不见天日的森林深处，到未经垦殖的荒野中去求生存。

鲁本与多卡丝只有一个儿子，如今刚满十五岁，正值美好的青春年华，看得出成年后前途将不可限量。他特别具有边疆拓荒生活的种种才干，而且已经开始显露出过人的能力。他跑起来疾步如风，打枪百发百中，思维敏捷，心地欢乐高尚；所有预见将与印第安人重新开战的人，无论谁说起塞勒斯·伯恩都把他看作这片土地未来的领袖。鲁本深沉地、默默地爱着儿子，仿佛他本人天性中一切美好和幸运的东西都传给了孩子，他所有的感情都凝聚其中。多卡丝虽然可爱，他也爱着她，但在他眼中甚至也远远比不上儿子珍贵。因为鲁本的隐秘和孤独性情已经渐渐使他成为一个自私的人，他已不能再有深沉的爱，除非那是他所看到的或想象出的自己心灵的反射物或相似物。从赛勒斯身上，他辨认出自己昔日的影子；时不时的他也似乎分享到儿子的情绪，重新恢复了鲜活快乐的生命力。鲁本在儿子的陪同下开始了他的远征，打算选择一块荒地，砍伐和烧掉树木，然后再把家搬过去。秋天里有两个月就这样过去了；随后，鲁本·伯恩和年轻的猎手就回拓居地去度过最后一个冬季。

第二年五月初，一家三口割断了与一切毫无生气的东西的感情羁绊，并与几个在厄运中还自称是他们朋友的人告别。对这三位远行者来说，临别之际的哀伤都具有其特定的慰藉作用。鲁本这个喜怒无常的人，因为不幸而愤世嫉俗，像平日一样眉头紧锁，目光低垂，大踏步地朝前走；他并不感到多么惋惜，也不屑于承认有这类感情。多卡丝泪水长淌，因为她纯朴深情的天性对种种事物依恋不舍却又不得不割弃，但又感到留驻在内心深处的东西始终在伴她同行，至于其他的一切则自有天意安排。儿子挥去了眼角的一滴泪珠，心中想的是在渺无人迹的森林中冒险的快乐。

啊，谁不曾在白日梦的激情中怀抱着希望，愿自己在夏日荒野的天地中漫游，手臂上轻盈地挽着个美丽温柔的人儿？在青年时代，他那自由不羁、欢乐跳跃的步伐，除了滔滔翻滚的海洋或白雪封顶的山峦，绝不知道有什么障碍；到了较为宁静的中年，他会选择一处家园，大自然将在明澈小溪流经的山谷中为他安排一块双倍丰饶的土地；待到经历过纯洁生活的漫长岁月，霜色偷偷地染上了双鬓，他这才发觉自己已成为一族之长，儿孙满堂，甚至可能成为一个强大民族的创始者。就像我们度过了幸福的白日将欢迎甜蜜的睡眠一样，到最后，死亡降临到他头上，子子孙孙会守着他可敬的骨灰齐声哀悼。传说将把他包裹在神秘色彩之中，未来的一代代人会说他像天神，渺远的后裔会看见他朦胧显现的雄伟身影，高高矗立在那道万年亘古的溪谷之上。

我的故事中的这一家人艰难跋涉在纷乱而阴暗的森林中，却是与白日梦者的幻境大不相同。不过，在他们的生存方式中蕴含着某种大自然的原始本性，如今只有从世间带来的痛苦烦恼才对他们的幸福构成阻碍。一匹强壮的长满粗毛的马驮着他们的全部家当，即使再驮上多卡丝也不会畏缩；只不过她生来就经受过艰苦磨炼，每天行程的后半段都能支撑着坚持走在丈夫身边。鲁本和儿子肩上扛着滑膛枪，背后挂着利斧，迈着不知疲倦的步伐，各自以猎人的目光搜寻着可充食物的野兽。饥饿的时候，他们就在林间的清溪岸边停下来准备做饭，他们跪下去用溪水湿润干渴的嘴唇，这时溪水会咕咕细语，可爱地表示不大情愿，就像是少女在接受恋人的初吻。他们睡在树枝搭成的窝棚下面，晨光初露之时醒来，精神振奋地迎接又一天的艰辛历程。多卡丝和儿子兴致勃勃地走着，甚至鲁本偶尔也会显出快乐的神情，不过他内心却感到一种冰冷的悲伤，他把这比作小溪穿行的幽谷洼地里堆积得很深的积雪，表面上却覆盖着葱茏蓬勃的绿叶。

塞勒斯对这种林中旅行已是轻车熟路，他发现父亲没有按去年秋天那次远征的路线走。他们现在保持着远向北方的方向，从拓居地出来越来越笔直地朝前奋进，深入到似乎仍由野兽与蛮族主宰着的区域。儿子有时对父亲暗示自己的意见，鲁本很注意地听着。也有一两次按照儿子的意见改变过行进的方向，但他在这样做了之后仿佛有些心神不安。他把锐利而游移的目光投向前方，显然是在搜寻潜藏在树干后面的敌人；他发现树后什么也没有，便又把目光转向身后，仿佛害怕后面有人在追赶。塞勒斯察觉到父亲又渐渐转回了老方向，尽管心生疑窦却又忍着不去干涉他，况且他那喜好冒险的天性也并不反感行程增长和充满神秘。

到第五天下午，他们停了下来，在日落之前一小时左右就安排好了简陋的宿营地。他们最后走过的几里路上景色变化很大，地势就像凝固的海浪一样凸凹起伏。就在这样一片洼地中，在一个荒凉奇崛之地，一家人搭起了窝棚，点燃了篝火。他们想到全家三口被亲情的坚强纽带维系在一处，与外部世界完全隔绝，不免产生某种既令人心寒又使内心温暖的感觉。黝黑阴森的松树俯视着他们，当风刮过树梢的时候，可以听见森林中枝叶振响出一片哀怜声；是不是那些古树在呻吟，害怕有人来挥动利斧最后砍断它们的根？多卡丝做饭的时候，鲁本和儿子打算出去搜寻猎物，当天沿途上还什么也没有捕猎到哩。儿子保证自己不离开营地附近区域，接着就蹦跳着跑开了，步伐轻快而矫健，就像他希望猎杀的一头野鹿那样。父亲凝视着儿子的背影，心头掠过一阵瞬刻即逝的幸福感，然后准备去相反的方向寻猎。这时候，多卡丝坐在用枯枝落叶燃起的火堆旁；这里有一棵多年前被连根拔起的大树，她就坐在那长满青苔的腐朽的树干上。她时不时地看看在火上快要烧得沸腾的水壶，一面翻看着当年的马萨诸塞历书，这本小册子和一本老式黑体字的《圣经》就是他们家的全部藏书了。对于时间流程中年月日的任意分隔，没有谁会比那些与世隔绝的人更加关注。多卡丝似乎觉得有个情况非常重要，提醒说今天正是五月十二日。丈夫猛然一惊。

“五月十二日！我应该记得很清楚的呀。”他喃喃地说，杂乱的思绪一时涌上心头，“我这是在哪儿？我正在往哪儿去？我把他丢在哪儿啦？”

多卡丝对丈夫难以捉摸的情绪早已见惯不惊了，对他这种表现不以为意。她把历书放在一旁，用哀伤的口气对丈夫说话，那语调流露出一颗温柔的心所怀抱的早已冷却和死灭的悲痛。

“十八年前，大概就是这个日子，我可怜的父亲离开了这个世界。在最后时刻，鲁本，幸亏有一只友爱的手臂在扶着他的头，有一个亲切的声音在鼓舞着他的心。从那时起，一想到你对他的忠诚照料，我就感到安慰。啊，一个人在这样的荒山野林里孤零零地死去，那会是多么可怕啊！”

“向上天祈祷吧，多卡丝，”鲁本哽哽咽咽地说——“祈祷上天保佑我们一家三口谁也别孤零零地死去，抛尸于荒野无人掩埋！”接着他就匆忙地走开，留下妻子在阴暗的松林下照管着篝火。

等到多卡丝的话无意之间带来的痛苦不再那么尖锐，鲁本那匆促的脚步也渐渐放慢下来。可是许多乱七八糟的奇怪念头却在心头蜂拥而至；他胡乱穿行着，不像个猎手而像个梦游者，但他虽说自己并没有刻意去留心，但绕来绕去却总走不出营地周围。他的脚步几乎是在不知不觉地兜圈子；他没有发现自己来到了一处树木浓密地带的边缘，但那些树木并不是松树。这儿长的是橡树和其他各种硬木；树根周围簇生着稠密的灌木丛，但树与树之间还留有一点空隙，被干枯的落叶厚厚地覆盖着。一旦树枝摇曳或者树干枯裂发出声响，就仿佛森林正从沉睡中醒来，鲁本就会本能地举起放在手臂上的滑膛枪，朝四面八方迅速而敏锐地张望；当他相信附近大概没有野兽之后，便又会陷入沉思。他反复思忖是什么奇怪的力量把他从预定路线引开，却把自己远远地带进了荒野的深处。他无法深入到自己的动机所潜藏的心灵隐秘之地，便认定有一种超自然的声音在召唤自己前进，有一种超自然的力量在阻止他后退。他相信上天有意要给他一个赎罪的机会；他希望能够找到那堆久未安葬的遗骨；在用泥土掩埋了它们之后，自己心中的坟墓也就会照射进安宁祥和的阳光了。他正想到这里忽然被惊醒，发现距他转圈的地方不远的森林中发出了一阵沙沙的响声。他觉得有什么东西在一片茂密的灌木丛后面动弹着，便以猎人的本能和老练射手的准确举枪射击。一声低微的呻吟告诉他打中了，甚至野兽也会用这样的声音来表达临死的痛苦，所以鲁本并没有留意。就在此刻，是什么突然闯入了他的记忆呢？

鲁本刚才射中的那片浓密的灌木丛紧靠着一片高地的顶部，它们簇生在一块岩石的脚下，岩石的形状和它那个光滑的表面显得颇似一块巨大的墓碑。这个景象就像反射在镜中一样，唤醒了鲁本的记忆。他甚至认出了那块巨岩上的石纹，仿佛是用早被遗忘的文字镌刻下的碑文；一切都没有改变，只是有一丛浓密的灌木遮挡着巨石的下部，假如麦尔文还坐在那儿，也会被遮掩住了。鲁本站在当年最后站立的地方，就在那棵被连根拔起的大树沾满泥土的树根后面，随即又发现了岁月造成的另一个变化。那棵小橡树，他曾经在梢头绑了一条带血手绢作为自己誓言的象征，已经长得又高又壮，虽未进入壮年期，却也枝叶如盖、浓荫广布。这棵树看上去有一处特别的地方，使鲁本感到胆战心惊。它中部和较低处的枝条生机勃勃，树干上也缠满藤蔓一直延伸到地面，但橡树的上部却显然遭受过摧残，顶部的树枝已萎缩、干枯，全都死了。鲁本想起了那条手巾在树梢枝头上迎风招展的情景，十八年前它是那么葱绿可爱。使它枯萎到底是谁的罪孽呢？

多卡丝在两位猎手离开以后继续准备着晚饭。她的林中餐桌是一棵倾覆的大树的长满苔藓的树干，她在树干最粗的地方铺开了一块雪白的桌布，摆放了留存下来的几件亮光闪闪的白镴餐具，这套餐具曾是她在拓居地引以为自豪的东西。在孤寂的大自然心脏地带有这么一个小小的充满家庭慰藉的处所，真是奇特的景象。阳光还在高地生长的树木梢头流连，但在宿营地所在的洼地里暮色已渐深浓；篝火烧得更红了，照亮了松林高高的树干，在环绕空地的浓密阴暗的叶簇之上闪烁着。多卡丝心中并不感到哀伤；因为她觉得与其置身于一群并不关心她的人当中孤独度日，倒不如跟随两个心爱的人在荒野中旅行。她一边忙着摆好两块朽木，在上面铺放树叶，好给丈夫和儿子当座位，一边唱起青年时代学会的一支歌曲，歌声抑扬起伏地荡漾在森林中。这支粗陋的曲调是一位无名歌手的作品，描绘的是冬夜中一所边境茅屋里，一家人安然地避开狂飙积雪的野蛮袭击，待在自家炉火边其乐融融。整首歌曲含有独创构思所特具的那种无以名状的魅力，而四句不断反复的歌词则好像是一片炉火中特别明亮的火光，激情讴歌着他们的欢悦之情。诗人借助几个简单的字词赋予歌曲以魔力，熔铸进了亲人之爱和天伦之乐的精粹，简直是将诗与画融为了一体。多卡丝这样歌唱着，仿佛又重新置身于已被抛离的家园之中；她的眼前不再是那片阴暗的松林，她的耳中也听不见风声，在她每次开始唱一段歌词的时候，风声就像在树枝间发出一声沉重的呼吸，然后在歌声的重压下化为空洞的叹息声渐渐消逝。营地附近的一声枪响猛地惊醒了她；要么是因为突发的枪声，要么是她在篝火边感到孤独，她突然浑身剧烈战抖。接着她又充满母亲的自豪大声笑起来。

“我那出色的小猎手！我的儿子打死了一只鹿！”她想到传来枪声的地方正是赛勒斯出猎的方向，便高声喊道。

她等了一阵子，想来该听见儿子轻快的脚步踏着沙沙响的落叶来报告成功的消息了。可是他并没有立刻出现；于是她发出欢快的声音，在丛林中去寻找儿子。

“赛勒斯！赛勒斯！”

仍然迟迟不见儿子到来；她心想枪声分明距离很近，便决定亲自去寻找他。再说，也许有必要帮忙把鹿肉搬回来，那是她引以为自豪的儿子猎取的啊。于是她动身沿着早已消失的枪声的方向走去，边走边唱着歌，为的是让孩子知道她来了，跑过来迎接她。在每棵大树的树身后，在每丛矮树浓密的叶簇中，她都希望能发现儿子的面孔，正出于爱意而调皮地哈哈大笑着。太阳此刻已落下了地平线，透过树枝投下的余晖十分朦胧，在她满怀期待的想象中制造了许多幻象。有好几次，她似乎隐约看见儿子的面孔从枝叶间向外探望；还有一次，她想象他就站在一块峻峭的岩石脚底在向她点头。然而她定睛一看，结果只不过是一棵橡树，树干上细枝环生一直长到地面，其中一枝比其余的伸得更长，被微风吹得摇摆不停。她绕着岩石脚下走了一圈，突然发现自己就在丈夫的面前，他是从另一个方向过来的。他身子靠着枪托，枪口向下抵着地面的枯叶，看来正全神贯注地打量着脚下的什么东西。

“这是怎么回事，鲁本？你杀了那头野鹿又望着它睡着啦？”多卡丝高声说，她刚一看见他那个姿势和表情就快乐地笑了起来。

鲁本一动也不动，眼光也不朝她这边看一眼；一股不明来源和对象的冷冰冰的、令人战栗的恐惧开始潜入她的血液。现在她发现丈夫的脸色惨白，五官僵硬，仿佛强烈的绝望感使他的表情凝固了，除此之外再也不能有任何其他表情。他丝毫没有显示出自己觉察到她在走近。

“看在上帝分上，鲁本，对我说话呀！”多卡丝大叫道；她自己奇异的声音甚至比死一般的寂静更令她恐惧。

丈夫猛然一惊，瞪着她的脸，把她拉到巨石前面，用手一指。

啊，儿子就躺在那里，睡着了，却不会做梦，就躺在一堆落叶上！他的脸颊枕在一只胳膊上——他的鬈发从额前拂向脑后——他的四肢微微软瘫着。是突然袭来的疲乏压垮了小猎手吗？妈妈的声音会把他唤醒吗？她知道儿子已经死了。

“这块宽阔的岩石就是你亲人的墓碑，多卡丝，”丈夫道，“你的泪将同时洒在你父亲和你儿子的身上。”

她听不见他说的话。带着一声狂厉的尖叫，那似乎是从不幸者灵魂的最深处被逼出来的，她毫无知觉地瘫倒在死去的儿子身旁。就在这一瞬刻，那棵橡树顶部的枯萎树枝在凝止的空气中忽然断裂，化作柔软轻盈的碎片落下，落在巨石上，落在枯叶上，落在鲁本身上，落在他妻子和孩子身上，也落在罗杰·麦尔文的遗骨上。鲁本的心受到猛然一击，泪水像岩间山泉一样迸流而出。当初带伤的青年立下的誓言，由那位受损害者亲自来兑现了。鲁本的罪过赎清了——他身上的诅咒消除了；就在他付出比自己的血更宝贵的血作为代价的时刻，一声祈祷，许多年来的第一声祈祷，从鲁本·伯恩的唇间升向了天堂。

能预言的画像

“这位画家可真了不起！”沃尔特·勒德洛兴奋地喊道，“他不仅在他那门特殊技艺上非常出色，还拥有关于所有其他的学术和科学的广博知识。他用希伯来语同马瑟博士谈话，又对博尔斯顿博士阐述解剖学。一句话，他在自己熟悉的领域里可以同我们当中受过最好教育的人相媲美。此外，他还是一位优雅的绅士——一位世界公民——是的，一位真正的世界主义者；因为他除了能讲我们森林地区的语言而外，讲起地球上任何地区和国家的语言来都像土生土长的人一样，他现在正要去周游世界。所有这一切还并非是我最佩服他的地方。”

“真的！”埃莉诺说，她一直带着女人的兴趣倾听着对这么一位男人的描述，“这就已经够令人钦佩的啦。”

“那是当然，”她的情人回答说，“可是远远比不上他适应形形色色人物的那种天生禀赋，所有的男人——包括所有的女人，埃莉诺——都能在这位了不起的画家身上看见自己的镜中影像。不过，最惊人的地方我还没有告诉你呢。”

“别说啦，如果他还有比这些更了不起的才能，”埃莉诺大笑着说，“这位可怜的先生住在波士顿可就危险啦。你是在跟我说一位画家呢还是巫师呢？”

“说老实话，”他回答道，“你这个问题或许比你所设想的要严重得多啦。人们说他不仅能画出一个人的相貌，还能画出他的思想和心灵。他捕捉到人的秘密感情和情欲，把它们投掷到画布上，就像一道阳光——或者说，如果在心灵阴暗的人的肖像上，就像一簇地狱之火的闪光。这真是一种可怕的才能，”沃尔特把热烈的语调压低，又接着说，“我几乎不敢坐下来让他画像。”

“沃尔特，你这话是当真的吗？”埃莉诺惊呼道。

“看在上帝分上，亲爱的埃莉诺，别让他画下你现在这副表情。”她的情人笑着说，不过笑中含有困惑，“好啦；那种神情现在消失了，不过你说话的时候好像害怕得要死，而且显得非常哀伤。你刚才在想什么？”

“没想什么，没想什么。”埃莉诺急忙回答道，“你在用自己的幻想画我的脸。好啦，明天来叫我，我们一道去拜访拜访这位了不起的画家。”

可是当年轻人离开之后，他的情人的年轻而美丽的脸上又分明出现了那副引人注目的表情。那是一种忧伤而焦虑的神情，与一个少女在结婚前夕应有的心情很不相符。然而，沃尔特·勒德洛又的确是她芳心所属的人。

“表情！”埃莉诺自语道，“假如它所表露的正是我有时内心的感觉，也难怪会让他吃惊了。根据自己的经验，我知道这种表情是多么可怕。不过这全都出于想象。我当时根本就不在意——后来也没有再见过这种表情——我只是梦见过它。”

于是她便忙着做一条绉领上的刺绣，请人画肖像的时候她打算戴上这条绉领。

他们刚才一直谈论的那位画家并不是当地土生土长的艺术家中的一位。那些艺术家生活在比故事发生之时更晚的时代，他们借用印第安人使用的色彩，用野兽的毛发制作画笔。这位画家假如能够召回自己的生命、重新安排自己命运的话，或许也会选择加入这种并无大师的画派，希望自己至少能够展示独创性，因为这一画派既无作品可模仿，也无法则须遵循。可是他却出生在欧洲，受教育也在欧洲。据说他曾经精研过艺术构思的崇高与优美，遍览了悬挂于陈列室和画廊中、描绘在教堂墙壁上的所有著名画作，体悟过出自大师之手的每一处神来之笔，直到再也没有什么可供强有力的大脑学习时为止。艺术已经无法再教给他任何东西，但是大自然却可以。因此，他就去探访艺术同行们从未涉足过的世界，饱览那些至今尚未被移植到画布上去的崇高与美丽的形象。贫乏的美洲不足以对这位杰出的艺术家产生别的任何诱惑，尽管许多殖民地上层人士在画师到来时就表示过希望，想借助他的技艺将自己的形象留给后代子孙。只要有人提出这类要求，他就会用锐利的目光紧盯住请求者，仿佛要把人家里里外外看个透。如果他看到的只是一张圆润柔滑、优裕自得的面孔，那么即使有黄金镶边的套子来装饰画像，又有许多金币作为画资，他也会彬彬有礼地拒绝这件工作和这份酬劳。但是如果他看到的这张面孔显示出某种不同寻常之处，无论是在思想、感情或者经历方面；如果他在街头碰见一个乞丐，长着雪白的胡须和布满皱纹的额头；如果有时遇见一个小孩子碰巧抬头微笑，他就会竭尽自己绝不屈服于金钱的全部技艺来描绘他们。

绘画技艺在殖民地是如此稀罕，所以这位画家也就成了众人好奇的目标。不过很少有人或根本就无人能够欣赏他作品的艺术成就，但在有些要点上众人的见解倒也与业余爱好者的正确评价具有相同价值。画家观察自己的每幅画作在这类缺乏素养的观众身上所产生的影响，并从他们的评论中引出教益，尽管在议论他这个似乎要跟大自然一争高下的画家的时候，他们同时也就想到要对大自然加以指点。必须承认，在他们的赞赏中糅杂着这个时代和这个国家的种种偏见。有些人认为，把上帝创造的这些活生生的形象画出来是对摩西律法(1)的悖逆，甚至是对造物主的放肆嘲弄。另一些人则对画家能够随意唤起幽灵、将死人的形体保留在活人中间感到惊骇，倾向于把画家看作魔法师，或者古老巫术时代著名的魔鬼，换了新的伪装来捣蛋作乱。持有这种愚蠢念头的人竟占民众的半数以上。甚至在上层人士社会圈子里，人们也对他怀着一种模模糊糊的敬畏感，这种敬畏感就部分而言是像烟圈一样从公众的迷信中散发出来的，但主要是由于他的画技能够运用变化多端的知识与才能。

处于结婚前夕，沃尔特·勒德洛和埃莉诺急切地想得到他们的肖像，他们无疑希望让这两幅画像成为未来一系列家庭画像中的第一批。在上述那次谈话后的第二天，他们就去登门拜访画家。仆人领他们进入一套公寓，虽然没有见到画家本人，这里却有不少令他们肃然起敬的人物。他们明白，这些都只不过是画像，但又觉得无法把如此惟妙惟肖的肖像同画中人物的生命与智慧分离开来。好几幅肖像上的人他们都认识，要么是当时的显赫人物，要么就是与他们有私交的熟人。有伯内特总督，就像刚刚收到众议院一份不负责任的通报，正在写一篇措辞尖锐的回复。库克先生就挂在他所反对的统治者旁边，神情坚毅，又有些拘谨，正符合一位民众领袖的形象。威廉·菲普斯爵士的那位老迈的夫人从墙上瞪着他们，她戴着一圈绉领，穿着一件用鲸骨环撑大的女裙——一个傲慢专横的老贵妇，人们还猜测她会巫术。约翰·温斯洛当时还很年轻，满脸洋溢着征战疆场的豪情，多年以后他终于成了一位战功卓著的将军。至于他们的私交，只要望一眼就能辨认。在大多数画像中，人物的心灵和性格都透过容貌表现出来，凝聚为一种独特的神态，因此可以说一句自相矛盾的话，即使画像的原型人物都不如画像那样酷似他们自己。

在这些现代名人当中，还有两位古老的大胡子圣徒，他们几乎消隐进日渐变黑的画布中了。还有一位虽然脸色苍白却容颜不减的圣母玛丽亚，她大概曾在罗马受到过礼拜，现在正用那么温柔圣洁的目光注视着这对恋人，以致他们也渴望顶礼膜拜了。

“想来多么奇怪啊，”沃尔特·勒德洛说，“这张美丽的脸两百多年来一直都这么美！啊，但愿一切美的事物都能如此经久不衰！你不妒忌她吗，埃莉诺？”

“假如尘世变成了天堂，我也许会妒忌，”她回答道，“可是在一切事物都会衰败的地方，做一个容颜不改的人是多么痛苦啊！”

“这个黑黝黝的老头子圣彼得带着一副又狠又丑的怒容，尽管他是个圣徒，”沃尔特接着说，“他让我心烦意乱。不过圣母看来对我们还算和蔼。”

“是的；不过，我觉得她显得很忧伤。”埃莉诺说。

这三幅旧画下面还支着一个画架，上面架着一幅最近才着手的画像。他们稍微察看一下以后，辨认出了他们自己的牧师科尔曼博士的容貌，就像从一片云彩里渐渐演化出了形体与生命。

“慈爱的老头儿！”埃莉诺叫道，“他瞧着我的样子就像要说出一句父辈的忠告似的。”

“而他望着我，”沃尔特说，“仿佛要摇摇头，为了某件猜想中的罪过而训斥我。不过他本人就是这个样子。我们不站在他面前结成夫妻，因为我在他的目光下是绝不会感到轻松自在的。”

就在这时，他们听到了脚步声，回过头来便看见了画家；他进屋来已经有一阵子了，也听见了他们的一些议论。他是个中年人，相貌倒颇值得他自己画上一画。的确，凭着他那身华贵的服装，虽然独具特色但又搭配得漫不经心，或许还因为他的心灵总是留驻在画内人物当中，所以他自己也多少有些像一幅画像了。两位客人觉察到这位艺术家同他的作品之间存在着某种亲缘关系，觉得好像是一位画中人物从画布上走下来跟他们打招呼似的。

沃尔特·勒德洛同画家有几分相熟，便向他解释来访的目的。在他说话的时候，一道阳光正好斜照在他与埃莉诺身上，造成了极为愉悦的效果，似乎使他们构成了一幅青春与美的活画图，而充满光明的未来命运更为此增添了欢快的气氛。艺术家显然深受触动。

“我的画架还要被占用好几天，而且我在波士顿的停留时间也很短。”画家若有所思地说，接着敏锐地看了他们一眼，又补充道，“不过你们的愿望将得到满足，虽说这让首席法官和奥利弗夫人失望。我不能丢失这个好机会，因为能在几厄尔(2)的细平布和锦缎上画画。”

画家表示他打算把两幅肖像融合在一幅画中，描绘他们的某个适宜的姿势。这个计划本来应该让一对恋人感到高兴的，可是他们不得不加以拒绝，因为这么大的画幅对他们打算用这幅画去装饰的那个房间不合适。这样，最后决定画两幅半身肖像。在他们告辞出来之后，沃尔特·勒德洛笑着问埃莉诺是否知道画家将对他们的命运具有怎样的影响。

“波士顿的老太太们都断言，”他接着说，“这位画家掌握了一个人的脸孔和身形之后，就可以按任何动作或任何情境把他画出来——那幅画还能预言未来。你相信吗？”

“不怎么相信。”埃莉诺笑着说，“不过即使他有这种魔力，看他的举止那么温文尔雅，我肯定他也会运用得很正当。”

画家选择了同时进行两幅画的方式，并用他时常使用的那种玄妙莫测的语言提出一个理由，说是两张面孔可以相互映照衬托。于是他时而画一笔沃尔特，时而又画一笔埃莉诺，两人的容貌开始栩栩如生地出现在画布上，仿佛他那臻于圆熟的技艺真能让他们的形象从画布上跳脱出来似的。在那片丰富的亮光和浓重的阴影中，他们看到的简直就是自己的幻影。不过，尽管形象能够完全达到酷似，他们对表情却并不感到十分满意；看来跟大多数画家的作品相比要更模糊一些。然而画家本人却对预期的成功颇为满意，而且因为对两位恋人深感兴趣，他还利用空闲时间，在他们不知道的情况下，为他们画了一张彩色铅笔的素描画。在他们坐着当模特的时候，他总是设法让他们同他谈话，从而在他们的面孔上激发出个性特征，尽管这样一来他们的表情会不停地变化，但他的目的正是要把一切结合起来并固定下来。最后他宣布说，他们只要再来一次，两幅画就可以完成并交付了。

“如果我的笔忠于我的构思，只要再按我的思考添加几笔，”他说，“这两幅画就将成为我最出色的作品。说实话，一个艺术家很少遇见这样好的主题。”

他一边说，一边仍然用他那富于穿透力的目光望着他们，一直目送他们走到楼梯底层。

在人类虚荣心的整个范围内，再没有什么比让人画一幅自己的肖像更能控制想象力的了。为什么会这样呢？镜子也罢，壁炉柴架上光亮的小球也罢，明净如镜的水面也罢，包括所有其他种种能反射影像的表面，都会不断地使我们看到自己的肖像，或者毋宁说看到自己的幻影，但我们瞥上一眼，立即就会忘掉它们。我们所以会忘掉它们，只因为它们会消失。而正是持久的观念——尘世不朽的观念——给我们自己的肖像赋予了如此神秘的兴味。沃尔特与埃莉诺当然不会没有这种感觉，因此他们按照预约的时间准时赶到画家的住处，去迎接那两幅将自己的形象留存给子孙后代的肖像。阳光照耀着他们进入那套房间，但门被关上之后室内却显得有些阴暗。

他们的目光立刻被自己的肖像吸引，这两幅画是靠在房间最远端的墙上的。透过朦胧的光线与距离，他们一眼就看见肖像与自己的惯常姿势和自己所熟悉的神态毫厘不差，不禁同时发出了快乐的惊叫。

“我们就站在那儿，”沃尔特激动地喊道，“永远身披阳光！脸上绝不会有阴郁的神情！”

“是呀，”埃莉诺较为平静地说，“也不会有恼人的变化来使我们忧伤。”

他们一边这样说一边往前靠近，因为还没有把画像完全看清。画家在同他们打过招呼之后，就一直忙着在桌前完成一幅铅笔素描，让客人自己去对他已完成的作品加以品评。他不时从深浓的双眉下投来一道目光，观察他们面容的侧影，这时他的画笔也在那幅素描上静止不动了。就这样，两位客人都在对方的肖像前站了一阵子，用入迷似的专注眼光凝视着，但都一声不吭。最后，沃尔特上前一步——接着又退回去——在不同的光线下审视着埃莉诺的肖像，终于开口了。

“没有一点儿变化吗？”他用疑虑而思忖的语气说，“是的；我看得越久，就越觉得发生了一点儿变化。当然这和我昨天所看到的是同一幅画；这身衣服——这副容貌——一切都相同；可是总有什么地方改变了。”

“那么，这幅画没有昨天那么像她本人啦？”画家这时走过来问道，显示出压抑不住的兴趣。

“埃莉诺的相貌画得无懈可击，”沃尔特回答说，“第一眼望去，神情也跟她一模一样。不过，在我久久观看的时候，总觉得画像上的面部表情改变了。那双眼睛在用奇怪的忧伤而焦虑的目光紧盯着我。不，那是悲痛和恐惧！这像埃莉诺吗？”

“比较一下她的脸和画上的脸。”画家说。

沃尔特斜着目光看了看他的情人，不禁大吃一惊。埃莉诺一丝不动，全神贯注——仿佛着了迷似的——正凝视着沃尔特的肖像，这时她脸上的表情同他刚才所抱怨的分毫不差。就算她在镜子前面演练上一个又一个钟头，也不能如此成功地把握住这种表情。即使这幅画是一面镜子，也不能把她现在的模样映照得更真切更令人抑郁了。她对艺术家和她的情人之间的谈话似乎浑然不觉。

“埃莉诺，”沃尔特惊骇地喊道，“你发生了什么变化啊？”

她没有听见他的话，也没有收回她凝视的目光，直到他一把抓住她的手，吸引了她的注意力为止。这时她才突然一震，从画像转过来望着画中人的脸。

“你没有在自己的画像里看出什么变化吗？”她问道。

“我的画像？——没有呀！”沃尔特回答，同时仔细审视着画像。“不过还是让我看一看！不错，有点微小的变化——我想，是画得更好了，虽然依旧是那么相像。表情比昨天更生动，仿佛目光里闪现出某种欢快的念头，就要从唇间吐露出来似的。我一旦看出了这种神情，它就变得明确无疑了。”

在他目不转睛地进行观察时，埃莉诺回头去看画家。她怀着悲伤和敬畏注视着他，并感到他也以同情和怜悯在回报她，虽然对其中的缘由她只能做朦胧的猜测。

“那种神情！”她悄声说，浑身在战抖，“怎么到画里去的？”

“小姐，”画家忧伤地说，同时握住她的手，把她引到旁边去，“这两幅画中，我所画的都是自己看见的东西。艺术家——真正的艺术家——必须深入到表象之下去探看。这就是他的才能——他最自豪却又常常是令人悲哀的才能——要看到人的心灵深处，并凭借一种甚至自己都无法解释的力量，通过能表达人们长年思想感情的目光，使心灵在画布上光彩焕发或者阴沉暗淡。但愿我能让自己相信，眼前这一例是我的一次失误！”

他们现在走近了那张桌子，桌上的画页里有粉笔画的人头像，有几乎与平常面孔一样富于表现力的手，有爬满青藤的教堂塔楼，有茅草屋顶的农舍，有遭雷电劈击的老树，有东方与古代的服装，以及一位艺术家在闲暇时刻产生的诸如此类的奇思异想。他一页页翻过去，仿佛漫不经心地露出了一张画着两个人像的铅笔素描。

“要是我画得不好，”他接着说，“要是你发现你的心灵没有反映在自己的肖像上——要是你出于什么秘密的原因而不相信我对另一幅画的描绘——现在动手修改它们还不算太晚。我也可以改变画上人物的动作。不过，这样就会对事情的发展产生影响吗？”

他把她的注意力引到了那张素描上。一阵毛骨悚然的感觉袭遍了埃莉诺的全身；她口中差点儿发出一声尖叫；但她克制住了，所有将恐惧与痛苦的思绪深藏心底的人都惯于这样自我克制。她从桌边转过头去，发现沃尔特已经走近得可以看见那张素描了，不过她还不能确定它是否已经引起了他的注意。

“我们不愿再改动那两幅画了，”她急忙说，“如果说我的那幅神情悲伤，那我以后只好显得更快乐些，好与它对照。”

“就这样吧。”画家回答说，鞠了一躬，“但愿你的忧伤都是想象的产物，只有你的画像会因此而悲哀！而你的快乐——但愿它们是真实而深沉的，会画在这张可爱的脸上，直到它证明我的艺术是虚假的！”

沃尔特与埃莉诺结婚之后，这两幅画像就成了他们寓所中最富光彩的装饰品。它们并排地挂在一起，只隔着一块窄窄的镶板，似乎一直在相互凝视着，却又总在回报观看者的目光。游历广泛的先生们熟知这一类绘画题材，认为这两幅画是现代肖像中最值得赞赏的典范作品；普通观众则拿它们同人物原型作比较，将面貌特征一一对比，欣喜若狂地赞叹它的惟妙惟肖。然而只有对第三种人——既非游历广泛的艺术鉴赏家，又非普通观众，而是那些天性敏感的人——这两幅画像才产生了最强烈的效果。这类人开始时会漫不经心地看一看，但在逐渐发生兴趣之后，便会一天接一天地重来这里，像研究一卷神秘的书那样细细琢磨画中人的面孔。沃尔特·勒德洛的肖像最早吸引他们的注意力。当他本人和他的新娘不在场的时候，他们常常会为画家试图在他面部体现的表情进行争论。他们一致同意那是一种意味深长的表情，不过没有哪两个人的解释是相似的。对于埃莉诺的肖像则较少意见分歧。的确，在试图评价她脸上那种阴郁神情的性质和程度时会见仁见智，但大家都同意那就是阴郁，而且与他们的这位妙龄女友的天性迥然相异。某位想入非非的客人竟声称在细加察看之后，结果发现两幅画是同一构思的两部分，埃莉诺脸上那种忧郁的情感力量与沃尔特脸上更加强烈的感情（或者按他的话说，是疯狂的激情）是相互关联的。他虽然并无绘画技能，竟亲自动手画起一张草图来，图中显示两个人物的动作是和他们共同的表情相呼应的。

随着一天天过去，朋友们中间有了悄声议论，说是埃莉诺脸上正笼罩上了一层越来越浓的郁郁沉思的表情，恐怕要不了多久就会使她成为自己忧郁画像的逼真副本了。另一方面，沃尔特不但没有获得画家在画布上赋予他的那种生动神情，反而变得寡言少语、萎靡不振了，不论内心郁积着什么情绪，绝不会流露半分。过了一段时间后，埃莉诺在两幅画像前挂上了一块绣满花朵、缀着粗重金色流苏的华丽的紫色丝帘，借口说灰尘会使画像的色彩灰暗，光照会使画像变得模糊。这就够了。客人们感到这块褶皱重重的丝帘是绝不能拉开的，当着女主人的面也绝不能提起画像的事。

时光流逝，画家又来到这里。他曾经远行天下，到北方去看水晶山那银白色的瀑布，从新英格兰最高的山顶上俯瞰浩瀚的云海林涛。但他并不用自己的艺术模仿来亵渎那些景象。他也曾躺在独木舟中荡漾于乔治湖的怀抱，让自己的心灵像镜子一样映照出它的秀丽与壮观，直到梵蒂冈的艺术收藏品中没有一幅画能比他的记忆更生动。他曾经与印第安猎人一道去过尼亚加拉大瀑布，并在那里再次绝望地把画笔抛下悬崖；他觉得自己倘若能画出汇聚成这大瀑布奇观的种种成分，倒不如说也能画出它如雷的喧嚣声了。事实上，他很少产生描摹自然景色的冲动，除非是为描绘充满思想、激情与苦痛的人的形体和面孔提供一个框架。他以这番冒险漫游所积累的见闻充实了自己：印第安酋长冷峻的尊严神态，皮肤黝黑的印第安少女的妩媚，印第安棚屋内的家庭生活，隐秘无声的行军，阴暗松林里的战斗，边境线上的军营要塞，生于宫廷却老于荒野沙漠的老法兰西党人的变异，这些就是他速写下来的景象和人像。危急关头的激情，狂暴情感的闪现，凶猛力量的搏斗——爱情、仇恨、悲痛、疯狂，总而言之，古老地球上所有疲惫心灵以新的形式向他展示的一切。他的画夹中满是他记忆储存的形象例证，天才将把它们转化为自己的财富，并赋予它们不朽性。他感到自己终于找到了一直在寻求的艺术的深刻智慧。

但是，置身于严酷或可爱的大自然怀抱里，身处于森林险境或它无边的宁静中，始终有两个幻影一路陪伴着他。就像整个身心被某种专注目的缠绕的其他所有人一样，他与人类大众相互隔绝。他没有目标——没有欢乐——没有同情——除了同他的艺术具有终极关系的一切。尽管他的风度举止优雅高尚，意愿与行动正直不阿，但他并不具备慈爱的情感：他的心是冰冷的，没有任何有生命的事物能充分接近他而使他温暖。然而，对这两个人他却发生了最强烈的兴趣，这种兴趣总能使他与他笔下的题材联为一体。他以敏锐的洞察力探究过他们的心灵，并通过自己的最高技巧将其结果绘入他们的容貌中，几乎达到了任何天才也不曾企及的那个标准，也就是他自己严格的艺术观念。他从未来的一片幽暗中捕捉到了——至少他想象是如此——一个可怕的秘密，并将这个秘密隐隐约约地透露在两幅肖像中。他自己——他的想象力和所有其他力量——在研究沃尔特与埃莉诺时耗费的代价是如此之大，以致他几乎把他们视为自己的创造物了，正像他在绘画领域中创造出的成千形象一样。因此，他们真的就在林间暮色中飞掠着，在飞瀑的雾霭中翱翔着，从平滑如镜的湖面上眺望着，也绝不会在正午的阳光下消失。他们时时呈现在他生动的想象中，不是生者的拙劣模仿物，也不是死者的苍白幽灵，而只是借助于肖像的外观，各自带着他用魔法从心灵洞穴中唤醒的那种不变的表情。他在重渡大西洋之前，非得再看一看两幅奇幻画像的原型不可。

“啊，辉煌的艺术！”热情洋溢的画家一边走在街道上一边沉思着，“你就是造物主自身的形象。无数在虚空中游荡的形体，只要你一点头就开始了生命，死去的事物又复活了。你把它们召唤回往昔的情境，给它们灰暗的阴影赋予更美好生命的光彩，使它们既是现世的又是永恒的。你把历史那些飞逝的瞬间夺了回来。对你而言往昔并不存在，因为只要你轻轻一触，一切伟大的东西就永远成为现实；杰出的人物会世代永生，让人目睹他们展示其杰出的行为。啊，威力无边的艺术！既然你能将朦胧显露的往昔带入阳光照耀的狭窄地带，也就是我们所说的现时，那么你能不能召唤隐藏着的未来与往昔同在现时汇聚呢？我还未曾做到这一点吗？难道我不是你的预言家吗？”

就这样，他怀着自豪的却又是阴郁的激情，几乎要高声喊叫起来，一边穿行在令他厌烦的街道上，身边的人们既不了解也不在乎他的白日梦。一个人独自怀着勃勃雄心并不是一件好事情。除非周围还有别的人为他提供榜样以调节自己，否则他的思想、欲求和希望会变得狂放无羁，他本人或许也会真正变成一个疯子。这位画家在以近乎超自然的敏锐洞察力探知别人的心灵时，却没有看到自己心灵的错乱。

“应该是这幢房子，”他在敲门之前先上下看了看建筑的正面，“愿上帝保佑我的记忆！那张画！我想它永远不会消失。不论我是看窗户还是看门，它总是框在里面，笔触浑厚有力，浓重的色彩光芒四射——画像中的两张面孔——素描里两个人的身形与动作！”

他敲门。

“那两幅画像！在里面吗？”他问仆人，接着便镇静下来——“你家主人和太太！他们在家吗？”

“在家，先生，”仆人说，他注意到画家那种无法摆脱的别具一格的模样，又补充道，“画像也在！”

客人被让进了客厅，客厅中间有道门通往大小相同的里间。因为外间空无一人，他就向通往里间的那道门走去，随即看到了两位主人的肖像，也看到了他们本人，这两个人正是他长期以来异常感兴趣的对象。他不自觉地在门口停住了脚步。

他们并未觉察到他的到来。沃尔特与埃莉诺正站在画像前，沃尔特已经把那块华丽宽大的重叠丝帘揭开，一只手抓着丝帘上金色的流苏，另一手紧抱着他的新娘。那幅遮蔽数月的画像再次呈现出它毫不衰减的光彩，似乎在满屋里投射下一道幽暗的光，而不是被外在的光线照亮。埃莉诺的肖像简直具有预言性。一种忧思，接着是一种温柔的哀伤，已经相继留驻在她的面容上，随着时光的流逝而加深，最后化为一种宁静的痛苦。如今倘若再掺进一分恐惧，就酷似画像上的表情了。沃尔特满脸阴郁和呆滞，或者说只偶尔闪现一点活力，随后则因短暂的活跃而变得更加阴沉。他的目光从埃莉诺脸上移到她的肖像上，然后再移到自己的肖像上，最后全神贯注地站在那儿沉思着。

画家仿佛听见命运之神的脚步正从他身后逼近，正在朝它的牺牲者走来。一个古怪的念头猛然跳进了脑海。他自己难道不正是命运体现的形式吗？难道他不就是自己所预示的这场即将到来的灾难的罪魁祸首吗？

沃尔特仍然在画像前面沉默着，仿佛在用自己的心与画像交谈，听任自己接受画家撒播在肖像面容之间的邪恶魔力的摆布。他的双眼逐渐燃起了火光；埃莉诺望着他脸上那越来越狂乱的神情，自己的脸上也泛起了恐惧。待到他终于转身向着她的时候，两个人的面容竟然都与他们的肖像一模一样。

“命运落在我们头上了！”沃尔特号叫道，“死吧！”

他拔出一把刀来，趁埃莉诺往地上倒的时候一把扶住她，把刀对准她的胸膛。在他们的动作中，在他们各自的神情和姿态中，画家看到了他那幅素描中的两个人物。那幅画终于以可怕的有声有色的形式完成了。

“住手，疯子！”他厉声喝道。

他此刻从门边冲上前去，横挡在两个可怜的人中间，觉得自己具有扭转他们命运的力量，就像他觉得自己能够改变画布上的景物一样。他站在那儿就像是一位魔法师，控制着被他召唤来的两个幽灵。

“什么！”沃尔特·勒德洛嘟哝着说，同时从狂热的激奋堕入无声的忧伤，“命运之神会阻挡自己的判决吗？”

“不幸的女人！”画家说，“我不是警告过你吗？”

“你警告过。”埃莉诺平静地回答，她这时恢复了刚才被恐惧扰乱的宁静的忧伤，“但是——我爱他！”

这个故事中不是包含着一种深刻的寓意吗？我们某种行为或所有行为的后果若能被预先显示并摆在我们面前，有些人会把它称作命运，急匆匆地冲向前，另一些人则会被自己的热切欲望席卷而去，没有谁会因能预言的画像而改变方向。

————————————————————

(1) 摩西律法（the Mosaic Law）：《圣经·旧约》载摩西率领犹太人出埃及，并制定律法。

(2) 厄尔（ell）：西方旧时度量布匹的长度单位，等于45英寸。

美的艺术家

一位老人，手挽着他漂亮的女儿，正沿街走着。他们从多云的黄昏的暮色中走出来，踏进从一家小店橱窗里投射到人行道上的光明之中。那是一爿向外凸出的橱窗；橱窗里悬挂着各种各样的表，有铜锌合金的，有银质的，也有一两块金质的，表的正面都背对着街道，仿佛吝啬地拒绝告诉路人现在是几点钟了。店内有一个年轻人横坐窗前，苍白的面孔正专注地低俯在一件精巧的机械上方，一盏带罩的灯把集中的光线投射在那东西上面。

“欧文·沃兰在干什么啊？”老彼得·霍文顿喃喃自语道，他本人是一位退休的钟表匠，也是这个年轻人从前的师父，所以很想知道他现在干的是什么活计。“这家伙到底在干什么？这六个月来我每次路过他的店铺，都看见他像这样一动不动地干活儿。这倒是远离了他素来想寻求永恒运动的愚蠢念头；不过我对自己的老行当太熟悉不过了，敢肯定他现在这么忙着的绝不是钟表的什么机械零件。”

“父亲，”安妮说，她对这个问题并没有表现出太大的兴趣，“也许欧文正在发明一种新的计时器呢。我肯定他有足够的独创性。”

“呸，孩子！他那点儿独创性根本做不出比荷兰玩具更好的东西来，”她父亲回答道，欧文·沃兰那种别出心裁的才能一直让他大为光火，“让这种独创性见鬼去吧！我只知道它的全部结果，就是把我店里几块最好的表鼓捣得走不准了。就像我刚才说过的，要是他那种独创性能弄出比小孩玩具更好的东西，那他会把太阳也弄得越出轨道，把整个时间进程也弄得乱七八糟。”

“嘘，父亲！他听见你的说话声了！”安妮悄声说，同时紧紧抱住老人的胳膊，“他的耳朵就跟他的感情一样敏感，你知道他是多么容易动感情。我们走吧。”

于是彼得·霍文顿与女儿安妮停止了交谈，继续朝前走，一直走进镇里的一条小街，经过一家铁匠铺敞开的店门前。店子里面有座锻铁炉，随着皮革风箱巨大的肺吸进和呼出空气的往复运动，时而烈焰腾腾，照亮又高又黑的屋顶，时而火光又只是照亮炉前一小块洒满煤屑的地面。凭借断续的光亮，很容易辨认出店铺远处角落里的种种物件和挂在墙上的马蹄铁；在亮光暗淡的短暂时刻，炉火似乎只在漫无边际的空间中闪耀着微光。铁匠的身影就在这红光闪耀和朦胧昏暗的交替之中不停晃动，这一幅明暗对照的生动图画真是值得观赏，那明亮的火焰在同黑沉沉的暗夜互相搏斗，仿佛每一方都想从对方那里把铁匠的优美力量抢夺过来。不一会儿，他就从炭火中抽出一根烧得白热的铁条，放在铁砧上，举起强有力的胳膊，身影很快就被无数的火星包裹起来，那些火星被他的铁锤敲打得纷纷扬扬地洒落进周围的昏暗中。

“嘿，真是赏心悦目的景象，”老钟表匠说，“我懂得雕琢黄金是怎么一回事；可是说千道万，我还是觉得当个铁匠最棒。他的工夫都花在实实在在的东西上。你说呢，女儿？”

“请别这么大声说话，父亲，”安妮悄声道，“罗伯特·丹福思会听见的。”

“他听见又有什么关系？”彼得·霍文顿说，“我再说一遍，靠花大力气和干实在活儿，靠铁匠的光乎乎的粗壮胳膊挣面包，那是诚实和健全的事情。钟表匠的脑袋却被一个齿轮里再套许多齿轮搅得昏天黑地，要么弄垮了身体，要么损坏了视力，就像我一样，一到中年或者刚过中年就发现自己做不了这个行当了，别的行当又干不了，还穷得不足以过上安心日子。所以我要再说一遍，我宁愿要体力而不要钱。还有，这能够赶走一个人脑袋里的荒唐念头！难道你听说过有哪个铁匠会像那边的欧文·沃兰那么傻头傻脑的吗？”

“说得好，霍文顿大叔！”罗伯特·丹福思从锻炉那边高喊道，声音饱满、深沉而快活，连屋顶都发出了回响。“安妮小姐对这番道理会怎么说呢？她呀，我猜想，会觉得修修小姐的表是比打马蹄铁或者做铁烤架更斯文的行业吧。”

安妮不让父亲有时间回答，就拉着他往前走。

不过，我们还得回到欧文·沃兰的小店去，再花点时间来思考一下他的生活经历和性格，而无论是彼得·霍文顿，或许还有他女儿安妮，或者欧文的老同学罗伯特·丹福思，都会认为这个问题是微不足道的。自打欧文那细小的指头能握住铅笔刀的时候起，他就因心思精巧、富于独创性而引人注目，有时候是用木头雕刻出一些漂亮的小玩意儿，大多是些花儿和鸟儿，有时候则似乎潜心专注于机械中隐藏的奥秘。不过他做这些事总是以美为目的，从来不去仿造实用的东西。他不像学童中的那群巧手工匠，在谷仓的角落上建造小风车，或者在附近的小溪上架小水磨。有的人发现这个孩子与众不同，认为值得花些时间去仔细观察他，常常觉得有理由猜想他是在试图模仿大自然优美的运动，正如鸟儿的飞翔或小动物的活动中所展示的那样。事实上，这似乎是爱美之心的一种新发展，很可能使他将来成为一位诗人、画家或者雕塑家，而且这种素质正如上述任何艺术门类那样的纯美优雅，完全摆脱了功利主义的粗俗气。他对僵化呆板的普通机械运动感到特别厌恶。有一次，人们带他去看一台蒸汽机，期望他对机械原理的直觉理解力能从中获得满足，可是他却脸色发白，感到恶心，好像给他看的是什么畸形怪异的妖魔。这种恐惧心理部分来源于那个钢铁机具的庞大体积和可怕力量；欧文的心灵是显微镜式的，天生就倾向于精细的东西，这与他瘦小的身材和手指的特别细巧精微的力量和谐一致。但这并不意味着他对美的感觉就因此而减弱为一种精致感。美的观念是和体积大小无关的，它可以在广阔的范围内完美地发展，既能小到只有显微镜下才能看清的事物，也能大到唯有横亘苍穹的彩虹才能衡量的辽阔空间。然而，无论如何，欧文·沃兰的审美目标与才能的这种独特的精细性，使得本可能赏识他天才的世人更不能理解他了。孩子的亲属们看不出能有什么更好的安排——或许本来就没有更好的安排——只能让他去跟一个钟表匠做学徒，希望他那奇异的创造力能得到调教，转到实用的目的上来。

彼得·霍文顿对自己徒弟的看法已经表述过了。他对这个孩子也无能为力。的确，欧文领悟起这个行业的奥秘来简直是快得不可思议；但他把钟表匠行当的伟大目标忘得一干二净，或者根本就鄙夷不屑；他对时间的度量毫不关心，哪怕是时间已经融入了永恒。不过，只要欧文还在师父的照管之下，由于他的体格尚不强健，严格的命令和严厉的监管还能将他那创造性的怪癖约束在一定限度之内；但是当他学徒期满，彼得·霍文顿又因为衰退的视力而不得不把小店转让给他时，人们才明白由欧文·沃兰这样一个人每天来给瞎眼的时间老人引路是多么的不合适。他的一项最合理的计划就是给表内的机械联结上一种音乐装置，以便使生活中一切刺耳的不谐和音都能变得美妙动听，使飞逝的每一瞬刻都凝成金光灿烂的圆润水珠，滴落进往昔的深渊中。如果有人把家里的钟交给他修理——那种高大而古老的座钟，因为曾经测量过许多代人的生命而几乎与人性融为了一体——他就会自作主张，在令人肃然起敬的钟面上装配一组舞蹈或送葬行列的小人像，用以代表十二个欢乐或忧伤的钟点。这种异想天开的事要不了几次，就完全破坏了那些四平八稳、讲求实际的人们对年轻钟表匠的信任，他们认为无论是把时间看作今生发达成功的媒介还是对来世的准备，都是不能用来随便开玩笑的。他的顾客迅速地减少了——这是一种不幸，然而在欧文·沃兰看来或许倒是一种可遇而不可求的好运，他现在越来越沉溺于一件秘密的工作之中，它吸尽了他的全部科学知识和灵巧技艺，也使他得以充分展示自己独特的天赋才华。这项追求已经耗费掉他好几个月的时光了。

在老钟表匠和他漂亮的女儿从幽暗的街头凝视过他之后，欧文·沃兰一直感到心绪不宁，手战抖得太厉害，没法继续干自己所从事的精工细活了。

“那就是安妮本人！”他喃喃地说，“在听见她父亲的声音之前，我的心就跳得这么厉害，应该明白是她来了。啊，心跳得多猛啊！我今晚再也无法做这个精致的机械了。安妮！最亲爱的安妮！你应该让我的心和手坚定，不该让它们这样抖动呀。因为，我努力把美的精魂融入形体并使它运动，都是为了你啊。啊，狂跳的心，静下来吧！要是我的工作就这样遭到挫败，会有迷糊而不安宁的梦来搅扰我，使我明天精神不振。”

就在他竭力使自己平静下来重新干活儿的时候，店门打开了，进来的不是别人，正是彼得·霍文顿在铁匠铺的光明与暗影之间驻足观赏的那个壮汉。罗伯特·丹福思带来了他亲手制作的一只小铁砧，那是年轻的艺术家最近特别定做的。欧文细细审视这个物件，说它做得正好符合他的希望。

“嗨，是呀，”罗伯特·丹福思说，他那浑厚的声音就像一把低音提琴响彻了小店，“要说我的这个行当，我觉得自己不输给任何人；尽管我长着这么个大拳头，跟你一比会很难看，”他大笑着说，还把自己的大手放到欧文那只纤巧的手旁边，“可那又有什么？我敲一下大锤所花的力气，比你从当学徒以来花费的全部力气还要多哩。这难道不是事实吗？”

“很有可能。”欧文用低微而细弱的声音回答道，“力气是世间的怪物。我绝不自夸力气大。我的力量，不管它是什么力量，都是属于精神的。”

“好啦，欧文，你在做什么呀？”他这个老同学问道，声音仍然是那么响亮，使得那位艺术家感到畏缩，尤其是因为这个问题关系到一项神圣的使命，那是他的想象迷醉不已的梦境。“人家都说你在设法寻找永恒运动。”

“永恒运动？胡说！”欧文回答道，一面做了个厌恶的手势；他装了一肚子的火气，“它永远也找不到。那不过是一个幻梦，也许会让一些被物质迷了心窍的人上当，我可不会。再说，即使可能有这种发现，如果获得这种秘密的目的只是为了产生蒸汽和水力现在所产生的作用，那也不值得我花费工夫。我并没有野心要想获得什么新型轧棉机之父的荣耀。”

“那可真是够滑稽的了！”铁匠高声说，禁不住放声大笑起来，使得欧文和他的工作台上的钟形玻璃罩都一齐颤动起来。“不，不，欧文！你造出的东西绝不会有钢筋铁骨。好啦，我也不打扰你了，晚安，欧文，祝你成功；如果你需要帮忙，只要是在铁砧上敲一锤子就能做到的，我一定效劳。”

这位体力强健的人又发出一声大笑，离开了小店。

“真是奇怪，”欧文·沃兰悄声自语道，用手撑住头，“我的一切冥想，我的种种目标，我对于美的激情，我所意识到的创造美的力量——一种更精巧更微妙的力量，这个庞然大物对此一无所知——这一切，这一切，只要遇见罗伯特·丹福思就会显得那么虚幻和无聊！要是我经常遇见他，他真会让我发疯的。他那顽固而野蛮的力量总是弄得我的精神暗淡而混乱；不过，我也要坚定地走自己的路。我不会向他屈服的。”

他从一个玻璃罩下面取出一块极其微小的机械装置，放到灯下聚集的光束中，全神贯注地透过一个放大镜观看，接着又用一种精密的钢制工具进行操作。然而，在一瞬间，他的身子猛然倒在椅上，双手紧握，脸上呈现出恐惧的表情，使他那细巧的五官变得像皱眉蹙额的巨人般触目惊心。

“天啊！我干了什么？”他惊叫道，“那种虚幻妄想，那种野蛮力量的影响——它迷惑了我，遮蔽了我的感觉。我终于碰了这么一下——致命的一击——我从一开始就担心会这样。全完了——几个月的心血，一生的目标啊。我被毁啦！”

他坐在那里，陷入了莫名的绝望，直到台灯在插口里闪烁了几下光亮，然后把这位美的艺术家留在一片黑暗之中。

他的种种观念——它们都是从想象中诞生出来的，对于想象而言显得如此美好，其价值远远超越了人们的所有价值观——就这样因与实际相接触而被撞得粉碎、泯灭无存了。理想的艺术家必须具备性格的力量，而这种性格力量与艺术的精致是难以相容的；当怀疑他的世人以绝对不信任的态度对他进行攻击的时候，他必须坚守住自己的信念；他必须挺身而出对抗全人类并始终做自己的唯一信徒，无论对于自己的天才还是对于它所追求的目标来说都是如此。

有一段时间，欧文·沃兰在这种严酷而不可避免的考验面前屈服了。好几个星期里他总是无精打采，一直用两手撑着脑袋，镇上的人几乎没有机会看到他的面容。当他终于抬起面孔对着阳光时，可以看出他的脸上有一种冷漠、呆滞和无可名状的变化。不过，在彼得·霍文顿和那些认为生活应当像铅锤驱动的时钟一样中规中矩的明智之士看来，这种改变完全是件好事。确实，欧文现在对他的生意是勤奋刻苦得多了。人们看到他那么慢吞吞地、一本正经地检查一块古老的大银表的齿轮，不禁颇感惊奇。表的主人欣喜异常，这块怀表放在他的表袋里那么久，已经被视为他生命的一部分，当然很介意它所受到的待遇。欧文·沃兰因此而获得了良好的声誉，结果被有关当局邀请去调试教堂尖塔上的时钟。他在这件关系公众利益的大事上干得十分成功，商人们在交易所里粗声大气地赞扬他的功绩；看护们在给病房送药的时候悄声地表扬他；情侣们因为能按时赴约会而为他祝福；全镇子的人都感谢欧文使得他们能够准时进餐。总之一句话，他精神上虽说压着沉重的负担，却使得一切都井然有序，不仅在他自己的机体内部是如此，所有听得见教堂时钟铿锵作响的地方也都一样。有件事情虽然微不足道，却也颇能代表他目前的状况，那就是顾客要求他在银匙上镌刻姓名或姓名首字母时，他现在尽可能使用最简明的字体，而把此前一直显得与众不同的种种花里胡哨的装饰一概省略。

一天，就在这段愉快的转变期间，老彼得·霍文顿前来探访他从前的徒弟。

“好啊，欧文，”他说，“我很高兴到处听到人们在夸奖你，特别是镇上那口报时钟，一天二十四小时都在称赞你哩。只要完全摆脱掉你那些关于美的废话，那些东西我不懂，别人也都不懂，再说你自己也不懂——只要你从里面解脱出来，那你在生活中的成功简直就像青天白日一样的可靠。嗨，要是你照这个路子继续走下去，连我都敢让你来修理我的这块宝贝老怀表啦；虽说除了我的女儿安妮，这世上就再没有我这么看重的东西了。”

“我连碰也不敢碰它咧，先生。”欧文有气无力地回答道，因为只要当着师父的面他就感觉精神上受到压抑。

“到时候，”师父说，“到时候，你就有本事对付它了。”

老钟表匠带着从往昔的权威中自然产生的随意态度，接着便审视起欧文手头正在干的活儿和他正在制作的其他东西来。那位艺术家这时简直不敢抬起自己的头。再没有什么比师父冰冷而毫无想象力的精明更与他的天性相背离的了，任何东西碰上它都会化作一场幻梦，除非是物质世界中密度最大的材料。欧文的心灵呻吟着，热切地祈祷上帝把自己从这个人手中拯救出来。

“这是什么？”彼得·霍文顿突然大叫一声，拿起一个布满灰尘的钟形玻璃罩，下面露出了一种机械装置，就像蝴蝶的躯体那样精微细小。“这是什么？欧文！欧文！这些小链条、小齿轮和小叶片里藏着妖法。看着！我只要用食指和拇指这么一捏，就把你从未来一切灾难中解救出来了。”

“看在老天的分上，”欧文·沃兰尖叫着，奋力跳了起来，“要是您不想逼我发疯，就别碰它！您的手指只要稍微用点力就会把我永远毁了。”

“啊哈，年轻人！有这么严重吗？”老钟表匠说，他用锐利的眼光盯着欧文，那种充满世俗气的刻薄非难折磨着他的灵魂。“好吧，你干你的吧；不过我要再次警告你，这个小小的机械装置里藏着你的邪恶灵魂。要我把它驱除掉吗？”

“您才是我的邪恶灵魂，”欧文回答道，情绪异常激动——“是您和这个冷酷粗俗的世界！您抛压在我心头的死气沉沉的思想和沮丧情绪才是我的障碍，要不然我早就完成上天赋予我的使命了。”

彼得·霍文顿摇了摇头，既是轻蔑又是愤慨；他所代表的一些人认为自己有权对所有的笨蛋抱着这种感情，那些笨蛋不去拣大道上摆放着的灰尘土块，而总是一心追求别的收获。他随即起身离去，还竖起一根手指头，满脸带着嘲讽，此后的好几个夜晚，他那副神情都一直纠缠着艺术家的睡梦。在他的师父来的时候，欧文差不多正要重新开始他业已放弃了的工作；可是由于这次不幸事件，他又被抛回了自己刚慢慢挣脱出来的原有状态。

然而，在这种表面的呆滞状态中，他心灵的固有倾向却一直在积聚着新的力量。伴随着夏季的进程，他几乎完全停止了工作，听任时间老人——这位老先生至今为止还是由他所控制的钟表充当代表——任意浪迹于人类生活，将无所适从的钟点系列弄得乱七八糟。根据人们的看法，他把大好的白日时光都浪费在树林里、田野上和小溪岸边的游荡中了。他在那里独得其乐，像孩子一样追逐蝴蝶，或者观看水中昆虫的运动。他久久凝视这些活生生的玩物乘着微风游戏，仔细考察自己捕捉到的一只大虫子的组织结构，那份专注简直令人感到不可思议。追捕蝴蝶倒不失为他付出了如此多美好时日去追求的理想的恰当象征；可是那美丽的理想是否会和作为它的象征的蝴蝶一样，被他的手把握住呢？对于这位艺术家的心灵而言，这些日子无疑是既甜蜜又惬意的。其中充满了灿烂的思想，这些思想的光辉照彻了他智慧的天地，就像蝴蝶翩翩闪耀于天空中一样；在此刻，这些思想对他来说就是真实的存在，不会因为试图使它们化为肉眼可见的形体而去劳作、困惑和经历许多失望。唉，可惜无论是借助诗歌还是运用其他素材的艺术家，都不会满足于对美的内心享受，他一定会去追寻那飞翔于他的幻想领域之外的奥秘，要以物质的手段来把握它，从而粉碎了心灵感受的脆弱生命。欧文·沃兰就感觉到那种要给自己的思想赋予外在真实的冲动，这种冲动和任何一位诗人或画家的冲动是同样的无法抗拒，他们对自己梦幻的丰富形态进行并不完美的复制，用一种更模糊、更朦胧的美来装扮世界。

现在，他利用夜晚时分来慢慢地重新实现那项集中了他一切智力活动的计划。他总是在暮色降临的时候悄悄溜进城，把自己锁在店铺里，耐心而细致地干上好几个钟头。有时候，他会被巡夜人的敲门声吓一跳，因为在整个世界都应该沉睡之时，巡夜人却看到欧文·沃兰小店的百叶窗缝隙间漏出了亮光。对于他那处于病态敏感性的心灵来说，白天似乎构成了一种影响他孜孜追求的侵扰。因此，在浓云密布、雨横风狂的日子里，他就独坐在小店里，双手撑着头，仿佛让自己敏感的头脑整个沉浸在朦胧遐想的迷雾之中；因为他在夜复一夜的劳作中总是逼迫自己要把心中的意念鲜明而清晰地予以呈现，这时他便能逃避出来而获得暂时的解脱。

有一次，他正处于这种恍惚状态中，安妮·霍文顿走进店来，惊醒了他。姑娘的态度既像一位顾客那样坦然随意，又带有童年伙伴般的亲密无间。她的银顶针磨出了一个洞，要欧文给修一修。

“不过我不知道你会不会委屈自己来做这样一件小事，”她笑着说，“因为你如今一心想着要把精神输入到机械里去。”

“你这种想法是从哪儿得来的，安妮？”欧文大吃一惊，说道。

“哦，是我自己想的，”她回答说，“很早以前也听你说过这类事情，那时候你还是个小男孩，我还是个小姑娘。好啦，你愿意给我修修这个糟糕的顶针吗？”

“为了你干什么都行，安妮，”欧文·沃兰说——“什么都行，哪怕是到罗伯特·丹福恩的炉子前去打铁。”

“那个样子可好看啦！”安妮回应道，带着难以觉察的轻蔑瞥了一眼艺术家那瘦小单薄的身子，“呃，顶针在这儿！”

“你那种想法真是奇怪，”欧文说，“那种使物质精神化的想法。”

他接着暗暗产生了一个念头，觉得这个年轻姑娘具有一种天生才能，比世上任何人都更能理解他的心思。假如他能获得唯一所爱的人的同情，那么在他孤单苦斗的时候将得到怎样的帮助和力量啊！那些与芸芸众生的追求迥然不同的人们——他们要么超越于世人之前，要么与世人隔绝——常常会有一种寒彻心脾的感觉，足以令灵魂战栗，仿佛置身于北极周围冰封雪冻的荒凉地带。先知、诗人、改革家、罪犯，或者任何怀有人的渴望却又因特殊命运而与世人隔绝的人，他们可能体验到的感情，可怜的欧文也体验到了。

“安妮，”他叫道，内心的念头使他脸色变得惨白，“我多么乐意把我追求的秘密告诉你啊！我想，只有你，才能正确地评价它。我知道，你听见它的时候一定会心怀敬重，而我绝不能指望苛刻而卑俗的世人会这样。”

“难道不是吗？我肯定会这样的！”安妮·霍文顿回答说，同时快活地笑起来，“好啦，快给我解释一下这个小陀螺是干什么用的，它做得这么精致，简直可以给麦布女王(1)做玩具了。看呀！我可以让它动起来。”

“别动！”欧文大叫道，“别动！”

安妮只不过拿起了一根针，用针尖极轻地碰了碰我们已经不止一次提到过的那个复杂机械的微小部件，艺术家就猛地一把抓住了她的手腕，用力之大竟使安妮尖叫起来。狂怒与痛苦的痉挛扭曲了他的面孔，使安妮非常惊骇。接着他低垂下头，双手掩面。

“走吧，安妮，”他喃喃地说，“是我欺骗了自己，应该自作自受。我渴望同情，我以为、我相信、我梦想你会给我同情；可是你并没有进入我的秘密之门的钥匙，安妮。刚才你那一碰已经毁了我好几个月的心血和一辈子的思考！这不是你的错，安妮；可是你毁了我！”

可怜的欧文·沃兰！他确实犯了错，但又应当原谅；因为如果有谁的心灵能对他眼中如此神圣的事业怀有足够敬重的话，那应该是位女性的心灵。即使说安妮·霍文顿吧，假如她对爱情的深邃信息有所知晓的话，也可能并不会令他失望的。

接下来的那个冬天里，艺术家的生活方式令所有一直预期他无可救药的人们甚为满意，事实证明他对于这个世界而言注定是个废物，而他本人也注定该遭厄运。一位亲戚的过世使他获得了一笔小小的遗产。这样他就不必再为谋生而操劳，而且因为失去了伟大目标的恒定影响——这个目标至少对他来说是伟大的——他便放纵于某些嗜好，而这些嗜好据说能有助于支持他那纤弱的体质。然而，当天才人物身上的超凡成分一旦被掩蔽，世俗成分便会发挥更加难以控制的影响力，因为他的性格脱离了上天精心调适的平衡，而在生性鄙俗的人身上，这种平衡是借助于别的某种办法来维持的。欧文·沃兰以自身来证明了狂饮闹宴中可以寻找到怎样的欢乐。他透过杯中金色的酒浆来看世界，凝视着伴随杯沿欢快的泡沫而升腾起的种种幻景，这些幻景使空中充溢着欢乐得疯狂的各色形影，但很快就又变得幽灵般缥缈和空虚凄凉。即使发生了这种令人沮丧而又不可避免的变化，年轻人却仍要继续举杯痛饮这迷人心魂的酒浆，尽管那虚幻的作用会给生命罩上阴影，阴影中又充满了嘲弄他的幽灵。其实这乃是心灵深处的某种厌倦感，这才是真实的，也是艺术家现在所深刻感受到的；它比纵情狂饮所唤起的任何虚幻的悲愁与恐惧都更难忍受。在纵情狂饮之时，即使他心中充满烦恼，尚能记起一切都只是幻觉；而在厌倦心理下，沉重的痛苦就是他的实际人生。

一桩偶发事件把他从这种危险状态中解救了出来，不止一个人目睹了那件事，但其中最精明的人也无法解释或猜想它在欧文·沃兰心灵中发生了怎样的作用。事情非常简单。在春季一个温暖的下午，艺术家坐在寻欢作乐的伙伴群中，面前放着一杯酒，这时忽然有一只色彩斑斓的蝴蝶飞进了敞开的窗户，在他头顶上翩翩起舞。

“啊，”一直在开怀畅饮的欧文叫了一声，“太阳的儿子和夏风的玩伴，你在阴沉的冬眠之后又复活了吗？那么，这也是该我动手干活儿的时候了！”

接着，他把尚未喝干的酒杯留在桌子上，转身离去，从此再也没有听说他沾过一滴酒。

现在，他又重新在树林间和田野上游荡起来。我们可以想象，当欧文同那些粗俗的寻欢作乐者们坐在一起的时候，那只像精灵般飞进窗户的斑斓蝴蝶真是一个精灵，前来召唤他重返他那超凡脱俗的纯洁而理想的生活。我们也可以想象，他是为了寻找这个精灵而到它时常出没的阳光灿烂之地去的；因为在夏天逐渐逝去时，人们仍然看见他轻轻潜行到一只蝴蝶降落的地方，出神地凝视着它。当它飞起来的时候，他的目光也追随着它扇动的翅膀，仿佛它在空中的轨迹指引着登上天堂的路径。不过，巡夜人看到从欧文·沃兰的百叶窗里透出的缕缕灯光，就明白他又恢复了没日没夜的劳作，那又是出于什么目的呢？镇中居民对这一切古怪现象有个无所不包的解释：欧文·沃兰疯了！采用这种方便的办法来说明任何超越世间平庸见解的事情，对于那些头脑狭隘而迟钝的人们来说是多么的百试不爽——多么的称心如意——对他们受伤害的感情来说又是何等的安慰！从圣保罗(2)时代直到我们这位可怜的小小的美的艺术家，这同一个法宝被用来对付那些言行富于智慧和道德的人们，解释他们的话语和行为中一切神秘莫解的地方。就欧文·沃兰的情况而言，镇里居民们的判断也许是正确的。他大概真是疯了。由于缺乏同情——他与邻人们之间的悬殊差别使得规范的约束不复存在——这已足以使他发疯了。也有可能是他受到了那么多超凡光华的照射，这种光华又与普通日光相混合，按照世俗的说法就弄得他神志迷乱了。

一天晚间，艺术家在习惯性的漫游后回家，打开台灯照亮那个精巧的机件；这项工作经常被打断，但仍然再次继续，仿佛他的命运就蕴含在那个机件之中。这时老彼得·霍文顿突然进来了，使他吃了一惊。欧文每次见到他心脏就会紧缩。在一切世人当中他是最可怕的，因为他具有敏锐的理解力，只要是他看到的，他就能看得一清二楚，而他不曾看到的，他便顽固地绝不相信。这一次，老钟表匠却只说了一两句很和气的话。

“欧文，我的孩子，”他说，“明天晚上你一定要上我家去。”

艺术家吞吞吐吐地说了些推托的话。

“哦，你一定要去，”彼得·霍文顿说，“看在你过去曾是我家一员的分上。怎么，孩子！难道你还不知道我女儿安妮已经跟罗伯特·丹福思订婚了吗？我们将以自己简慢的方式招待大家，庆祝这件喜事。”

“啊！”欧文说。

这轻轻的“啊”就是他所说的一切；在彼得·霍文顿听来，这语音显得冷漠和无动于衷。然而它却是可怜的艺术家内心的一声被窒息了的呼喊，他把它强行压抑在心中，就像紧紧按压住一个邪恶的精灵。不过，老钟表匠未曾察觉到的是，年轻人还是让自己小小地发泄了一下。他拿起正准备干活的工具，听任它落在那个细小的机械装置上，这件东西已再度花费了他几个月的思虑与劳作，在这一击之下变得粉碎了！

假如爱情不曾插在其他种种力量当中，偷偷夺走了欧文·沃兰的巧手奇技，那他的故事也就不足以成为努力创造美的人们的忧患人生的写照了。从表面上看，他并不是一个热情满腔、勇于追求的情人；他的激情的骚动起伏都被完全限制在艺术家的想象之中，而安妮本人对此却除了女性的直觉以外一无所知。但在欧文看来，这种爱情却笼罩着他生命的全部领域。上次她未能对他的话做出任何深刻反应，对这件事他已浑然忘却，而是坚持要把自己一切艺术成功的美梦同安妮的形象联系起来；对他来说，她就是体现自己所崇拜的精神力量的化身，他希望自己能在那圣坛上奉献一份不无价值的供品。当然，他是在欺骗自己；安妮·霍文顿并不具有他的想象所赋予她的那些品质。在他内心中呈现出的安妮形象，正如那件神秘的机械装置假如得以完成一样，都只是他自己的创造物。倘若他借助于爱情的成功而认识到自己的错误——倘若他能将安妮拥入怀抱，从而目睹她从天使蜕变为平常妇人——这种失望或许还能逼迫他回头来，集中精力追求自己剩下的唯一目标。也可能是另一种情况，假如他发现安妮真的符合他的想象，那他的命运就美不胜收，只要利用其中多余的材料就能创造出许多美的作品，比他一直辛苦制作的东西更有价值。可是，痛苦披上伪装来到他的身旁，他感到自己生命中的天使遭到强夺，竟被许配给了一个粗俗的铁匠，而那个人既不需要也不能欣赏她的优美品质——命运就是如此乖戾反常，使得人的生存显得那么荒谬和矛盾，简直不必再抱别的希望，也无须再怀有别的忧惧。欧文·沃兰在世上已经一无所有了，只能像个被打晕了的人那样木然呆坐着。

他生了一场大病。病好之后，他那瘦小纤弱的身躯同过去相比平添了许多蠢肉。尖尖的下巴长成了圆形；富于灵性、臻于鬼斧神工的纤细小手，变得比壮实的婴儿的手还要丰满。他的面容呈现出小孩子的稚气，可能会逗引得陌生人想去拍拍他的头——不过伸出的手又会停下来，心里纳闷这个孩子的神态怎么这样奇怪。灵魂仿佛已经脱离了他的心窍，只留下肉体像植物一样蓬勃生长。这并非意味着欧文·沃兰成了一个白痴。他能说会道，而且有条有理。他差不多成了个唠叨鬼，的确，人们都开始这样看待他了；因为他总喜欢不厌其烦地谈论从前读过的书里记载的那些机械奇迹，说他现在总算明白了那全都出于杜撰。他历数艾伯塔斯·马格努斯制造的铜人和培根修士制造的青铜头像，然后讲到近代，提到几匹马拉着小马车的自动机械，据说是给法国皇太子制造的；还说到有一只像苍蝇一样在人耳边嗡嗡叫的昆虫，其实不过是由细小的钢丝弹簧组成的一种装置。他还讲过一个有关鸭子的故事，它能摇摇摆摆地走、嘎嘎地叫和吃东西；不过，要是有哪位诚实的公民买下它去做菜，就会发现自己原来被一只机械制成的假鸭子欺骗了。

“所有这类记载，”欧文·沃兰说，“我现在总算明白了全是骗人的。”

接下来，他又会用神秘的口气承认自己曾经并不这样认为。在那些闲荡和做梦的日子里，他还以为在某种意义上可能把精神赋予机械，使机械与新的生命和运动相结合，从而创造出大自然本想在万物中达到却并未尽力去实现的理想的美。然而，无论是对于实现这个目标的过程还是对这种计划本身，他看来都没有清晰的认识。

“现在我把这一切都扔到一边去啦，”他会这样说，“那不过是年轻人一贯用来迷惑自己的梦幻而已。如今我既然获得了一点儿常识，回头一想就只会让我哈哈大笑了。”

可怜的、可怜而堕落的欧文·沃兰啊！这些迹象表明，他已不再属于围绕着我们的那个看不见的美好世界了。他已经丧失了对无形世界的信念，如今正像这类可悲可叹的人们一贯所做的那样，因世俗的智慧而自鸣得意，甚至摈弃了能目睹的东西，除了能亲手触摸的东西之外一概都不肯相信。这就是这类人的不幸之所在，他们的精神逐渐消亡而只剩下更粗钝的理解力，越来越同化于自己唯一能认知到的东西。不过，欧文·沃兰的精神尚未死灭也未消失，它只是在沉睡而已。

他的精神是怎样再次复苏的，已无案可查。也许麻木的沉睡因一阵抽搐的剧痛而惊醒；也许和过去那一次相同，有蝴蝶飞来在他头顶盘旋飞舞，再次给了他灵感——的确，这阳光之子总是给艺术家传递着神秘的使命——是蝴蝶用他往昔的生活目的来重新激励了他。无论使他全身血管战栗的是痛苦还是欢乐，总之他的第一个冲动就是感谢上天使他再次成为具有思想、想象和最敏锐感觉的人，他已经很久不是这种人了。

“现在动手工作吧，”他说，“我从来没有感到像现在这样充满力量。”

然而，尽管他觉得自己很强壮，但他也因担心死亡会在工作的中途突然袭来而焦虑，这激励着他更加勤奋地苦干。这种对死亡的焦虑，或许在全心全意投身于事业的人当中是十分常见的，在他们心目中那种事业是如此崇高，以致生命被仅仅视为成功的一项重要条件。只要我们热爱生命是为了生命本身，我们就不怎么害怕失去它。当我们渴望生命是为了达到某个目标，这才认识到生命的构造是多么脆弱。不过，与这种不安全感同时存在的，还有一种至关重要的信念，即当我们在从事任何仿佛是上天注定适合于自己的任务时，我们绝不会受到死亡之箭的伤害，这项任务如果我们不完成它，全世界都有理由为之哀痛。难道深受改造人类的信念所鼓舞的哲学家会相信，在他正要说出启发蒙昧之言的一瞬间，死亡会召唤他离弃智慧的生命吗？假如他就这样死去，人类将等待若干困乏的世代慢慢逝去——整个世界生命的流沙将一粒一粒地坠落——然后才会生就另一位哲人来展现当时即可揭示的真理。可是，历史又提供了许多例证来表明，在任何特定的时代，体现最宝贵的精神的个人，按照凡人的标准来判断却往往过早夭折，没有足够的机会来完成自己在人间的使命。哲人易萎，心灵麻木思想怠惰者却长命百岁。诗人之歌中途而废，或者只有在凡人听不见的地方、在天国的合唱中去完成。画家——正如奥斯顿(3)那样——将自己的构思一半留在画布上，以其不完整的美让我们悲伤，却打算用天堂的色彩来描绘出整个画面，假如这么说不算失敬的话。但更有可能的则是今生未完成的构想再没有任何地方可以完成。人的种种最珍贵的计划如此频繁地半途而废，这只能证明尘世的行为无论因虔诚和天才而显得多么超凡入圣，其实是毫无价值的，只不过是作为精神的演练和表现形式而已。在天堂里，一切平常无奇的思想都要比弥尔顿(4)的诗歌更崇高更优美。那么，他是否愿意给他留在人间的未完之作再添上一行呢？

还是回到欧文·沃兰的故事上来吧。他的命运就是要达到自己的生活目标，无论这命运是好是坏。我们略而不谈他经历了很长一段时间的紧张思索、满怀渴望的努力、精密细致的劳作、损心伤神的焦虑，以及随后独享成功欢乐的一瞬：这一切都留给读者去想象吧。后来，在一个冬夜，我们看到艺术家去拜访罗伯特·丹福思，来到了他家的壁炉边。在那里，他看到身躯魁梧的铁匠被家庭生活氛围熏陶得温和而宁静。他也看到了安妮，如今已成为家庭主妇，平添了许多她丈夫那直率刚强的性格，但欧文·沃兰仍然相信她浑身透出一种更精纯的优雅，使她能够充当力与美之间的沟通者。碰巧老彼得·霍文顿当晚也是女儿炉火旁的客人；首先与艺术家的目光相遇的，依然是那种记忆犹新的锋利、冷漠的挑剔神情。

“我的老朋友欧文！”罗伯特·丹福思叫道，他一跃而起，用他那惯于把握铁条的大手紧紧握住艺术家纤细的手指，“到底来看我们啦，这才算好友近邻啊。我还担心是那永恒运动把你迷住了，忘记老交情啦。”

“我们见到你真高兴，”安妮说，一道红晕泛上了她那少妇的面颊，“这么久不来看我们，可不够朋友啊。”

“喂，欧文，”老钟表匠首次致意就是发问，“你那美丽的小玩意儿怎么样啦？你终于造出来了吧？”

艺术家并没有马上回答，因为他被一个在地毯上打滚的壮实小孩吓了一跳——这是一个从无垠空间中神秘地钻出来的小家伙，身板却那样粗壮结实，好像是用地球上最密实的物质压铸而成的。这个前途无量的婴儿朝新来者爬过来，然后像罗伯特·丹福思所说的那样“竖立”起来，用一双如此精明的眼光凝视着欧文，使得那位母亲不由得与丈夫交换了一下自豪的眼神。不过艺术家却被孩子的目光弄得很是局促不安，他觉得这孩子的神态和老彼得·霍文顿的惯常表情非常相似。他甚至想象是老钟表匠被压缩成了这个小孩的形状，透过那双幼童的眼睛在望着他，重复着（老钟表匠这时正好再次发问）那个带有恶意的问题：——

“那个美丽的玩意儿，欧文！那个美丽的玩意儿怎么样啦？你造出来了吗？”

“我造出来啦。”艺术家回答道，眼睛中瞬间闪过一道欢乐的光辉，露出阳光般的微笑，然而又浸透着如此深沉的思绪，简直可以说是近乎哀伤。“是的，朋友们，我说的是实话。我造出来了。”

“当真！”安妮喊道，脸上又隐隐透出少女般的欢乐，“现在总可以问一问这秘密是什么了吧？”

“当然，我来就是为了揭开秘密的，”欧文·沃兰回答说，“你会知道、看到、摸到并拥有这个秘密！因为，安妮——如果我还能这样称呼我童年时代的伙伴——安妮，正是为了要送你一件新婚礼物，我才制作出这个精神化的机械，这个具有和谐的运动和美的神秘的东西。它的确来得晚了些；不过正因为随着我们年龄的增长，事物都开始失去了鲜艳的色彩，我们的灵魂也丧失了微妙的感受力，所以才特别需要美的精神。只要——原谅我，安妮——只要你懂得该怎样估价这件礼物，它就绝不算来得太晚。”

他一边说，一边掏出一个像是珠宝盒的匣子。那是他亲手用乌檀木精雕而成的，上面镶嵌着窗格形的奇异珍珠花饰，描绘一个小男孩在追逐着一只蝴蝶，在另一处，那只蝴蝶化作了一个长翅膀的精灵，正在向天堂飞去；那个男孩或者少年为了赢得这只美丽的蝴蝶，从强烈的渴求中获得了超凡的能耐，竟从地面飞升到云端，又从云端直抵浩渺的天宇。艺术家打开了这个乌木匣，叫安妮把手指放在匣边。她照办了，但几乎惊叫起来，因为这时有一只蝴蝶突然闪翅飞出来，落在了她的指尖上，扑闪着华丽夺目的带有金色斑点的紫色翅膀，仿佛准备着要腾空飞翔。那种辉煌、那种华美、那种精致豪华尽被柔化融合入这件物体的纯美之中，简直无法用言语来形容。大自然理想的蝴蝶在这里获得了完美的实现；它并非仿照那种在大地花丛中飞翔的色彩暗淡的小昆虫，而是盘旋在天堂的草地上，让小天使和早逝婴儿的灵魂追逐嬉戏的神奇之物。可以看到它的翅膀上有一层茂密的绒毛，它那眼睛的光泽似乎充满了灵气。炉火的亮光在这神奇之物四周微微闪烁——烛光在它身上闪耀着虹彩；但它分明是借助于自己的光辉而发亮，照彻了它所留驻的手指和那只伸出的手，就像镶嵌在那里的一块散发着乳白光芒的宝石。它的美无与伦比，使人完全不去考虑它形体的微小。但即使它的翅膀大得横跨天穹，人的心灵所获得的充实和满足也莫过于此。

“真美呀！真美呀！”安妮叫道，“它是活的吗？它是活的吗？”

“活的？当然是活的啰，”她的丈夫回答说，“你以为哪个凡人有本事造出一只蝴蝶？或者既然任何一个孩子都能在夏天的午后逮到十几只，谁还会自找麻烦去造一只出来？活的？当然是活的！不过，这个漂亮匣子却无疑是我们的朋友欧文造出来的；它倒的确能给他争光。”

就在这时，那只蝴蝶又再次扇动翅膀，动作是那么栩栩如生，竟让安妮吓了一跳，甚至感到了畏惧；因为尽管丈夫有那种看法，她自己却无法肯定它到底是活的呢，或者只是一件奇妙的机械。

“是活的吗？”她重复道，比原先更加认真。

“你自己来判断吧。”欧文·沃兰说，他站在那儿，神情专注地凝视着她的脸。

这时候蝴蝶蓦然飞到了空中，围绕着安妮的头顶盘旋，然后又飞翔到客厅远处的角落，但依然可以感觉到它翅膀扇动所化成的一圈闪烁的光辉。躺在地板上的小孩子用他那双精明的小眼睛追寻着它的飞翔路线。蝴蝶在屋里飞了一圈之后，绕了道盘旋的曲线，重新落到了安妮的手指上。

“可它到底是不是活的呀？”她又一次惊呼道；她的那根手指战抖得那么厉害，停留在上面的那个灿烂夺目的神秘之物不得不展开翅膀来保持平衡。“告诉我，它到底是活的呢，还是你造出来的？”

“为什么要问是谁造的，既然它这么美？”欧文·沃兰回答道，“是不是活的？是的，安妮；你满可以说它具有生命，因为它已经把我的生命吸收入体内了；在这只蝴蝶的奥秘中，在它的美中——它的美不仅在于外形，更深及整个机体——体现了一个追求美的艺术家的智慧、想象、感觉、灵魂！是呀；我创造了它，但是”——说到这儿他的脸色稍微有点改变——“现在这只蝴蝶对我来说，已经不是青春时代白日梦中所遥望的那个东西了。”

“不管它是什么，总归是件漂亮玩意儿，”铁匠说，一边带着孩童似的欢乐咧开嘴笑，“不知道它肯不肯屈尊停落在我这根又大又笨的指头上？把它移到这里来，安妮。”

在艺术家的指点下，安妮把她的指尖挨到丈夫的指尖上；稍微等待了片刻，蝴蝶就从这根手指飞到了那根手指上。它在开始第二次飞翔之前也先扑腾了一阵翅膀，与第一次相似却又不尽相同。接着，它便从铁匠那结实的手指上飞起，绕着逐渐加大的圈子盘旋着，一直飞到天花板，围着屋子飞了一大圈之后，又以波浪般起伏的动作返回原地。

“嗨，简直是巧夺天工！”罗伯特·丹福思喊道，他用自己所能想得出的话来表达衷心的赞美；的确，即使他只说得出这么一句，任何言辞更优雅、感受更细腻的人也很难再找出什么话来补充了。

“这个我可办不到，我得承认。不过，那又有什么关系？我的大铁锤这么一敲，比起我们的朋友欧文浪费了整整五年工夫造出的这只蝴蝶来，更有实际用处。”

这时候，那个小孩子拍着手，含糊不清地咿咿呀呀大叫起来，看样子是想要这只蝴蝶来做玩具。

与此同时，欧文·沃兰瞟了一眼安妮，想知道她是否赞同她丈夫关于美与实用之间价值高低的评价。在她对他的亲切态度中，在她审视他亲手创造的神奇作品和他理念的化身时所表现出的惊异与赞美中，含有某种隐秘的蔑视——太隐秘了，或许她自己也没有意识到，只有艺术家的这种本能的辨析力才能感知。不过欧文在自己理想追求的后期业已超脱出来了，否则这样的发现是会使他备受折磨的。他明白，世人和作为世人代表的安妮无论给予他什么赞美，都无法以贴切的话语和恰当的感情来对一位艺术家做完全的报偿，而这位艺术家却以微末之物来体现一种崇高精神——将凡俗之物转化为精神的珍宝——终于将美捕捉到自己的作品之中。他并不是到了这最后一刻才明白，一切高尚行为的报偿只能在行为本身里去寻找，向别处寻找只能是徒劳。不过，安妮和她的丈夫，甚至彼得·霍文顿，可能对这件事的重要性也有充分的理解，他们也满意地看到他多年的心血总算得到了与之相称的回报。欧文·沃兰本可以告诉他们，这只蝴蝶，这个小玩意儿，这件可怜的钟表匠送给铁匠妻子的新婚礼物，实际上是一件艺术珍宝，帝王君主都愿意用荣誉和巨额财富来交换，并作为自己王国最稀罕最奇妙的宝物来钟爱。然而艺术家只是笑了笑，把这个秘密藏在了心里。

“爸爸，”安妮说，心想老钟表匠说点赞许的话也许能使当年的徒弟开心，“过来欣赏一下这只漂亮的蝴蝶呀。”

“让我们看一看吧。”彼得·霍文顿说，他从椅子上爬起来，脸上带着讥嘲的笑容，这副神气常常令人像他本人一样怀疑除了物质之外的任何事物。“我的手指头在这儿，让它落上来吧。我一旦摸到它心里就更清楚了。”

可是，让安妮越来越惊诧的是，当她父亲的指尖刚挨到蝴蝶所停留的她丈夫的手指时，小昆虫就垂下了翅膀，仿佛立即就要跌落到地板上。甚至连它翅膀上和身子上的那些灿烂的金色斑点——除非她的眼睛在欺骗她——也变得暗淡了，明亮的紫色蒙上了一层灰翳，同时在铁匠手掌周围闪亮的点点光彩也越来越微弱，最后消失了。

“它快死了！快死了！”安妮惊惶地大叫道。

“它的制作非常微妙，”艺术家平静地说，“正像我告诉你的，它吸收了一种精神要素——可以叫它生物磁力，或者随便什么。在怀疑和讥嘲的气氛中，它的精微感觉会受到折磨，正像将自身生命倾注在它里面的那个人灵魂也会受到折磨一样。它已经丧失了它的美；再过片刻，它的机械性能将要受到无法弥补的损坏。”

“把您的手拿开，爸爸！”安妮恳求道，脸色变得苍白，“我的孩子在这儿，让蝴蝶停在他纯洁的手上吧。在那儿，也许它的生命会复活，色彩也会变得更加鲜明。”

她的父亲带着辛辣的笑容，缩回了他的手指。接着，蝴蝶似乎恢复了自由运动的能力，色彩也呈现出原有的光泽，那星光般闪烁的光芒是它最奇妙的特征，现在也重新聚为一圈围绕着它的光环。一开始，当它从罗伯特·丹福思的手上转移到孩子的小手指上时，这道光芒变得非常明亮，竟清晰地把孩子的身影投射到了墙上。同时，那个孩子也照着爸爸妈妈的动作，伸出胖乎乎的小手，带着童稚气的喜悦看着蝴蝶扇动翅膀。可是，孩子脸上透出某种古怪的精明神气，使欧文·沃兰觉得面前就是老彼得·霍文顿，只不过是把他那顽固不化的怀疑主义部分地变换成了孩童气的信任而已。

“这小淘气看上去多聪明啊！”丹福思悄声对妻子说。

“我从来没有见过小孩子能有这种神态。”安妮回答道，她赞赏自己的孩子是有充足理由的，远远胜过对艺术家的蝴蝶的赞赏。“小宝贝比我们更懂得这东西的奥秘。”

似乎蝴蝶也和艺术家一样，意识到这孩子的天性中存在着某种与它不完全投合的东西，便时而闪烁亮光，时而又变得暗淡。最后，它从孩子的小手上飞起，以轻盈的动作毫不费力地向上飞翔，仿佛主人的精神所赋予它的超凡本能在驱使着这个美好幻影不由自主地向一个更高领域飞升。要是这里没有障碍的话，它很可能已经飞进天宇，化为不朽之物了。然而它的光辉只能闪耀在天花板上；翅膀的精微构造擦刮到那种粗陋的物体，几点光亮像星尘一般飘坠下来，落到地毯上微微闪烁着。随即蝴蝶便飞落下来，但并没有返回那个小孩子的手指，而是被艺术家的手吸引过去了。

“别这样！别这样！”欧文·沃兰喃喃地说，仿佛自己的作品能听懂他的话，“你已经从主人的心中诞生出来，再也不能回去了。”

蝴蝶略为犹豫了一阵，发出了一道战抖的光芒，接着便挣扎着飞向那个孩子，似乎想要落到他的手指上；可是就在它仍然在空中盘旋的时候，那个浑身力气、脸上带着外祖父的精明神气的孩子猛然伸手抓住这个奇妙的虫子，紧紧地把它握在手中。安妮尖叫起来。老彼得·霍文顿则爆发出一阵冷酷的、嘲讽的大笑。铁匠用尽力气掰开孩子的手，发现掌心里只剩下一堆闪闪发光的碎片，美的奥秘已经在那里永远消失了。至于欧文·沃兰，却心平气和地看着自己的毕生心血付之毁灭，然而这绝不是毁灭。他已经捕捉到了远比这只蝴蝶更重要的东西。当艺术家的人格升华到至美的境界，他为了使世人感知到美而借助的那个象征物，在他眼中便没有多少价值了，而他的精神则在现实的欢乐中臻于圆满自足。

————————————————————

(1) 麦布女王（Queen Mab）：英国民间传说中的小仙后。

(2) 圣保罗（St．Paul，5—67）：耶稣门徒之一。

(3) 奥斯顿（Washington Allston，1779—1843）：美国画家、作家和诗人。

(4) 弥尔顿（John Milton，1608—1674）：英国诗人，著有长诗《失乐园》《复乐园》等。

雪人

一个寒冷冬日的下午，当太阳在漫长的暴风雪过后发出寒光的时候，两个孩子央求妈妈准许他们跑出家门，到地里新降的雪中去玩耍。大孩子是个小姑娘，因为她性情温柔谦和，大家又都觉得她长得挺美，所以父母亲和熟悉她的人总是叫她“紫罗兰”。不过大家都知道她弟弟的名字叫作“牡丹”，因为他圆嘟嘟的小脸老是红通通的，让每个人都想到阳光和一朵朵大红花。两个孩子的父亲叫林赛先生，我们必须着重说明，他是一位很优秀的却又特别务实的人，经营五金生意，考虑一切事情都毫不动摇地惯于采取所谓“常识”的观点。他的心肠差不多跟别人的一样软，但脑筋却跟他卖的铁茶壶一样坚硬和难以穿透，因此大概也是同样的空空如也。至于那位母亲，性格中却含有一种诗意的气质，一种超越凡俗的美——就好像一朵娇柔带露的鲜花，安然无损地度过了富于想象力的青春时代，在充当主妇与母亲的枯燥无聊的现实生活中依然保持着勃勃生机。

就这样，正像我开头所说的，紫罗兰与牡丹央求妈妈让他们跑出去，到新降的雪中去玩耍。因为尽管原先雪花看上去那么阴沉乏味，一直从灰蒙蒙的天空飘飘坠落着，但现在阳光正照射在雪地上，呈现出一派非常欢乐的景象。孩子们住在城里，没有更宽敞的游玩地，只是家门前有一个小小的花园，一道白色的篱笆把它与街道隔开，一棵梨树和两三棵李子树向园中投下浓荫，客厅窗下还长着一丛玫瑰。不过，果树和玫瑰这时节都落光了叶子，细枝上裹着一层薄雪，仿佛是冬季的叶簇，这儿那儿还挂着冰柱，权且充作果实。

“好吧，紫罗兰——好吧，我的小牡丹，”他们那和蔼的母亲说，“你们可以出去到雪地里玩。”

于是，这位好太太用羊毛外套和厚袜子把两个小宝贝裹起来，在他们的脖子上围上羊毛围巾，再给他们各自的小腿套上一双带绑腿的高筒靴，给他们的小手戴上毛线手套，然后给他们各自一个亲吻当作驱走严寒的咒语。两个孩子冲出门去，蹦蹦跳跳地立刻扎进了一大堆雪的中央，然后紫罗兰像只雪鹀那样钻出了雪堆，小牡丹则手脚扑腾着爬出来，露出鲜花盛开般的圆脸蛋。他们玩得多么快活啊！看着他们在冬日的花园中嬉戏，你会觉得阴郁无情的暴风雪所以会到来并不为别的，只是为了给紫罗兰和牡丹提供一种新游戏；两个孩子所以会被创造出来，也与雪鹀一样是为了要在暴风雪中、在大地的银装素裹中求取欢乐。

最后，当他们彼此用一把把白雪撒满全身时，紫罗兰开心地对着小牡丹大笑了一阵，然后猛然冒出了一个新主意。

“你看起来活像一个雪人，牡丹，”她说，“要是你的脸蛋儿不这么红的话。这让我想出了一个好主意！让我们堆个雪人吧——堆个小姑娘——她可以做我们的妹妹，整个冬天都跟着我们到处跑、一起玩。这不是个好主意吗？”

“啊，好！”牡丹叫道，他尽量想把意思表达清楚，因为他还只是个小男孩。“这个主意真好！妈妈也会看见它的！”

“是呀，”紫罗兰回答说，“妈妈也会看见这个新来的小姑娘。不过她不能让小姑娘进温暖的客厅里去；因为，你知道，我们的小雪妹妹是不喜欢温暖的。”

于是孩子们立即着手执行这项重大任务，要堆出一个会到处跑的雪人；这时候妈妈正坐在窗前，听到了他们的谈话，忍不住对他们开始行动时那一本正经的模样发笑。他们似乎真以为用雪堆出一个活生生的小姑娘一点儿也不困难。说句真话，假如能够创造出奇迹的话，其实正应该像紫罗兰和牡丹这样头脑纯朴、心无疑虑，马上开始动手干，甚至于不知道它是否是一桩奇迹。母亲就是这么想的；她还想到刚从天上降下来的新雪倒是创造新生命的绝好材料，假如不是那么冰冷就好了。她再看了一会儿孩子们，高兴地望着他们小小的身影——女儿，个头儿长得超过了年龄，体态优雅而灵活，肤色娇嫩，看上去就像一种欢乐的意念，而不像血肉之躯——牡丹的个子却往宽处长不往高处长，迈着又短又结实的双腿滚来滚去，像一头大象般壮实，虽说并没有那么庞大。接着妈妈又继续干她的活儿。我记不起她干的是什么活儿了；总之不是在为紫罗兰修整绸帽，就是在织补小牡丹的短腿穿的一双长袜吧。不过她忍不住一而再、再而三地把头转向窗口，去看孩子们的雪人堆得怎么样了。

的确，这真是极其令人愉悦的景象，两个生气勃勃的小家伙在忙着干自己的工作！看着他们干得那么内行那么熟练，又是多么的美妙。紫罗兰担任指挥，吩咐弟弟该干什么，而她则用自己纤细的小手塑造雪人更细致的部位。事实上，雪人似乎不是两个孩子堆出来的，倒像是在他们手下逐渐长大的，而他们一直在同雪人玩耍和天真地交谈着。他们的母亲看到这一切非常惊奇；她看得越久，就越是惊奇。

“我的孩子多出色呀！”她心想，怀着母亲的骄傲微笑着，同时也在笑自己怎么会为孩子感到如此骄傲。“别的孩子第一次尝试就能用雪堆出这么活灵活现的小姑娘吗？唔——可我现在必须缝好牡丹的新外衣，因为他爷爷明天要来，我想让小家伙看上去漂亮些。”

于是她拿起那件外衣，很快就像两个孩子忙着堆雪人那样又忙碌地缝起来。不过当母亲在衣服上飞针走线的时候，仍然倾听着紫罗兰和牡丹快活的声音，从而使她的劳作变得轻巧而愉快。两个孩子一直在相互交谈着，舌头和手脚一样地动个不停。时不时地，她会听不清他们谈些什么，只是喜滋滋地感到他们彼此亲亲爱爱，正玩得非常开心，堆雪人的活儿也进行得很顺利。不过有时候紫罗兰和牡丹碰巧会提高声音，他们说的话便能字字听清，就像在母亲眼下置身的客厅里说话一样。啊，这些话在她心里多么愉快地回响着啊，即使他们自己根本无意说得这么聪明和精彩！

不过你应该明白，一位母亲在倾听时用心远胜于用耳朵，这样她就常常会因仙乐的颤音而感到欢悦，别的人对此却一无所闻。

“牡丹！牡丹！”紫罗兰高声喊着弟弟，他跑到花园的另一边去了。“给我运一些新雪来，牡丹，从最远的那个角落，我们还没踩过的地方。我要用它来做小雪妹妹的胸膛。你知道那部分必须非常洁白，就同刚从天上落下的雪一样。”

“给你，紫罗兰！”牡丹回答道，他的语气很粗率——但那语气也非常可爱——一面从踏得半紧的雪堆中踉踉跄跄地走过来。“给你做胸膛的白雪。啊，紫罗兰，她的模样开始变得多么——美——丽呀！”

“是呀，”紫罗兰若有所思地轻声说，“我们的雪妹妹的确很可爱。我真没有想到，牡丹，我们能堆出一个这么漂亮的小姑娘。”

妈妈一边听一边想，假如仙女们——或者更好些——小天使们能从天堂下凡，隐着身形同她的宝贝们一起玩耍，帮助他们堆雪人，并赋予它仙童般的相貌，那该是多么美妙的事情啊！紫罗兰和牡丹是不会觉察到这些神仙玩伴的，他们只会在干活儿的时候看到雪人变得非常美丽，还以为全是自己的功劳呢。

“我的小姑娘和小男孩配有这种玩伴，只要人间的孩子曾经有过这种经历！”母亲自语道，接着又为自己母性的骄傲而自嘲地笑起来。

然而，这个念头却牢牢抓住了她的想象；她不时地朝窗外瞥上一眼，半梦半真地觉得自己会看到来自天堂的金发仙童正在同金发的紫罗兰和红脸蛋的牡丹玩耍着。

现在，有一阵子，又传来两个孩子匆促而热切的却又不太分明的说话声，这是紫罗兰和牡丹正高兴地协力干活儿。紫罗兰好像仍然在当指挥，牡丹则更像是出劳力的，从远处近处给她运雪过来。不过这小淘气显然很通晓自己的行当！

“牡丹，牡丹！”紫罗兰喊道，因为弟弟又跑到花园另一边去了。“把绕在梨树矮枝上的小雪圈弄些过来。你可以爬到雪堆上去，牡丹，这样就容易摸到了。给雪妹妹做鬈发非得要用它！”

“给你，紫罗兰！”小男孩回答，“当心别弄碎了。干得好！干得好！多漂亮啊！”

“她是不是很可爱啊？”紫罗兰的声音里含着满足，“现在我们还得弄些闪亮的小冰块来，给她做亮晶晶的眼睛。她还没完工哪。妈妈会觉得她非常美丽；不过爸爸会说：‘啐！瞎胡闹！——快从冰冷的外面进屋来！’”

“我们叫妈妈朝窗外看，”牡丹说，接着就大声喊，“妈妈！妈妈！！妈妈！！！朝外看，看我们做了一个多可爱的小雪妹妹呀！”

母亲暂时放下手中的活儿，朝窗外望去。可是碰巧这时太阳已经降落得接近地球边缘——因为今天属于一年中白昼最短的季节——余晖正斜照着这位太太的双眼。所以你要明白，她被晃得眼花缭乱，不太能看清花园里的东西。不过，透过夕阳与新雪那明亮炫目的光线，她还是看到园中有一个小小的白色身影，似乎跟真人一模一样。她也看到了紫罗兰和牡丹——实际上她看他们的时间比看雪人更长——她看到两个孩子还在忙着干活儿；牡丹在运送新雪，紫罗兰则把雪堆到雪人身上，谨严得就像一个雕塑家在给他的塑像雏形添加黏土。她虽然不太能看清雪娃娃的模样，却暗自思忖过去从没见过谁能把雪人做得这么精巧，更没见过有这么可爱的小姑娘和小男孩能做得出来。

“他们干什么事都比别的孩子强，”妈妈说，心里很是得意，“难怪雪人也堆得更好！”

她又坐下来干她的活儿，而且尽量干得更快些；因为天色很快就要暗下来了，而牡丹的外衣还没有完工，预计爷爷明天一大早就会乘火车到达。于是她飞针走线，缝得越来越快。孩子们也一直在花园里忙碌着，不过母亲仍然在倾听，尽量捕捉到他们的只言片语。她颇有兴味地注意到两个孩子把自己幼稚的想象同正在干的事儿融合在一起，不由自主地完全沉浸在想象之中。他们似乎认定雪孩子真的会跟着他们跑来跑去，一道玩耍哩。

“她会是我们多好的玩伴啊，整整一个冬天！”紫罗兰说，“我希望爸爸不会害怕她让我们患感冒！你能不喜欢她吗，牡丹？”

“啊，喜欢！”牡丹叫道，“我还要抱住她，她会紧挨着我坐，喝我的热牛奶！”

“啊，不行，牡丹！”紫罗兰回答，一本正经地显示自己有见识，“那根本不行。热牛奶不适宜我们的小雪妹妹的身体健康。像她这样的小雪人除了冰棍儿什么也不吃。不，不，牡丹；我们不能给她喝任何热东西！”

有那么一两分钟静默无声，因为小腿儿不知疲倦的牡丹又跑到花园的另一边去了。突然，紫罗兰快乐地大叫起来：“快看这儿，牡丹！快来呀！从那片玫瑰红的云彩里射出了一道光，正照在她的脸蛋儿上！玫瑰红色一直不消失！不是很美丽吗？”

“是呀，真——美——丽，”牡丹回答道，特意留神把三个音节念准确，“啊，紫罗兰，看看她的头发！像金子一样！”

“啊，当然，”紫罗兰平静地说，好像这完全是毋庸置疑的事，“这种颜色，你知道，是从我们看见的天上那些金色云彩里得来的。她现在差不多完工了。不过她的嘴唇应当很红——比她的脸蛋儿更红。牡丹，要是我们都亲亲她的嘴唇，说不定就能使它变红！”

于是，母亲听见了两下轻快的亲吻声，好像两个孩子都在雪孩子那冰凉的嘴上亲了亲。不过，似乎这样并没有使雪孩子的嘴唇足够红润，紫罗兰又建议让雪孩子去亲吻牡丹的红脸蛋儿。

“来吧，小雪妹妹，亲亲我！”牡丹喊道。

“好啦！她亲过你了，”紫罗兰接着说，“现在她的嘴唇很红了。她还窘得有点脸红了哩！”

“啊，多凉的吻啊！”牡丹叫了起来。

这在这时候，西边吹来一股洁净无尘的微风，扫过花园，刮得客厅的窗户咯咯作响。风声令人顿感料峭的冬寒，母亲正要用她戴着顶针的手指去敲窗玻璃，唤两个孩子进屋来，他们却突然齐声对她发出喊叫。那并不是惊诧的声音，不过能明显地听出他们非常激动；像是因为眼前发生的什么事而欢欣鼓舞，而那件事他们一直在盼望着并且料想到会发生。

“妈妈！妈妈！我们的小雪妹妹做成了，她正在跟我们一道在花园里跑呢！”

“多么富于想象力的小家伙啊！”母亲心想，一面给牡丹的外衣缝上最后几针，“说来也怪，他们让我几乎也变成他们那样的小孩子了！现在，我也禁不住相信那个小雪人真的变活啦！”

“亲爱的妈妈！”紫罗兰喊道，“请往外面看，看看我们有个多么可爱的玩伴啊！”

母亲被孩子们这么一央求，再也不能耽搁，赶紧从窗户往外看。太阳这时已从天际消失，但把光明的丰厚遗产留给了那些紫色和金色的云霞，使得冬日的黄昏显得如此壮观。不过，窗户上和雪地上没有一丝刺眼和炫目的亮光，所以那位慈爱的太太能够将花园遍览无遗，看清园中的每一件东西和每一个人。你猜她在花园里看见了什么？当然，看见了紫罗兰和牡丹，她的两个宝贝孩子。啊，可是除了他们，她还看见了什么东西或者什么人呢？嗨，如果你肯相信的话，花园里还有一个小姑娘的身影，她穿着一身雪白的衣裳，脸颊泛着玫瑰色的红晕，鬈发辉耀着金黄的光泽，正同两个孩子在那儿玩哩！尽管她是个陌生人，却显得跟紫罗兰和牡丹挺亲密，他们对她也是这样，仿佛三个人自出生以来就一直在一起玩似的。母亲心中暗想，这一定是某位邻居家的小女儿，看到紫罗兰和牡丹在花园里，就穿过大街跑来同他们一起玩耍。于是，这位慈爱的太太就走到门口，想邀请这个偷跑出来的小姑娘进自己舒适的客厅里来；因为阳光已经消逝，户外的空气正变得越来越寒冷了。

可是，她打开房门后，却在门槛前站立了片刻，犹豫着是不是该请这孩子进来，或者是不是该跟她讲话。的确，她几乎怀疑这究竟是不是个真孩子，或者只是新降下的雪所映照出的一个光圈，被猛烈的寒风刮得在花园里到处转。这个陌生小孩的模样颇有些不寻常。在所有邻居的孩子中，太太想不起谁有这样一张脸孔，有这么洁白的皮肤，有这样精致的玫瑰红的脸蛋儿，额前和脸颊边还有金色的鬈发在飘扬。至于她的衣裳，一身都是雪白的，在风中招展着，在严寒的冬季，有理智的女人是绝不会让孩子穿着这样的衣裳到户外去玩耍的。只要看一看那双小脚，慈爱而细心的母亲就不禁打了个寒战；脚上什么也没有穿，只有一双极薄的白色小拖鞋。然而，她尽管穿得极其单薄，却似乎丝毫也不感觉寒冷，竟那么轻盈地在雪地里翩翩起舞，脚尖在地面上几乎没留下一个脚印。紫罗兰只能勉强赶上她的脚步，牡丹的腿太短，不得不落在后头。

在他们游戏的过程中，新来的孩子有一次跑到紫罗兰和牡丹中间，分别牵起他们的一只手，快活地朝前跳，他们也跟着她跳。可是，牡丹几乎立刻就抽出了他的小手，开始用力地搓，好像手指头被冻疼了似的。紫罗兰也松开了她的手，不过动作没有那么突然，同时一本正经地说还是别拉手好些。穿白袍子的小姑娘什么也没说，只是继续跳舞，和原先一样的快活。就算紫罗兰和牡丹不愿意跟她一起玩，她也能让轻快而寒冷的西风做她的好玩伴，让风儿把她刮得在花园里转悠，任风儿对她那么随意放肆，似乎他们已是多年相熟的老朋友了。母亲一直站在门口看着，心里纳闷小姑娘怎么会那样像飞舞的雪花，或者说雪花怎么会那样像小姑娘。

她把紫罗兰叫过来，悄声地说：

“紫罗兰，我的宝贝，这个孩子叫什么名字？”她问道，“她就住在我们附近吧？”

“嗨，亲爱的妈妈，”女儿大笑着回答，心想妈妈连这么明白的事情都不懂，“这就是我们刚才一直在做的小雪妹妹呀！”

“是呀，亲爱的妈妈，”牡丹高声说，一面朝妈妈跟前跑去，抬起头率真地望着她的脸，“这就是我们的小雪人！她不是一个可爱的小孩子吗？”

就在这时候，有一群雪鹀从空中飞掠而至。很自然，它们躲开了紫罗兰和牡丹，但是——这看来很奇怪——它们立刻就向白衣小姑娘飞去，在她头上急匆匆拍翅飞翔着，然后停落到她肩头上，仿佛确认她是一个老朋友似的。而小雪人呢，见到这些小鸟儿——冬爷爷的小孙子——显然很高兴，就像它们见到她很高兴一样，并且伸出她的双手来欢迎它们。于是小鸟们全都急着要落到她的两只手掌上和十根小手指上，你挤我我挤你，小翅膀使劲地扑腾着。一只可爱的小鸟温柔地蜷在她的胸怀中，另一只则伸出嘴去亲她的嘴唇。它们始终是那么快活，那么惬意，正像你也许见过的它们同暴风雪嬉戏时的情景。

紫罗兰和牡丹站在那里，看着这美妙的情景开怀大笑；他们分享着新伙伴与这些长着小翅膀的客人共度的欢乐时光，就像自己也参与其中一样。

“紫罗兰，”母亲颇感困惑地说，“跟我讲实话，别开玩笑，这个小姑娘是谁？”

“我亲爱的妈妈，”紫罗兰回答道，她严肃地望着母亲的脸，显然对她竟需要进一步的解释感到吃惊，“我已经告诉过你她是谁了。她是我们的小雪人，是牡丹同我一起造出来的。牡丹也会像我这样告诉你。”

“是的，妈妈，”牡丹断然肯定说，红红的小脸显得非常严肃，“这就是雪孩子。她不是很可爱吗？不过，妈妈，她的手多冷啊！”

正当妈妈犹豫着不知该怎么想和怎么做的时候，临街的大门忽然被推开了，紫罗兰和牡丹的父亲走了进来。他穿着宽大的厚绒呢短外衣，毛皮帽低低拉下来罩在耳朵上，戴着一双极厚的手套。林赛先生是个中年人，那张被风吹红、被霜刺疼的脸上显露出疲乏却又快乐的神情，仿佛他已经忙碌了一整天，现在很高兴能回到安宁的家中。他看到妻子和孩子们，不由得双眼一亮，虽然发现全家人在这么阴冷的天气，而且在日落之后都站在露天里，忍不住说了一两句表示惊奇的话。他很快就发觉了那个穿白衣的陌生小姑娘，正在花园里跑来跑去，就像一只旋舞的雪花圈，还有一群雪鹀在她头上飞翔着。

“嗨，那个小姑娘是谁呀？”这位深明事理的男人问道，“她母亲一定是疯了，竟让她在今天这样冷得刺骨的天气里跑出来，只穿着那件轻飘飘的白袍子，那么一双薄薄的拖鞋！”

“亲爱的丈夫，”他妻子说，“关于这个小家伙我知道的并不比你多。我猜想，大概是哪家邻居的孩子吧。可我们的紫罗兰和牡丹，”她接着又补充道，暗自笑话自己居然会重复一个如此荒唐的故事，“却硬说她只不过是个小雪人，他俩差不多整个下午都在花园里忙着干这件事。”

母亲一边说着，一边把目光投向孩子们原来堆雪人的地方。当她看到孩子们费了那么多工夫堆成的雪人竟然无踪无影，是何等惊异啊！——根本没有雪人——甚至也没有雪堆！——什么也没有，除了一块空地周围留下的一圈小脚印！

“这真是太奇怪了！”她说。

“有什么奇怪的，亲爱的妈妈？”紫罗兰问，“亲爱的爸爸，难道你还不明白吗？这就是我们的小雪人，是牡丹和我造出来的，因为我们想再有个玩伴。是不是，牡丹？”

“是呀，爸爸，”红脸蛋儿的牡丹说，“这是我们的小雪妹妹，她不是很——美——丽吗？可是她给了我一个那么冷的吻！”

“啐！胡说八道，孩子们！”他们那正直而诚实的父亲大喝道，我们已经提到过，他看待事物特别符合常情常理。“别告诉我什么用雪造出活人来的胡话。好啦，太太；这个陌生的小姑娘片刻也不能在阴冷的户外待下去了。我们要把她带进客厅里去；你用热面包和热牛奶给她做一餐晚饭，尽量让她舒适些。同时，我到几个邻居家去问一问；如果有必要，叫城里传呼消息的人沿街喊一喊，通知大家这儿有个走丢了的孩子。”

这位为人诚实而且心地非常仁慈的男子一边这么说着，一边朝白衣小姑娘走去，心中怀着世上最良好的意愿。可是紫罗兰和牡丹每人拉住父亲的一只手，急切地恳求他别带她进屋。

“亲爱的爸爸，”紫罗兰喊道，把身子朝他跟前一挡，“我给你说的是实话！这是我们的小雪妹妹，她不呼吸寒风就一刻也活不下去。别带她进暖和的屋子！”

“是的，爸爸，”牡丹高声叫道，热切地用力跺着他的小脚，“这就是我们的小雪娃娃！她不喜欢热烘烘的炉火！”

“胡说八道，孩子们，胡说八道，胡说八道！”父亲喝道，他认为他们这是愚蠢的固执，半觉恼怒，半觉好笑。“跑步进屋去，马上跑！现在天太晚了，不能再玩了。我必须赶紧照料这个小姑娘，不然她会冻死的！”

“亲爱的丈夫！”妻子悄声地说——她一直在仔细观看那个雪孩子，现在感到比原先更迷惑了——“这件事里有些地方真的很奇特。你会觉得我在犯傻——不过——不过——说不定我们的孩子做雪人的那种单纯与真诚，吸引了某个隐身的天使吧？说不定她在那永恒生命中花上一个钟头，来和两个可爱的小家伙玩耍了一会儿吧？其结果就产生了人们所说的奇迹。不，不！别笑我；我知道这是个愚蠢的想法！”

“我亲爱的太太，”丈夫开心大笑着回答，“你简直跟紫罗兰和牡丹一样是个孩子。”

在某种意义上看，她的确是如此，因为她终其一生都让自己的心充满了孩子般的单纯与真诚，她的心就像水晶一样纯洁清澈；而且她透过这明澈的心去看待一切事物，常常能看到极为深刻的真理，其他人却将其视为愚蠢与荒唐而加以嘲笑。

然而此刻，好心的林赛先生已经挣脱了两个孩子，走进了花园；两个孩子仍然在他身后尖叫着，央求他让雪孩子自由自在地留在寒冷的西风中。当他一走近，那群雪鹀就全飞走了。白衣小姑娘也往后逃，一边摇着头，仿佛在说：“请别碰我！”看上去她好像还淘气地把他引向雪堆的最深处。有一次，那位好心人脚下一绊，踉跄着摔了个嘴啃泥，爬起来的时候粗呢外衣上沾满了雪，白花花的活像个最大号的雪人。与此同时，有些邻居从自家窗户里望见他，都纳闷可怜的林赛先生中了哪门子邪，竟在自己的花园里跑来跑去，追赶被西风刮得四处窜的一团雪！终于，经过了千辛万苦，他把陌生的小姑娘赶进了一个角落，这下她再也没法从他手中逃走了。妻子一直在旁边看着，这时已接近天黑时分，她突然惊奇地发现雪孩子身上晶莹闪烁，好像浑身上下都在发光；被赶进那个角落里时，她简直就像一颗星星那样闪耀着光辉！那是一种冷若冰霜的光辉，犹如冰柱在月光下发出的寒光。妻子心想，奇怪的是林赛先生竟看不出雪孩子有任何异常的地方。

“过来，你这古怪的小家伙！”诚实的人喊叫道，一把抓住雪孩子的手，“我终于逮住你啦，我要让你舒舒服服的，不管你愿意不愿意。我们要给你冻伤的小脚穿上一双暖和的毛线袜，再用又软又厚的披巾把你包起来。我担心你那可怜的小白鼻子已经冻坏啦，不过我们会把一切弄妥帖的。快跟我进屋去。”

就这样，这位意愿极其良好的先生尽管满脸冻成了青紫色，却仍然带着最慈爱的笑容，拉住雪孩子的手朝家门走去。雪孩子跟着他，垂头丧气，满心的不乐意；她身上所有的光辉和闪光都消失了。刚才她还像霜冻时节缀满群星的明亮黄昏，在寒冷的地平线上焕发出绯红的余晖，现在却像融化了的冰雪一样阴郁暗淡，没精打采。在慈爱的林赛先生带她走上门前的台阶时，紫罗兰和牡丹窥视着他的脸——他们眼中充满了泪水，没等流下脸蛋儿就冻成了冰——姐弟俩再次恳求他别带小雪人进屋。

“不带她进去！”那位好心肠的人惊呼道，“嗨，你疯啦，我的小紫罗兰！——真是疯了，我的小牡丹！她已经这么冰凉啦，她的手几乎把我的手给冻坏了，尽管我戴着厚厚的手套。你们想让她冻死吗！”

在他走上台阶的时候，妻子又久久地凝视着陌生的白衣小姑娘，目光热切，几乎充满了敬畏。她不知道这是不是一场梦，但她总觉得自己看到这孩子的脖子上印着紫罗兰细小的手指印。大概紫罗兰在堆雪人的时候曾经用手轻轻地拍过她一下，却忘了把迹印抹平。

“不管怎么说，我的丈夫，”母亲再次想起天使们也许会跟她自己一样，很高兴同紫罗兰和牡丹一起玩，“不管怎么说，这孩子的确出奇地像个雪人！我相信她是雪做成的！”

一阵西风刮到雪孩子身上，她又像一颗星星那样闪光了。

“雪做成的！”林赛先生重复道，硬把不情愿的客人拉进他那殷勤好客的房门，“难怪她看上去就像雪。她都冻得半死啦，可怜的小家伙！不过旺旺的一炉火就能使她一切正常！”

这位极其仁慈和富于常识的好人不再多说，而且怀着一贯的良好愿望，把白衣小姑娘拽离严寒的户外，带进了舒适的客厅；而小姑娘则垂头丧气，越来越萎靡不振。客厅里一只海德堡火炉里填满了熊熊燃烧的无烟煤，正透过铁门上的云母薄板射出明亮的火光，把炉子上的水壶烧得雾气腾腾，咕咕欢唱。一股温暖闷人的气息弥漫在整个房间里。离炉子最远的一面墙上挂着一只温度计，显示着八十度(1)。客厅里挂着红色窗帘，铺着红色地毯，看上去和室内的温度一样使人感到暖融融的。这儿的气氛同室外寒冷的冬日黄昏真有天壤之别，正像从新地岛(2)一步跨入印度最热的地区，或者从北极一下子钻进了火炉。啊，这对陌生的白衣小姑娘可真是个好地方！

那位通晓常识的人让雪孩子站在炉前的地毯上，正对着嘶嘶作响、腾腾冒气的火炉。

“现在她会感觉舒服啦！”林赛先生高声说，一边搓着双手，环顾左右，脸上露出你所见过的最愉悦的微笑。“就跟在自己家里一样别拘束，我的孩子。”

白衣小姑娘站在炉前的地毯上，炉火的热浪像瘟疫一样猛扑过来，她显得是那么忧伤，忧伤而又消沉。有那么一次，她渴望地朝窗外投去一道目光，透过红色窗帘瞥见了白雪覆盖的屋顶，闪着寒光的星星，以及寒夜一切激动人心的美妙景象。寒风吹得窗户玻璃咯咯作响，仿佛正在召唤她前去，可是雪孩子却站在火热的炉前，越来越萎靡！

然而，通晓常识的林赛先生却看不出有什么不恰当。

“好啦，太太，”他说，“马上给她穿一双厚袜子，裹一条羊毛披巾或者毯子；告诉朵拉，牛奶一烧开就给她吃点暖和的东西当晚饭。你们，紫罗兰和牡丹，逗你们的小朋友开开心。你们看看，她发现自己来到一个陌生的地方，是那么没精打采。至于我嘛，要去几家邻居那儿转转，弄清楚她是谁家的孩子。”

这时候母亲就去找披巾和袜子，因为无论她生性多么敏感而细腻，到头来自己的观点总是会向丈夫顽固的实利主义让步。林赛先生毫不理睬两个孩子的抗议，任他们咕哝着说什么小雪妹妹不喜欢暖和，径直走了出去，还小心地回手把客厅门关好。他把大衣领子翻上去罩住耳朵，走出了屋子，刚走到临街的大门前，就听到紫罗兰和牡丹在尖声叫他回来，还有一只戴着顶针的手指在敲客厅的窗户。

“丈夫！丈夫！”妻子喊道，她惊恐的脸出现在窗户玻璃后面，“用不着去找孩子的父母啦！”

“我们告诉过你的，父亲！”当他回到客厅里的时候，紫罗兰和牡丹尖叫着说，“你非要带她进来；现在我们可怜的——可爱的——美丽的小雪妹妹融化了！”

两个孩子自己可爱的小脸蛋也融化出了滔滔泪水；父亲看到在这平凡无奇的世界上竟会偶尔发生这等怪事，于是颇为忧虑自己的孩子也会融化掉！他怀着极度的困惑，要求妻子给他解释一下，而她只能回答说，自己被紫罗兰和牡丹的叫喊声唤回客厅，发现白衣小姑娘已经渺无踪影，只留下一堆白雪，就在她仔细查看的时候，白雪也快在地毯上融化光了。

“你看那儿，就只剩下这个啦！”她补充说，指着炉子跟前的一汪水。

“是呀，爸爸，”紫罗兰说，她透过泪水用责备的目光看着他，“我们可爱的小雪妹妹只剩下一摊水啦！”

“讨厌的爸爸！”牡丹跺着脚喊道——我讲到这儿发起抖来——他还朝那位通晓常识的人挥舞着小拳头哩，“我们告诉过你会发生什么事！你为什么非要拉她进来？”

海德堡火炉似乎也透过铁门上的云母薄板对好心的林赛先生怒目而视，就像一个红眼魔鬼，为自己的恶作剧而扬扬得意！

你会说这是一桩罕见的怪事，然而它也会偶尔发生，常识一碰上这种事就不知所措。对于林赛先生所属的那个精明阶层的人来说，尽管小雪人的奇特故事或许只是件孩子气的傻事，然而也可以按照不同方式引出种种教训，给他们带来巨大的启示。譬如说教训之一就是，人们，尤其是心地仁慈的人们，应该预先考虑清楚自己要做的事，在按照自己的慈善目的行动之前，应该确信自己弄清了行动的性质和一切与之相关的东西。对某一个人而言是确凿无疑的有益之事，对另一个人来说则可能是绝对的灾祸。即使是客厅的温暖吧，对于像紫罗兰和牡丹这样的血肉之躯可谓适宜——尽管并不能说对他们的健康就非常有益——但对于不幸的小雪人来说，却只会导致毁灭。

但是，说到底，对于林赛先生这种类型的聪明人而言，是不可能引出任何教训的。他们通晓一切——啊，的确！——包括过去的一切，现在的一切，将来可能发生的一切。假如有某种源于自然或者出于天意的现象超越了他们的思维，他们是辨认不出来的，哪怕就在他们的鼻子尖下面发生。

“太太，”林赛先生在沉默片刻之后说，“你看孩子们的脚带进来多少雪啊！弄得炉子前面那么大一摊水。叫朵拉拿几条毛巾来吸干它！”

————————————————————

(1) 此处系指华氏温度（The Fahrenheit scale）。

(2) 新地岛（Nova Zembla）：前苏联欧洲部分东北部的两个岛屿。

六

从此以后，他在树林中和沙阜上，旋儿的旁边，似乎不再那么高兴和自得了。凡有旋儿所讲述和指示的，都不能满足他的思想。他每次必想那小书，但议论却不敢。他所看见的，也不再先前似的美丽和神奇了。云是这样地黑而重，使他恐怖，仿佛就要从头上压下来。倘秋风不歇地摇撼和鞭扑这可怜的疲倦的林木，致使浅绿的叶腹翻向上边，以及黄色的柯叶和枯枝在空气中飘摇时，也使他觉得悲痛。

旋儿所说的，于他不满足。许多是他不懂，即使提出一个他所日夜操心的问题来，他也永是得不到圆满分明的答案。他于是又想那一切全都这样清楚和简单地写着的小书，想那将来的永是晴明而沉静的秋日。

“将知！将知！”

“约翰，我怕你终于还是一个人，你的友情也正如人类的一样，在我之后和你说话的第一个，将你的信任全都夺去了。唉，我的母亲一点也不错。”

“不，旋儿！你却聪明过于将知，你也聪明如同小书。你为什么不告诉我一切的呢？就看罢！为什么风吹树木，至使它们必须弯而又弯呢？它们不能再——最美的枝条折断，成百的叶儿纷坠，纵然它们也还碧绿和新鲜。它们都这样地疲乏，也不再能够支撑了，但仍然从这粗野的恶意的风，永是从新的摇动和打击。为什么这样的呢？风要怎样呢？”

“可怜的约翰！这是人的议论呵！”

“使它静着罢，旋儿。我要安静和日光。”

“你的质问和愿望都很像一个人，因此既没有回答，更没有满足。如果你不去学学质问和希望些较好的事，那秋日便将永不为你黎明，而你也将如说起将知的成千的人们一样了。”

“有这么多的人们么？”

“是的，成千的！将知做得很秘密，但他仍然是一个永不能沉默他的秘密的胡涂的饶舌者。他希望在人间觅得那小书，且向每个或者能够帮助他的人宣传他的智慧。他并且已经将许多人们因此弄得不幸了。人们相信他，想自己觅得那书，正如几个试验炼金的一样地热烈。他们牺牲一切，忘却了所有他们的工作和他们的幸福，而自己监禁在厚的书籍、奇特的工具和装置之间。他们将生活和健康抛在一旁，他们忘却了蔚蓝的天和这温和的慈惠的天然——以及他们的同类。有时他们也觅得紧要和有用的东西，有如从他们的洞穴里，掷上明朗的地面来的金块似的。他们自己和这不相干，让别人去享用，而自己却奋发地无休无息地在黑暗里更向远处掘和挖。他们并非寻金，倒是寻小书，他们沉沦得越深，离花和光就越远，由此他们希望得越多，而他们的期待也越滋长。有几个却因这工作而昏聩了，忘其所以，一直捣乱到苦恼的儿戏。于是那山鬼便将他们变得稚气。人看见，他们怎样地用沙来造小塔，并且计算到它落成为止要用多少粒沙；他们做小瀑布，并且细算那水所形成的各个涡和各个浪；他们掘小沟，还应用所有他们的坚忍和才智，为的是将这掘得光滑，而且没有小石头。倘有谁来搅扰了在他们工作上的这昏迷，并且问，他们做着什么事。他们便正经地重要地看定你，还喃喃道：‘将知！将知！’

“是的，一切都是那么的可恶的山鬼的罪！你要小心他，约翰！”

但约翰却凝视着对面的摇动和呼哨的树木。在他明彻的孩童眼上，嫩皮肤都打起皱来了。他从来没有这样严正地凝视过。

“而仍然——你自己说过——那书儿是存在的！阿，我确实知道，那上面也载着你所不愿意说出名字来的那大光。”

“可怜的，可怜的约翰！”旋儿说，他的声音如超出于暴风雨声之上的平和的歌颂，“爱我，以你的全存在爱我罢。在我这里，你所觅得的会比你所希望的还要多。凡你所不能想像的，你将了然，凡你所希望知道的，你将是自己。天和地将是你的亲信，群星将是你的同胞，无穷将是你的住所。”

“爱我，爱我——霍布草蔓之于树似的围抱我，海之于地似的忠于我——只有在我这里是安宁，约翰！”

旋儿的话消歇了，然而颂歌似的袅袅着。它从远处飘荡而来，匀整而且庄严，透过了风的吹拂和呼啸——平和如月色，那从相逐的云间穿射出来的。

旋儿伸开臂膊，约翰睡在他的胸前，用蓝的小氅衣保护着。

他夜里却醒来了。沉静是蓦地不知不觉地笼罩了地面，月亮已经沉没在地平线下。不动地垂着疲倦的枝叶，沉默的黑暗掩盖着树林。

于是问题来了，迅速而阴森地接续着，回到约翰的头里来，并且将还很稚弱的信任驱逐了。为什么人类是这样子的？为什么他应该抛掉他们而且失了他们的爱？为什么要有冬天？为什么叶应该落而花应该死？为什么？为什么？

于是深深地在丛莽里，又跳着那蓝色的小光。它们来来去去。约翰严密地注视着它们。他看见较大的明亮的小光在黑暗的树干上发亮。旋儿酣睡得很安静。

“还有一个问。”约翰想，并且溜出了蓝的小氅衣，去了。

“你又来了？”将知说，还诚意地点头。“这我很喜欢。你的朋友在那里呢？”

“那边！我只还想问一下。你肯回答我么？”

“你曾在人类里，实在的么？你去办我的秘密么？”

“谁会觅得那书儿呢，将知？”

“是呵，是呵！这正是那个，这正是！——你愿意帮助我么，倘我告诉了你？”

“如果我能够，当然！”

“那就听着，约翰！”将知将眼睛张得可怕地大，还将他的眉毛扬得比平常更其高。于是他伸手向前，小声说：“人类存着金箱子，妖精存着金锁匙，妖敌觅不得，妖友独开之。春夜正其时，红膆鸟深知。”

“这是真的么，这是真的么？”约翰嚷着，并且想着他的小锁匙。

“真的！”将知说。

“为什么还没有人得到呢？有这么多的人们寻觅它。”

“凡我所托付你的，我没有告诉过一个人，一个也不。”

“我有着，将知！我能够帮助你！”约翰欢呼起来，并且拍着手，“我去问问旋儿。”

他从莓苔和枯叶上飞回去。但他颠踬了许多回，他的脚步是沉重了。粗枝在他的脚下索索地响，往常是连小草梗也不弯曲的。

这里是茂盛的羊齿草丛，他曾在底下睡过觉。这于他显得多么矮小了呵。

“旋儿！”他呼唤。他就害怕了他自己的声音。

“旋儿！”这就如一个人类的声音似的发响，一匹胆怯的夜莺叫喊着飞去了。

羊齿丛下是空的——约翰看见一无所有。

蓝色的小光消失了，围绕着他的是寒冷和无底的幽暗。他向前看，只见树梢的黑影散布在星夜的空中。

他再叫了一回。于是他不再敢了。他的声音，响出来像是对于安静的天然的亵渎，对于旋儿的名字的讥嘲。

可怜的小约翰于是仆倒，在绝望的后悔里呜咽起来了。

III

“Well，where is he，Presto？ Where is your little master then？”How alarming to wake in the boat among the reeds—quite alone—the master vanished entirely！this is something indeed to be frightened at．And now run about，hunting on all sides with timid little whinings，poor Presto！How could you sleep so soundly as not to notice when your master left the boat？ Generally you are wont to wake if only he moves a little．Here—you can see here where your master landed；but now you are on land the track is very much confused．All your busy snuffing is in vain！What a misfortune！The little master gone，quite lost！Seek，Presto，seek him then！“Look！ There，against that low mound just before you—Is there not a little dark figure lying？ Look at it closely！”

For a moment the dog stood motionless，looking eagerly into the distance．Then he suddenly stretched out his head and flew as fast as his four slender legs could carry him to the dark object on the mound．

And when he found that it really was the little master he had so sorely missed，all his powers were too feeble to express his joy and thankfulness．He wagged his tail，his whole body wriggled with glee，he leaped，barked，yelped，and laid his cold nose against his re-found friend，licking and sniffing all over his face．

“Down，Presto！Go to your basket！”cried Johannes，but half awake．

How stupid of master！There was no basket to be seen，look where he might．

Slowly，slowly，light began to dawn on the little sleeper's mind．Presto's sniffing！—he was used to that，every morning．Faint images still floated before his soul，dream-pictures of elves and moonlight， like morning mists over a landscape of sand-hills．He feared that the cold breath of day would waft them away．“Keep your eyes shut，”said he to himself，“or you will see the clock against the wall where it always hangs！”

But there was something strange about his bed．He felt that he had no bed-clothes over him．Gently and warily he opened his eyes， just a little way．

Bright daylight．Blue sky．Clouds．

Then Johannes opened his eyes very wide and said：“Then it was true？”Yes．He was lying among the sand-hills．The cheerful sunshine warmed him；he breathed the fresh morning air；a filmy mist hung over the woods beyond．He saw the tall beech-tree by the pool，and the roof of his own home rising above the shrubbery．Bees and beetles were buzzing around him，overhead a lark was singing；in the distance he could hear dogs barking and the hum of the neighbouring town．It was all real，beyond a doubt．

What then had he dreamed，and what was true？ Where was Windekind？ And the rabbit？

He saw nothing of either．Only Presto，who sat as close to him as possible and looked at him expectantly．

“Can I have been walking in my sleep？”Johannes murmured softly to himself．

By his side there was a rabbit's burrow；but there were so many in the down．He sat up to see more plainly．What was this in his tightly clasped fingers？

A glow flashed through him from head to foot as he opened his hand．In it lay a bright little gold key．For a few moments he sat silent．

“Presto，”said he then，and the tears almost came into his eyes，“Presto．Then it was true！”

Presto sprang up，and tried by barking to make his master understand that he was hungry and wanted to go home．

Home？ To be sure．Johannes had not thought of that，and he did not particularly care to go．However，he presently heard his name called by loud voices．Then he began to understand that his proceedings would certainly not be regarded as right and satisfactory， and that far from kindly words awaited him on his return．

For a moment he could hardly be sure whether his tears of joy had not，in vexation，turned to tears of fear and contrition；but then he remembered Windekind，who was now his friend，his friend and ally；and the Elfin King's gift；and the splendid，indisputable reality of all that had happened；—and so he made his way homeward calmly，and prepared for whatever might betide．

It fell out as he had anticipated．But he had not imagined that the distress and alarm of the house-hold could be so serious a matter．He must solemnly promise never again to be so naughty and heedless．This quite restored his presence of mind．“That I cannot promise，”he said very resolutely．They looked at him in amazement．He was questioned，coaxed，threatened．But he thought of Windekind and was firm．What did he care for punishment so long as he had Windekind for his friend—and what would he not endure for Windekind's sake？ He clutched the little key tightly to his breast and shut his mouth firmly，answering every question with a shrug of his shoulders．“I cannot promise，”was all he replied．

But his father said：“Leave him in peace；he is quite in earnest about it．Something strange must have happened to him．He will tell us all about it some day．”

Johannes smiled，ate his breakfast in silence，and crept up to his little room．There he nipped off a bit of the blind-cord，slipped it through his precious little key and hung it round his neck next to his breast．Then he very contentedly went to school．

Things went ill with him at school that day．He knew none of his lessons and paid no attention at all．His thoughts were constantly wandering to the pool，and the wonderful things which had happened last evening．He could scarcely believe that a friend of the fairy king's could be expected and required to do sums and conjugate verbs．But it had all been true，and no one there knew anything about it，or would believe it or understand it；not even the master，however cross he might be，calling Johannes an idle little boy in a tone of great contempt．He took the bad marks he had earned with a light heart，and did the task set him as a punishment for his inattention．

“You，none of you understand anything about it．You may scold me as much as you please．I am Windekind's friend，and Windekind is worth more to me than all of you put together．Ay，with the master into the bargain！”

This was not respectful of Johannes．But his estimation of his fellow-creatures had not been raised by all the evil he had heard said of them the evening before．But，as is often the case，he was not yet wise enough to use his wisdom wisely，or，better still，to keep it to himself．

When the master went on to say that man alone of all creatures was endowed by God with speech，and appointed lord over all other animals，Johannes began to laugh．This cost him a bad mark and serious reproof．And when his next neighbour read the following sentence out of an exercise-book：“The age of my wilful aunt is great，but not so great as that of the Sun”—parsing“the Sun”correctly as feminine，Johannes shouted out loudly，correcting him：“Masculine，masculine！”

Every one laughed excepting the master，who was amazed at such utter stupidity as he thought it，and he desired Johannes to remain in school and write out a hundred times：“The age of my wilful aunt is great，but not so great as that of the Sun（feminine）， and greater still is my arrogant stupidity．”

His school-fellows had departed，and Johannes sat alone writing，in the great empty school-room．The sun shone in brightly， making the dust-motes glitter in its beams，and painting the wall with patches of light which crept round as time went on．The master， too，was gone，slamming the door behind him．Johannes had just got to the fifty-second“wilful aunt”when a tiny，brisk mouse，with black，beady little eyes and erect ears，came out of the farthest corner of the room and ran noiselessly along by the wall．Johannes kept as still as death，not to scare the pretty little thing；but it was not shy and came close to where he was sitting．It looked sharply about for a minute or two，with its small，bright eyes；then with one spring leaped on to the bench，and with a second on to the desk on which Johannes was writing．

“Well done！”said he half to himself，“you are a very bold little mouse．”

“I ought to know whom I should be afraid of，”said a wee-wee voice，and the mouse showed his little white teeth as if he were laughing．

Johannes was by this time quite used to marvels；still，this made him open his eyes very wide．Here，in school，in the middle of the day—it was incredible．

“You need not be afraid of me，”said he，very gently for fear of frightening the mouse．“Did Windekind send you？”

“I am sent to tell you that the master was quite right，and that you thoroughly deserved your extra task．”

“But it was Windekind who told me that the sun was masculine．He said he was his father．”

“Yes；but no one else need know it．What have men to do with that？ You must never discuss such delicate matters with men；they are too gross to understand them．Man is an astonishingly perverse and stupid creature that only cares to catch or kill whatever comes within his reach．Of that we mice have ample experience．”

“But why then，little mouse，do you live among men？ Why do you not run away to the woods？”

“Oh，that we cannot do now．We are too much accustomed to town living．And so long as we are prudent，and always take care to avoid their traps and their heavy feet，we get on very well among men．Fortunately we are very nimble．The worst of it is，that man ekes out his own slowness by an alliance with the cat；that is a great grievance．But in the woods there are owls and hawks，and we should all be starved．Now，Johannes，mind my advice—here comes the master．”

“Mouse，mouse；do not go away．Ask Windekind what I am to do with my little key．I have tied it round my neck，next my skin．But on Saturday I am tubbed，and I am so afraid that it will be found．Tell me，where can I hide it？”

“Underground，always underground，that is always safest．Shall I keep it for you？”

“No，not here in school．”

“Then bury it out in the sand-hills．I will tell my cousin the field-mouse that he must take care of it．”

“Thank you，little mouse．”

Tramp，tramp！In came the master．While Johannes was dipping his pen the mouse had vanished．The master，who wanted to go home，let Johannes off the other forty-eight lines．

For two days Johannes lived in constant dread．He was kept strictly within sight，and had no opportunity of slipping off to the sand-hills．It was already Friday，and still the precious key was about his neck．The following evening he would inevitably be stripped；the key would be discovered and taken from him—his blood turned cold at the thought．He dared not hide it in the house or garden—no place seemed to him safe enough．

Friday afternoon，and dusk was creeping down！Johannes sat at his bedroom window，gazing with longing at the distance，over the green shrubs in the garden to the downs beyond．

“Windekind，Windekind，help me！”he whispered anxiously．

He heard a soft rustling of wings close at hand，he smelt the scent of lilies of the valley，and suddenly heard the sweet，well-known voice．

Windekind sat by him on the window-sill，waving the bells of a lily of the valley on their slender stems．

“Here you are at last！”cried Johannes；“I have longed for you so much！”

“Come with me，Johannes，we will bury your little key．”

“I cannot，”said Johannes sadly．

But Windekind took him by the hand and he felt himself wafted through the still evening air，as light as the wind-blown down of a dandelion．

“Windekind，”said Johannes，as they floated on，“I love you so dearly．I believe I would give all the people in the world for you，and Presto into the bargain．”

“And Simon？”

“Oh，Simon does not care whether I love him or not．I believe he thinks it too childish．Simon loves no one but the fish-woman， and that only when he is hungry．Do you think that Simon is a common cat，Windekind？”

“No，formerly he was a man．”

Whrrr—bang！There went a fat cockchafer buzzing against Johannes．

“Can you not look where you are going？”grumbled the cockchafer，“those Elves fly abroad as though the whole air were theirs by right．That is always the way with idlers who go flitting about for pleasure；those who，like me，are about their business， seeking their food and eating as hard as they can，are pushed out of their road．”

And he flew off，scolding loudly．

“Does he think the worse of us because we do not eat？”asked Johannes．

“Yes，that is the way of cockchafers．According to them，the highest duty is to eat a great deal．Shall I tell you the history of a young cockchafer？”

“Ay，do，”said Johannes．

“There was a pretty young cockchafer who had just crept out of the earth．That was a great surprise．For a whole year he had sat waiting in the dark earth，watching for the first warm summer evening．And when he put his head out of the clod，all the greenery， and the waving grass，and the singing-birds quite bewildered him．He had no idea what to be about．He touched the blades of grass with his feelers，spreading them out in a fan．Then he observed that he was a male cockchafer，very handsome in his way，with shining black legs，a large，fat body，and a breastplate that shone like a mirror．As luck would have it，he at once saw，not far off，another cockchafer，not indeed so handsome as himself，but who had come out the day before and who was quite old．Very modestly，being still so young，he crept towards the other．

“‘What do you want，my friend？’said the second cockchafer rather haughtily，seeing that the other was a youngster，‘do you wish to ask me the way？’

“‘No，I am obliged to you，’said the younger one civilly，‘but I do not know what I ought to be doing．What is there for cockchafers to do？’

“‘Dear me，’said the other，‘do not you know that much？ Well， I cannot blame you，for I was young myself once．Listen，then，and I will tell you．The principal thing in a cockchafer's life is to eat．Not far from this is a delicious lime-walk which was placed there for us， and it is our duty to eat there as diligently as we can．’

“‘Who put the lime-walk there？’asked the younger beetle．

“‘Well，a great being who means very kindly to us．He comes down the Avenue every morning，and those who have eaten most he takes away to a splendid house where a beautiful light shines，and where chafers are all happy together．Those，on the other hand，who， instead of eating，spend the night in flying about are caught by the Bat．’

“‘What is that？’asked the young one．

“‘A fearful monster with sharp teeth who comes flying down on us all on a sudden and eats us up with a horrible crunch．’

“As the chafer spoke they heard a shrill squeak overhead which chilled them to the very marrow．‘Hark！There he is！’cried the elder，‘beware of him，my young friend，and be thankful that I have given you timely warning．You have the whole night before you．Make good use of your time．The less you eat，the greater the risk of the bat's seizing you．And none but those who choose a serious vocation in life ever go to the house where the beautiful light is．Mark that；a serious vocation．’

“Then the chafer，who was by a whole day the elder，disappeared among the blades of grass，leaving the other greatly impressed．“Do you know what a vocation is，Johannes？ No？ Well，the young chafer did not know．It had something to do with eating—he understood that．But how was he to find the lime-walk？

“Close at hand stood a slender but stalwart grass-stem，waving softly in the evening air．This he firmly clutched with his six crooked legs．It seemed a long journey up to the top，and very steep．But the cockchafer was determined to reach it．‘This is a vocation！’he thought to himself，and began to climb with much toil．He went but slowly and often slipped back；but he got on，and when at last he found himself on the slender tip，and rocked with its swaying，he felt triumphant and happy．What a view he had from thence！It seemed to him that he could see the whole world．How blissful it was to be surrounded by air on all sides！He eagerly breathed his fill．What a wonderful feeling had come over him！Now he craved to go higher！ In his rapture he raised his wing-cases and quivered his gauzy wings．Higher！and yet higher I His wings fluttered，his legs released the grass-stem，and then—oh joy！Whoo-oo I He was flying—freely and gladly，in the still，warm evening air！”

“And then？”said Johannes．

“The end is not happy．I will tell it you some day later．”

They were hovering over the pool．A pair of white butterflies fluttered to meet them．

“Whither are you travelling，elves？”they asked．

“To the large wild rose-tree which blooms by yonder mound．”

“We will go with you；we will go too！”

The rose-bush was already in sight in the distance，with its abundance of pale-yellow sheeny blossoms．The buds were red and the open flowers were dashed with red，as if they remembered the time when they were still buds．The wild down-rose bloomed in peaceful solitude，and filled the air with its wonderfully sweet odours．They are so fine that the down-elves live on nothing else．The butterflies fluttered about and kissed flower after flower．

“We have come to place a treasure in your charge，”cried Windekind．“Will you keep it safe for us？”

“Why not—why not？”whispered the rose．“It is no pain to me to keep awake—and I have no thought of going away unless I am dragged away．And I have sharp thorns．”

Then came the field-mouse—the cousin of the school-mouse—and burrowed quite under the roots of the rose-tree．And there he buried the little key．

“When you want it again you must call me；for you must on no account hurt the rose．”

The rose twined its thorny arms thickly over the entrance and took a solemn oath to guard it faithfully．The butterflies were witnesses．

Next morning Johannes awoke in his own little bed，with Presto，and the clock against the wall．The cord with the key was gone from round his neck．

V

Have you ever loitered in the woods on a fresh autumn day？ When the sun shines calmly and clearly on the richly-tinted foliage；when the boughs creak，and the dry leaves rustle under foot．

The forest seems weary of life；it can merely think，and lives in its memories of the past．A blue mist hangs about it like a dream，full of mysterious splendour，and the glistening gossamers float on the air with slow undulations—a sweet aimless musing．

And now from the moist ground among the mosses and withered leaves suddenly and inexplicably the strange forms of toadstools spring into being．Some sturdy，deformed and fleshy；others slim and tall with ringed stems and gaily painted hats．These are the quaint dream-figures of the forest．

On the decayed tree-trunks，too，there are little white columns in numerable，with black heads as though they had been burnt．Certain learned men regard them as a sort of fungus．But Johannes knew better：—

They are little tapers．In the still autumn nights they burn while the boguey-sprites sit near them，reading their little books．

Windekind had told him this one such tranquil autumn day，and Johannes dreamily drank in the faint earthy smell which came up from the mouldering ground．

“How is it that the leaves of the ash-trees are so speckled with black？”

“Ah！the boguey-sprites do that too，”said Windekind．“When they have been busy writing at night，in the morning they throw out what is left in their ink-bottles over the leaves．They do not love the ash-trees；crosses are made of ash-wood，and poles for church bags．”

Johannes was curious to know all about the busy little sprites， and he made Windekind promise to take him to see one of them．

He had now stayed some time with Windekind，and he was so happy in his new life that he felt very little regret for his promise to forget all he had left behind him．And he had no hours of loneliness or terror，when repentance is always apt to intrude．Windekind never quitted him，and with him he felt everywhere at home．He slept soundly in the swinging nest，where it hung between the green reeds， however ominously the bittern might boom or the raven croak．He knew no fear of the pelting rain or howling storm—he could creep into a hollow tree or a rabbit's burrow，and hide close under Windekind's cloak，and listen to his voice as he told him tales．

And now he was to see the Wood-Sprites．

It was a good day for such a visit．So calm，so still，Johannes fancied he could already hear tiny voices and the rustle of little feet，though it was mid-day．The birds had almost all fled；only the thrushes were feasting on the scarlet berries．One was caught in a snare．There he hung with flapping wings，struggling till his sharp clenched claws were almost torn away．Johannes made haste to set him free，and he flew off with a happy chirp．

The toadstools had a great deal to say．

“Only look at me！”said a fat puffy Toadstool．“Did you ever see the like？ See how thick and white my stem is，and how my hat shines．I am the biggest of you all．And that in one night！”

“Pooh！”said the red spotted toadstool．“You are most vulgar！—so brown and clumsy．Now，I sway on a tall stem like a reed；I am of a splendid red like the rowan berries，and most elegantly speckled．I am the handsomest of you all．”

“Hush！”said Johannes，who knew them both of old．“You are both poisonous．”

“That is a virtue，”said the red fellow．

“Or are you a man by chance？”retorted the fat toadstool．“Then indeed I wish you would eat me．”

But Johannes did not eat him；he took some dry twigs and stuck them into his round hat．That looked funny，and all the others laughed；even a swarm of slender toadstools with little brown heads who had only come up a few hours since，and pushed themselves everywhere to look out on the world．The fat toadstool turned blue with spite，thus displaying his venomous nature．

Earth-stars raised their little pert heads on angular stems．Now and then a little cloud of the finest brown powder puffed out of the opening in a round head．Wherever that dust fell on the moist soil，threads would tangle and plait beneath the dark earth，and next year myriads of fresh stars would come up．

“What a beautiful existence！”they said to each other．“The happiest lot in life is to shed dust．What joy to think we may do it as long as we live！”

And they puffed the little smoke-like cloud into the air with the deepest concentration．

“Are they really happy，Windekind？”

“Why not？ What higher joy can they know？ They are happy，for they ask no better because they know no better．”

When night fell，and the shadows of the trees were merged in uniform gloom，the mysterious vitality of the forest knew no rest．The branches snapped and cracked，the dry leaves rustled hither and thither among the grass and in the underwood．Then Johannes felt the touch of invisible wings and was aware of the presence of invisible beings．He could plainly hear the murmur of little voices and tripping of little feet．There！there in the darkest depth of the thicket，a tiny blue spark glowed and vanished．There was another and another！—Hark！When he listened attentively he could hear a rustling in the leaf-strewn floor near him，close to the black tree-trunk．The blue lights again were visible and then stood still on the top．

Now Johannes saw such lights all about him；they flitted among the brown leaves，dancing along with airy leaping；and in one place a large sparkling mass beamed like a blue bonfire．

“What fire is that？”asked Johannes．“It burns splendidly．”

“That is a rotten tree-stump，”replied Windekind．

They went towards a bright light which remained steady．

“Now I will introduce you to Wistik．He is the oldest and wisest of the Wood-Sprites．

As they approached Johannes saw him sitting by his candle．The wrinkled little face with its grey beard could be plainly seen by the blue light；he was reading diligently with knitted brows．On his head he wore an acorn-cup with a tiny feather in it．Before him sat a wood-spider listening to his reading．

When the pair went near him，the little boguey，without raising his head，looked up from his book and lifted his eyebrows．The spider crept away．

“Good-evening，”said he．“I am Wistik．Who are you？”

“My name is Johannes．I should like to make acquaintance with you．What are you reading？”

“It is not meant for your ears，”said Wistik．“It is only for wood-spiders．”

“Just let me once look at it，dear Wistik，”begged Johannes．

“I cannot．This is the sacred book of the spiders，and is in my charge．I may not let it out of my own hands．I have the keeping of the sacred books of the snails，and the butterflies，and the hedge-hogs，and the moles，and all the creatures that live here．They cannot all read，and when they want to know anything I read it to them．This is a great honour for me，a post of trust，you understand．”

The sprite nodded very gravely several times，and pointed with his tiny forefinger．

“And what were you studying just now？”

“The history of Kribbelgauw，the great hero among spiders， who lived very long ago and had a net which spread over three trees， and in which he caught millions of flies every day．Before the time of Kribbelgauw spiders made no nets，but lived on grass and dead creatures；but Kribbelgauw was a very clever fellow，and proved that all living insects were created on purpose for food for spiders．Then，by the most laborious calculation，Kribbelgauw discovered the art of making nets，for he was very learned．And to this day the wood-spiders make their nets exactly as he taught them，thread for thread，only much smaller．For the spider race is greatly degenerate．Kribbelgauw caught great birds in his net，and murdered thousands of his own children—he was something like a spider！At last there came a great storm and carried away Kribbelgauw and his net，with the three trees it was made fast to，through the air to a distant wood， where he is now perpetually honoured for his great achievements and sagacity．”

“Is that all true？”asked Johannes．

“It is all in this book，”said Wistik．

“Do you believe it？”

The boguey shut one eye and laid his forefinger to his nose．

“The sacred books of other creatures，when they mention Kribbelgauw，speak of him as a hateful and contemptible monster．But that is no concern of mine．”

“And is there a Sprites' Book，Wistik？”

Wistik looked at Johannes rather suspiciously．

“What sort of creature are you really，Johannes？ There is something—just something—human about you，so to speak．”

“No，no；be easy，Wistik，”said Windekind，“we are elves．But formerly Johannes saw a good deal of men and their doings．You may trust him entirely．It can do him no harm．”

“Ay，ay，well and good．But I am called the wisest of the sprites—and I studied long and hard before I knew what I know．So now I must be cautious with my learning．If I tell you too much，I shall lose my reputation．”

“But in what book do you think that the truth is to be found？”

“I have read a great deal，but I do not believe that I have ever read that book．It is not the Elves' Book nor the Sprites'．Yet it must exist．”

“The Men's Book perhaps？”

“That I do not know，but I do not think it．For the True Book must bring with it great peace and great happiness．In it there must be an exact explanation of why everything is as it is，so that no one need ever ask or inquire any more．Now men，I believe，have not got so far as that．”

“Oh dear，no！”said Windekind，laughing．

“Is there anywhere such a book？”said Johannes eagerly．

“Yes，yes，”whispered the sprite．“I know there is，from very ancient legends．And—hush！—I know where it is，and who can find it．”

“Oh，Wistik！Wistik！”

“Why then have you not yet got it？”asked Windekind．

“Patience，patience，—it will be found．I know as yet no particulars，—but I shall soon find it．I have toiled for it and sought it all my life．For to him who finds it life shall be one perpetual autumn day—blue air above and blue mists all round，—only no falling leaves shall rustle，no twigs shall snap，no raindrops patter， the shadows shall not change，the sun-gold on the tree-tops shall not fade．What seems to us now to be light shall be darkness；what seems to us now to be joy shall be woe by comparison，to those who read that book！Ay！I know this much，and some day I shall find it．”

The Wood-Sprite raised his eyebrows very much and laid his finger on his lips．

“Wistik，if you could but teach me—”Johannes began；but before he could say more he felt a strong gust of wind and saw a great，broad black shroud overhead，which silently and swiftly swept by．

When he looked for Wistik again he saw one little foot just vanishing into the hollow tree．Whisk！the sprite had leapt into his cave，book and all．The candles burnt paler and paler and suddenly went out．Those were very strange little candles．

“What was that？”asked Johannes，clinging in terror to Winde-kind in the darkness．

“An owl，”said Windekind．

Then they were both silent for some time．Presently Johannes said：—“Do you believe what Wistik said？”

“Wistik is not so wise as he thinks himself．He will never find such a book，nor you either．”

“But does it exist？”

“It exists，as your shadow exists，Johannes．However fast you run，however cautiously you seize it，you can never overtake it or hold it．And at last you discover that you are trying to catch yourself．Do not be foolish；forget the sprite's chatter．I can tell you a hundred finer tales．Come along！We will go to the outskirts of the wood and see how our good father draws off the white woollen coverlets of dew from the sleeping meadows．Come．”

Johannes went；but he did not understand Windekind's words， nor did he follow his counsel．And while he watched the dawn of the glorious autumn morning，he was meditating over the book in which it is written why everything is as it is，and repeating to himself in a low tone，“Wistik！”

VI

It seemed to him，all the next few days，as though it was no longer so delightful or so beautiful to be with Windekind in the wood or on the sand-hills．His thoughts were no onger wholly occupied with all that Windekind told him or showed him．He could not help thinking of that Book，but he dared not speak of it．The things he saw seemed to him less fine and wonderful than before．The clouds were so black and heavy，he was afraid lest they should fall upon him．It distressed him when the unresting autumn wind shook and bowed the poor weary trees，so that the sallow under side of the leaves was seen，and yellow leaves and dry twigs were swept before the gale．

What Windekind told him had ceased to interest him．A great deal of it he did not understand，and he never got a perfectly clear and satisfactory answer when he asked one of his old questions．And this again made him think of that Book in which everything was set forth so plainly and simply；and of that everlasting still and sunny autumn day which would ensue．

“Wistik！Wistik！”he murmured．

Windekind heard him．

“Johannes，I am afraid you ought to have remained a human being．Even your friendship is as that of men—the first person who has spoken to you after me has won all your confidence from me．Ah！my mother was right after all！”

“No，Windekind．But you are much wiser than Wistik—as wise as that Book．Why do you not tell me everything？ See now！Why does the wind blow through the trees so that they bend and bow？ Look，they can bear it no longer；the boughs snap and the leaves are flying by hundreds on all sides，though they are still green and fresh．They are so tired they can no longer hold on，and yet they are constantly shaken and thrashed by the rude，spiteful wind．Why is it so？ What does the wind mean？”

“My poor Johannes，you are talking as men talk．”

“Make it stop，Windekind．I want calm and sunshine．”

“You question and want as a man；there is no answer，no fulfilment．If you cannot learn to ask or wish better，the autumn day will never dawn for you，and you will be like the thousands of human beings who have talked to Wistik．”

“What，so many？”

“Yes，thousands．Wistik affects great mystery，but he is a chatterbox who cannot keep his own secrets．He hoped to find the Book among men，and communicates his knowledge to every one who might be able to help him．And he has made many as unhappy as himself．They believe in him，and go forth to seek the Book with as much zeal as some use in seeking the art of making gold．They sacrifice everything，give up their calling and their happiness， and shut themselves up among big volumes or strange matters and instruments．They risk their lives and health，they forget the blue sky and kindly gentle Nature—nay，even their fellow-creatures．Some find good and useful things，as it were gold nuggets，which they throw out of their holes on to the bright sunlit surface of the earth；but they do not themselves care for these；they leave them for others to enjoy，while they dig and grub on in the dark without cessation or rest．They are not seeking gold but the Book．Some lose their wits over the work，forgetting their object and aim，and becoming mere miserable dotards．The sprite has made them quite childish．You may see them building up little castles of sand，and calculating how many grains more are needed to make them fall in；they make little watercourses，and estimate precisely the bends and bays the water will make；they dig trenches，and devote all their patience and reason to making them very smooth and free from stones．If these poor idiots are interrupted in their work and asked what they are doing，they look up with great importance，shake their heads and mutter，“Wistik，Wistik！”

“Yes，it is all the fault of that little foolish Wood-Sprite．Have nothing to say to him，Johannes．”

But Johannes stared before him at the swaying，creaking trees．The smooth brow above his clear childish eyes puckered into furrows．He had never before looked so grave．

“And yet—you yourself said—that there is such a Book！And oh！I am quite sure that in it there is all about the Great Light，whose name you will not tell me．”

“Poor，poor little Johannes！”said Windekind，and his voice rose above the dizzy clamour of the storm like a peaceful hymn，sounding very far away．“Love me，only love me with all your might．In me， you will find even more than you wish．You shall understand that which you cannot conceive of，and be，yourself，what you desire to know．Earth and heaven shall be familiar to you，the stars shall be your neighbours，infinitude shall be your dwelling-place．”

“Love me！only love me！Cling to me as the hop-bine to the tree，be true to me as the lake is to its bed—in me alone shall you find rest，Johannes．”

Windekind ceased speaking，but the choral psalm still went on．It seemed to float at an immense distance，in solemn rhythm，through the raging and sighing of the wind—as tranquil as the moonlight shining between the driving clouds．

Windekind opened his arms and Johannes fell asleep on his breast，under the shelter of the blue cloak．

But in the night he awoke．Peace had suddenly and imperceptibly fallen on the world；the moon was below the horizon；the leaves hung limp and motionless；the forest was full of silence and darkness．

And questions came back on Johannes's mind，in swift spectral succession，dislodging all his newly-born confidence．Why were men thus made？ Why must he come away from them and lose their love？ Why must the winter come？ Why must the leaves fall and the flowers die？ Why—why？

Down in the thicket the blue lights were dancing again．They came and went．Johannes gazed at them with eager attention．He saw the larger，brighter light shining on the dark tree-trunk．Windekind was sleeping soundly and peacefully．

“Just one more question！”thought Johannes，creeping out from under the blue mantle．

“So，here you are again！”cried Wistik，with a friendly nod，“I am very pleased to see you．And where is your friend？”

“Out yonder．But I wanted to ask you one more question—alone．Will you answer it？”

“You have lived among men，I am sure．Has it anything to do with my secret？”

“Who will find the Book，Wistik？”

“Ay，ay！That's it，that's it．If I tell you，will you help me？”

“If I can—certainly．”

“Then listen，Johannes．”Wistik opened his eyes astonishingly wide，and raised his eyebrows higher than ever．Then he whispered behind his little hand．“Men have the golden casket；elves have the golden key；the foe of the elves can never find it，the friend of men alone can open it．The first night of Spring is the right time，and Robin Redbreast knows the way．”

“Is that true，quite true？”cried Johannes，remembering his little key．

“Yes，”said Wistik．

“How is it that no one has found it yet？”asked Johannes，“so many men are seeking for it．”

“I have never confided to any man，never to any man，what I have told you．I never before knew a friend of the Elves．”

“I have it，Wistik，I can help you！”Johannes leaped and clapped his hands．“I will ask Windekind about it．”

Away he flew over the moss and dry leaves．But he stumbled now and then and his feet were heavy．Stout twigs snapped under his tread，while before，it had not even bent the blades of grass．

There was the shady fern under which they had been sleeping．Their bed was empty．

“Windekind！”he called．But he started at the sound of his own voice．

“Windekind！”It sounded like a human voice．A scared night-bird flew up with a shriek．

There was no one under the fern．Johannes could see no one．The blue lights had vanished．It was very cold and perfectly dark on all sides．Overhead，he saw the black tree-tops against the starry sky．

Once more he called．Then he dared no more；his voice was an insult to the silence，and Windekind's name a mockery．

Poor Johannes fell on the ground and sobbed in helpless grief．

VIII

“Now he will come back，”thought Johannes，the first time the snow had melted here and there，and the snowdrops peeped out in bunches．“Will he come now？”he asked of the snowdrops．But they did not know，and stood there with hanging heads，looking down at the earth as if they were ashamed of their haste to come out，and would gladly creep back again．

If only they could have done so！The numbing east wind soon began to blow again，and the snow drifted deep over the foolish， forward little things．

Some weeks later came the violets；their sweet smell betrayed them among the brushwood；and when the sun had shone warmly on the mossy ground the pale primroses came out by hundreds and thousands．

The shy violets with their fine fragrance were the mysterious harbingers of coming splendour，but the glad primroses were the glorious reality．The waking earth had caught and captured the first sunbeams and turned them into a golden jewel．

“Now—now he will certainly come！”thought Johannes．He eagerly watched the leaf-buds on the trees as they slowly swelled day by day and freed themselves from the bark，till the first pale-green tips peeped out between the brown scales．Johannes would stand gazing for long at the little young leaves—he could never see them move，but if he only turned round，they seemed to have grown bigger．“They dare not，so long as I am looking at them，”thought he．

The shade had already begun to be green．Still Windekind did not come，no dove had settled near him，no little mouse had spoken to him．When he spoke to the flowers they merely nodded and never answered．“My punishment is not yet ended，”thought he．

One sunny spring morning he went to the pond by the great house．The windows were all wide open．Had the people who lived there come back？

The bird-cherry which grew by the water-side was entirely covered with fresh leaves；every twig had a crop of delicate green winglets．On the grass by the tree lay a young girl；Johannes could only see that she had a light-blue dress and fair hair．A robin，sitting on her shoulder，fed out of her hand．She suddenly turned her head and looked at Johannes．

“Good-day，little man！”said she，with a friendly nod．

Johannes felt a glow from head to foot．Those were Windekind's eyes；that was Windekind's voice．

“Who are you？”he asked．His lips trembled with excitement．

“I am Robinetta，and this is my bird．He will not be afraid of you．Are you fond of birds？”

The Redbreast was not afraid of Johannes；it flew on to his arm．This was just as it used to be．The being in blue must be Windekind．

“And tell me what your name is，boy，”said Windekind's voice．

“Do you not know me？ Do you not know that my name is Johannes？”

“How should I know that？”

What did this mean？ For it was the sweet familiar voice，and those were the same dark，heavenly-deep blue eyes．

“Why do you look at me so，Johannes？ Have you ever seen me before？”

“Yes I have，indeed．”

“You must surely have dreamed it．”

“Dreamed it？”thought Johannes．“Can I have dreamed it？ Or can I be dreaming now？”

“Where were you born？”he inquired．

“A long way from hence，in a great town．”

“Among human beings？”

Robinetta laughed—it was Windekind's laugh．“Why，I should think so．Were not you？”

“Oh yes，I was too．”

“Do you object to that？ Do you not like human beings？”

“No．Who could？”

“Who？—Well，Johannes，you are a very strange little boy．Do you like beasts better？”

“Oh，much better，—and flowers．”

“So do I myself sometimes；just for once in a while．But it is not right．We ought to love our fellow-men，my father says．”

“Why is it not right？ I love whom I choose，whether it is right or not．”

“Fie，Johannes！Have you no parents or any one to take care of you？ And do you not love them？”

“Yes，”said Johannes thoughtfully，“I love my father．But not because it is right—nor yet because he is a man．”

“Why then？”

“That I do not know，—because he is not like other men；because he too is fond of birds and flowers．”

“And so am I，Johannes，as you may see．”And Robinetta called the robin to sit on her hand and talked to him fondly．

“That I know，”replied Johannes，“and I love you very much．”

“Already？ That is quick work！”laughed the girl．“And whom， then，do you love best？”

Johannes hesitated．Should he utter Windekind's name？ The fear that he might accidentally speak it in the presence of other persons was never out of his thoughts．And yet，was not this fair-haired creature in blue Windekind in person？ How else could she give him such a sense of rest and gladness？

“You，”he suddenly replied，looking full into those deep blue eyes．He boldly made a complete surrender；but he was a little alarmed nevertheless，and anxiously awaited her reception of his precious offering．

Robinetta laughed again，a light clear laugh；but she took his hand and her look was no colder nor her voice less full of feeling．

“Why，Johannes，”said she，“what have I done to deserve it all at once？”

Johannes made no reply，but stood looking at her with trustful eyes．Robinetta rose and laid her arm on his shoulder．She was taller than he．Thus they wandered on through the wood，gathering great bunches of cowslips till they could have hidden under the mass of bright yellow blossoms．The robin flew，as they went on，from branch to branch，and watched them with his glittering little black eyes．

They did not talk much，but looked at each other now and then， with a side glance．They were both embarrassed by this meeting and did not know what to think of each other．But Robinetta had soon to turn back．It was growing late．

“I must go now，Johannes．But will you come and walk with me again？ I think you are a nice little boy，”she said as they turned round．

“Weet，weet！”piped the robin，and flew after her．

When she was away and he had only her image left to think of， he had not a moment's doubt as to who she was．She it was to whom he had given his friendship：the name of Windekind faded from his mind，and that of Robinetta took its place．

And now everything was the same to him again as it had formerly been．The flowers nodded gaily，and their scent drove away the melancholy home-sickness which he had felt and encouraged now and then．Amid the tender greenery，in the warm，soft breeze of spring，he all at once felt himself at home，like a bird that has found its nest．He spread out his arms and drew a deep breath；he was so happy．As he went homewards the figure in light blue with yellow hair，floated before him whichever way he turned his gaze．It was as though he had looked on the sun，and its image danced before his eyes where-ever he looked．

From that day forward Johannes found his way to the pond every fine morning．He went early，as soon as he was roused by the squabbling of the sparrows in the ivy round his window，and by the twitter and wheeze of the starlings as they fluttered on the roof and wheeled in the early sunshine．Then he flew off through the dewy grass，to wait close by the house，behind a lilac-bush，till he heard the glass door open and saw the light figure come out．

Away they went，wandering through the wood and over the sand-hills which skirted it．They talked of all they saw，the trees，and the plants and the downs．Johannes had a strange bewildered feeling as he walked by her side；sometimes he felt so light that he fancied he could fly through the air．But that never happened．He told her all the stories of the flowers and animals that he had heard from Windekind．But he had forgotten who had told them to him，and Windekind did not now stand before him，only Robinetta．He was happy when she smiled at him and he saw her friendship for him in her eyes；and he would talk to her as of old he had talked to his little dog，telling her everything that came into his head，without reserve or timidity．During the hours when he could not see her he thought of her；and in everything he did he asked himself whether Robinetta would think it right or nice．

She herself seemed no less pleased to see him；she smiled and ran quicker to meet him．She told him indeed that there was no one she was so glad to walk with as with him．

“But，Johannes，”said she one day，“how do you know all these things？ How do you know what the cockchafers think about，what the thrushes sing，what the inside of the rabbit-holes is like，and how things look at the bottom of the water？”

“I have been told，”answered Johannes，“and I have myself been inside a rabbit-burrow，and down to the bottom of the water．”

Robinetta knit her pretty eyebrows and looked at him half mockingly．But he looked as if he were speaking the truth．

They were sitting under lilac-trees covered with large bunches of purple blossoms．In front of them was the pond with its reeds and duck-weed．They saw the black water-snails gliding below the surface，and red spiders busily swinging up and down．It was swarming with life and movement．Johannes，lost in remembrance， gazed down into the depths and said—

“I went down there once．I slipped down a reed to the very bottom．It is covered all over with dead leaves which fall so lightly and softly．It is always twilight there—green twilight，because the light comes through the green duck-weed．And over my head I saw the long white rootlets of the duck-weed hanging down．Newts came and swam round me；they are very inquisitive．It is strange to see such great creatures swimming overhead；and I could not see far before me，it was too dark，and all green．In that darkness， the creatures appeared like black shades．Water-snails with their swimming-foot and flat shells，and sometimes a little fish．I went a long way，for hours，I believe，and in the middle was a great forest of water-plants，where snails were creeping and water-spiders wove their glistening nets．Sticklebacks shot in and out，and sometimes paused to stare at me，with open mouth and quivering fins—they were so much astonished．I made friends there with an eel，whose tail I unfortunately trod on．He told me the history of his travels；he had been as far as the sea，he said．For this，he had been chosen king of the pool，for no one else had ever been so far．He always lay sleeping in the mud，except when he got something to eat which the others brought him．He ate a terrible quantity．That was because he was king；they like to have a very fat king；it looks grand．Oh！it was lovely down in that pool．”

“They why do you not go down there again now？”

“Now？”repeated Johannes，looking at her with wide，bewildered eyes．“Now？ I can never go again now．I should be drowned．But I do not care．I had rather stay here，by the lilac-bush，with you．”

Robinetta shook her yellow head，much puzzled，and stroked Johannes's hair．Then she looked at her bird，which seemed to be finding all sorts of delicious morsels by the edge of the pond．It glanced up at that moment，and watched the pair for a moment with its bright little eyes．

“Do you understand anything of all this，Dicky-bird？”

The Robin looked very knowing and went on hunting and pecking．

“Tell me something more，Johannes，of the things you have seen．”

This Johannes was very glad to do，and Robinetta listened with attentive belief in all he said．

“But where did this all happen？ Why cannot you go now with me？ Everywhere—all about？ I should like it so much．”

Johannes did his best to remember，but a sunlit mist covered the dim landscape where he had once wandered．He could not quite make out how it was that his former happiness had deserted him．

“I do not know exactly—you must not ask about that．A foolish little being spoiled it all．But it is all right now—better even than before．”

The scent of the lilac poured down on them from the bushes， and the humming of the insects on the pool，and the peaceful sunshine filled them with pleasant drowsiness，till a bell rang at the great house with a swinging clang，and Robinetta flew off．

When Johannes went into his little room that evening，as he looked at the moon-shadows of the ivy leaves which stole across the brick floor，he fancied he heard a tap at the window．He thought it was an ivy leaf shaken by the wind．But it was such a distinct knocking，three taps each time，that Johannes softly opened the window and cautiously peeped out．The ivy against the wall glistened in the blue gleam—the dark world below was full of mystery；there were hollows and caves，where the moon lighted up small blue sparks，which made the darkness behind seem deeper still．

After staring for a long time into the marvels of the shadow-world，Johannes discerned the form of a tiny mannikin，close to the window，screened by a large ivy leaf．He at once recognised Wistik by his large wondering eyes and uplifted eyebrows．The moon had set a spark of light on the tip of Wistik's long nose．

“Have you forgotten me，Johannes？ Why do you never think of me？ It is the right time of year．Have you asked Robin Redbreast to show you the way？”

“Oh，Wistik，why should I ask？ I have all I can wish for．I have Robinetta．”

“But that cannot last long．And you might be happier still—and certainly Robinetta might．And is the little key to lie there？ Only think how splendid it would be if you two were to find the Book！ Ask Robin Redbreast about it，and I will help as far as I can．”

“I can ask about it at any rate，”said Johannes．Wistik nodded， and nimbly scrambled down to the ground；and Johannes looked at the deep shadows and the shining ivy leaves for a long time before he went to bed．Next day he asked the Redbreast whether he knew the way to the golden chest．Robinetta listened in surprise．Johannes saw the Robin nod his head and give a side-glance at Robinetta．

“Not here！not here！”piped the little bird．

“What are you asking，Johannes？”said Robinetta．

“Do you know anything about it，Robinetta？ Do you know where it is to be found？ Are you not waiting for the little golden key？”

“No，no．Tell me，what is it？”

Johannes told her all he knew about the Book．

“And I have the key，and I thought that you must have the little golden chest．Is it not so，Dicky-bird？”

But the bird pretended not to hear，and flew about among the young pale-green birch boughs．

They were sitting under a sand-hill，on which little birches and broom shrubs grew．A grassy path ran up the slope，and they sat at the edge of it，on the thick，dark，green moss．They could see over the tops of the low shrubs，a green sea of leaves with waves in light and shade．

“I believe，”said Robinetta，after thinking for some time，“that I can find what you want before you do．But what do you mean about the little key？ How did you come by it？”

“Ah！—how did I？—How was that？”muttered Johannes to himself，staring across the green landscape into the distance．

Suddenly，as though they had come into being under the sunny blue sky，a pair of white butterflies met his sight．They flitted and wheeled，and shone in the sunshine with purposeless giddy flutterings；but they came close to him．

“Windekind！Windekind！”The name came back to Johannes， and he spoke it in a whisper．

“What is Windekind？”asked Robinetta．

The Redbreast flew chirping up，and the daisies in the grass at their feet seemed all at once to be staring at Johannes in alarm with their round white eyes．

“Did he give you the little key？”the girl went on．Johannes nodded；still he said nothing，but she wanted to know more about it．“Who was it？ Did he tell you all these things？ Where is he？”

“He is gone．—Now it is Robinetta—no one but Robinetta—only Robinetta．”He took her arm and laid his head against it．

“Silly boy！”she said，laughing，“I will make you find the Book；I know where it is．”

“But then I must go to fetch the key，and it is a long way off．”

“No，no，you need not．I can find it without the key．—To-morrow，I promise you，to-morrow．”

And as they walked homewards，the butterflies flitted in front of them．

That night，Johannes dreamed of his father，of Robinetta，and of many others．They were all good friends；they stood round him and looked at him kindly and trustfully．But on a sudden，their faces were changed，they looked coldly and laughed at him．He gazed about him in terror—on all sides there were none but angry，unfriendly faces．He felt a nameless misery，and awoke with a cry．

IX

Johannes had sat waiting for a long time．The air was chill， and heavy clouds swept over the scene in endless succession．They spread a dark grey mantle in wide folds，and lifted their proud heads to the bright light which shone above them．Sunshine and shadow chased each other with wonderful swiftness across the trees，like a fitfully blazing fire．Johannes was uneasy in his mind；he was thinking of the Book，not really believing that he should ever find it．Between the clouds very，very high up，he saw the clear，deep blue strewn with fleecy white clouds，soft and feathery，floating in calm and motionless rest．

“It must be like that！”thought he．“So high，so bright，so still！”

Then came Robinetta．Her bird was not with her．“It is all right， Johannes！”she cried out．“You may come and see the Book．”

“Where is Robin Redbreast？”said Johannes doubtfully．

“He did not come；as we are not going for a walk．”

So he went with her，still thinking to himself：“It cannot be．—It will not be like this，—it must be quite different．”

However，he followed the shining golden hair which lighted up the way．

Alas！Sad things now befell little Johannes．I wish that his history ended here．Did you ever have a beautiful dream of an enchanted garden，with flowers and beasts who loved you and talked to you？ And have you in your dream had the consciousness that you would presently awake，and all the glory of it vanish？ Then you try with all your might to hold it fast，and not to see the cold light of morning．

Johannes had just such a feeling as he followed Robinetta．

She led him into the big house，into a passage where his steps echoed．He could smell the scent of clothes and food；he thought of the long days when he had been kept indoors—of his school-days—and of everything in his life which had been cold and gloomy．

They went into a room full of men and women；how many，he could not see．They were talking，but as he went in they were silent．He noticed that the carpet had a pattern of huge，impossible flowers in gaudy colours．They were as strange and monstrous as those on the curtains in his bedroom at home．

“So that is the gardener's little boy？”said a voice opposite him．“Come here，my little friend；there is nothing to be afraid of．”

And another voice close to him said—“Well，Robbie，you have found a nice little companion．”

What did it all mean？ The deep lines gathered again above Johannes's dark childlike eyes，and he looked about him in bewilderment and alarm．

A man dressed in black sat near him，looking at him with cold，grey eyes．

“So you want to see the Book of Books？ I am surprised that your father，whom I know for a pious man，should not have put it into your hands before now．”

“You do not know my father；he is far，far away．”

“Indeed！Well，it is the same thing．Look here，my little friend！ Read this diligently；it shall show you the way of life—”

But Johannes had already recognised the Book．This was not what he wanted．No，something very different．He shook his head．

“No，no！that is not what I mean．I know this Book．This is not it．”

He heard exclamations of surprise，and felt the looks which were fixed on him from all sides．

“What？ What do you mean，little man？”

“I know this book．It is the book men believe in．But there is not enough in it—if there were，there would be peace and goodwill among men．And there is none．I mean something different—something which no one can doubt who sees it；in which it is written，precisely and clearly，why everything is as it is．”

“How is that possible？ Where can the boy have picked up such a notion？”

“Who taught you that，my little friend？”

“I am afraid that you have read some wicked books，child，and are talking like them．”

Thus spoke the various voices．Johannes felt his cheeks burning—his eyes were dim and dazzled—the room turned round，and the huge flowers on the carpet swayed up and down．Where was the little mouse who had so faithfully helped him that day in the school-room？ He wanted her badly．

“I am not talking like any book，and he who taught me what I know is worth more than all of you together．I know the language of flowers and animals，and am friends with them all．And I know too what men are，and how they live．I know all the fairies' secrets and the wood-sprites'；for they all love me—more than men do．”

Johannes heard sounds of disapprobation and laughter behind him，and all sides．There was a singing and roaring in his ears．

“He seems to have read Hans Andersen's tales．”

“He is not quite right in his head．”

The man opposite to him said：

“If you know Andersen，my little man，you ought to have more of his reverence for God and His Word．”

“For God！”He knew that word，and he remembered Windekind's teaching．

“I have no reverence for God．God is a great Petroleum-lamp which leads thousands to misery and misfortune．”

There was no laughter now，but a terrible silence，in which horror and amazement might be felt on all sides．Johannes was conscious of piercing looks，even at his back．It was like his dream of the night before．

The man in black stood up and took him by the arm．This hurt him and almost crushed his courage．

“Listen to me，youngster：I do not know whether you are utterly ignorant or utterly depraved，but I suffer no ungodly talk here．Go away，and never come in my sight again，I advise you．I will keep an eye on what becomes of you，but you never more set foot in this house．Do you understand？”

Every face was cold and hostile as he had seen them in his dream．

Johannes looked about him in anguish．

“Robinetta—where is Robinetta？”

“Ay indeed！You would contaminate my child！Beware if you ever dare to come here again！”

And the cruel grip led him down the echoing passage—the glass door slammed—and Johannes found himself outside，under the black driving clouds．He did not turn round，but stared straight before him as he slowly walked away．The sad furrows above his eyes were deeper，and did not smooth out again．

The Redbreast sat in a lime hedge looking after him．He stopped and gazed back，but did not speak；but there was no longer any confidence in the bird's timid sharp little eyes，and when Johannes took a step nearer，the quick little creature shot away in hasty flight．

“Away，away！Here is a man！”piped the sparrows who were sitting in a row on the garden path，and they fluttered away in all directions．

Even the open blossoms laughed no more，but looked grave and indifferent，as they do to all strangers．

Still Johannes did not heed these signs，but only thought how cruelly he had been hurt by those men；it was as though a cold hard hand had been laid on his inmost secret soul．“They shall believe me yet！”thought he．“I will fetch my little key and show it to them．”

“Johannes，Johannes！”called a tiny voice．There was a bird's nest in a holly bush and Wistik's big eyes peeped out over the edge of it．“Where are you off to？”

“It is all your fault！”said Johannes．“Leave me in peace．”

“What took you to talk with men？ Men can never understand you．Why do you tell men such things？ It is most foolish．”

“They laughed at me，and hurt me．They are detestable creatures！ I hate them．”

“No，Johannes；you love them．”

“No，no！”

“If you did not，it would not vex you so much to find yourself different from them；it could not matter to you what they say．You must learn to care less．”

“I want my key．I want to show it to them．”

“You must not do that；and they would not even then believe you．Of what use would it be？”

“I want my little key from under the rose-bush．Do you know where to find it？”

“Yes，certainly；by the pool you mean？ Yes，I know it．”

“Then take me there，Wistik．”

Wistik clambered up on Johannes's shoulder and showed him the way．They went on and on，all the day；the wind blew，and heavy rain fell from time to time，but towards evening the clouds ceased driving，and packed into long grey and gold bars．

When they reached the sand-hills which Johannes knew so well， his heart was sad within him，and he whispered again and again，“Windekind，Windekind！”

There was the rabbit-hole，and the sand-hill where he had fallen asleep．The grey reindeer-moss was soft and damp，and did not crack under his feet．The roses were all over，and the yellow evening-primroses with their faint oppressive scent opened their cups by hundreds．Higher yet grew the tall mulleins with their thick woolly leaves．

Johannes looked carefully to espy the small russet leaves of the wild rose．

“Where is it，Wistik？ I do not see it．”

“I know nothing of it，”said Wistik．“You buried the key，not I．”

Where the rose-tree had stood there was a plot covered with yellow Oenotheras staring heedlessly at the sky．Johannes questioned them，and the mullein too；but they were much too proud， for their tall stems rose far above his head；so he asked the little three-coloured pansies on the sandy ground．However，no one knew anything of the wild rose．They were all new-comers this summer， even the mullein，arrogant and tall as it was．

“Oh！where is it？ where is it？”

“Have you too deceived me？”cried Wistik．“I expected it；it is always so with men．”

And he let himself slip down from Johannes's shoulder，and ran away among the broom．

Johannes looked about him in despair—there stood a tiny wild rose-bush．

“Where is the big rose-bush？”asked Johannes；“the big one which used to stand here？”

“We never talk with human creatures，”said the shrub．That was the last thing he heard；everything remained silent．Only the broom-shrubs sighed in the light evening breeze．

“Am I then a man？”thought Johannes．“No！it cannot be，it cannot be！I will not be a man！I hate men！”

He was tired and sick at heart．He lay down at the edge of the meadow，on the soft grey moss which gave out a strong，damp scent．

“Now I cannot find my way back，and shall never see Robinetta again．Shall I not die if I have not Robinetta？ Shall I live and grow to be a man—a man like those others who laughed at me？”

On a sudden he saw once more the two white butterflies which came flying towards him from the side where the sun was setting．He watched them anxiously；would they show him the way？ They fluttered over his head，sometimes close together and sometimes far apart，flitting about as if in whimsical play．By degrees they went farther and farther from the sun，and vanished at last over the ridge of the sand-hills towards the wood，where only the topmost boughs were now red in the evening glow which blazed out brightly from beneath the long dark levels of cloud．

Johannes rose and went after them，but as they flew up over the first trees he saw that a black shadow followed them and overtook them with noiseless flight．The next instant they were gone．The black shade pounced swiftly down on them，and Johannes in terror covered his face with his hands．

“Well，my little friend，what have you to cry about？”said a sharp mocking voice close at hand．Johannes had seen a big bat coming towards him，but when he now looked up a little black dwarf not much taller than himself was standing on the sand-hill．He had a large head with big ears which stuck out dark against the bright evening sky；a lean shape and thin legs．Johannes could see nothing of his face but the small twinkling eyes．

“Have you lost anything，my little fellow？ Can I help you seek it？”said he．

But Johannes shook his head in silence．

“Look here．Would you like to have these？”he began again， opening his hand．In it Johannes saw something white which still moved a little．This was the two white butterflies，their crushed and broken wings quivering in their death-struggle．Johannes shuddered as though some one had blown against the nape of his neck，and he looked up in alarm at the strange being．“Who are you？”he asked．

“You would like to know my name？ Well，call me Pluizer—simply Pluizer．I have other prettier names，but you would not understand them yet．”

“Are you a man？”

“Better and better！Well，I have arms and legs and a head—see what a head—and the boy asks me whether lama man！Why， Johannes，Johannes！”And the mannikin laughed with a shrill piercing note．

“How do you know who I am？”asked Johannes．

“Oh，that，to me，is a mere trifle．I know a great deal more than that．I know whence you have come and what you came to do．I know a wonderful deal—almost everything．”

“Ah，Master Pluizer—”

“Pluizer，Pluizer—without any fine words．”

“Then do you know anything—”but Johannes was suddenly silent．“He is a man，”thought he．

“Of the little key，do you mean？ Why，to be sure！”

“But I did not think that any man could know about that．”

“Foolish boy！Besides，Wistik has told me all about it．”

“Then do you know Wistik too？”

“Oh yes！One of my best friends—and I have many friends．But I know it without Wistik．I know a great deal more than Wistik．Wistik is a very good fellow—but stupid，uncommonly stupid．Now， I am not！Far from it！”And Pluizer tapped his big head with his lean little hand．

“Do you know，Johannes，”he went on，“what Wistik's great defect is？—but you must never tell him，for he would be very angry．”

“Well，what is it？”said Johannes．

“He does not exist．That is a great defect，but he does not admit it．And he says the same of me，that I do not exist．But that is a lie．I not exist，indeed！What next，I wonder？”

And Pluizer put the butterflies into his satchel，and suddenly turning a somersault stood before Johannes on his head．Then，with a hideous grin，he stuck out a vile long tongue．Johannes，who did not feel at all at his ease alone with this strange being in the growing dusk on the deserted sand-hills，now fairly quaked with fear．

“This is a delightful manner of surveying the world，”said Pluizer，still upside down．“If you like I will teach you to do it．You see everything much clearer，and more life-like．”

And he flourished his little legs in the air and waltzed round on his hands．As the red light fell on his inverted face Johannes thought it perfectly horrible；those little eyes twinkled in the glow and showed the whites at the lower edge where it is not generally visible．

“You see，in this position the clouds seem to be the ground and the earth the top of the world．It is just as easy to maintain that as the converse．There is really no above or below．A very pretty place to walk on those clouds must be！”

Johannes looked up at the long stretches of cloud．They looked to him like a ploughed land，with red furrows，as though blood welled up from it．Just over the pool yawned the gate of the cloud-grotto．

“Can any one go there and enter in？”he asked．

“What nonsense！”said Pluizer，suddenly standing on his feet again，to Johannes's great relief，“Nonsense！If you were there you would find it just the same as here，and it would look as beautiful as that further on again．But in those lovely clouds it is all foggy and grey and cold．”

“I do not believe you，”cried Johannes．“Now I see you really are a man．”

“Come，come！You do not believe me，my little friend，because I am a man？ And what sort of creature are you then，I should like to know？”

“O Pluizer！Am I，too，really a man？”

“What do you suppose？ An elf？ Elves are never in love．”And Pluizer unexpectedly sat down on the ground at Johannes's feet with his leg crossed under him，staring at him with a villainous grin．Johannes was unutterably embarrassed and uncomfortable under his gaze，and wished he could escape or become invisible．But he could not even take his eyes off him．“Only men fall in love，Johannes，d'ye hear！And so much the better，or there would be none left by this time．And you are in love like the best of them，although you are but a little fellow．Of whom are you thinking at this moment？”

“Of Robinetta，”whispered Johannes，hardly above his breath．

“Whom do you most long for？”

“Robinetta．”

“Without whom do you think you could not live？”

Johannes's lips moved silently：“Robinetta．”

“Well then，youngster，”grinned Pluizer，“what made you fancy that you could be an elf？ Elves do not love the daughters of men．”

“But it was Windekind，”Johannes stammered out in his bewilderment．

But Pluizer flew into a terrible rage and his bony fingers gripped Johannes by the ears．“What folly is this？ Would you try to frighten me with that whippersnapper thing？ He is a greater simpleton than Wistik—much greater．He knows nothing at all．And what is worse， he does not exist in any sense，and never has existed．I only exist， do you understand？ And if you do not believe me，I will let you feel what I am．”

And he shook the hapless Johannes by the ears．Johannes cried out—“But I have known him such a long time，and have travelled such a long way with him！”

“You dreamed it，I tell you．Where are the rose bush and the little key，hey？ But you are not dreaming now．Do you feel that？”

“Oh！”cried Johannes，for Pluizer nipped him．

It was by this time dark，and the bats flew close over their heads and piped shrilly．The air was black and heavy，not a leaf was stirring in the wood．

“May I go home？”asked Johannes，—“home to my father？”

“To your father！What to do there？”said Pluizer．“A warm reception you will get from him after staying away so long．”

“I want to get home，”said Johannes，and he thought of the snug room with the bright lamp light where he would sit so often by his father's side，listening to the scratching of his pen．It was quiet there， and not lonely．

“Well then，you would have done better not to come away，and stayed so long for the sake of that senseless jackanapes who has not even any existence．Now it is too late，but it does not matter in the least；I will take care of you．And whether I do it or your father， comes to precisely the same in the end．Such a father—it is a mere matter of education．Did you choose your own father？ Do you suppose that there is no one so good or so clever as he？ I am just as good，and cleverer—much cleverer．”

Johannes had no heart to answer；he shut his eyes and nodded feebly．

“And it would be of no use to look for anything from Robinetta，”the little man went on．He laid his hands on Johannes's shoulders and spoke close into his ear．That child thought you just as much a fool as the others did．Did you not observe that she sat in the corner and never spoke a word when they all laughed at you？ She is no better than the rest．She thought you a nice little boy，and was ready to play with you—as she would have played with a cockchafer．She will not care that you are gone away．And she knows nothing of that Book．But I do；I know where it is，and I will help you to find it．I know almost everything．”

And Johannes was beginning to believe him．

“Now will you come with me？ Will you seek it with me？”

“I am so tired，”said Johannes，“let me sleep first．”

“I have no opinion of sleep，”replied Pluizer，“I am too active for that．A man must always be wide awake and thinking．But I will grant you a little time for rest．Till to-morrow morning！”

And he put on the friendliest expression of which he was capable．Johannes looked hard into his little twinkling eyes till he could see nothing else．His head was heavy and he lay down on the mossy knoll．The little eyes seemed to go further and further from him till they were starry specks in the dark sky；he fancied he heard the sound of distant voices，as though the earth beneath him were going away and away—and then he ceased to think at all．

X

Even before he was fairly awake，he was vaguely conscious that something strange had happened to him while he slept．Still he was not anxious to know what，or to look about him．He would rather return to the dream which was slowly fading like a rising mist—Robinetta had come to be with him again，and had stroked his hair as she used to do—and he had seen his father once more，and Presto， in the garden with the pool．

“Oh！That hurt！Who did that？”Johannes opened his eyes，and in the grey morning light，he saw a little man standing at his side who had pulled his hair．He himself was in bed，and the light was dim and subdued，as in a room．

But the face which bent over him at once carried him back to all the misery and distress of the past evening．It was Pluizer's face， less boguey-like and more human，but as ugly and terrifying as ever．

“Oh，no！Let me dream！”cried Johannes．

But Pluizer shook him．“Are you crazy，sluggard？ Dreaming is folly；you will never get any further by that．A man must work and think and search；that is what you are a man for．”

“I do not want to be a man．I want to dream．”

“I cannot help that；you must．You are now in my charge，and you must work and seek with me．With me alone can you ever find the thing you want．And I will not give in till we have found it．”

Johannes felt a vague dismay；still，a stronger will coerced and drove him．He involuntarily submitted．

The sand-hills，trees，and flowers had vanished．He was in a small dimly-lighted room；outside，as far as he could see，there were houses，and more houses，dingy and grey，in long dull rows．

Smoke rose from every one of them in thick wreaths，and made a sort of brown fog in the streets．And along those streets men were hurrying，like great black ants．A mingled，dull clamour came up from the throng without ceasing．

“Look，Johannes，”said Pluizer．“Now is not that a fine sight？ Those are men，and all the houses，whichever way you look，and as far as you can see—even beyond the blue towers there—are full of men—quite full from top to bottom．Is not that wonderful？ That is rather different from a sand-hill！”

Johannes listened with alarmed curiosity，as though some huge and hideous monster had risen up before him．He felt as if he stood on the creature's back，and could see the black blood flowing through its great arteries，and the murky breath streaming from its hundred nostrils．And the portentous hum of that terrible voice filled him with fears．

“Look how fast the men walk，”Pluizer went on．“You can see that they are in a hurry and are seeking something，cannot you？ But the amusing thing is，that not one of them knows exactly what he is seeking．When they have been seeking for some little time，some one comes to meet them—his name is Hein．”

“Who is he？”asked Johannes．

“Oh，a very good friend of mine．I will introduce you to him some day．Then Hein says to them，‘Are you looking for me？’To which most of them reply，‘Oh no．I do not want you！’But then Hein says again，‘But there is nothing to be found but me．’So they have to be satisfied with Hein．”

Johannes understood that he meant death．

“And is it always，always so？”

“To be sure，always．And yet，day after day，a new crowd come on，who begin forthwith to seek they know not what，and they seek and seek till at last they find Hein．This has been going on for a good while already，and so it will continue for some time yet．”

“And shall I never find anything，Pluizer—nothing but—？”

“Ay，you will find Hein some day，sure enough！but that does not matter；seek all the same—for ever be seeking．”

“But the Book，Pluizer，you were to make me find the Book．”

“Well who knows？ I have not taken back my word．We must seek it diligently．At any rate we know where to look for it；Wistik taught us that．And there are folks who spend all their lives in the search without even knowing so much as that．Those are the men of science，Johannes．But then Hein comes and it is all over with their search．”

“That is horrible，Pluizer！”

“Oh no，not at all！Hein is a very kind creature；but he is misunderstood．”

Some one was heard on the staircase outside the bedroom door．Tramp，tramp，up the wooden steps—tramp，tramp，—nearer and nearer．Then some one tapped at the door，and it was as though iron rapped against the panel．

A tall man came in．He had deep-set eyes and long lean hands．A cold draught blew into the room．

“Good-day，”said Pluizer，“so it is you！Sit down．We were just speaking of you．How are you getting on？”

“Busy，busy！”said the tall man，and he wiped the cold dews from his bald，bony forehead．

Without moving Johannes looked timidly into the deep-set eyes which were fixed on his．They were grave and gloomy，but not cruel， not angry．After a few minutes he breathed more freely and his heart beat less wildly．

“This is Johannes，”said Pluizer．“He has heard of a certain book in which it is written why everything is as it is，and we are now going to seek it together，are we not？”And Pluizer laughed significantly．

“Ay，indeed？ That is well！”said Death kindly，and he nodded to Johannes．

“He is afraid he will not find it，but I tell him first to seek it diligently．”

“To be sure，”said Death．“Seek diligently，that is the best way．”

“He thought，too，that you were very dreadful．But you see， Johannes，that you were mistaken．”

“Oh yes，”said Death good-humouredly，“men speak much evil of me．I am not attractive to look upon，but I mean well， nevertheless．”

He smiled faintly，as one who is occupied with more serious matters than those he is speaking of．Then he took his dark gaze from Johannes's face，and looked out thoughtfully over the great city．

For a long time Johannes dared not speak；but at last he said in a low voice—

“Are you going to take me with you？”

“What do you mean，my child？”said Death，roused from his meditations．“No，not now．You must grow up and become a good man．”

“I will not grow to be a man like all the rest．”

“Come，come，”said Death，“there is no help for it．”

And it was easy to hear that this was a frequent phrase with him．He went on—

“My friend Pluizer can teach you how to become a good man．There are various ways of being good，but Pluizer can teach you admirably．It is a very fine and noble thing to be a good man．You must never look down on a good man，my little fellow．”

“Seek，think，look about you，”said Pluizer．

“To be sure，to be sure，”said Death．And then he inquired of Pluizer：“To whom will you take him？”

“To Doctor Cypher，my old pupil．”

“Ah yes，—a very good pupil．A very capital example of a man！ Almost perfect in his own way．”

“Shall I see Robinetta again？”asked Johannes，trembling．

“What does the boy mean？”asked Death．

“Oh，he was in love，and fancied that he was an elf．Ha，ha，ha！”laughed Pluizer spitefully．

“No，no，my little man，that will never do，”said Death．“You will soon forget all that when you are with Doctor Cypher．Those who seek what you seek must give up everything else．All or nothing．”

“I shall make a real man of him．I will let him see some day what being in love really means，and then he will cast it from him altogether．”

And Pluizer laughed heartily．Death again fixed his black eyes on poor Johannes，who had some difficulty in refraining from sobbing．But he was ashamed to cry in the presence of Death．

Death suddenly rose．“I must be going，”said he．“I am wasting my time in talk，and there is much to be done．Good-bye， Johannes！—We shall meet again．But you must not be afraid of me．”

“I am not afraid of you；I wish you would take me with you．”

But Death gently pushed him away；he was used to such entreaties．

“No，Johannes．—Go now to your work in life；seek and see！ Ask me no more．I will ask you some day，and that will be quite soon enough．”

When he had disappeared Pluizer again began to behave in the wildest fashion．He leaped over the seats，turned somersaults， climbed up the cupboard and chimney-shelf，and played break-neck tricks at the open window．

“Well，that was Hein，my good friend Hein！”said he．“Did you not like him greatly？ A little unattractive and bony-looking，perhaps．But he can be very jolly too，when he takes pleasure in his work．Sometimes it bores him；it is rather monotonous．”

“Pluizer，who tells him where he is to go next？”

Pluizer stared at Johannes with a look of cunning inquiry．

“What makes you ask？—He goes where he pleases—He takes those he can catch．”

Later，Johannes came to see that it was not so．But as yet he knew no better，and thought that Pluizer was always right．

They went out and up the street，moving among the swarming throng．The men in their black clothes bustled about，laughing and talking so gaily that Johannes could not help wondering．He saw how Pluizer nodded to several，but no one returned the greeting；they all looked in front of them as if they did not even see him．

“They go by and laugh now，”said Pluizer，“as if they none of them knew me．But that is only make-believe．When I am alone with one of them they cannot pretend not to know me，and then they are not so light-hearted．”

And as they went on Johannes was presently aware of some one following them．When he looked round he saw that the tall pale figure was striding on among the people，with long noiseless steps．He nodded to Johannes．

“Do the people see him too？”asked Johannes of Pluizer．

“Certainly，but they do not choose to know him．Well，I pardon them for their arrogance！”

The crowd and the turmoil produced a sort of bewilderment which made Johannes forget his woes．The narrow streets and the high houses，which cut the blue heavens above into straight strips， the people going up and down them，the shuffling of feet and the clatter of vehicles，ousted the visions and dreams of the night，as a storm dissipates the images in a pool of water．It seemed to him that there was nothing in the world but walls，and windows，and men．He felt as if he too must do the same，and rush and push in the seething， breathless whirl．

Presently they came to a quieter neighbourhood，where a large house stood，with plain grey windows．It looked stern and unkindly．Everything was silent within，and Johannes smelt a mixture of sour， unfamiliar odours，with a damp，cellar-like atmosphere for their background．In a room filled with strange-looking instruments sat a lonely man．He was surrounded by books，and glass and copper objects，all unknown to Johannes．A single ray of sunshine fell into the room above his head，and sparkled on flasks full of bright-coloured liquids．The man was gazing fixedly through a copper tube and did not look up．

As Johannes approached he could hear him murmuring，

“Wistik，Wistik！”

By the man's side，on a long black board，lay something white and furry which Johannes could not see very clearly．

“Good-morning，doctor，”said Pluizer；but the doctor did not move．

But Johannes was startled，for the white object which he was watching intently，suddenly began to move convulsively．What he had seen was the white fur of a rabbit lying on its back．The head， with the mobile nose，was fixed in an iron clamp，and its four little legs were firmly bound to its body．The hopeless effort to get free was soon over，then the little creature lay still again，and only the rapid movement of its bleeding throat showed that it was still alive．

And Johannes saw its round，gentle eye staring wide in helpless terror，and he felt as if he recognised the poor little beast．Was not that the soft little body against which he had slept that first delightful night with the elves？ Old memories crowded in his mind；he flew to the rabbit．

“Wait，wait！Poor rabbit！I will release you！”and he hastily tried to cut the cords which bound the tender little paws．

But his hands were tightly clutched，and a sharp laugh sounded in his ear．

“What do you mean by this，Johannes？ Are you still such a baby？ What must the doctor think of you？”

“What does the boy want？ What brings him here？”asked the doctor in surprise．

“He wants to become a man，so I have brought him to you．But he is still young and childish．That is not the way to find what you are seeking，Johannes．”

“No，that is not the way，”said the doctor．

“Doctor，set the rabbit free！”

But Pluizer held him by both hands till he hurt him．

“What did we agree on，little man？”he whispered in his ear．“To seek diligently，was it not？ We are not on the sand-hills now， with Windekind and the dumb brutes．We are to be men—men．Do you understand？ If you mean to remain a child，if you are not strong enough to help me，I will send you about your business and you may seek by yourself．”

Johannes was silent，and believed him．He would be strong．He shut his eyes so that he might not see the rabbit．

“My dear boy，”said the doctor，“you seem still too tender-hearted to begin．To be sure—the first time it is horrible to look on．I myself，for some time，was most averse to it，and avoided it as far as possible．But it is indispensable；and you must remember we are men and not brutes，and the advancement of mankind and of science is of more importance than a few rabbits．”

“Do you hear？”said Pluizer，—“science and mankind．”

“The man of science，”the doctor went on，“stands far above all other men．But he must make all the smaller feelings which are common to the vulgar give way to the one grand idea of science．Will you be such a man？ Is that your vocation，my boy？”

Johannes hesitated；he did not know justly what a vocation might be—any more than the cockchafer．

“I want to find the book of which Wistik spoke，”said he．

The doctor looked surprised and asked，“Wistik？”

Pluizer hastened to reply．“He will，doctor；I know he really will．He desires to seek the highest wisdom and to understand the true nature of tilings．”

Johannes nodded，“Yes！”So far as he understood the matter， that was what he meant．

“Very well；but then you must be strong，Johannes，and not timid and soft-hearted．Then I can help you．But remember：all or nothing．”

And with trembling fingers Johannes helped to tighten the relaxed cords round the rabbit's little paws．

席勒名剧《阴谋与爱情》及其在中国的接受
——代译序

杨武能

弗里德里希·席勒（Friedrich Schiller, 1759-1805）是德国文学史上与歌德齐名的大诗人、大剧作家和美学理论家。他最著名的诗作为经贝多芬谱曲后唱遍全世界的《欢乐颂》；此外他还有一些抒情诗、哲理诗和叙事谣曲，也受到后世广泛的重视。

但是，作为剧作家，席勒的成就更多、更大，在德语文学乃至世界文学史上的地位也更加显赫和重要。他创作的《强盗》《阴谋与爱情》《堂·卡洛斯》《华伦斯坦三部曲》《玛利亚·斯图亚特》《裴阿斯柯在热拉亚的谋反》《奥里昂的姑娘》和《威廉·退尔》等剧本，不仅至今仍脍炙人口，经常被搬上德国和世界的戏剧舞台，有的还多次拍成电影，而其中的《阴谋与爱情》又是最著名和最富影响的一部。

《阴谋与爱情》（1784）是席勒青年时期创作的主要代表作，堪称德国狂飙突进运动少数几个最硕大的成果之一，曾被恩格斯誉为“德国第一部有政治倾向的戏剧”。该故事发生于18世纪分裂、落后、名存实亡的所谓日耳曼民族的神圣罗马帝国，具体讲则是在德国境内数以百计的小邦之一的某一个公国。这个公国小则小矣，其在剧中所反映出的政治生态和社会风情的方方面面，于当时整个德国的现实却极具典型性，可以作为其封建、腐朽、愚昧的象征和代表。

该剧通过一对门第悬殊的年轻人由相恋而毁灭的悲惨故事，对荒淫无耻、阴险卑劣的封建统治者及其帮凶，做了无情的揭露和鞭笞。剧本情节紧凑、曲折，矛盾冲突环环相扣，然而演进、展开却自然合理；临近高潮时剧情紧张得叫人几乎透不过气来，但于紧张激烈之中又不乏抒情和诗意，阅读起来也与看舞台演出一样引人入胜。一些场次，如第二幕第二场老侍从给弥尔芙特夫人送去公爵以无数青年给外国充当炮灰为代价换来的珠宝，第四幕第七场露意丝与弥尔芙特夫人之间的尴尬会晤和唇枪舌剑，以及第五幕剧终前年轻的恋人双双为爱情付出了宝贵的生命等等，都可谓精彩之极，堪称德国古典戏剧不朽的经典。

剧中的人物全都刻画得十分成功：正面人物一个个除去其可爱之处，又令人信服地有着各自的弱点，如男主人公斐迪南侠肝义胆，对爱情无比忠诚，同时却嫉妒、多疑，其毒杀恋人的举动更不能不说是可怕的自私的表现[1]；女主人公露意丝天真无邪，心地纯善，同时却生性软弱而且迷信，结果给了坏人可乘之机；乐师米勒作为德国市民阶级的代表，虽不乏自爱、自尊，却惧怕官府，等等。在反面人物中，宰相封·瓦尔特寡廉鲜耻，残忍毒辣，无疑是一个古今中外都有的权奸典型，他为了获得更大的权势不择手段，甚至不惜牺牲自己儿子的终生幸福；宰相的秘书伍尔穆更可谓一肚子坏水，是个为虎作伥、阴险诡诈的地道小人，人间的悲剧往往由这种看似不足道的人引发，剧中的伍尔穆为此提供了生动的例证；侍卫长封·卡尔勃则是任何封建宫廷里都少不了的小丑，在剧中同样并非可有可无的点缀。还有一个看似次要的人物即公爵的情妇弥尔芙特夫人，其身份、遭遇、性格都既复杂又充满矛盾，在剧中地位尴尬而又关键，是一个十分值得注意和颇堪玩味的人物典型。

读《阴谋与爱情》，很容易想到莱辛和莎士比亚的一些著名悲剧，例如前者的《爱米丽雅·迦洛蒂》，后者的《罗密欧与朱丽叶》和《奥赛罗》等。不过比较起来，《阴谋与爱情》的政治和社会意义似乎更明显，批判的锋芒也更锐利、有力，也正因此，它才成为了“德国第一部有政治倾向的戏剧”。

综上所述，《阴谋与爱情》是席勒的一部杰作，不仅在德语文学史和世界戏剧史上占有突出而重要的地位，而且也少有的精彩和好看。

*

古典和近代的德语文学，其在我国流传最广、影响最大的长篇小说无疑是歌德的《少年维特的烦恼》，中篇小说则为施笃姆的《茵梦湖》，而剧本恐怕就数席勒的《阴谋与爱情》了，虽然以中文译本之多而论，它远远无法与已有十多二十种中译的《维特》与《茵梦湖》相比。包括眼前的拙译在内，《阴谋与爱情》迄今仅出版了三种译本，即还有1934年上海商务印书馆出版的张富岁译本，以及1955年北京人民文学出版社出版的廖辅叔译本。拙译曾于1993年收入我本人的三十年译文自选集《德语文学精品》（漓江出版社出版），后来还入选权威的《世界经典戏剧全集》（童道明主编，浙江文艺出版社出版），后来出单行本时做了相当多的修订和润色。不论在席勒本人的创作中，还是在整个德国戏剧文学中，《阴谋与爱情》都可称是一部最为中国读者和观众所熟知和喜爱的作品。

这一论断，可以从下面一些似乎不乏文化思想史意义的事件和事实中得到印证。

首先，在我国的三个不同历史时期，《阴谋与爱情》至少由三个不同的中国剧团公演过，这在席勒本人乃至整个德语的戏剧文学中，都是绝无仅有的。

最为人熟知和受人称道的一次演出在1959年，演出的剧团为北京著名的中国青年艺术剧院。那一年的11月，为了纪念席勒诞辰二百周年，我国首都文化界千余人举行盛大集会，出席纪念会的有文化部部长沈雁冰和首都文艺界的丁西林、老舍、田汉等知名人士，以及德意志民主共和国驻华大使汪戴尔等外交官员。被国外某些研究者称为“中国的席勒”[2]的田汉，在会上做了长篇报告，分析了包括《阴谋与爱情》在内的一系列席勒代表作。作为盛大纪念会的最后一个节目，中国青年艺术剧院首演了由周来执导的《阴谋与爱情》。会后，此剧又连演许多场，成了当时首都文化生活中的一件大事。

从报刊发表的一系列报道和评介文章看，这次为配合席勒诞辰纪念而带应景和急就章性质的演出很是成功，因此著名戏剧评论家李健吾发出感叹说：“看一出演得好的席勒的戏，还想克制沸腾着的热情，是需要功夫的。”[3]

但是，演出尽管成功，仍难免带上那年头奉为圭臬的文艺为政治——现实政治服务的鲜明印记，具有不可忽视的外交和政治意义。难怪评论在极力突出原剧的政治和阶级斗争含义之余，还要顺带批判一下西德的“反动势力”。

1959年青艺的演出，曾由电视台在一间仅两米见方的简陋演播室中直播了十五分钟；可以想见，观众面仍然很是狭窄。不过，话虽如此，对于席勒作品特别是《阴谋与爱情》一剧在中国的影响和接受来说，青艺的演出不能不说具有相当重要的意义。

《阴谋与爱情》的另一次演出，远远不像青艺的演出那么受人重视。从1959年的一两篇文章中得知，那是在“多年前”，即新中国成立前，而且“不怎么成功”。李健吾先生说：“首先，把首相改成警察局局长（记得是这样类似的身份），政治背景缩小了，愤恨的目标也就缩小了。阶级对立的情况被抹杀，故事落入一般贫富之间的婚姻纠葛。就当时来说，这样的改编是出于不得已……”[4]由此，我们不也可以窥知“多年前”那次演出的时代特色吗？

第三次也即最近的一次演出，在“文革”结束不久后的1979年。虽说那时文艺演出异常贫乏，它却并未为一般研究者和评论界所重视。原因也许在演出单位是没有太大名气的东北某省剧团。但是，这次笔者曾在北京通过电视转播观看的演出，在当年对于文艺与政治的关系格外敏感的中国观众看来，却有着超乎寻常的巨大现实意义。[5]人们自觉不自觉地把舞台上发生的事情和现实联系起来，目睹成为封建等级制度牺牲品的年轻主人公的悲剧，很自然地便想到现实生活中受反动血统论戕害的千百万青年男女的不幸遭遇，就把愤怒的目光和批判的矛头同样对准以搞阴谋为其特长的“四人帮”。所以，《阴谋与爱情》的第三次公演不论成功与否，也不论演出的剧团水准高低和评论界反应怎样，在我们研究《阴谋与爱情》的接受和影响时都不应该忽视。

其次，通过上述的三次公演，通过后两次公演时的电视转播和德发电影制片厂同名影片的反复放映，通过两三个文学译本和一册江浚、谭晓春编绘的同名连环画（天津人民美术出版社出版）的流传，《阴谋与爱情》的故事在中国可以说差不多家喻户晓，并在中国公众特别是在青年一代里产生了很大的影响。

可以举一个反映在文学作品中的具体例子。1982年，中国青年出版社出版了叶辛的《蹉跎岁月》。在这部曾经十分畅销并被改编成了同名电影的长篇小说中，有两个与《阴谋与爱情》关系密切的场面：

第一个场面

一天夜里，刚认识不久的男女主人公在庄稼地里值夜，他向她谈到了家庭出身不好给自己带来的苦恼；她想给他宣传党的政策，可是没起多大作用。随后，她关切地问：“哎，我来的时候，你在看什么书？我见你看书时眼里有泪光，这书一定很好看吧！”“是剧本，《阴谋与爱情》。”他掏出一本薄薄的小书说。“这样的书？”她有点意外。“是啊，德国人席勒作的。写一对出身、门第相当悬殊的青年男女的爱情悲剧。”他回答时“带着深深的感情”。可出身“红五类”的她呢，对这类“封、资、修”的书却不感兴趣：“一听名字就觉得不是好书，什么阴谋与爱情，肯定又是写哪个资本家的儿子爱上了一个贫穷的姑娘，不择手段耍弄阴谋想达到目的。听着都作呕。”[6]

第二个场面

三年后，她由于父亲被打成“走资派”而沦为“黑五类”，受到了坏人的迫害。一天卧病在床，为了排遣自己对他的相思，把从他手里借来的《阴谋与爱情》翻开来看。这时作者叶辛写道：

杜见春看了第一场戏，就被深深地吸引住了。她捧着书，听不到鸡啼狗吠，听不到走过集体户门外人的说话声，忘记了自己是个病人，一口气，把这本薄薄的小书读完了。尤其是最后那场戏，杜见春读着读着，不由自主地落下泪来，低声抽泣着。

看完书，她没有把最后那一页合上，呆痴痴地坐着，仰起脸来，两眼瞪得老大，凝视着光线晦暗的屋头。根本没察觉，时间已是午后，也根本不觉得肚子饿。[7]

这两个场面很是感人。它们有力而具体地说明，中国青年——包括出身经历不同的现代青年——是怎样理解和接受席勒的悲剧杰作《阴谋与爱情》的。

至此，自然会提出一个问题：为什么这部在两百年前产生于德国诗人笔下的剧本，能获得中国文艺界和中国观众包括现代青年的理解和喜爱，产生如此深远的影响呢？

原因应该说不止一个，除了原著本身巨大的文学魅力，除了中文译本、中国青年艺术剧院等的演出以及德发电影制片厂的影片都相当成功，还须提及的是中国也有许多类似题材的传统文学作品，因而群众接受起来没有任何困难。但是最重要和最根本的原因，仍在于剧本那反对封建等级制度和门阀观念、争取恋爱自由和个性解放的题材和主题思想。具有这类题材和主题的优秀作品，一般较易超越时代和地域的限制，因为它们表达了人类共同的理想和追求，而对于刚刚脱离“四人帮”封建法西斯桎梏的中国，人们的这一理想和追求又更加强烈。在中国封建社会持续的时间特别长，反封建的民主革命很不彻底，千百年来直至“文革”时期在现实生活中不知演出了多少阴谋与爱情的悲剧。也就难怪，《阴谋与爱情》这部杰作能为我们的读者和观众很快地理解、接受。出于同样的原因，《少年维特的烦恼》和《茵梦湖》则成了在中国流传最广、影响最大的德语古典长篇小说和中篇小说。这样一类的文学接受现象，应该讲绝非偶然或巧合，而是读者集体心理意识的曲折流露和群众理想追求的隐蔽反映。也就是说，从读者的接受和反应不只可以判断作品优劣，而且能窥知一定的社会现实。这，似乎也证明了文学接受与影响研究的意义和价值。

[1]　照现代的观念，窃以为斐迪南毒死自己“不忠”的情人，更应该讲是非人道的犯罪行为。

[2]　田汉年轻时就曾以席勒自比，详见他与宗白华、郭沫若合著的《三叶集》。

[3]　李健吾：《现实与理想——看〈阴谋与爱情〉的演出》，载《光明日报》1959年12月16日。

[4]　同上。

[5]　在同一时期，还演出了宗福先的《于无声处》和布莱希特的《伽利略的水平》等意义鲜明的戏剧，显然并非偶然。

[6]　见《蹉跎岁月》，第40页，中国青年出版社1982年版。

[7]　同上，第402-403页。杜见春是《蹉跎岁月》女主人公。

第一场

乐师家里的一房间。

米勒正从圈椅里站起来，把大提琴靠在一旁。米勒太太坐桌旁喝咖啡，还穿着睡衣。

米勒　（很快地踱来踱去）事情就这么定了。情况正变得严重起来。我的女儿和男爵少爷已成为众人的话柄。我的家已遭人笑骂。宰相会得到风声的——一句话，我不准那位贵公子再进咱家的门。

米勒太太　又不是你求他上你这儿来的——又不是你把闺女硬塞进了他怀里！

米勒　我是没有求他上咱家来——我是没有把闺女硬塞给他；可谁会计较这些呢？——身为一家之主，我本该更严厉地管教自己的女儿，本该更好地提防那位少校——或者立刻去见他的父亲大人，把事情原原本本报告给他。男爵少爷最终会闹出乱子来的，这我无论如何都该知道，而一切罪责将通通落在我这个提琴师的头上。

米勒太太　（将咖啡喝得一点不剩）笑话！胡扯！什么会落在你头上？谁又能把你怎么着？你仍然干你的老行道，仍然招收学生，只要什么地方还有招的。

米勒　可是，你告诉我，这整个买卖结果又会怎样？——他不可能娶咱闺女——根本谈不上娶不娶的问题；而做他的一个——上帝怜悯！——得啦得啦！——就说有这么位贵公子，东游西荡地鬼知道已经尝试过多少美酒，眼下自然也会有胃口来饮一点清水。当心！当心！即使你对每一只夜蛾子都保持警惕，他也会在你鼻尖儿底下把你的闺女骗走，叫她吃亏上当，自己却溜之大吉。姑娘呢，便一辈子身败名裂，要么待在家里嫁不出去，要么就继续操那可恶的营生。（用拳头击打自己额头）耶稣基督啊！

米勒太太　愿上帝发发慈悲，保佑我们！

米勒　是需要上帝保佑。那么个花花公子还会安什么心！——姑娘生得漂亮——苗条——步履轻盈。至于脑顶下边有没有脑子，就无所谓了。一般人都不管你们妇女脑子怎样，只有亲爱的上帝才没有忽视最根本的东西——一当那轻浮少年把这方面的底细摸透了——嗨，瞧吧！他马上就会像我的罗德尼[1]嗅到了法国人似的心花怒放，立刻会挂起满帆，大胆发动攻击，不——不是我把他想得很坏。人总是人。这我不会不知道。

米勒太太　可你也该读读男爵少爷写给你女儿的那些信。上帝啊，真是甜蜜美极啦！他倾心的纯粹是她美好的心灵。

米勒　唯其如此，更加糟糕！为了驱赶驴子，却鞭打袋子。要想向可爱的肉体致意，只得让美好的心灵当信使。我当初是怎么来着？只要先规规矩矩，做到心心相印！等火候一到，肉体便会呼啦一下，跟着也姘在一起！奴仆总是学老爷的样儿；银色的月亮说到底不过是个皮条匠。

米勒太太　你还是先看看少校先生拿到咱们家来的那些精美的书吧。你的女儿常常用它们做祷告哩。

米勒　（吹了一下口哨）呸！祷告！你那吃惯了杏仁饼的肠胃太娇嫩，消受不了这自然的生炖牛肉汤——他必须让它在无聊文人的黑死病魔厨里再煨一煨。快将那些废物扔进火里去！我闺女天知道满脑袋都吸收了些什么荒谬绝伦的东西！它们将渗进她的血液，就像西班牙的蚊虫，把我这父亲勉勉强强还维系着的一点点基督精神也给冲散。扔进火里去，我说！那丫头会满脑袋魔鬼念头，会听信那些懒人乐园中的胡说八道，结果再也找不到回家的路，忘记了她父亲米勒是一个提琴师，以有我这样的父亲为耻。到头来，她将使我失去一个能干诚实的女婿，一个热心关照我的女婿……不！上帝惩罚我！（气急败坏地跳起来）一不做，二不休，我要叫那少校——是的是的，叫那少校明白，咱家不欢迎他这个客人。（准备出门去）

米勒太太　别胡来，米勒！光他送的礼物就值多少钱啊……

米勒　（走回来站在她面前）我女儿的卖身钱，是吗？——你给我见鬼去吧，不要脸的老鸨！——我宁肯带着我的提琴沿街乞讨，为换取一盆热汤而演奏；宁肯砸碎我的大提琴，把大粪灌进共鸣箱中，也不愿靠我独生女儿拿灵魂和幸福换来的钱养活——别再喝你那该死的咖啡，吸你那该死的鼻烟！这样，你就用不着到市集上去出卖你女儿的脸蛋。在那可恶的浑蛋闯进咱们家之前，我同样吃得饱饱的，穿得暖暖的。

米勒太太　只是别操之过急，莽莽撞撞。瞧你眼下真叫火冒三丈！我不过说，别去得罪少校先生，人家到底是宰相的公子。

米勒　问题就在这儿。正因此事情才必须在今天就解决。宰相一定会感谢我，要是他是位好父亲。快给我把红绒外套刷一刷，我要去谒见宰相大人。我要对大人说：您的公子看上了我的女儿，可小女不配做您的公子的妻子；然而她又不能做公子的婊子，因为她是我的心肝宝贝！事情到此结束——在下的名字叫米勒。

[1]　罗德尼（Rodney, 1719-1792），英国海军上将，以在西印度群岛的海战中歼灭法国舰队而名噪一时。

第二场

伍尔穆秘书，前场人物。

米勒太太　哟，早上好，秘书先生。非常高兴又见到您！

伍尔穆　我也一样，我也一样，嫂夫人。哪儿有了贵人的眷顾，那儿就再也瞧不上咱这样的小市民啰。

米勒太太　哪儿的话，秘书先生！少校斐迪南的光临固然给了我们脸面，可我们也并不因此瞧不起任何人啊。

米勒　（厌烦地）给先生搬椅子来，老婆子！要宽宽衣吗，老乡？

伍尔穆　（放下帽子和手杖，坐下来）好的！好的！她怎么样，我未来的——或者说过去的人儿？——我可不希望——我不能见见她——见见露意丝小姐吗？

米勒太太　多谢您问起她，我的女儿可是一点儿都不高傲。

米勒　（生气地用胳膊撞自己的妻子）老婆！

米勒太太　遗憾的只是，她没有见到秘书先生您的荣幸。她正好赶弥撒去了，我的女儿。

伍尔穆　我很高兴，我很高兴。她有朝一日会成为我笃信基督的好太太。

米勒太太　（愚蠢而傲慢地一笑）是啰是啰——不过呢，秘书先生——

米勒　（显然十分尴尬，拧了拧妻子的耳朵）你！

米勒太太　可是——正如秘书先生您将亲眼见到的……

米勒　（极其生气地撞了老婆的臀部一下）蠢婆娘！

米勒太太　好就是好，更好就是更好；对自己的独生闺女，谁又会挡她的道，不让她获得幸福呢？（愚蠢而骄傲地）但愿您将来别记恨我才好，秘书先生！

伍尔穆　（不安地在圈椅里扭来扭去，一会儿搔搔耳朵，一会儿扯扯衬衫袖头和胸前的褶襞）记恨？哪儿的话？——对了——您到底是什么意思？

米勒太太　喽——喽——我只是想——我是说，（咳嗽了两声）亲爱的上帝偏偏要让咱闺女成为一位贵夫人，所以您……

伍尔穆　（从圈椅中一跃而起）您在说什么？什么？

米勒　请坐下，请别激动，秘书先生。这婆娘是头蠢猪。哪儿会有什么贵夫人？胡说八道，愚蠢透顶！

米勒太太　你爱怎么骂怎么骂吧。我知道的，反正知道；而少校先生说过的话，反正已经说过。

米勒　（气急败坏，奔过去抓他的提琴）看你还不住嘴？是想我拿琴揍你脑袋不成？——你能知道什么？他能说什么？别信她胡扯，秘书先生——滚，回你的厨房去！——别当我是个大傻瓜，以为我会指望着靠女儿出人头地！您不会这样想我，对吧，秘书先生？

伍尔穆　我也没资格品评您，乐师先生。您在我眼中始终是个讲信誉的人，而我对令爱提出的请求也是完全算数的。我有一份足以养家糊口的差事；宰相挺器重我；如果我想升迁，是不会缺少举荐的。您看见了，我对露意丝小姐诚心诚意，要是她不让一个纨绔公子搞得晕头转向……

米勒太太　伍尔穆秘书先生！我想请您尊重……

米勒　你给我住嘴，我说！——请别介意，秘书先生。还是老样子，去年秋天我对您说过的话，今儿个我可以重复一遍。不过我不想强迫我的女儿。去亲近她吧，好好儿地——让她看出和您在一起会得到幸福。要是她摇头——那更好——以主的名义我想说——要那样，您只好认了，只好来和她的父亲喝上几杯——不得不和您一起过日子的是姑娘——不是我——干吗我要固执己见，硬把一个不合她口味的男人塞给她，成为她的累赘呢？——这么做了，我在自己垂暮之年将没脸见人，将坐卧不安，饮食无味，仿佛时时刻刻都有人在骂我：你这个坏蛋，是你毁了自己的孩子！

米勒太太　废话少说——我绝对不会同意；咱闺女生就的富贵命；要是我丈夫让人说昏了头，我就找法院去。

米勒　贫嘴婆娘，看我不捶断你的腿！

伍尔穆　（对乐师夫妇）在女儿眼中，父亲的意见非常重要，但愿您会了解我，米勒先生！

米勒　倒了邪霉！必须了解您的是姑娘。我这个吹毛求疵的老头子看得起的，恰恰不会对年轻的馋嘴小妞的口味。我能够准确无误地告诉您，你是否适合当一名乐队队员——可即使对一位乐队指挥来说，女人家的心眼儿也太尖太细。而且实话实说，老乡——咱是个粗鲁的直肠子德国人——我的意见到头来很难得到您的感谢。我不会劝我女儿嫁给任何人——我却要劝她别嫁给您，秘书先生。请让我说完。一个缠着女方父亲帮忙的求婚者——请允许我说——我不相信会有任何出息。否则，他就会羞于走这种老路，而径直去向自己心上人表白的。他要是没有勇气这样做，那就是一个胆小鬼；而一个胆小鬼就甭想得到什么露意丝！——是的，他必须背着父亲去追求女儿。他必须使得姑娘心甘情愿让父母见鬼去也不肯失去他——或者使她自己跑来跪在父亲膝下，苦苦哀求父亲：要么让她服毒自杀，要么同意她嫁给自己唯一的心上人——这样，我才称他是好样儿的！这才叫作爱情！——谁要不能叫女人痴心到这个程度，谁就只好——抱着鹅毛管打盹儿去。

伍尔穆　（拿起帽子和手杖，走出房门）多谢了，米勒先生。

米勒　（慢慢跟着他）谢什么呢？谢什么呢？您可是一点儿便宜没得着啊，秘书先生。（回到房中）他什么也没听明白，他走了——可我一见这个耍笔杆的家伙，就像吞了毒药和砒霜似的浑身不自在。他是那样阴阳怪气，令人厌恶，活像是某个走私客从地狱里偷带进上帝的世界里来的——一双细眯眯、贼溜溜的老鼠眼——头发火红火红——腮帮子向前伸得老长，就像造物主出了一件废品，一生气将这个坏蛋扔到世界的某个角落里来了似的——不！要我把女儿送给这样一个恶棍，我宁肯让她——上帝饶恕我……

米勒太太　（恶狠狠地啐了一口唾沫）这条狗！——不过呢，你也别在那儿不干不净地骂啦。

米勒　还有你，也别再对我提你那瘟神少爷——刚才你已叫我气得要死——本该你，上帝保佑，机灵一点的时候你却格外愚蠢。胡扯一通贵夫人啊，你的女儿啊，究竟有什么意思？他在我看来是头狐狸。你只要对他提提这种事，保管明天就会传得满城风雨。他正是这么个成天走东家串西家、对什么都说长道短的角色，你一不小心漏出一句怪话——得！马上公爵、公爵夫人和宰相全知道啦，叫你吃不了兜着走。

第三场

露意丝·米勒上，手里捧着一本书。前场人物。

露意丝　（放下书，走到乐师面前，握着他的手）早上好，亲爱的爸爸。

米勒　（亲热地）乖，我的露意丝——我很高兴，你经常想着创造你的主。坚持下去吧，他会扶助你的。

露意丝　呵，我是个罪孽深重的女子，爸爸。他来过了吗，妈妈？

米勒太太　谁呀，孩子？

露意丝　唉！我忘了除去他还有别人——我的脑子全乱了——他没来过吗，瓦尔特？

米勒　（伤心而严肃地）我原以为，我的露意丝已经把这个姓氏遗忘在教堂里了！

露意丝　（呆呆地望着他好一会儿，然后说）我理解你，爸爸——感觉得到你戳进我良心的那把刀子；可是已经晚了——我再也不能专心地祷告，爸爸——上天和斐迪南从两边撕扯我流血的灵魂，我害怕呀——我害怕——（停了一停）可是不，我的好爸爸。如果我们由于欣赏一幅画而忽视了画家，那他定会觉得是对他的最高赞美——现在我因为喜爱上帝的杰作而忽视了上帝本身，爸爸你说，难道不同样令他高兴吗？

米勒　（不快地一屁股坐进圈椅）瞧吧，瞧吧！这就是读那些不敬上帝的书的结果。

露意丝　（不快地走向窗口）他这会儿会在哪里呢？看着他——听着他谈话的，都是些高贵的小姐。而我，一个贫贱的女孩，被他遗忘了。（说到这儿吓了一跳，赶紧奔向她父亲）可是不！不！原谅我！我不为自己的命运哭泣。我只是愿意有时——想一想他——这不用付出任何代价。我的卑微的生命——我想把它变作一缕宜人的清风，吹送到他脸上，使他感到凉爽！——我这青春的小花儿——就算小得如一朵紫罗兰，我也希望他踩上去，我愿卑微地在他的脚下死掉！这样我已经满足了，爸爸。高傲、威严的太阳是不会惩罚蚊虫的，如果它仅仅是在阳光中获取温暖！

米勒　（感动地俯身在圈椅扶手上，手蒙着面孔）听我说，露意丝——我的这点残余的岁月，我真愿意将它舍去啊，要是你从来不曾见过那个少校。

露意丝　（惊恐地）他说什么？他说什么？——不！他不是这个意思，我的好爸爸。他不会知道，斐迪南是我的，生来就是我的，是慈爱的天父为了使我快乐而创造的。（伫立沉思）当我第一次见到他——（加快语速）热血便涌上我的脸颊，我的所有血管都流动得更加欢畅，每一次脉搏都在说，每一下呼吸都在低语：是他，就是他！——我的心也认出了它渴慕已久的人，向我证实道，就是他！而周围的整个世界似乎都在同声欢呼和共鸣。那一瞬——呵，那一瞬我的灵魂中出现了第一个清晨。千万种青春的情感从心里涌出，像春来时大地百花怒放。世界从我眼前消失了，可我却意识到，世界从来没有像现在这样美好。我不知道还有上帝，可却从来没有像现在这样热爱上帝。

米勒　（奔向露意丝，把她抱在胸前）露意丝——宝贝儿——好孩子——把我这老朽的头颅拿去吧——把我的一切——一切一切全拿去吧！——可那位少校——上帝做证——我永远不能给你！（下）

露意丝　我现在也不指望得到他呵，父亲。我的生命有如一滴朝露——一个关于斐迪南的梦想就已将它饮尽。今生今世我甘愿失去他。可是将来，妈妈——将来啊，当等级差别的篱笆垮掉以后——当出身微贱的皮壳从我们身上剥落以后——人又纯粹是人——我除去自己的纯洁清白之外一无所有，可父亲不是经常讲嘛，当上帝到来之时，金银首饰和显贵头衔将一钱不值，而心却会受到珍视。那时候，我将变得十分富有。那时候，眼泪将成为胜利的标志，美好的思想将取代高贵的门第。那时候，我也变得高贵了，妈妈——那时候，他还有什么高过他的姑娘之处呢？

米勒太太　（急匆匆站起身）露意丝！少校来啦！他跳过了篱笆！叫我藏到哪儿才好哟！

露意丝　（开始战栗起来）别，妈妈。你留下。

米勒太太　我的上帝！瞧我这副模样！我一定会羞死的。我不能在少爷面前丢人现眼。（下）

第四场

斐迪南·封·瓦尔特和露意丝。

（他飞跑向她——她面色苍白地瘫倒在圈椅上——他站在她面前——他与她四目相对，默默无言地过了一会儿。）

斐迪南　你脸色怎么这样苍白，露意丝？

露意丝　（站起来，扑进他怀里，搂住他的脖子）没什么。没什么。你来了一切都好了。

斐迪南　（捧起她的手亲吻）可我的露意丝还爱我吗？我的心仍然和昨天一样。你的心也是这样的吗？我迫不及待地跑来，只是想看看你是不是高兴，然后也高高兴兴地离开——可你并不高兴！

露意丝　不，不，亲爱的。

斐迪南　我的双眼告诉我，你真的不高兴。我能像看透这颗清亮如水的钻石一般看透你的心。（指了指手上的戒指）这里没有任何一点小气泡我看不见——你脸上流露出来的任何心事，同样逃不过我的眼睛。你怎么啦，快告诉我！我只要看见你这面镜子没有尘埃，整个世界对于我便晴空万里。到底什么事叫你烦恼啊？

露意丝　（默默地、意味深长地注视了他一会儿，然后伤感地）斐迪南啊斐迪南！要是你也理解，在我们的语言中，所谓市民少女含义多么奇妙……

斐迪南　什么意思？（迷惑不解）姑娘！听我说！你怎么想到这个！——你是我的露意丝。谁告诉你说，你还是别的什么来着？你看看，你这虚情假意的人儿，你竟这样地给我泼冷水！要是你全心全意地爱我，哪来时间去琢磨那些事？我呢，一到你身旁，整个理智都融化成了对你的注视，一离开你又化作对你的梦想——可你在爱我的同时还能头脑清醒？——你真该害羞！你为那些想法而苦闷的一分一秒，都是对你年轻爱人的剥夺和背叛！

露意丝　（抓住他的手，摇着头）你想诳我，斐迪南——你想把我的目光从我必定会掉下去的深渊边沿引开。我看见了我的未来——荣誉的呼唤——你的前程——你的父亲——我的一无所有。（惊恐地，将他的手丢开）斐迪南！你我头顶上悬着一把剑！——他们一定会拆散咱们俩！

斐迪南　（跳起身来）拆散我俩！你从哪儿来的这种预感，露意丝？拆散我俩！——谁有能耐拆散两颗联结在一起的心？拆散两根琴弦发出的共鸣？——我是一个贵族——可咱们倒要看一看，我的封爵文书是否比天长比地久？我的贵族族徽是否比露意丝眼里的纹章更加有力量？这纹章表示的是：这个女子注定属于这个男人！——我是宰相的儿子。正因为如此，除去你的爱情，又有什么能抵销我父亲掠夺来的财产将遗传给我的诅咒？

露意丝　我真畏惧他哟——你那父亲！

斐迪南　我什么也不畏惧——什么也不害怕——只怕你的爱情有了限度。让我俩之间阻隔着崇山峻岭好啦，我将像登楼梯一般攀越它们，飞进我露意丝的怀抱。厄运的风暴只会鼓起我的感情之帆，危难只会使我的露意丝更加妩媚迷人。——我说，亲爱的，什么也别害怕。我——我愿亲自守护着你，就像魔龙守护着地下的宝藏——信赖我吧。你不再需要守护天使——我愿置身于你和命运之间——承受你的一切伤痛——为你搜集快乐之杯的一点一滴，然后用爱情的金盏盛着奉献给你。（温柔地搂着她）这条胳膊将支撑我的露意丝走完人生旅程；当上帝在迎接她时，将发现她比离开时更加美丽，因而惊叹塑造灵魂的工作最后只能由爱情来完成……

露意丝　（推开他，异常激动）别说啦！我求求你，别说啦！——要是你知道——别折磨我——我不知道，你的这些希望如何像箭一样刺痛我的心。（想走开）

斐迪南　（拉住她）露意丝！怎么啦？怎么回事？干吗突然这样？

露意丝　我原本忘掉了这样的梦想，生活得幸福、宁静。——可现在！可现在！——从今以后——我生活的平静失去了。——胸中将不断骚动着——我知道——种种的痴心妄想。——走吧——上帝宽恕你！——你在我宁静的年轻心房中扔了一把火，它永远永远不会熄灭。（冲出房去。斐迪南无言地追赶）

第五场

宰相家的大厅。

宰相颈上挂着枚十字勋章，勋章旁边还有一颗宝星，和秘书伍尔穆一同上场。

宰相　迷上了一个姑娘！我的儿子？——不，伍尔穆你永远别想让我相信。

伍尔穆　请大人恩准我提供证据。

宰相　要说他向一个市民的小妞献献殷勤——说些个奉承话——甚至胡诌什么情呀爱呀的——这些事情在我看来通通可能——通通可以原谅——不过呢——竟然是一名吹鼓手的女儿，你说？

伍尔穆　是乐师米勒的闺女。

宰相　模样儿俊吗？——那还用问。

伍尔穆　（提起了劲头儿）标准的金发美人，毫不夸大地说，即使排在宫里的佳丽队中，仍然出众超群。

宰相　（笑）你告诉我，伍尔穆——你显然看上了这个妞儿，我断定。——可你瞧，我亲爱的伍尔穆——如果说我儿子也对姑娘有好感，那就让我产生了一个希望：夫人小姐们将不会因此嫌弃他，他在宫里原本是有所作为的。你说那姑娘很美，这使我为我儿子高兴，他眼力不错嘛。他在傻丫头面前表现得很真诚？那就更好嘛——我看，这说明他足够机灵，可以拿谎话换得实惠，是块当宰相的材料。他甚至得手了？妙极妙极！这说明他交了桃花运。——闹剧竟然以一个健康的小孙儿收场——那更妙得无与伦比！那我便要为我家庭的兴旺发达再喝一瓶西班牙甜酒，并且替他的婊子代缴风化罚金。

伍尔穆　我唯一的希望是，大人，您不会为了消愁解闷，才不得不喝这瓶甜酒。

宰相　（严肃地）伍尔穆，你放明白点，我一旦相信什么，就会相信到底；一旦生起气来，就会暴跳如雷——你企图煽动我，我却拿它寻开心。你意在摆脱你争风吃醋的对手，对此我深信不疑。你想从姑娘身边挤走我的儿子却力不从心，就打算拿我这个老子当苍蝇拍使，这我也觉得可以理解——你出手不凡，将来定会成为一个大无赖，这甚至令我不胜欣喜——只是呢，我亲爱的伍尔穆，你千万别妄想连我也算计进去。——只是呢，你了解我，千万别把你的阴谋诡计搞得来破坏了我的基本准则。

伍尔穆　大人原谅。即使真的——如您所疑心的那样——在这里存在着吃醋的问题，那充其量也只是用到了眼睛，还没轮上舌头。

宰相　我倒认为完全可以不吃醋。你这个傻蛋，你从铸币厂得到金币，或者从银行里得到金币，这两者难道有什么区别吗？你只要想想此地的贵族老爷们，你便会心安理得啦：有意也罢，无意也罢——在我们这儿举行的每一次婚礼上，至少总有半打以上的男宾——或者侍从——是对新郎的乐园的几何尺寸了如指掌的。

伍尔穆　（鞠了一躬）在这点上，大人，我宁肯做个平民。

宰相　不过，现在我要让你高高兴兴，给你一个反击情敌的绝好机会。正是目前，为了迎接新公爵夫人的到来，内阁正筹划安排弥尔芙特夫人假意离开，并且让她新结一门亲事，以便把事情办得毫无破绽。你知道，伍尔穆，我的声望在多大程度上仰仗夫人的垂青——我的权势如何受到公爵的情绪影响。他正在为弥尔芙特寻找新的搭档。也有别人可能去应征——去做这笔交易，通过夫人博取公爵的信任，变成他无法离开的宠幸——是的，为使公爵仍然留在我的家族的网中，我要让斐迪南去娶弥尔芙特……你明白了吗？

伍尔穆　我豁然开朗，眼花缭乱……宰相大人至少向我证明，他当父亲只是位新手。要是斐迪南以牙还牙，像您做他慈爱的父亲似的做你孝顺的儿子，那就会违抗你的要求，外加提出抗议。

宰相　所幸我从来还不曾担心过什么计划不能实现，只要我认为：就该这么办！——喏，你瞧，伍尔穆，我们又回到先前的话题上来啦。今天上午我就要向我儿子宣布他订婚的事。他的表情要么证实有道理，要么将疑虑一笔勾销。

伍尔穆　大人，请您原谅我多嘴。令郎肯定不会对您有好脸色的：这既要怪您准备从他怀中夺走的那个丫头，也要怪您决定配给他的这位未婚妻。我求您做一次结论更明确的试验。您不妨选国内最清白无瑕的女孩做他的对象，他要说一声好，那我伍尔穆这个秘书甘愿去锤三年石头子儿。

宰相　（咬着嘴唇）魔鬼！

伍尔穆　情况就是这样。那女孩的母亲——一个地道的蠢婆娘——傻里傻气地全给我叨叨了出来。

宰相　（踱来踱去，强忍怒火）对！就在今天上午。

伍尔穆　大人只是别忘记了，少校是——我恩主您的公子。

宰相　注意别伤害他就是了，伍尔穆。

伍尔穆　我将尽力效劳，帮大人摆脱一个讨厌的儿媳……

宰相　我将报答你，帮你讨一个称心如意的妻子，是吗？——行啊，伍尔穆。

伍尔穆　（得意地鞠躬）永远是您的仆从，大人。（准备离开）

宰相　刚才我对你讲的是心腹话，伍尔穆——（威胁地）你要讲出去了……

伍尔穆　（笑）那大人就兜出我伪造文书的事。（离去）

宰相　你确实被攥在咱手心里。我抓住你的把柄，就像抓住拴甲壳虫的线。

内侍　（走进来）侍卫长封·卡尔勃大人到……

宰相　来得正好。——请他进来。（内侍下）

第六场

宫廷侍卫长封·卡尔勃和宰相。

前者身着华丽而俗气的朝服，背上搭着象征他职务的金钥匙，胸前挂着两只表，腰挎一柄长剑，肋下夹着平顶帽，头发梳理成了所谓的刺猬式。他大声喊着奔向宰相，身上散发的麝香味弥漫了整个大厅。

侍卫长　（拥抱宰相）啊，早安，亲爱的！休息得好吗？睡得好吗？——原谅我这么晚才来请安——公务紧急——厨房要的菜单——请帖——安排今儿个的雪橇郊游——唉——接着还得去殿下卧室上早朝，向他报告今儿个的天气。

宰相　是的，侍卫长。这么一来，您当然分不开身啦。

侍卫长　这还不算，那个混账裁缝还拖住我。

宰相　可到底彻底解决了吧？

侍卫长　事情还没完——今天真是倒霉一个接着一个。您听听！

宰相　（心不在焉）哪能呢？

侍卫长　您听着好啦。我刚跨下车，那些马就惊了，又是跳又是蹬，溅得——我请您想想！——我两条腿上全是烂泥浆。怎么办啊？请看在上帝分上设身处地为我想一想，男爵。我束手无策。时间这么晚了。事关一天的旅行——而这副德行去见殿下！上帝主持公道！——您猜我想起了什么？——您猜我想起了什么？我假装晕倒了。仆人们急急忙忙把我抬进马车。我这才十万火急地赶回家——换好了衣服——再往回赶——您说怎么着？——仍然第一个出现在谒见厅里——您看怎么样？

宰相　真是急中生智，大智大慧——可先别谈这个，卡尔勃——您和公爵谈过了吗？

侍卫长　（扬扬得意地）谈了二十分零三十秒钟。

宰相　我说哩！——这么讲，毫无疑问您给我带来了重要消息啰？

侍卫长　（先沉吟一会儿，煞有介事地）殿下今儿个穿了一件鹅黄色的海狸皮袍子。

宰相　我看呐——不，侍卫长，我今天可以告诉您一件更好的消息——弥尔芙特夫人要成为封·瓦尔特夫人啦，对您这肯定算得上新闻吧？

侍卫长　真的！——已经定了吗？

宰相　千真万确，侍卫长——我想劳您驾马上去见弥尔芙特夫人，让她准备好接待少校去拜访，并且把斐迪南的决定在整个京城公布出去。

侍卫长　（兴奋地）呵，非常乐意，亲爱的。——对我来说再好不过！——我火速赶去——（拥抱宰相）再见——不出三刻钟，全城都会传开的。（跳跳蹦蹦地出去了）

宰相　（望着侍卫长的背影笑起来）还说什么世界上的这种人是废物！——瞧着吧，要么斐迪南乖乖地同意，要么就不得不怪全城的人都在撒谎。（按铃。伍尔穆走进来）叫我儿子来一下。（伍尔穆下。宰相在厅里走来走去，心事重重）

第七场

斐迪南，宰相。

伍尔穆上场后立刻又退下。

斐迪南　您找我，父亲大人……

宰相　为了有朝一日我能为我的儿子感到荣幸，我不得不叫你来——让我们单独待一会儿吧，伍尔穆！——斐迪南，我已经观察了你好长时间，发现你已不再是一个令我欣喜的开朗快活的青年。你脸上隐隐流露出一种异样的苦闷——你躲着我——躲着你的朋友们——呸！像你这个年龄，我宁可原谅你十次放荡不羁，也不愿看见你一次这么忧心忡忡的样子。把你的苦闷告诉我，亲爱的孩子！让我为你谋幸福，照着我的话去做，别东想西想。——来，拥抱我，斐迪南！

斐迪南　您今天很慈蔼，爸爸。

宰相　今天？你这坏小子！——而且在说出这两个字时还酸溜溜的！（严肃地）斐迪南啊斐迪南！——为谁我踏上了成为公爵心腹的危险之路？为谁我昧了天理和良心，永远地？——听着，斐迪南——我是同我的儿子讲话——我除掉了我的前任，又是为谁铺平道路？——这段历史像刀一样刺着我的心，我越是想对世人隐藏真相，它越刺得我鲜血淋漓。听着，告诉我，斐迪南，我干这一切都是为了谁啊？

斐迪南　（吓得倒退一步）该不是为我吧，父亲？这一罪行的血红反光，该不会落在我的头上吧？万能的天主在上，我宁肯没生出来，也别成为这种罪行的借口才好！

宰相　这是什么话？什么话？算啦！原谅你这个满脑袋浪漫想法的傻瓜——斐迪南——爸爸不生你的气，你这自以为是的小家伙——你就是这样报答我那许许多多的不眠之夜吗？就这样报答我无尽的忧虑关怀，我良心的永恒刺痛吗？——罪责我来承担——法庭的诅咒和惩罚我来忍受——你获得的是第二手的幸福——罪孽不会附着在遗产上面。

斐迪南　（朝天举起右手）我在此起誓，绝不继承只会让我想起一个可耻的父亲的遗产。

宰相　听着，年轻人，别激怒我！——要按你的想法行事，你一辈子只能在地上爬行。

斐迪南　噢，那也不错，父亲，那毕竟比围着王侯的宝座爬来爬去要好。

宰相　（强压住怒火）哼！——必须强迫你认识自己的幸福所在。许多别的人千辛万苦也休想爬上去的位置，你玩儿似的糊里糊涂便给捧上去了。你十二岁当上见习士官，二十岁当上少校，这些都是我在公爵面前争取的结果。你将来会脱下军装，进入部里。公爵已提到过枢密顾问——驻外使节——特别的恩宠什么的。在你眼前正展示着美好的前程——一条平坦的大道直通公爵的宝座——直通与权力本身一样有价值的权力的象征——这，难道不令你鼓舞、神往吗？

斐迪南　不，因为我对伟大和幸福的理解与您不完全相同——您的幸福，很少不以毁灭为表现。嫉妒、恐惧、怨恨是一面面可悲的镜子，显赫的王侯便对着这样的镜子微笑。——眼泪、诅咒、绝望是可怕的筵席，供众所称赞的有福之人尽情享受；当他们喝得醉醺醺地站起来时，就该踉踉跄跄地去上帝的宝座前接受审判，永劫不复啦！——我关于幸福的理想，是知足而自我克制的。我的所有愿望，都埋藏在我的心中。

宰相　了不起！没说的！妙极了！过去了三十年第一次再聆听教导！——可惜啊，我五十岁了，脑袋已经顽固得再也学不进去！——对啦——为了不埋没你这罕有的才能，我要在你身边放上一个人，和她在一起，你可以尽情地去发挥你那些稀奇古怪的狂想——你得下决心——今天就下决心——娶一个妻子。

斐迪南　（惊愕，后退）爸爸？

宰相　别客气——我已经以你的名义给弥尔芙特夫人送了帖子。务必劳驾你过去告诉她，你是她未来的丈夫。

斐迪南　告诉弥尔芙特？爸爸！

宰相　如果你认识她……

斐迪南　（失去了自持）好个在公国中万人唾弃的女人！——可是我大概十分可笑，爸爸，竟把您一时的气话当了真？您未必愿做一个无赖儿子的父亲，他竟娶了一个有权有势的婊子？

宰相　岂止愿意。她要肯嫁一个五十岁的老头，我自己还会去向她求婚哩——难道你就不肯做这无赖父亲的儿子不成？

斐迪南　不！只要还有上帝！

宰相　放肆之极，我敢担保！只因为太少见，我不见怪……

斐迪南　求求您，爸爸！别再让我惶惑、难受，不清楚我是否还能称自己是您儿子。

宰相　孩子，别傻气啦！与自己的国君在某个地方交换角色，哪个聪明人不渴求获取这份殊荣呢？

斐迪南　您对我真成了一个谜，爸爸。您竟把与公爵一起分享低贱下流的乐趣，称作殊荣？

宰相　（放声大笑）

斐迪南　您笑吧，爸爸，我不计较。可真那样做了，叫我有何脸面去见一个哪怕最低贱的工匠？——他在娶老婆时至少有她完整的身体作为陪嫁。叫我有何脸面去见世人？去见公爵？去见那个将用我的耻辱来洗刷她名誉污点的姘妇本人？

宰相　你从哪儿学来这张利嘴的啊，孩子！

斐迪南　我当着您对天发誓，爸爸！您这样抛弃您的儿子，自己并不能得到幸福，而只会使他不幸。我愿意把生命交给您，如果它能帮您高升。我的生命来自于您；我将毫不犹豫地为了您的飞黄腾达而牺牲生命。——可我的荣誉，爸爸——如果您想把我的荣誉夺走，那您给予我生命就是一桩轻率的无赖行径，那我就只能诅咒您，骂您是个拉皮条的。

宰相　（拍了拍儿子的肩膀，慈蔼地）好样儿的，亲爱的孩子。现在我知道了，你是个十足的男子汉，配得上公国内最有德行的女人——她应该属于你——今天上午，你就去和奥斯特海姆女伯爵订婚吧。

斐迪南　（又一次感到愕然）怎么，这个时辰注定要完全毁了我吗？

宰相　（窥视着儿子）但愿你的荣誉再没什么好反对的！

斐迪南　不，爸爸！弗莉德里克·封·奥斯特海姆可以使任何别的男人无比幸福。（极度迷惘地自言自语）在我心中尚未被他的狠毒破坏的一点点东西，正被他的好意扯得粉碎。

宰相　（始终目不转睛地盯着儿子）我等着你感谢我喽，斐迪南——

斐迪南　（扑上去热烈地吻他的手）爸爸！您的恩情令我万分感动——爸爸！我最衷心地感谢您的关怀——您的选择完美无缺——可是——我不能——我不该——原谅我吧——我不能爱女伯爵。

宰相　（倒退一步）哈哈！这下算逮住你啦，少爷！你中了圈套，狡猾的伪君子——这就是说，并非荣誉阻止你娶弥尔芙特夫人啰？——你厌恶的不是人，而是结婚本身啰？

斐迪南　（先呆若木鸡，一会儿以后清醒过来，准备跑出去）

宰相　去哪儿？站住！这就是你对我该有的尊重吗？（少校退了回来）已经通知夫人你要去了。我答应过公爵。宫里城里尽人皆知。——你要是把我变成个说谎者——听着，孩子——或者让我发现了你的那些事情……等一等！哈哈！你的脸上怎么一下子黯淡无光，失去红润了呢？

斐迪南　（脸色苍白，浑身颤抖）什么？什么？没有的事儿，爸爸！

宰相　（目光凶狠地盯着儿子）可要是有什么——要是让我发现了你这么不听劝告的原因在哪里——哼，孩子，就算纯属怀疑也会叫我气疯的。先去吧！检阅马上开始了。一喊解散你就得去夫人那儿——我要生了气，整个公国都会打哆嗦。让咱们瞧瞧，我是否对一个顽固脑袋儿子毫无办法。（走出去又转回来）孩子，我告诉你，你必须去，要不就躲开我，躲开你愤怒的父亲！（下）

斐迪南　（恍若噩梦初醒）他走啦？那是一位父亲的声音吗？——是的！我愿去夫人那儿——愿意去——去告诉她一些事情，给她看一面镜子，这下流无耻的女人！——在这之后，如果她还要求嫁给我——当着全体贵族、军官和民众的面——用你英格兰的全部骄傲束紧你的腰——我，一个德意志青年，还是要唾弃你！（匆匆跑出去）

第一场

弥尔芙特夫人穿着宽松而迷人的晨衣，头发未经梳理，坐在钢琴前出神；使女索菲从窗前走回房中。

索菲　军官正好解散。检阅结束了——可我还没看见瓦尔特。

夫人　（十分不安，站起来，走过大厅）我不知道今天怎么啦，索菲——我从来没有这样过啊！——你说你压根儿没看见他？——当然当然——他用不着着急——我胸口憋闷得就像做了亏心事——去，索菲，让人把马厩里最野的那匹马给我牵来——我得去野外——去见一见人，看一看蓝天，痛痛快快地跑一跑，好让心头轻松一点。

索菲　你要感觉不舒服，夫人，那就请朋友来聚会吧。让公爵在这儿开宴会，或者把玩纸牌的桌子搬到您沙发跟前。要是公爵和他的整个宫廷都听我调遣，我干吗还闷闷不乐呢？

夫人　（猛然坐到沙发上）我求你，别再烦我。只要你让我清静，我愿每个钟头赏你一枚金刚钻！竟要我让那些个家伙来装点我的房子？——这是些卑贱、可怜的人，一当我脱口说出一句热诚的心里话，他们便张大嘴巴和鼻孔，傻愣愣地像见了幽灵似的——全都是拴在一条线上的木偶，操纵起来比我钩花边还容易。——这种人的心跳得跟他们的怀表一样四平八稳，我与他们有什么交道好打啊？我预先便知道他们会回答我什么，我哪儿还有兴致向他们提出问题呢？他们连发表与我不同的意见的胆量都没有，我怎么会乐意与他们交谈呢？——去他们的吧！一匹连缰绳都不敢咬的马，骑起来可真没劲儿！（踱到窗前）

索菲　可公爵你该觉得是个例外吧，夫人？整个公国最美的男子——最热烈的情人——最机智的头脑！

夫人　（从窗前踱回来）因为这是他的国家——而只有这个公国，索菲，对于我的口味来说还可成为差强人意的借口——你说人家羡慕我？可怜的东西！他们应该同情我才是。在所有吸吮殿下乳汁的人中间，情妇是最可悲的一个；因为只有她知道这个显赫而豪富的人其实不过是个叫花子——不错，他可以用他权力的灵符唤起我心头的种种欲望，就像从地里唤出一座仙女的宫殿。——他可以把两个印度的血浆摆上我的筵席——可以叫荒野出现乐园——可以使他国中的泉水喷上天空，划出骄傲的弧形，或者将他的臣仆的骨髓变成烟火，燃放到空中去——可他也能命令他的心，在一颗博大而火热的心面前，同样博大而火热地跳动吗？他能强令他那平庸的脑子，哪怕认同唯一一种美好的感情吗？——我尽管感官享受充足，心却忍受着饥渴。在一个我不得不窒息激情的地方，千百种情感对我又有什么用处？

索菲　（惊异地望着弥尔芙特）我伺候您多久了啊，夫人？

夫人　你今天才认识我吗？——不错，亲爱的索菲——我把自己的荣誉出卖给了公爵，不过我的心仍然是自由的——这颗心，好妹妹，也许还配得到一个男人的爱——宫廷的毒雾拂过它，只不过如明镜上哈了一口气——相信我，亲爱的，要不是虚荣心阻止我将宫中第一夫人的位置让出去，我早就不会听任这位寒酸的公爵的摆布啦。

索菲　您的心就这么甘愿做虚荣的奴隶吗？

夫人　（激动地）已经受到了惩罚，不是吗？——现在还在受惩罚，是不是？——索菲哟！（意味深长地，手抚着索菲的肩膀）我们女人只能在统治与效忠之间进行选择；可是执掌权力的最大乐趣，也只不过是一种可怜的补偿，我们失去了更大的快乐——成为一个我们所钟爱的男子的奴仆的快乐。

索菲　千真万确的真理，夫人，可我极不情愿听您说出来。

夫人　为什么呢，索菲？难道从这执掌权杖的幼稚举动，不能看出我们只配去牵小儿学步的带子吗？难道你看不出这任性的轻浮，这种种粗野的享乐，只不过是为了掩盖我胸中更加狂暴的欲望吗？

索菲　（吃惊地后退一步）夫人！

夫人　（更兴奋地）满足这些欲望吧！把我所想念的——所祈求的男子给我吧！索菲——我要么为他而死，要么占有他。（神往地）让我从他嘴里听到，我们眼里爱情的泪水比我们发间的珠宝更加晶莹，更加美丽，（狂热地）我将把公爵的心连同他的公国掷于他的脚下，同他——同我钟爱的男子一起逃跑，逃到世界最偏远的沙漠里去……

索菲　（惊恐地望着弥尔芙特）天哪！你说些什么？您怎么啦，夫人？

夫人　（愕然）干吗脸色苍白？——我说得也许过了头？——噢，那就让我把你的舌头和我的信任捆在一起吧——我还要对你说更多——对你说出一切——

索菲　（畏葸地环顾四周）我害怕，夫人——我害怕——我不需要再听。

夫人　让我与少校结合——你和世人全犯了傻，以为那是宫廷里司空见惯的阴谋——索菲——别脸红——别为我害臊——那是我的爱情的——杰作。

索菲　上帝做证！我早有预感！

夫人　他们让我说动了，索菲——那软弱的公爵——那圆滑的宰相——那愚蠢的侍卫长——他们一个个赌咒发誓，说这场婚事是为公爵保住我的万无一失的手段，它将使我和公爵的结合更加紧密牢固。——呸！将把它永远分开！将使我永远挣脱这可耻的锁链！——这帮受了骗的骗子！竟让一个弱女子给蒙了！——是你们自己把我的心上人送到了我面前！这我真叫求之不得啊——只要我一得到他——得到他——呵，永远永远滚开吧，可恶的荣华——

第二场

公爵的一名老侍从捧着首饰匣。

前场人物。

侍从　公爵殿下向夫人致意，派我送来这些钻石作为您结婚的礼物。它们刚从威尼斯运到这里。

夫人　（揭开首饰匣，惊讶得往后退去）天哪！公爵为这些宝石花了多少钱？

侍从　（脸色阴沉地）没花他一个子儿。

夫人　什么？你疯了吗？没花一个子儿？——瞧你（从老人身边后退了一步）——怎么这样瞪着我，好像要看穿我似的！——这些无价之宝没花他一个子儿？

侍从　昨天，又有七千子弟出发去了美洲[1]——他们偿付了一切。

夫人　（突然放下首饰匣，疾步穿过大厅，一会儿又回到侍从跟前）喂，你怎么啦？我看，你在哭？

侍从　（擦干眼泪，浑身战栗，嗓音凄惨）这儿的宝石——我也有几个儿子跟着去了。

夫人　（一怔，转开脸，握住老人的手）总不会有谁是被迫的吧？

侍从　（狂笑）呵，上帝——不——全都心甘情愿！当时有那么几个多嘴的小伙子走出队列，问上校，公爵卖他们出去定价多少钱一对？——谁知咱们仁爱无比的国君命令所有团队一齐开上阅兵场，当众枪决了那几个快嘴多舌的小子。我们只听见噼噼啪啪一阵枪响，看见孩子们的脑浆飞溅到了广场的石头地上，与此同时，全军齐声呼喊：哟嘿，去美洲啰！——

夫人　（震惊，跌倒在沙发上）上帝！上帝！——我却什么也没听见！我却什么也没察觉！

侍从　是喽，夫人——不然在擂响起程鼓的时候，您和咱们主上干吗偏偏要去追捕狗熊呢？——您倒是真不该错过那辉煌的场面！当刺耳的鼓声向人们宣布，出发时间到了，便只见这儿一群哭喊着的孤儿在追赶还活着的父亲，那儿一个母亲发了疯，正冲上去准备把尚在吃奶的婴儿插到刺刀上去；为了把新婚的夫妇分开，军官们只好用刀劈；咱们老头子只好绝望地站在原地，临了儿也把手杖扔给孩子们，让手杖陪伴他们到新世界去——呵，战鼓一直擂得震天价响，为的是全能的主听不见我们的祷告声——

夫人　（从沙发上站起，激动异常）把这些钻石拿走——它闪闪烁烁，把地狱的火焰射进了我心里！（温和地转向侍从）别太难过，可怜的老人。他们会回来的。他们会再见到自己的祖国。

侍从　（动情地，专注地）只有上帝知道！他们会的！——到了城门口他们还转过身来高呼：“上帝与你们同在，老婆和孩子们——咱们的公爵万岁——等到接受上帝审判那天，咱们会回来的！”

夫人　（大步绕室疾走）可耻！可怕！——他们骗我说，我已拭干了公国所有的眼泪——现在我算睁开眼了，恐怖地睁开眼了——去吧——去告诉你的主上——我将当面向他道谢！（侍从准备退下，她将自己的钱包扔进他帽子里）拿去吧，作为你对我说了真话的报酬——

侍从　（轻蔑地将钱包扔回桌子上）请留下吧，对您说来是不会嫌多的。（下）

夫人　（惊讶地目送着他）索菲，快追上去，问他叫什么名字。我要让他再见到他的儿子。（索菲下。夫人沉思着走上走下。少顷，对重新上场的索菲）最近不是传说边境上有座城市发生火灾，使四百个家庭沦为乞丐了吗？（按铃）

索菲　你怎么突然想到这个？是有这么回事，那些不幸的人现在多数成了他们债主的奴隶，不然就在公爵的银矿里卖命。

仆人　（走进来）夫人有何吩咐？

夫人　（把首饰匣递给他）立刻送到市里去！——马上换成现钱，我命令；然后把换来的钱分给那四百户遭了火灾的穷人。

索菲　夫人，您考虑考虑，您这样做会失去公爵恩宠的。

夫人　（庄严地）难道要我头上戴着全国的诅咒吗？（挥手示意仆人离开）要不你愿意这些眼泪凝成的可怕首饰压得我倒下吧？——去，索菲——还是头上戴一些假珠宝，心里意识到做过这样的善事更好。

索菲　可刚才那样的珠宝！难道您不能拿你次一点的去卖吗？不，真的，夫人，你这样做太不该！

夫人　傻丫头！这样做了，刹那间我便得到了更多的钻石和珠宝，比十个国王戴在王冠上的还要多，还更美——

仆人　（又走进来）封·瓦尔特少校到。

索菲　（冲向夫人）天哪！您多么苍白——

夫人　这是第一个使我惊慌失措的男人——索菲——我不舒服，爱德华[2]——等一等——他开心吗？他面带笑容吗？他说什么来着？呵，索菲！我很难看，是不是？

索菲　我求求您，夫人……

仆人　您吩咐我打发他走吗？

夫人　（结结巴巴地）说我欢迎他。（仆人下）告诉我，索菲——我对他讲什么好？我怎样接待他？——我会哑口无言的——他将讥讽我的软弱——我心多么虚啊——你要离开我吗，索菲？——留下——唉不！走吧！——还是留下好些。（少校穿过前厅，走进屋来）

索菲　精神一点！他已经来了。

[1]　美国独立战争期间，德国的诸侯们曾出卖农奴给英王乔治三世当炮灰。

[2]　仆人名。

第三场

斐迪南·封·瓦尔特。前场人物。

斐迪南　（微微一鞠躬）要是我打扰了您，夫人……

夫人　（心激烈地跳着）一点儿也不，少校先生，您来再好不过。

斐迪南　我来是奉家父之命……

夫人　那我得感谢他。

斐迪南　奉他之命告诉您，我俩将要结婚——父亲吩咐的就这些。

夫人　（失色，战栗）不是您自己的心愿吗？

斐迪南　大臣们和拉牵做媒的人一样，从来不问这个。

夫人　（惊惧，语塞）而您自己就没有一点别的要说吗？

斐迪南　（瞅了使女一眼）还有很多，夫人。

夫人　（示意索菲，索菲退出）可以请您坐在这张沙发上吗？

斐迪南　我将尽量简短，夫人。

夫人　喏？

斐迪南　我是个堂堂的男子汉。

夫人　我敬重这样的男人。

斐迪南　还是个骑士。

夫人　公国里出类拔萃的骑士。

斐迪南　还是军官。

夫人　（讨好地）您只提到一些其他人与您同样具备的优点。您干吗对那些更加重要的独特品格避而不谈呢？

斐迪南　（冷冷地）我在这儿用不着它们。

夫人　（越来越恐惧）可是，我该如何理解您这开场白呢？

斐迪南　（缓慢而加重语气）理解为自尊心的抗议，如果您真有兴趣来强迫我娶您。

夫人　（生气地）这是什么话，少校先生？

斐迪南　（从容地）我的心里话——我的族徽的话——这把宝剑的话。

夫人　这把宝剑是公爵赐给你的。

斐迪南　是国家假公爵之名将它给了我——我的心就是我的上帝——我家族的纹章已有五百年历史。

夫人　公爵的名义……

斐迪南　（激动地）公爵难道能歪曲人类的准则，或者像铸造他的三分铜币一样任意支配人的行动吗？——他自己不威严、崇高，却能够用金子堵住尊严的嘴巴。他可以用银鼬皮袍遮盖他的耻辱。我请求您别再扯这些，夫人——这儿要谈的不再是抛弃了的前程和祖先——不再是这剑上的穗子——不再是世人的看法。我做好准备了，一旦您能证明，我获得的奖赏不低于付出的代价，上面所说的一切我通通可以抛弃。

夫人　（痛心地离开他）少校先生，我不配让你做出这么大的牺牲。

斐迪南　（抓住她的手）请原谅。我们在这儿谈话没有第三者。使您和我今天——除了今天再也不会走到一起来的情况迫使我，使我有理由对您不再隐讳我心灵深处的情感。——我真不敢相信，夫人，一位这么美丽、这么富有灵气的女子——她这些品质会得到男人的尊重——怎么可能委身于一个只是贪恋她的肉体的公爵；这个女子怎么不知羞耻，竟然同时又向另一位男子献上她的心。

夫人　（睁大眼睛瞪着他的脸）请痛痛快快地说完吧。

斐迪南　您自称是个英国人。恕我冒昧——我不能相信您真是英国人——一个天底下最自由的人民的生而自由的女儿。她太骄傲了，对别国的德行尚且不屑一顾，不肯受其影响，更永远别提会附和他人的罪孽呐。不可能，您不会是一位英国女子——要不，您这英国女人的心脏必定太小太小，不配有真正英国女子豪迈而勇敢跳动的脉搏！

夫人　您说完了吗？

斐迪南　有人也许会回答，这是妇女的虚荣心——重感情——易冲动——好享受。经常是德行比名声更能持久。曾经有过一些人，开始时名誉扫地，后来却以自己的高尚行为取得了世人谅解，用善举把丑恶化为了高贵——可是，目前公国内为何压迫空前未有的深重、可怕？——一切都盗用了国家的名义！——我没什么说的了。

夫人　（温柔地，庄重地）瓦尔特，这是头一次有人敢对我讲这种话；而您，是唯一一个我愿意给予回答的男子。——你鄙视与我结合，我因此尊重您。您亵渎我的心，我不怪罪您。我不相信，您真这么鄙弃我。一个人敢于去这样侮辱一位翻掌之间就可以毁掉他的妇女，必定是相信这位妇女有一颗博大的心，要不然——他就精神失常。——您把国家的灾难归罪到我身上，但愿万能的上帝会原谅您；有朝一日，他将让您和我和公爵对质的。——可您竟然怀疑我是一名英国女子：对您这样的指责，我的祖国不会不给予回答的。

斐迪南　（身子倚着佩剑）我急于马上知道。

夫人　那就听好了。除您之外，我还从未告诉任何人，也不愿告诉任何人。——我不是一个冒险家，瓦尔特，像您认为的那样。我本可以趾高气扬地说：我有着高贵的血统——出身在为苏格兰女王玛利亚牺牲了的不幸的托马斯·诺弗克家族。[1]——先父是国王陛下的侍从长官，受人诬陷，被认定背叛国家，勾结法兰西。议会判他有罪，他被斩了首。——我家的所有财产都归王室所有了。我们自己被驱逐出了英国。我母亲死在父亲被处决的当天。我本人——一个十四岁的小姑娘——跟着保姆逃到了德国，带着一盒珠宝——还有这个家传的十字架；我母亲在弥留之际一边给我最后的祝福，一边把它戴在了我胸前。

斐迪南　（慢慢陷入沉思，盯着夫人的目光变得温暖起来）

夫人　（越往下说越是激动）带着病——没有名声——没有保护人和财产——我一个异国孤女来到了汉堡。除了一点法语——一点针线活儿和会弹钢琴之外，别无任何本领；相反倒习惯了使用金银餐具——盖锦缎被褥，呼奴使婢，颐指气使，接受大人先生们的阿谀奉承。——终于哭着过完了六年。——最后的一件首饰飞掉了——我那保姆也一命呜呼——这时我的命运之星将您的公爵带到了汉堡来。那天我在易北河边散步，正望着江水开始胡思乱想，想弄清楚是这江水更深呢还是我的痛苦更深，公爵看见了我，跟踪我到了我的住处——跪在我脚下发誓说他爱我。（激动得停下来，然后哽咽着往下说）我幸福的童年又带着美丽迷人的光彩，一幕一幕呈现在眼前——可是未来却黑暗如同墓穴，令我毛骨悚然——我的心渴望从另一颗心获取温暖——于是便与他的心靠在了一起。（从斐迪南身边跑开）现在您可以诅咒我了！

斐迪南　（非常感动，追上去拉住她）夫人！呵，天哪！我听见了什么？我干了些什么？——我的罪孽突然明摆在我面前，可怕啊！您再也不可能原谅我啦。

夫人　（走回来，努力克制着自己）您往下听。公爵虽然使我这个没有反抗能力的少女感到措手不及——可我身上的诺弗克家庭的血液却提出抗议：你，一位天生的侯爵小姐，艾米莉，竟甘当一个国君的情妇吗？——公爵将我带到这儿，在我眼前突然展现出最可怖的情景，于是自尊和命运在我心里开始了长期的斗争。——这个世界的大人物荒淫纵乐，就像永远不知饱足的鬣狗，老在贪婪地搜寻着牺牲品。——在这个公国内他们横行肆虐——拆散一对对新婚夫妇——撕碎神圣的婚姻纽带——破坏家庭的幸福温馨——让年幼无知的心遭受黑死病的传染毒害，而一些女学生在临死前一边痉挛，一边诅咒，流着泡沫的嘴里泄露出来的竟是她们教师的名字。——我被夹在了羔羊和虎狼之间，常常在幽会的温情时刻逼着公爵许下誓愿：那样可憎的牺牲该到头啦！

斐迪南　（激动得绕室狂走）别说了，夫人！别再说下去！

夫人　这可悲的时期后面接着更加可悲的时期。一时间，宫廷和后宫中充斥着意大利来的下流货，风骚的巴黎女人用可怕的权杖打情骂俏，民众在她们喜怒无常的摆布下流着鲜血——你们全都经历过当时的情景。是我，后来让她们失了势，因为我比她们更风流。我让暴君在我的怀抱中飘飘然，从他有气无力的手中夺过了权柄——你的祖国，瓦尔特，才第一次感受到人的抚慰，信赖地靠在了我的胸口上。（停下来，脉脉含情地望着他）呵，这个唯一我不愿意他误解我的男子，现在逼得我只好夸夸其谈，把我秘而不宣的德行讲了出来，任赞叹的阳光暴晒！——瓦尔特，我砸碎过牢狱的铁锁——撕碎过死刑判决书——缩短过苦役船上可怕的终身流放。给无法治愈的创伤至少注入了减轻痛苦的油膏——并且常常叫有权有势的罪犯倒霉，年轻人，那才叫痛快呀！任何对于我高贵出身的责难，我的心都可以无比骄傲地予以驳斥！——可那唯一能够给我所作所为以报偿的男子——那我多咎的命运创造来弥补我已承受的痛苦的男子——那我在梦中已热烈渴慕和拥抱的男子，他现在竟来……

斐迪南　（抢过话头，极度震惊地）够啦！够啦！这违反了约定，夫人！您可以洗刷对您的责难，指出我的罪过。可请您怜惜——我请求您——怜惜我的心；它快要被惭愧和悔恨撕碎啦——

夫人　（紧握他的手）要么现在讲，要么永远别讲了。这个女人已经勇敢地坚持了很长时间——现在必须让您再感到她泪水的分量。（语气温柔地）听我说啊，瓦尔特——如果一个不幸的女子——受到你不可抗拒的强有力的吸引——用她满怀着无限热爱的胸脯贴近你的身体——瓦尔特呵——你此刻还会冷冰冰地谈什么荣誉吗？——如果这个不幸的女子——忍辱含羞——厌倦了行恶——在德行的召唤下勇敢地站了起来——这样投身你的怀抱（边说边抱住瓦尔特，恳求地，庄严地）——希望你拯救她——希望由你重新送进天国，或者（背转脸，嗓音空虚而颤抖）从你面前逃开，发出可怕的绝望的号叫，听天由命，重新沦落进更加可憎的罪恶的深渊……

斐迪南　（挣脱她的怀抱，狼狈之极）不，伟大的上帝知道，我受不了啦！——夫人，我必须——凭着天地起誓——我必须向您承认一件事情，夫人。

夫人　（从他身边逃开）现在别！现在别！我以对我神圣的一切的名义求你——在这可怕的一刻，我的心像被万千支匕首刺破了似的在流血——死也罢，活也罢——我现在不能——我现在不愿——听你表白。

斐迪南　你得听，你得听，好夫人！您必须听我讲。我现在要对您讲的话，将减轻我的罪过，并稍微表示一下我对刚才发生的事情的歉意——我看错了您，夫人。我曾期待——我曾希望您是该当受我蔑视的。我所以来府上，就是下定决心要侮辱您，招您的恨——要是我这打算成功了，我俩会多幸福啊！（沉默片刻，然后更加轻声，更加羞怯）我爱上了，夫人——爱上了一个市民姑娘——她叫露意丝·米勒小姐，一位音乐家的女儿。（夫人脸色苍白地背转身去。他更兴奋地往下讲）我知道我堕入了怎样的境地；可要是智慧能让激情沉默，责任的声音却更加响亮——我负有罪责！一开头，我撕破了她处女的金子般的宁静——用痴心妄想迷住她的心，把它出卖给了狂野的激情。——您会提醒我注意我的地位——我的出身——我父亲的信条——可是我爱她！——我天性的追求与种种陈规陋习越是背道而驰，我抱的期望就越高。——我的决心与世俗的偏见誓不两立！——让我们看看，能永远存在下去的是时尚，或是人的本性。（这期间夫人已退到大厅的尽头，双手捂住了脸。斐迪南一直紧跟着她）您还想对我讲什么吗，夫人？

夫人　（表情异常痛苦）没有了，封·瓦尔特先生！除去您将毁掉自己，毁掉我，并且毁掉另外一个女人之外，什么都没有了！

斐迪南　还有另外一个女人？

夫人　我们在一起不会幸福。可我们又不得不成为您父亲急性子的牺牲品。一个只是被迫将手伸给我的男人，我一辈子也不可能得到他的心。

斐迪南　被迫，夫人？被迫伸手给您？可到底给了没有呢？您难道能够强夺一只并不情愿伸给您的手不成？您难道能强使一个视这姑娘为整个世界的男子离开她，来到您的身边不成？夫人啊，您——在这一刻之前，您还是一位令人钦敬的英国女子——您能够这样做吗？

夫人　因为我必须这样做。（严肃而坚定地）我的热情，瓦尔特，压不过我对您的柔情。我的名声，再也不能……全城的人都在谈论我俩的结合。所有的眼睛，所有嘲讽的利箭，全瞄准了我。要是公爵的一个臣仆尚且拒绝了我，那对我将是一个永远洗刷不掉的奇耻大辱。和您的父亲理论去吧！尽可能地反抗吧！——我将一不做，二不休！（快步走下。少校瞠目结舌，呆若木鸡，随后也冲出门去）

[1]　苏格兰女王玛利亚·斯图亚特（1542-1587）于新旧教之争中偏袒旧教，失败后逃往英格兰，向伊丽莎白女王求救不成反遭囚禁。托马斯·诺弗克公爵（1536-1572）在审判她时暗中予以保护，企图与教皇和西班牙一起帮助她复辟，事情败露后被处决。本剧的故事发生在18世纪，剧中人所述并不完全符合历史事实。

第四场

乐师家的房间。

米勒、米勒太太、露意丝同上。

米勒　（疾步走进房来）我早说过了不是！

露意丝　（胆怯地迎上去）怎么啦，爸爸，怎么啦？

米勒　（绕室狂奔）拿我的礼服来——快点——我必须赶在他前边——还有一件活袖头的白衬衫！——我早料到会出事！

露意丝　看在上帝分上！怎么啦？

米勒太太　出了什么事？到底什么事？

米勒　（将假发扔得老远）快拿去理发师梳一下！——怎么啦？（跳到镜子面前）还有胡子也半卡长了！——出了什么事？——还会出什么事哟，你这个死人！——报应到啦，活该你遭雷劈！

米勒太太　瞧瞧吧！啥事儿都赖我。

米勒　赖你？是啊，不赖你这该死的尖嘴婆娘还赖谁？今儿个一早，和你那恶魔小爷——我不是马上说了吗？——伍尔穆那家伙给叨叨出去啦！

米勒太太　嗨，什么！你怎么会知道？

米勒　我怎么会知道？——得！大门口已经有宰相的一个狗杂种在探头探脑，打听提琴师家的情况。

露意丝　我快完了。

米勒　不只是你，还有你那对情意绵绵的眼睛！（恶狠狠地，大笑）真是不错：魔鬼在谁家下了蛋，谁家就会养出个漂亮妞儿。——我现在算领教了！

米勒太太　你从哪儿知道是冲咱露意丝来的？——没准儿有谁向公爵推荐了你。没准儿他要你进他的乐队。

米勒　（跳过去抓棍子）倒你鬼老婆子的邪霉！还乐队咧！——可不，来叫你这老媒婆用号叫充女高音，叫我这青紫的屁股给你作低音伴唱。（猛地坐到椅子上）天上的主啊！

露意丝　（脸色惨白，坐下）妈！爸！怎么我突然心慌意乱？

米勒　（从椅子上跳起来）可那耍笔杆儿的要是什么时候让我给撞上？——让我给撞上？不管是在阳世还是在阴间——我要不把他的肉体和灵魂捶成烂酱，要不拿他的狗皮来抄《圣经》“十诫”和七篇“悔罪雅歌”，抄《摩西五书》以及先知穆罕默德的经文，让世人到亡灵复活之日还看得见他皮上的蓝色字迹，那我就……

米勒太太　是的是的！你咒吧，你跳吧！你这样就可以镇住魔鬼啦！救救咱们啊，仁慈的主！现在怎么办？谁能给咱们出主意？怎么才收得了场喽？米勒老爹，你可是说呀！（哭喊着在房中乱跑一气）

米勒　我这就去见宰相。我要抢先开口——要自己说明原委。你呢，知道得比我早，本该提醒我才是。这丫头也许还劝得回来。也许时间还来得及——可是你没有！——这里边没准儿能捞到点好处哩，这里边没准儿能钓上条大鱼哩！于是你火上浇油！——现在该你去领你的媒婆赏钱啦！你这叫自作自受！我呢，只管带着我的女儿，离开这个国家。

第五场

斐迪南·封·瓦尔特冲进房间，慌慌张张，上气不接下气。

前场人物。

斐迪南　我父亲来过了吗？

露意丝　（惊惶不安）你父亲？万能的主啊！

米勒太太　（双手一拍）宰相大人！咱们完啦！（三人异口同声）

米勒　（冷笑两声）赞美上帝！咱们报应到了！

斐迪南　（奔向露意丝，把她抱在怀中）你是我的，不怕天堂和地狱从中阻拦！

露意丝　我注定活不了啦——说下去——你刚才说了一个可怕的名字——你的父亲？

斐迪南　没什么，没什么。事情已经过去了。我又重新得到了你。你又重新得到了我。让我先在你怀中喘口气吧。刚才那一刻太可怕啦。

露意丝　怎样的时刻呢？你快急死我了！

斐迪南　（倒退一步，若有所悟地打量着她）一个在我的心与你之间，露意丝，插进来一个陌生人的时刻——一个使我的爱在我的良心面前变得苍白失色的时刻——一个我的露意丝不再是她斐迪南的一切一切的时刻……

露意丝　（蒙着脸，倒在椅子上）

斐迪南　（跑向她，目光呆滞地站在她面前，说不出一句话，然后突然离开她，激动异常）不！绝不！不可能，夫人！您太过分了！我不能为您牺牲这个纯洁无邪的少女！——不，以永恒的上帝起誓！我不能背弃我的誓言，它像天上的雷霆一样大声地警告我，从这双失去了神采的眼睛里——夫人，您瞧瞧吧，瞧瞧吧——像乌鸦一般狠心的父亲呵，你要掐死这个天使吗？你要我在她圣洁的胸中撒播地狱之火吗？（坚决地跑回露意丝跟前）我要领她去接受世界末日的审判，让永恒的上帝讲，我爱她是不是犯罪。（拉住露意丝的手，扶她站起来）鼓起勇气，亲爱的！——你胜利了。在那最危险的搏斗中，我成了胜利者。

露意丝　不！不！什么也别瞒着我！说出来吧，那可怕的判决。你提到你父亲？你提到夫人？——我怕得要命——人家说，她要结婚了。

斐迪南　（茫然地跪倒在她脚下）是跟我哟，不幸的人！

露意丝　（停了停，声音微微颤抖，可怕的沉着镇静）喏——我还担的哪份儿惊呢？——那边那位老人不是一再告诫我——要我永远别相信他的话。（稍停，然后哭着扑进米勒怀中）爸爸，你的女儿回到你身边来啦——原谅我吧，爸爸——别怪你的孩子，那个梦太美啦，可是啊——现在醒来越加可怕！——

米勒　露意丝！露意丝！——上帝呵，她神经不正常了！——我的女儿，我可怜的孩子！——该死的诱骗者！——该死的拉皮条的婆娘！

米勒太太　（哭喊着扑向露意丝）我该受这样的咒骂吗，我的女儿？上帝饶恕您，男爵——这小羊羔做了什么错事，您要掐死她？

斐迪南　（从露意丝脚下跳起来，坚定地）可我一定要戳穿他的所有阴谋——扯断那一切偏见的锁链——我要像个男子汉似的自由地选择爱人，让那班小人在我爱情的参天大树下晕头转向吧！（准备离去）

露意丝　（战栗着从椅子上站起来，追上他）别走！别走！你要去哪儿？——爸爸——妈妈——在这可怕的时刻他要离开我们？

米勒太太　（追上去拉住斐迪南）宰相大人会上这儿来——他会虐待咱闺女——他会虐待我们——封·瓦尔特少爷，你却要扔下我们吗？

米勒　（狂笑）扔下我们。当然当然！干吗不呢？——她已经把一切给了他！——（一只手拉着少校，一只手拉着露意丝）别着急，先生！要离开我的家，只能从她身上踩过去！——你要不是流氓，就先等令尊大人来——告诉他，你怎么偷走了她的心，你这骗子，要不然，上帝做证！（把女儿扔给斐迪南，狂暴地）就当着我的面，先把这只因为爱你而身败名裂的可怜虫给踩死！

斐迪南　（回到房中，沉思着踱来踱去）宰相的权力固然很大——父权也是个含义广泛的词儿——罪行本身可以隐藏在他脸上的皱纹中——他可以为所欲为——为所欲为！——然而，只有爱情能做到一切——来，露意丝，把手伸给我！（拉住露意丝的手，用力地）就这样，直到最后一息上帝也不会离开我，真的！——那分开这两只手的一瞬，也将扯断我与造化的联系。

露意丝　我害怕！转过脸去，你嘴唇颤抖。你眼睛转动起来叫人害怕……

斐迪南　不，露意丝，别哆嗦。我不是在说胡话。在这关键时刻，被压抑的心胸唯有想入非非才可能舒畅舒畅，这时候能够做出决断的，唯有上帝特殊的恩赐！——我爱你，露意丝——你应该和我在一起，露意丝——现在去见我的父亲！（疾步出房，正撞上宰相跨进门来）

第六场

宰相带着一帮侍从。前场人物。

宰相　（边进门边说）他已经在这里。

众人　（惊恐）

斐迪南　（后退几步）在一个清白人家。

宰相　在儿子能学会孝敬父亲的地方吗？

斐迪南　请您别扯这个——

宰相　（打断他，脸转向米勒）他是父亲吗？

米勒　米勒乐师。

宰相　（脸朝米勒太太）她是母亲？

米勒太太　没错儿！母亲。

斐迪南　（对米勒）爸爸，您把女儿带走吗——她快晕倒了。

宰相　瞎操心，我还有话问她呐。（对露意丝）你认识宰相的少爷多久了？

露意丝　我从不管什么少爷不少爷。从十一月份起，斐迪南·封·瓦尔特就来家里看我。

斐迪南　来追求她。

宰相　你得到什么许诺了吗？

斐迪南　就在刚才，当着上帝的面，我给了她最庄严神圣的许诺。

宰相　（恼怒地冲着儿子）蠢材，有你后悔的！（对露意丝）我等你回答哩。

露意丝　他起誓他爱我。

斐迪南　而且将信守誓言。

宰相　非要我命令你住口吗？——你接受他的誓言？

露意丝　（温柔地）我给了他回报。

斐迪南　（语气坚定地）已结下海誓山盟。

宰相　我非把你这应声虫扔出去不可。（恶毒地冲着露意丝）他可是每次都付现钱，对吗？

露意丝　（专注地）我不完全明白您问的什么意思。

宰相　（暗暗冷笑）不明白？喏喏！这只是说——操任何营生，俗话说，总有它的搞头——而你呢，我希望，也不会白白奉送，没捞到好处——或者你想的只是玩一玩，对吗？

斐迪南　（勃然大怒）混账！这叫什么话？

露意丝　（对斐迪南，庄重而无奈地）封·瓦尔特先生，现在您自由了。

斐迪南　爸爸！德行即使衣衫褴褛，如同乞丐，同样应该受到尊重。

宰相　（大笑）可笑的妄想！竟要老子尊重儿子的婊子。

露意丝　（昏倒）天啊！天啊！

斐迪南　（与露意丝同时开口，并且拔出剑来刺向父亲，半道上却垂下了宝剑）爸爸！您原本有权要我把我的生命还给您——现在算是清了账了（插回宝剑）——从此我这个儿子不再欠您任何的情！——

米勒　（一直恐惧地站在一边，这时激动地走上前来，一会儿气得咬牙切齿，一会儿怕得牙齿磕磕碰碰）我说大人——孩子是父亲的骨肉心肝——劳驾您给我记住——谁骂他女儿是婊子，谁就打了他的耳光；而你打他他也得同样打你——咱们的信条如此——劳驾您给我记住。

米勒太太　行行好吧，上帝和救世主！——现在老头子也火啦！——咱们大难临头了！

宰相　（似未完全听明白）怎么，老龟头也发火了吗？——我们这就跟你算账，老龟头！

米勒　劳您的驾，我的名字叫米勒，如果您听我奏一段柔板的话——给娼妓拉客咱不干。多会儿宫里边还有足够的人手，就轮不上咱这些平民百姓。劳您的驾！

米勒太太　看在上帝分上，老头子！你要害死你老婆孩子啦！

斐迪南　您在这儿扮演的什么角色哟，爸爸，竟当着这么多人的面。

米勒　（走过宰相，鼓起勇气）明明白白地说吧。劳您的驾！在公国范围内，大人您有权有势，想干啥可以干啥。可这儿是我的家。如果有朝一日我要递交份请愿书，我也许会毕恭毕敬；可一个没礼貌的客人，我将马上赶他出门去——劳您的驾！

宰相　（气得脸色苍白）什么？——什么意思？（逼近米勒）

米勒　（缓缓后退）我就是这个意思，大人——劳您的驾。

宰相　（火冒三丈）哈，反了你啦！你口出狂言，想蹲监狱是不是！——去，把法警叫来。（随从数人下。怒气冲冲，绕室狂奔）把父亲关进监狱——把母亲和卖淫的女儿绑到耻辱柱上示众——法律的铁腕将代我平息我的愤怒。对这样的侮辱，我一定要狠狠报复——难道能容忍这样的下流坯破坏我的计划，离间我们父子而不给予惩处！——哈，这帮该死的家伙！我要你们通通完蛋才解恨，我要用复仇的怒火把你们全家，父亲、母亲和女儿，烧成灰烬！

斐迪南　（走到米勒一家中间，从容坚定地）呵，别这样！用不着害怕！有我在哩。（对宰相，恭顺地）别太性急，爸爸！如果您自爱，就别使用暴力——我心中有一个地方，父亲这个字眼还从未进入过——请您别硬要进里边去。

宰相　不要脸的东西！住嘴！别给我火上加油！

米勒　（从惊吓中回过神来）看好你孩子，老婆。我去找公爵。——他御用的裁缝——上帝指点了我！——他御用的裁缝在跟我学吹横笛。在公爵那儿我不会有问题的。（打算离开）

宰相　找公爵，你说——你忘了吧，我是公爵的门槛！你想跳过去，不摔断脖子才怪哩！——找公爵，你这傻瓜！——你试一试，看我不把你扔进深深的地牢，扔进那不见天日、不闻人声、阴森恐怖如同地狱的地方，活不成，也死不了——到那时，你将铁索锒铛，哭哭哀哀，说什么：我真是太不幸啦！

第七场

法警数名。前场人物。

斐迪南　（奔向露意丝。她昏倒在他臂弯里，不省人事）露意丝！帮我一下！救救她！她被吓昏过去了！

米勒　（抓起一根藤条，戴上帽子，准备动粗的样子）

米勒太太　（跪倒在宰相面前）

宰相　（冲法警亮了亮他的勋章）动手吧，以公爵的名义——孩子，离开这个婊子——管她晕倒不晕倒！——等她脖子套上铁链，别人就会用石头将她砸醒的。

米勒太太　发发慈悲吧，大人！发发慈悲！发发慈悲！

米勒　（一把将妻子拽起来）给上帝下跪去吧，老虔婆，别给——别给恶棍下跪，我反正少不了进监狱！

宰相　（咬了咬嘴唇）你算计错啦，混蛋。还有绞架等着哩！（对法警们）难道要我再说一遍吗！

众法警　（冲向露意丝）

斐迪南　（从露意丝身边跳起，挡在她面前，怒不可遏）看谁敢动一动！（举起带鞘的宝剑，用剑柄挥打法警）谁敢碰一碰她，谁就当心自己的脑袋。（对宰相）请你放珍重点。别逼我太过分，爸爸！

宰相　（威胁法警）你们还要饭碗吗，胆小鬼……

众法警　（重新冲向露意丝）

斐迪南　该死的东西！我说：退回去——我再说一遍！您怜悯怜悯自己吧，爸爸！别逼我走极端！

宰相　（气急败坏地斥责法警）你们就这样恪尽职守？混账东西！

众法警　（猛冲上去）

斐迪南　事已至此——（拔出剑来，砍伤法警数人）只好请你们法律的代表原谅了！

宰相　（怒不可遏）我倒要看看，你这剑是否也会砍在我的身上。（亲手抓住露意丝，拽起她来交给一名法警）

斐迪南　（大声惨笑）爸爸，爸爸，你的行为是对上帝最尖刻的讽刺！他竟善恶不辨，把十足的刽子手变成了堂堂宰相！

宰相　（对其他人）带走她！

斐迪南　爸爸，绑她上耻辱柱吧，但是连同少校，连同宰相的少爷一起！——您还固执己见吗？

宰相　那戏就更有看头，更加有趣喽——带走！

斐迪南　爸爸！为了这姑娘，我宁可放弃少校的佩剑——您还坚持吗？

宰相　剑挂在你那不知羞耻的身上，已经毫无价值！——带走！带走！我命令。

斐迪南　（推开那个法警，一条胳臂搂住露意丝，另一只手举起剑）爸爸！在您让我妻子受辱之前，我决心刺死她——您还坚持吗？

宰相　刺吧，要是你的剑还锋利。

斐迪南　（放开露意丝，怒视空中）万能的主呵，你看见啦！是人想得出来的办法我全已试过——现在不得不用魔鬼的伎俩了！在你们带她去站耻辱柱的时候（凑近宰相的耳朵大声道）——我就向整个京城讲那段您爬上宰相宝座的故事。（下）

宰相　（五雷轰顶似的猛然一惊）你想干什么？——斐迪南！——放了她！（急急追赶少校）

第一场

宰相和秘书伍尔穆上。

宰相　事情搞糟了。

伍尔穆　跟我担心的一样，大人。强迫经常使热恋的人更加铁心，而从来不能叫他们回心转意。

宰相　本来我对这一招信心十足。我断定：一旦姑娘名声扫地，他身为军官便不得不回头。

伍尔穆　完全正确。可问题却在要真的名声扫地。

宰相　不过哩——我现在冷静地思考了一下——我还是不该上他的当——他只不过是威胁一下罢了，大概永远不会动真格的。

伍尔穆　您可别这么想。一个热恋者惹急了什么蠢事都干得出来。您常告诉我，少校先生对您能执政一直摇脑袋。这我相信。他从大学里学来的那些信条，一开始我就觉得不可理解。他那些关于伟大心灵和高尚人格的梦想，在宫廷里能派啥用场？宫廷里最大的智慧不外乎不紧不慢，圆滑机灵，能缩能伸。他年纪太轻，脾气火爆，根本不懂得徐缓、迂回的权术谋略的奥妙，野心勃勃，动辄便追求伟大和冒险。

宰相　（不耐烦）可您这番高论对事情有什么弥补呢？

伍尔穆　我讲这些是给阁下指出问题的症结，也许还有挽救的办法不是。一个那种性格的家伙——恕我冒昧——他绝不能做您的亲信，也不可让他与您为敌。他厌恶您飞黄腾达所采用的手段。到目前为止，也许只是儿子拴住了叛徒的舌头。您要给了他适当的机会和借口，您要是一再伤他的感情，使他认为您不是一个慈爱的父亲，那么，他心中爱国者的责任感便会占上风。是的，仅仅给正义祭坛献上一份绝妙的牺牲这个奇思异想，就足以刺激他亲手打倒自己的老子。

宰相　伍尔穆啊伍尔穆！——你把我领到了可怕的悬崖边上。

伍尔穆　不，我是想把您领回来，大人。允许我怎么想怎么讲吗？

宰相　（坐下）就像一个囚犯对他的同案犯。

伍尔穆　那就请大人海涵——我想，您当宰相完全靠的是圆滑的宫廷艺术，您干吗又不能用它当父亲呢？我记得，当时您是如何好劝歹劝，把您的前任请去玩扑克，并且用上等法国葡萄酒亲亲热热地灌了他半夜；而就在这天夜里，巨大的地雷行将爆炸，那好人必定飞上天——为什么您对令郎又非得摆出一副敌对的架势不可呢？千万别让他知道，我了解他恋爱的底细。从姑娘方面下手去挖它的墙脚，进而控制住您那公子的心。您要像一位聪明的将军似的分化瓦解敌人，而不是去攻击它的中坚核心。

宰相　具体如何行事？

伍尔穆　再简单不过——还有牌在咱们手里嘛。您暂时委屈一下，别摆父亲架子。别去跟痴心的情郎较量，任何阻力都只会使他更加痴傻，更加倔强——把他们交给我，我要用他们的狂热，孵化出吞噬掉这狂热自身的虫子。

宰相　我急欲知道究竟。

伍尔穆　要么我太不懂得人心，要么令郎吃起醋来也十分可怕，就跟他闹恋爱一样。让他对那些姑娘产生疑心吧——不管有没有这回事。一丁点儿酵母，就会引起剧烈反应，将这个罗曼史破坏掉。

宰相　可去哪儿弄这点儿酵母呢？

伍尔穆　现在咱们到了节骨眼儿上啦——首先，大人，您得给我讲清楚，要是少校继续抗拒下去，您将担多大风险？——对您来说，让他结束与一个平民丫头的罗曼史，跟弥尔芙特夫人结婚，究竟重要到了什么程度？

宰相　这还用问吗，伍尔穆？——要是与夫人的婚事吹了，我的整个地位都会动摇；要是我过分逼迫少校，我的脑袋就有危险！

伍尔穆　（兴高采烈）那好，大人，您请听——对少校先生，我们只能用计谋诱使他进入罗网。对那丫头，我们将动用您的全部权威。我们口授一封她给第三者的情书，叫她亲笔写出来；然后，我们巧妙地让信落进少校手里。

宰相　想入非非！好像她一说便通，会马上写下自己的死亡判决书似的？

伍尔穆　她一定会写，只要您让我放手去干。这颗善良的心我了如指掌。它只有两个致命弱点，容易受到我们的攻击——她的父亲和那位少校。少校可以完全不加考虑；正因此，我们就可以更加放手地对付那位乐师。

宰相　具体办法呢？

伍尔穆　根据大人给我讲的在他家已上演的那场戏看，最简单的办法就是威胁她父亲，说要让他吃官司。公爵殿下的宠臣和掌玺官等于是殿下的影子——侮辱他就等于侮辱殿下——至少我要用这纸糊的鬼怪，把那家伙逼得走投无路。

宰相　不过——可别搞得太过火。

伍尔穆　才不会呢——只等把一家人逼上了绝路，便适可而止。也就是说，我们将悄悄地把乐师关起来——为了把情况搞得更严重点，也可以连那母亲也一块儿逮进去——同时就讲对罪行起诉呀，上断头台呀，终身监禁呀什么什么的，而获释的唯一条件，是女儿的那封信。

宰相　好！很好！我明白了。

伍尔穆　她爱她的父亲——我想说——爱得要命。他的生命——至少是他的人身自由——受到了威胁——她的良心将自我谴责，是她招惹了是非——与少校结合又不可能——最后再加她的头脑已被搅昏，这事儿就包在咱身上——十拿九稳——她非掉进陷阱不可。

宰相　可我儿子呢？他会不会马上得到风声？他会不会更加疯狂呢？

伍尔穆　一切让我来操心吧，大人！——在全家赌咒发誓对整个经过保守秘密并承认那封信是真的之前，咱们绝不释放她的父母。

宰相　赌咒发誓？赌咒发誓顶屁用，蠢货！

伍尔穆　对于我们是屁用没有，大人。可对他们那号人，用处大着哩。——您瞧一瞧，咱俩只这么一招就能如愿以偿，有多妙——姑娘失去了少校的爱情和自己清白的名声。父亲母亲垂头丧气，心甘情愿地向命运屈服，这当口儿我才去向他们的女儿求婚，帮她挽回一点儿面子，到头来他们还会感激我对他们发了善心哩。

宰相　（边笑边摇脑袋）真的，我服你啦，恶棍！这一招可算魔鬼的杰作。青出于蓝而胜于蓝喽！——现在的问题是，信写给谁？我们让她和什么人关系暧昧！

伍尔穆　必须是一个由于令郎的决定要么赢得一切，要么输掉一切的人。

宰相　（稍微考虑了一下）我想只能是侍卫长了。

伍尔穆　（耸耸肩膀）要是我叫露意丝·米勒，他自然不合我的口味。

宰相　为什么不？怪了！一套令人眼花缭乱的穿戴——浑身的巴黎香水味儿和麝香味儿——每一句蠢话都换得来大把的金币——这一切还不够叫一个市民丫头垂涎三尺？——呵，老弟，人吃起醋来不会考虑那么多。我这就派人去请侍卫长。（摇铃）

伍尔穆　这事和把提琴师米勒抓起来的事就请大人亲自处理了；我呢，得去起草刚才讲的那封信。

宰相　（踱到写字台前）写好了马上送来我看看。（伍尔穆下。宰相坐在桌旁书写着什么，一名侍从走进来，他站起身递一张纸给侍从）这份逮捕令立刻送到法院去——同时再派个人去请侍卫长来见我。

侍从　侍卫长老爷的车正巧到了门外。

宰相　那更好——不过，告诉下边，仔细准备好后再动手，免得引起骚乱。

侍从　遵命，大人。

宰相　明白吗，一点不能声张？

侍从　明白，大人。（下）

第二场

宰相和侍卫长。

侍卫长　（急匆匆地）只是顺道儿来看看，老伙计！——您怎么样？过得好吗？今儿晚上上演大型歌剧《狄多》[1]——烟火棒极啦——整座城市一起烧起来——您不来看看吗？怎么样？

宰相　我后院里火已烧得够猛啦，眼看会将我的整个荣华富贵化为灰烬——您来得正好，亲爱的侍卫长，有件事正需要您出主意和出力气哩。此事将要么叫咱俩飞黄腾达，要么彻底毁了我和老弟您。坐下谈吧！

侍卫长　别吓唬我，老兄。

宰相　就这么回事——要么飞黄腾达，要么彻底毁灭。您清楚我对我儿子和弥尔芙特夫人的安排。您也明白，对于巩固咱俩的幸福，这样的安排必不可少。一切都可能功亏一篑哟，卡尔勃。我儿子斐迪南不愿意。

侍卫长　不愿意——不愿意——可我已讲遍全城啦！人人都在谈论这桩婚事。

宰相　您将变成一个散布谣言的家伙，在全城的人面前出乖露丑。他爱的是另一个女的！

侍卫长　开玩笑！难道这也算得上障碍？

宰相　遇上了那么个顽固脑袋，简直是最没法克服的障碍。

侍卫长　他竟会这么痴傻，送上门来的幸福都不要？嗯？

宰相　您问他自己去，听他回答您什么吧。

侍卫长　可我的天！他到底能回答什么哟？

宰相　他将向全世界揭露咱俩的罪行，让世人知道咱们是怎样爬上来的——他将告发咱们伪造文书和字据的勾当——他将把咱俩送上断头台——他能回答这一切！

侍卫长　您神经有毛病怎么的？

宰相　这是他的回答。他打定主意这么干——我甚至低声下气地求他，他仍不放弃自己的打算。现在您说吧，怎么办？

侍卫长　（一脸蠢相）我的脑袋不中用了。

宰相　这还不算。我同时还接到我的密探们的报告，御酒监封·波克跃跃欲试，正准备向夫人求婚呐。

侍卫长　您要急死我了。谁，您说？封·波克，您说？——您也知道，我和他可是死对头！您也知道，我们怎样结的仇？

宰相　这我倒想听听。

侍卫长　老伙计！您就听好了，但愿您别坐立不安——如果您还记得宫里那次化装舞会——眼看就是二十年前的事啦——您知道，大伙儿刚跳完第一轮英国土风舞，大吊灯上的蜡烛油便热乎乎地滴了一些在默尔绍姆伯爵带帽兜的长袍上——我的天啊！这您一定还记得！

宰相　这样的事谁忘得了？

侍卫长　对啦！阿玛丽公主正跳在兴头上掉了一条箍袜带——不难想象，这下所有人全慌作一团——封·波克和我——我们那会儿还在当宫内侍从——我俩一起在舞厅中爬来爬去找那袜带儿——终于，我发现了它——封·波克一见马上扑过来——硬从我手中夺走了袜带儿——我请您想一想！——他把它交还给公主，扬扬得意地抢去了本应属于我的一次取宠的机会——您做何感想？

宰相　无耻！

侍卫长　抢去了我取宠的机会！——我差点儿晕倒过去。没见过这样的穷凶极恶！——终于，我鼓起了勇气，踅到公主殿下跟前，说道：“殿下，封·波克真太幸运，能把袜带奉还给您；可那第一个找到袜带的人，却不事声张，只在心眼儿里感到满足。”

宰相　讲得好，侍卫长！再好不过！

侍卫长　不事声张——可我一定要对封·波克报这个仇，哪怕是到了世界的末日——这下流无耻的谄媚者！——而且还不止此呐——在我俩同时扑去捡袜带的一刹那，这狗杂种把我假发右边的香粉蹭了个精光，将我在舞会上的形象完完全全给毁了！

宰相　正是这小子要娶弥尔芙特夫人，从而成为宫里的头号人物。

侍卫长　您给我心里戳了一把刀子。要？要？他凭什么要？怎能说他一定会娶她？

宰相　因为我的斐迪南不愿意，除了他又没别的人来顶替。

侍卫长　可您难道没有任何办法让少校改变主意？——不管事情多么棘手，多么令人绝望！——只要能排除那该死的封·波克，世界上再讨厌的事情咱们现在不是也乐意干吗？

宰相　我只知道一个办法，行不行就看您喽。

侍卫长　看我？什么办法？

宰相　把少校和他的情人拆散。

侍卫长　拆散？您的意思是？——您要我干什么？

宰相　只要使他对姑娘产生疑心，就万事大吉。

侍卫长　让他以为她偷了东西，对吗？

宰相　唉，不是不是！他怎么会相信这个？——要他以为她还和另一个男人有关系。

侍卫长　这另一个男人？

宰相　必须您来当，男爵。

侍卫长　我来当？我？——她是贵族吗？

宰相　干吗是贵族？异想天开！——一个乐师的女儿。

侍卫长　就是说平民喽？这不行。嗯？

宰相　什么不行？笑话！天地间谁会想到查问漂亮脸蛋儿们的祖宗八代，家庭出身？

侍卫长　可请您考虑，一位有妇之夫！还有我在宫里的名声！

宰相　那是另外一回事。对不起，我还不知道，在您看来做品德高尚的丈夫，会比当有权有势的大官更重要。咱们别谈了吧？

侍卫长　请别误会，男爵。我不是这个意思。

宰相　（冷冷地）不——不！您完全有道理。再说呢，我也烦了。我将就此撒手。我祝封·波克荣升宰相。世界上还有的是去处。我向公爵主动辞职。

侍卫长　那我呢？——您说得容易，您！您是位有学问的人！可我算什么？——天呐，要是殿下撤了我，叫我干什么好哇？

宰相　老皇历。死脑筋。

侍卫长　我求您，老朋友，大好人！——快打消这个念头！什么事我都情愿干。

宰相　您愿意借出您的名字，让那个米勒姑娘写封信约您去幽会吗？

侍卫长　以上帝的名义起誓，我愿意！

宰相　愿意在某个一定会让少校看见的场合将信掉出来，对吗？

侍卫长　例如在检阅的时候，我可以假装掏手帕，将信漫不经心地扔在地上。

宰相　并且在少校面前坚持扮演情郎的角色？

侍卫长　得啦得啦！我一定收拾他！我一定扮演个狂热的情郎，把这自以为是的小家伙的胃口倒掉。

宰相　这就对喽。信今天就写好。天黑前您得再来取信，并且和我一起将您的角色琢磨琢磨。

侍卫长　一旦我请完那十四个最最重要的安，立刻就赶来。请原谅，我得马上告辞。（下）

宰相　（摇铃）全靠您的老练狡猾啦，侍卫长。

侍卫长　（扭过头来喊道）嗨，我的天！您还不了解我！

[1]　《狄多》是17世纪英国作曲家普赛尔所作歌剧，原名《狄多与埃涅阿斯》（Dido and Aeneas）。女主人公狄多系腓尼基公主，因女巫作祟失去了情人特洛伊王子埃涅阿斯而自杀。

第四场

米勒家的一间房间。

露意丝和斐迪南。

露意丝　我求求你，别再来啦。我不相信还会有什么幸福的日子。我已经失去我的一切希望。

斐迪南　可我希望的却更多了。我父亲很生气。我父亲会用一切手段对付我们。他将逼得我做个不孝之子。我再不会尽什么儿子的责任。愤怒和绝望将迫使我揭开他谋杀前任的黑幕。儿子将把父亲送到刽子手手中——这叫铤而走险——而且必须铤而走险，如果我的爱情不得不迈出这勇敢的一步的话！——听着，露意丝——有一个想法，伟大、豪迈如我的爱情，它一阵又一阵地撞击着我的灵魂——这就是你，露意丝，还有我和我们的爱情！在这个圆圈里不包含着整个的天空吗？难道你还需要别的第四种什么？

露意丝　行啦，什么也别再说。一想到你想说的那些话，我便会脸色苍白。

斐迪南　对世界我们已毫无所求，干吗还要去乞求它的喝彩？既然已不可能赢得任何东西而只会失去一切，干吗不冒冒险？——这双眼睛不管是倒映在莱茵河中还是易北河中，还是波罗的海，不是同样的温柔、明亮吗？哪儿有露意丝爱我，那儿就是我的祖国。你在荒漠中的足迹，对我来说比我故乡的大教堂更值得欣赏——难道我们还会思念城市的繁华吗？只要哪儿有我俩在，那儿就有太阳升起，太阳落下，露意丝——这壮丽景象将使一切艺术的铺张煊染相形见绌。我们不能再上任何教堂侍奉上帝，夜晚却会在我们的头顶上张开庄严的天幕，盈缺交替的月亮会给我们传播忏悔之道，满天繁星会和我们一起向上帝祈祷。我们的绵绵情话怎么会说得完呢？——我的露意丝嫣然一笑，便足够谈论几个世纪；要体会出你的一滴泪水的含义，生命之梦已做到尽头。

露意丝　难道你除了爱我，不承担任何别的职责？

斐迪南　（拥抱她）保证你的安宁，就是我最神圣的职责。

露意丝　（非常严肃地）那就请你住口，并且离开我——我有一位父亲，他除去我这独生女儿，便一无所有——明天他将满六十岁——他提心吊胆，知道宰相准会对他进行报复……

斐迪南　（迅速抢过话头）让他和我们一块儿走。这样便没啥好说了吧，亲爱的！我马上去变卖值钱的东西，并且从父亲账上提些款子出来。抢夺一个强盗的财物不算犯法；他那许多财产，不都是国家的血泪吗？——半夜打一点时有辆车驶到门口来，你们赶紧跳上车。咱们远走高飞。

露意丝　可你父亲会在背后诅咒我们——这样的诅咒，我的冒失鬼啊，就是杀人犯说出来也总会传到上帝耳边，就是缚在绞刑架上的强盗听了也会视为上天的报应，因而心惊胆寒。这样的诅咒将像幽灵，无情地驱赶我们这些流浪者，从天涯到海角，从此岸到彼岸——不，亲爱的！如果只有罪孽能使我得到你，那我还有失去你的力量和勇气。

斐迪南　（黯然站着，脸色阴沉地喃喃道）真的吗？

露意丝　失去你！——呵，这个想法真可怕得要命——够讨厌的，钻不朽的灵魂的牛角尖，让欢乐的灼热面颊变得苍白冰冷——斐迪南啊斐迪南！我怎能失去你哟？不过，只有占有过的东西才可能失掉，而你的心属于你的等级。——我占有它的想法实属大逆不道和狂妄，因此只好战战兢兢地将它放弃。

斐迪南　（沉下脸孔，咬住嘴唇）你要放弃？

露意丝　不！瞧着我，亲爱的瓦尔特。别那么咬牙切齿的。来！让我以自己作为榜样，拯救你那垂死的勇气。让我暂充一充女中豪杰——把一个浪子送还给他的父亲——放弃这一使市民社会解体，使永恒的公共秩序崩溃的结合。——我是一个罪人——胸中充满了狂妄、愚蠢的渴望——我的不幸实在是我该受的惩罚。让我继续相信它是我作的牺牲吧——这样的妄想令我感到甜蜜和欣慰——你会拒绝给我这点乐趣吗？

斐迪南　（神思恍惚而激愤地抓过一把提琴，准备要拉——突然却扯断琴弦，将琴摔碎在地，爆发出高声的狂笑）

露意丝　瓦尔特！天上的主啊！你怎么啦？振作起来！——这样的时刻需要镇定——这分手的时刻！你有一颗高贵的心，亲爱的瓦尔特。我了解它。你的爱情像生命一般热烈，并且自由不羁、无穷无尽——把它献给一位高贵而显赫的女子吧——她从此将不再艳羡女性中那些最最幸运的人——（忍住眼泪）请你别再来看我——在寂寞的围墙内，轻率地受蒙骗的姑娘将独自悲痛哭泣，没有任何人再管她是否在流泪——我的未来空虚而无望——可是，我仍将不时地去闻那往昔的花束，虽然它已经枯萎。（转过脸去，同时向他伸出颤抖的右手）请多保重，封·瓦尔特少爷。

斐迪南　（跃起身来，恍若大梦初醒）我决心逃走，露意丝。你真不愿跟我走吗？

露意丝　（在房间里侧坐下，双手蒙着脸）我的职责要求我留下，并且逆来顺受。

斐迪南　毒蛇，你撒谎！一定是别的什么拴住了你的心。

露意丝　（音调流露出内心的深沉哀痛）您保留着这样的疑心吧——它也许会使您好受些。

斐迪南　用冰冷的职责克制火热的爱情！——这样的鬼话哄得了我吗！——必定有个情夫叫你恋恋不舍；如果我的疑心得到了证实，你和他都将认识我！（冲出房去）

第六场

露意丝和秘书伍尔穆。

伍尔穆　（走近她）晚上好啊，小姐！

露意丝　上帝！谁在那儿讲话！（转过身，看见了秘书，吓得连连后退）可怕！可怕！我的不祥预感这么快就得到最不幸的应验。（用鄙夷的目光瞅了瞅伍尔穆）您准是找宰相！他已经走了。

伍尔穆　小姐，我找您！

露意丝　那我就奇怪了，您本该到市集广场上去才对。

伍尔穆　为什么偏偏去那儿？

露意丝　去接您的未婚妻呀，从示众台上。

伍尔穆　米勒小姐，您冤枉我了……

露意丝　（欲答又止，转过话头）请问有何贵干？

伍尔穆　我来是受您父亲的委托。

露意丝　（一惊）受我父亲的委托？——我父亲在什么地方？

伍尔穆　在他不情愿待的地方。

露意丝　上帝啊！快讲！我已感到大难临头——我父亲在什么地方？

伍尔穆　在大牢里，既然您一定要知道。

露意丝　（仰面望着天空）有这样的事！竟有这样的事！——在大牢里？为什么在大牢里？

伍尔穆　遵照公爵的命令。

露意丝　公爵的命令？

伍尔穆　他侮辱了公爵殿下，因为他竟敢对殿下的代表……

露意丝　什么？什么？呵，万能的永恒的上帝啊！

伍尔穆　已经决定从严惩处。

露意丝　还没有完哩！还有这个！——当然当然，我心中除去少校之外，还有另外一些宝贵的情感——它也不容忽视——侮辱殿下——老天有眼！呵，快挽救挽救，快挽救挽救我的信仰，它正在失去！——还有斐迪南呢？

伍尔穆　他要么娶弥尔芙特夫人，要么遭受诅咒，被剥夺继承权。

露意丝　可怕的自由选择！——不过——不过，他还是比较幸运。他没有父亲可失去。虽说压根儿没有父亲也够悲哀的！——我父亲犯上有罪——我爱人要么娶夫人，要么受诅咒并失去继承权——真是太了不起啦！完完全全的无赖也算一种完美！——完美吗？不！还有一点欠缺——我母亲在什么地方！

伍尔穆　在感化院。

露意丝　（轻声惨笑）现在完美了！——完美了，我已经无牵无挂——解除了一切义务——不再有眼泪——不再有快乐——不再受到庇护。我也不再需要它们——（可怕的沉默）您也许还有一大堆新闻吧？尽管讲好了。我现在全都可以听。

伍尔穆　发生了的事情，您已经知道。

露意丝　这么说，就不会再发生什么吗？（又安静下来，从头到脚打量着秘书）可怜的人！你干的是件可悲的差使，从中你不可能得到快乐的。使别人不幸已经够可怕，而更可怕的是还得去向他们宣布——对他们唱猫头鹰的不祥之歌，站在一旁看着他们的心在命运的矛尖上战栗不止，鲜血淋漓；看着基督徒们怀疑是否还存在上帝——老天保佑我！即使你看见的因恐怖而滴落的鲜血一滴能换一桶黄金——我也不愿意变成你。——还会怎么样？

伍尔穆　我不知道。

露意丝　您竟不知道？——这桩见不得阳光的差事您害怕说出来声音太响，可您墓穴一般阴沉沉的面孔已告诉我有鬼——还有什么花招！——您刚才说，公爵要从严惩处？您说的从严是什么意思？

伍尔穆　别再问了吧。

露意丝　听着，坏蛋！你这刽子手的门徒，你知道如何拿刀子先慢吞吞割断人家脆弱的手脚，接下来却以假惺惺的怜悯去抚弄、舔舐人家颤抖的心！——我父亲的命运将会怎样！你含笑说出的话语中已藏着死亡；你秘而不宣的事情又会是什么？说出来吧。让我一下子担负起全部重荷，哪怕被压得粉身碎骨也行啊！——等待着我父亲的是什么？

伍尔穆　受刑事审判。

露意丝　可这是什么意思！——我是个无知而单纯的女孩子，听不懂你们那些可怕的外国话。什么叫刑事审判？

伍尔穆　决定生死的审判。

露意丝　（镇定地）多谢您了！（急忙走进隔壁房间）

伍尔穆　（不知所措地站在原地）她要去哪儿？这傻丫头难道要——见鬼！她该不会是——我得赶上去——我必须对她的生命负责。（准备去追她）

露意丝　（披了一件斗篷走回来）对不起，秘书先生，我要锁门了。

伍尔穆　这么急上哪儿去？

露意丝　去见公爵。（欲走）

伍尔穆　什么？去哪儿？（慌慌张张地拉着她）

露意丝　去见公爵。您听不明白吗？去见的就是那个想要人审判我父亲，决定我父亲是死是生的公爵——不！不是他想要——而是他必须让人审判，因为有几个恶棍希望如此；他仅仅把他的威严和他君王的签名，给予了这个所谓犯上作乱案子的审判罢啦。

伍尔穆　（纵声大笑）去见公爵！

露意丝　我知道您笑什么——可我也并不指望在那儿得到怜悯——上帝保佑我！会得到的只有厌恶——只有对我的呼喊声的厌恶。人家告诉我，世上的大人物都不了解悲惨是什么，而且也不屑于了解。我现在就要告诉他，什么叫悲惨——要用死亡的种种扭曲的怪相，给他描绘出悲惨的嘴脸——要用撕心裂肺的钻进他骨髓的叫唤，让他听见悲惨的语言——即使他这时已听得毛骨悚然，我最后还要冲着他耳朵大吼：到了垂死的一刻，就连地上的神灵也一样会喘不过气来；末日审判中用来甄别善恶的，无论对王侯还是对乞丐，将是同一把筛子！（欲走）

伍尔穆　（恶毒而貌似和气地）您去吧，呵，您快去呀。真的，您这样子再聪明不过。我赞成您去，我向您担保，公爵会乐于开恩的。

露意丝　（突然站住）您说什么？——您自己也劝我去？（快步走回房中）嗯？我到底想干啥？连这个人都赞成的，准是件可鄙可恶的事情——您从哪儿知道，公爵会对我开恩？

伍尔穆　因为他会得到报答。

露意丝　报答？难道做一件合乎人道的好事，也可以开出价码吗？

伍尔穆　要说价码呢，漂亮的求情人本身已经足够。

露意丝　（呆呆地立着，随后突然爆出一声喊叫）公正无私的主啊！

伍尔穆　而且我希望，为了救出您父亲，您不会认为公爵的这个价码定得太高吧！

露意丝　（来回疾走，失去了控制）是的！是的！一点不错。你们那些大人物，他们万无一失地躲在堡垒中——躲在将他们与真理隔开的罪孽后面，就像躲在天使们的宝剑背后一样——万能的主啊，救救我！爸爸，你女儿情愿为你而死，可是不愿为了你而与人同流合污。

伍尔穆　对那可怜的孤老头，这大概还是个新闻哩——“我的露意丝，”他对我说，“我的露意丝害我摔了跤。我的露意丝也会把我扶起来……”——赶快把回音带给他吧，小姐。（装着要走的样子）

露意丝　（赶上去拉住他）等一等！等一等！别着急！——在需要折磨人的时候，这魔鬼真叫机灵！——我害他摔了跤。我必须把他扶起来。您说吧！您吩咐吧！我可以做什么？我必须做什么？

伍尔穆　只有一个办法。

露意丝　一个什么办法？

伍尔穆　也是您父亲希望的——

露意丝　我父亲也希望？那该是啥办法呢？

伍尔穆　对您来说轻而易举。

露意丝　对我说来最难莫过于丧失廉耻。

伍尔穆　要是您同意放弃少校……

露意丝　放弃他的爱情？您在取笑我吧？——明明硬逼我这么做，又来问我乐意不乐意！

伍尔穆　不是这个意思，亲爱的小姐。得让少校首先主动退出。

露意丝　他不会的。

伍尔穆　看样子是这样。否则来找您干什么，要不是只有您能促使他那样做？

露意丝　难道我能强迫他恨我不成？

伍尔穆　咱们可以试一试。请坐下。

露意丝　（茫然地）嘿，你捣的什么鬼？

伍尔穆　坐下吧。请您写！这儿是笔、纸和墨水。

露意丝　（极度不安地坐下来）叫我写什么？叫我写给谁？

伍尔穆　写给您父亲的刽子手。

露意丝　哈！你真是个拷打人灵魂的老行家！（抓起笔）

伍尔穆　（开始口授）“亲爱的先生——”

露意丝　（哆哆嗦嗦地写着）

伍尔穆　“难以忍受的三天已经熬过去了——熬过去了——我们没能够见面——”

露意丝　（一怔，放下笔）信是给谁的？

伍尔穆　给您父亲的刽子手呀。

露意丝　我的主啊！

伍尔穆　“为此，您只能怨少校——怨少校——他整天守着我，像百眼巨人阿耳戈斯[1]——”

露意丝　（猛然站起来）卑鄙无耻！有谁听说过！——这封信到底写给谁？

伍尔穆　写给你父亲的刽子手呗。

露意丝　（绞着手指，走来走去）不！不！不！太残酷啦，天啊！如果世人得罪了你，你给他们惩罚吧，可为什么要把我置于进退维谷的可怕境地？为什么要把我夹在死亡与耻辱之间，颠来倒去，受尽折磨？为什么要让这个吸血的恶魔骑在我脖子上，肆意欺凌我？——你们想怎么办就怎么办吧！这信我决不再写了。

伍尔穆　（伸手取帽子）悉听尊便，小姐。写不写完全看您自愿。

露意丝　自愿，您说？看我自愿？——滚，野蛮的家伙！你把一个不幸的人吊在地狱的深渊上边，要求她做件什么事，然后却亵渎上帝，问不幸的人是否自愿！——呵，您再清楚不过，我的心就像拴在铁链上一样，牢牢地被父女之情束缚住了。——其他一切都已经无所谓。继续往下念吧，我什么都不再考虑。对阴险狡诈的地狱，我认输了。（重新坐下）

伍尔穆　“整天守着我，像百眼巨人阿耳戈斯”——这句写好了吗？

露意丝　往下念！往下念！

伍尔穆　“昨天，宰相上我家里来了。看见好心的少校拼命维护我的名誉，我心里直乐……”

露意丝　呵，妙，妙！太高明啦！——只管往下念。

伍尔穆　“我假装晕倒过去——晕倒过去——怕的是会笑出声来”——

露意丝　呵，天哪！

伍尔穆　“可这假面具戴着实在难受——实在难受——真恨不得马上逃走”——

露意丝　（停下笔，站起身，低着头来回地走，好似在地上寻找什么，然后又坐下去继续写）“恨不得马上逃走”——

伍尔穆　“明天他值勤——注意他啥时候离开我这里，然后您就去我俩那个地方”——“我俩那个”写上了吗？

露意丝　一字不差。

伍尔穆　“去我俩那个地方找您温柔的……露意丝吧”——

露意丝　现在还差收信人。

伍尔穆　“致宫廷侍卫长封·卡尔勃大人。”

露意丝　永恒的主啊！我从来没听见过这个名字，就像我的心从来没想到过这些可耻的勾当。（站起来，呆呆地凝视着自己写的东西好半天，临了儿还是把它递给秘书，嗓音嘶哑地，气息奄奄地）拿去吧，我的先生。我现在交给您的——是我清白的名字——是我的斐迪南——是我生命的全部欢乐！——现在我已成了一无所有的乞丐！

伍尔穆　嗨，没的事儿，别灰心，亲爱的小姐。我打心眼儿里同情您。也许——谁知道呢？——也许我仍然可以不计较某些事——真的！上帝做证！我同情您。

露意丝　（目光直瞪着他，像要把他看穿似的）得啦，先生，别说出来，您正在转的念头太可怕。

伍尔穆　（打算吻她的手）要是这只可爱的小手……怎么样，亲爱的小姐？

露意丝　（庄严地，厉声地）当心我在新婚之夜掐死你，然后再心满意足地自行走上绞架！（打算离开，但马上又走回来）先生，我们现在清账了吗？小鸽子可以飞走了吗？

伍尔穆　还有一点点小事，小姐。您必须当着我的面去教堂发誓，承认这封信是自愿写的。

露意丝　上帝啊！上帝啊！难道你必须亲自给这地狱的杰作打上封印，以便它完美无缺吗？（被伍尔穆强拉下场）

[1]　希腊神话中看守美女伊娥的巨人。

第二场

斐迪南独自飞快地读完信，一会儿呆若木鸡，一会儿绕室狂奔。

斐迪南　不可能。不可能！在这天使一般的躯体内，不可能藏着一颗魔鬼的心……可事实却明摆着！明摆着！就算所有的天使都下到人世，为她的清白担保——就算天和地，就算造物和造物主都聚集起来，为她的清白担保——这可是她的亲笔信呀！——闻所未闻的无耻欺骗，人类从来不曾经历过的欺骗！——这就是为什么她死也不肯逃走！——为的就是这个——上帝呵！——现在我算醒悟啦，现在对我才算真相大白！——就为这个，她才大大方方地放弃了我对她的爱情；我差一点，差一点就受了她那天使的假面具的蒙蔽！（越奔越快，最后又停下来静静地沉思）完全摸透了我！——我的每一次感情冲动，每一声心灵震颤，每一回热血激荡，都得到了回应——凭一声细微到极点的无法描述的叹息把握我的心境——用一滴泪水测算出我的感情——伴随我攀登上热情的座座险峰，当我快坠入可怕的深渊时突然出现在眼前——上帝啊！上帝啊！这一切难道仅仅是假象？——假面具？——呵，要是谎言的色泽能这般经久不褪，又怎么可能没有魔鬼混进天国里去呢？

当我指出我们的爱情已处于危险中的时候，这虚伪的女人一下子便脸色苍白，装得真是太像啦！对我父亲的无礼讥嘲，她像个高傲的胜利者似的不屑搭理，可在这一瞬间，这娘儿们似乎也心虚了——不是吗？她到底经受不住真理的严峻考验——这伪善的女人晕倒了过去。你现在还能说什么呢，感情？连淫妇也晕倒了啊。你用什么来替自己辩解呢，贞操？——连婊子也晕倒了啊。

她知道，她已把我变成了什么样子。她看透了我的整个灵魂。在第一次亲吻时我满脸通红的一刹那，我的目光已彻底地展示了我的心——她难道会毫无感觉？或许她仅仅感觉到了胜利的喜悦？——在幸福陶醉的时刻，我幻想她心里装着整个天国，最狂野的愿望也沉默下来了——我心头除去永恒的天国和这个姑娘，别无其他念头——上帝啊！她竟一点没感觉到吗？她唯一感到的，就是她的诡计得逞了吗？就是她卖弄风情赢得了青睐，因而扬扬得意吗？死也要报这个仇！没有别的原因，只为我受骗了吗？

第三场

侍卫长和斐迪南。

侍卫长　（小步跑进房来）您叫人找我吗，亲爱的——

斐迪南　（喃喃自语）我要扭断一个流氓的脖子！（提高嗓音）侍卫长，这封信想必是您在检阅时从口袋里掉出来的——我呢，（冷笑）很幸运地把它给捡到了。

侍卫长　您？

斐迪南　一个太有趣的巧合。您追究万能的上帝的责任去吧！

侍卫长　您瞧，男爵，您把我吓成了啥样子。

斐迪南　念一念吧！念一念吧。（离开侍卫长）既然我不够资格做个情人，那就不如心甘情愿地为你们搭桥拉纤。（趁侍卫长念信的时候，走到墙边取下两支手枪）

侍卫长　（将信扔在桌子上，准备溜走）该死！

斐迪南　（拽住胳臂将他拉回来）慢着，亲爱的侍卫长。这些新闻我觉得挺有趣。再说，我还没有得到捡信人的酬劳哩。（把枪递给他）

侍卫长　（惊愕，后退）请您理智点，亲爱的。

斐迪南　（声音大而可怕）我太理智了，所以决心把你这样的流氓送到另一个世界去。（硬塞一支枪在他手里，同时从口袋里掏出一张手绢）拿着！抓住这张手帕！——它是我从那婊子手里得到的。

侍卫长　以手帕为界决斗？您疯了吗？瞧你想到哪儿去啦！

斐迪南　抓住这一头，我说。不然你会射偏的，胆小鬼！——瞧他抖得多厉害，这个懦夫！你应该感谢上帝，懦夫，他将让你后脑勺第一次尝到枪子儿的滋味。（侍卫长拔腿溜走）等一等！我请你啦。（赶到他前边，拴上门）

侍卫长　在房子里决斗，男爵？

斐迪南　好像和你也值得跑到城外去似的！——宝贝儿，在房里枪声会更加响亮，这可是你在世界上发出的空前绝后的声音呀——举起枪来吧！

侍卫长　（擦拭额上的汗水）难道您打算拿您宝贵的生命来冒险吗，前程远大的年轻人？

斐迪南　瞄准，我说！在这个世界上，我已别无所求。

侍卫长　可我求的还多着哩，我最最杰出的朋友。

斐迪南　你，奴才？你追求什么？——去干世人全都不屑于干的勾当？去不住地点头哈腰，卑躬屈膝，活像只被大头针钉着的蝴蝶？去记录你主子上厕所的次数，对他讲的笑话应声打哈哈？同样地，我也愿意像带着只稀罕的土拨鼠一样带上你，让你像只猴子似的应和着地狱中死鬼们的吆喝声跳舞，狗颠屁股似的奔来跑去伺候他们，用你混迹宫廷的伎俩去娱悦那些永劫不复的罪人。

侍卫长　老爷吩咐小的什么都可以——只是请把手枪放下！

斐迪南　瞧这窝囊废的德行！——真让用第六天造人的上帝感到羞耻！就像迪宾根某个书商粗制滥造的盗印本！——你这脑瓜儿实在不争气，太可惜了它里边那两勺子脑髓，真太可惜！仅仅这点儿脑髓，就足以把一只猢狲变成人，可它现在却只造成理性的破坏——我偏偏得和这样一个家伙分享她的心？——太失格了！太不负责任了！——对这样一个家伙，让他改邪归正还来不及，哪能再刺激他去造孽呢？

侍卫长　呵，感谢上帝，他变聪明了！

斐迪南　我让他配受你的感谢。既然连毛毛虫也得到宽容，就让这家伙也沾点光吧。人家将来碰见他也许会耸耸肩，对上帝的英明发出赞叹，佩服他竟然用残渣和垃圾喂养出了这样一些生物；佩服他竟然给刑场上的乌鸦和皇家厕所里的佞臣准备了餐桌——最后，人们还要惊叹上帝的远见卓识，甚至在地狱中他还豢养了一些以毒攻毒的蝮蛇和蜘蛛——可是，（重新怒不可遏）不许害虫碰我的花朵，要不我就将它（抓住侍卫长猛烈摇晃）如此这般地捏得粉碎。

侍卫长　（自怨自艾）上帝呵！谁离开这里就真有福！离开得远远儿的，就算住进巴黎的疯人院也不错！只要别和这人在一起！

斐迪南　混蛋！要是她不再清白无瑕！混蛋！要是你在我顶礼膜拜的圣地寻花问柳！（狂怒）在我侍奉上帝的天国耽于淫乐！（突然静下来，然后咄咄逼人地）要是你是这样一个混蛋，你就真该早早逃进地狱去还好些，免得在天堂里撞在我的气头上！——你和那姑娘的关系究竟有多深？坦白讲！

侍卫长　请您放开我。我把一切全讲出来。

斐迪南　呵！和这姑娘乱搞，该比尽情地嫖娼宿妓更带劲儿吧！——她愿意放荡，她愿意她能够贬低灵魂的价值，以淫乐冒充德行。（用手枪顶住侍卫长胸口）你和她究竟有什么关系？要不我开枪，要不你说出来！

侍卫长　什么关系也没有——真的什么关系也没有。请您哪怕忍耐一分钟。您上当受骗啦。

斐迪南　用得着你来提醒我吗，恶棍？——你和她关系有多深？说，要不我杀了你！

侍卫长　我的上帝！我的上帝！我说就是了——您只管听着吧——她父亲——她的亲生父亲——

斐迪南　（狠狠地）把他女儿拉来和你姘在一起？那么你和她已经到了什么程度？说，不说我要你的命！

侍卫长　您疯了。您听不进我的话。我从没见过她，也不认识她。我压根儿不了解她的情况。

斐迪南　（连连后退）你从没见过她？也不认识她？压根儿不了解她的情况？——米勒姑娘为你失去了清白，你却一口气对她说三个不？——滚，坏蛋！（用枪揍他一下，把他推出房间）这样的人不值得浪费火药！

第五场

宰相和斐迪南。

斐迪南　（退回房中）呵！——爸爸！

宰相　很好，咱们在这儿碰见了，孩子。我来通知你一件叫你高兴的事，亲爱的儿子，一件准会叫你喜出望外的事。咱们坐下来好吗？

斐迪南　（久久地凝视着父亲，然后激动万分地跑上去抓住他的手）爸爸！（吻他的手，同时跪在他脚下）呵，爸爸！

宰相　怎么啦，孩子？快站起来。你的手又烫又哆嗦。

斐迪南　（极其热烈、冲动）原谅我的忘恩负义，爸爸！我是个不孝的逆子。我误解了您的好心。您待我一片慈爱——呵！您要早有先见之明——现在已太迟啦——原谅我！原谅我！给我您的祝福吧，爸爸！

宰相　（装出莫明其妙的样子）站起来，孩子！想一想，你这不是给我打哑谜吗？

斐迪南　米勒那丫头，爸爸——呵，您了解这个人——当时您生气是完全对的，是表现了高尚的慈父之爱——只是爱子心切，方法不当——米勒那丫头！

宰相　别折磨我了，孩子。我恨自己太严厉！我是来请你原谅的。

斐迪南　请我原谅？诅咒我吧！——您的不同意十分明智。您的严厉是对我天大的爱惜——米勒那丫头，爸爸……

宰相　是个高贵而可爱的姑娘——我收回我操之过急的怀疑，她已赢得我的尊重。

斐迪南　（震惊得跳起来）什么？您也？……爸爸！连您也？……可不是吗，爸爸，生就一副纯洁无邪的好模样——爱这样的姑娘，真是太合乎人情了。对吗？

宰相　也可以说：不爱她等于犯罪。

斐迪南　闻所未闻！岂有此理！——以往您可是很能洞悉人心的哟！而且您通常都是用仇恨的眼睛观察他人！——绝无仅有的伪善——这个米勒丫头，爸爸……

宰相　她有资格做我的女儿。我把她的德行看作高贵的出身，我珍视她的美貌如同金子。我的原则对你的爱情低头了——她应该属于你！

斐迪南　（发疯似的冲出房间）绝不！再见吧，爸爸。（下）

宰相　（跟着他）等等！等等！你奔哪儿去？（下）

第六场

弥尔芙特夫人十分豪华的客厅。

夫人和使女索菲走进来。

夫人　这么说你见着她了？她会来吗？

索菲　马上来。她还随便穿着在家时的衣服，准备赶快换一换。

夫人　别告诉我她的任何情况——什么也别讲——要见到这个幸运的人，这个和我可怕地心心相印的女子，我哆嗦得跟个罪犯一样——在接到邀请时她态度如何？

索菲　她好像很吃惊，沉思着，睁大眼睛瞪着我，一声不响。我原本做好了她会推辞的思想准备，谁知她却眼睛一亮，完全出乎我意料地回答说：“您夫人吩咐的，正是我明天要去求她的事。”

夫人　（非常不安）饶了我吧，索菲。可怜可怜我。要是她只是个平凡的女子，我一定会脸红；要是她超出了平凡，我更会胆怯啊。

索菲　可是夫人——您并非心血来潮，贸然接待一位情敌。想一想，您是什么人。让您的出身、您的地位、您的权势，来替您壮胆吧。一颗骄傲的心，定能提高您仪表的端庄和美丽。

夫人　（魂不守舍地）胡说些什么呀，傻瓜！

索菲　（狡黠地）如此看来，今天这些最值钱的宝石在您身上闪闪发光，也许是碰巧喽？还有，您碰巧正好今天穿上了最名贵的衣料缝的裙子——并且在您的房里挤满了仆人和侍者，还要在您宫内最豪华的客厅接待一个市民少女，对吗？

夫人　（气急败坏地走来走去）真该死！真过分！女人看女人的弱点眼睛就跟夜猫子一样！——可我堕落得有多深啊，多深啊，竟让这样个贱人来揭自己的底！

侍从　（走上场）米勒小姐到……

夫人　（冲索菲）走吧，你！退出去！（索菲还迟疑着。语气变得严厉）走！我命令你！（索菲下。在厅内转了一圈）好！很好，我动了气。我就想这样子。（对侍从）叫小姐进来。（侍从下。猛地坐进沙发，摆出个高贵的懒洋洋的姿势）

第八场

弥尔芙特独自站在厅中，目光呆滞地瞪着露意丝冲出去的厅门，震惊得失去了自持；终于，她从神志迷乱中清醒过来。

夫人　我这是怎么啦？怎么回事？那不幸的女孩她说了些什么？——呵，天啦！它们，她那些可怕的、诅咒我的话语还撕扯着我的耳朵：把他拿去吧！她说。——谁呢，不幸的姑娘？你临终喘息的馈赠——你绝望恐怖的遗物吗？上帝！上帝！我已经堕落到这步田地——已经这么突然从所有骄傲自尊的王座上摔下来，以致饿鬼似的渴望着，期待着，要去接受一个女乞丐在垂死挣扎时抛过来的施舍吗？——把他拿去吧！她说话时是那样一种语气，还伴着那样一种眼色——哈！艾弥丽呀艾弥丽！难道你就为此而越出女性的规范？你就必须为此而做人家的姘妇，丧失伟大的不列颠女性的名节，让自己荣誉的大厦在一个低贱的平民女子更高的德行旁倾覆吗？——不，傲慢而不幸的姑娘！不！——艾弥丽·弥尔芙特可以忍受耻辱——可绝不让人辱骂！我也一样有能力放弃。（神情庄严地来回走着）滚开吧，软弱的愁眉苦脸的女人！——别了，爱情甜美的金色的梦境！——从此我要以心胸博大为行动的准绳！——那相爱的一对儿完了，要不就只有我打消心头的欲念，并且让公爵永远将我忘记！（稍停，兴奋地）就这么办！——搬掉可怕的障碍——割断我与公爵之间的一切联系——驱走我心中狂暴的爱情！——德行啊，我要投身你的怀抱！——收留她吧，你的悔过自新的女儿艾弥丽！——哈，我一下子心情多么舒畅！我一下子感到多么轻松！多么高尚！——今天，我就要像落日一般伟大地步下权势的高峰；我的荣华富贵将与我的爱情一道逝去；陪伴我完成高傲的放逐的，仅仅是我的心。（坚决地走向写字台）必须马上就办——立刻就办，免得那可爱的青年再迷住我，重新引起我内心的殊死斗争。（坐下开始写）

第九场

弥尔芙特夫人，一名侍从以及索菲。随后又来了宫廷侍卫长，最后再进来仆人若干名。

侍从　侍卫长奉公爵之命来到，正等候在前厅里。

夫人　（写得正起劲）他会给搞糊涂的，他们木偶似的公爵！诚然，也够异想天开啊，竟这样去剖他那至尊的脑袋瓜儿！——他那班宠幸会变成热锅上的蚂蚁——全国上下将乱作一团。

侍从和索菲　侍卫长，夫人……

夫人　（转过头来）谁？什么？——那更好！这类畜生来到世界上就为的是驮大口袋。请他进来吧。

侍从　（下）

索菲　（怯生生地踅近夫人）我不得不担心，夫人，我这样做近乎放肆——（夫人仍一个劲儿地往下写）米勒那丫头发疯似的冲过前厅——您也满脸通红——自言自语——（夫人继续写着）我害怕——准保会闹出什么乱子来的？

侍卫长　（走进来，冲着夫人的脊背不住地鞠躬，发现她没看见，就踅过去，站在她的椅子背后，轻轻抓起她的裙裾来按在嘴上吻了一下，细声细气地，诚惶诚恐地）公爵殿下他……

夫人　（一边往信上撒沙子同时飞快检查信的内容，一边接过话头）他将怪我忘恩负义呐！——我曾经孤苦伶仃，他把我从苦难中拉扯了出来——从苦难中？——好个令人恶心的交易！——该撕掉你的账单了，骗子！我以终身的耻辱还清了你的高利贷！

侍卫长　（围着夫人转了一圈仍未受到注意）夫人像有点心不在焉——看来我只好鼓一鼓勇气了。（猛地提高嗓门儿）殿下派我来请问夫人，今晚是演法国通俗剧呢还是德国喜剧？

夫人　（笑着站起来）随便哪个都行，我的天使。——顺便请您把这张条子带给公爵当饭后果！（转向索菲）你，索菲，吩咐套好车，并把我的行装全部集中到厅里来——

索菲　（惊惶地退下）呵，天！我不早有预感吗！谁知还会出什么事？

侍卫长　您挺激动吗，夫人？

夫人　这样就可以少装模作样——哈哈，侍卫长大人！这儿将空出一个位置来，拉皮条的该交好运啦！（发现侍卫长在瞟字条）您念吧！您念吧！——我希望，信的内容不仅仅成为两个人之间的秘密。

侍卫长　（念信，夫人的仆役们慢慢在大厅后部聚集起来）“公爵殿下！一纸您随随便便就撕毁了的契约，对我也再不会有约束力了。您的公国民众的幸福，曾是我爱您的条件。三年来我一直在受骗，现在才睁开眼睛。我厌恶您给我淌着您臣民们泪水的恩惠。——我不再报答您的爱，您就把它给予自己哭泣的国家，并向一位不列颠女公爵学习，像她一样怜悯您的德意志人民吧。一小时后，我已在公国境外。约翰娜·诺弗克。”

全体仆役　（吃惊地嘀嘀咕咕）已在公国境外？

侍卫长　（吓得把字条放回桌子上）上帝保佑，我最仁慈的夫人！带信的人和写信的人一样，脑袋恐怕都有危险。

夫人　那就是你的问题了，宝贝儿！——遗憾的是我知道，你们这号人在重复别人念的经时也会噎死！——好吧，我就给你出个主意，把信烤在野味饼里得啦；这样殿下自会在盆子里发现它的——

侍卫长　老天！这样做太放肆！——您考虑考虑，您可是想一想，这会叫大家多么狼狈，夫人！

夫人　（转向聚集起来的仆人们，怀着内心的激动说出下面的话）你们都惊呆了，我的好人们，都惶惶不安地等待着谜底将怎样揭开，是吗？——走近些，亲爱的朋友！——你们侍候我既诚实又体贴，更经常地注意我的眼睛，而不是我的钱袋。你们的奉命唯谨是出于你们的热情，出于你们的骄傲——是对我的恩惠！——可叹啊，怀念你们的忠诚，同时必然想起我的屈辱！悲惨的命运啊，我最黑暗的日子偏偏是你们幸福的日子！（眼里噙着泪水）我现在就辞退你们，我的孩子们——弥尔芙特夫人不复存在，而约翰娜·诺弗克又太穷，无力偿付她欠的债。——我的管账先生将倾我的所有，任随你们瓜分。——这座府邸仍旧属于公爵。你们中最寒碜的，在离开此地时，也将比你们的女主人富有。（伸出手去，众仆役挨个儿上前热烈地亲吻）我理解你们，我的好人们——再见了！永远再见了！（强压悲哀，打起精神）我听见车已经到了。（抽身准备出去，侍卫长急忙拦住去路）可怜的家伙，你还站在这儿？

侍卫长　（一直魂不守舍地盯着字条发愣）要我把这张条子呈到公爵殿下高贵的手里吗？

夫人　可怜的家伙！呈到他那高贵的手里，并且向他高贵的耳朵禀报，因为我不能赤着脚去圣地洛莱托清洗罪孽，我将做一个自食其力的人，以便洗刷掉我曾经左右过他的耻辱。（冲出厅去。其余的人全都激动地各奔东西）

第一场

露意丝静静地、一动不动地坐在最幽暗的屋角里，头伏在胳臂上。过了好久，才见米勒提着灯笼走进来，惊惶不安地在屋里照来照去，却没有发现露意丝。随后他摘掉帽子，放在桌上，再将灯笼放下。

米勒　这儿也没有她。这儿还是没有——我跑遍了大街小巷，去过所有熟人家里，每一道城门都问过了——人家哪儿也没见着我的孩子。（沉默良久）得有耐心，可怜而不幸的父亲。等着吧，等到明天再说。也许你的独生女儿到时候就游到岸边来了——上帝啊！上帝啊！是我的心太眷念这个女儿，把她当神一般对待了吗！——你的惩罚太重啦，天父啊，太重啦！我不想抱怨，天父，可惩罚太重啦。（痛苦不堪地倒在一把椅子上）

露意丝　（在屋角里说）你做得对，可怜的老爸爸！你还得及时学会失去哟。

米勒　（一跃而起）是你吗，我的孩子？你在这儿？——干吗这么孤零零的，灯也不点？

露意丝　我并不因此孤独。正因为我周围一片黑暗，才会有贵客上门。

米勒　上帝保佑你！只有良心的蛀虫才迷恋猫头鹰，罪孽和鬼魅都害怕光明。

露意丝　还有永劫，爸爸，还有无须任何帮助便与灵魂对话的永劫。

米勒　孩子！孩子！你这是些什么话呀？

露意丝　（站起来往前走）我刚经历了一场激烈的斗争，上帝清楚，爸爸。是他给了我力量。胜败已经决定了，爸爸！世人总说我们女性是娇嫩的，脆弱的。别再相信这种话。在一只蜘蛛面前我们是会吓得发抖；可那带来腐烂和毁灭的黑色巨魔，我们却可以玩儿似的搂进怀里。这就是我要告诉你的，爸爸。你的露意丝快活着哩。

米勒　听着，女儿！我倒希望你大哭一场。这样子，我会更加喜欢。

露意丝　我多想斗败他啊，爸爸！我多想骗过那个暴君啊，爸爸！——爱情比心肠狠毒更狡猾和大胆——他不懂得这个道理，那个倒霉的家伙。——呵，他们是够奸刁的，在他们仅仅对付头脑的时候；可一当他们要对付人心，这些恶棍就愚蠢起来了！——他竟想以一句誓言替他的骗局保险！誓言也许能束缚住活人，爸爸，可人一死，连宣誓的铁链也会熔化。到那时，斐迪南会理解他的露意丝。——你愿意替我送封信吗，爸爸？你愿意行行好吗？

米勒　送给谁，我的女儿？

露意丝　问得好怪！无限的宇宙和我的心加在一起，也不够容纳我对他唯一的思念。——我还能向别的什么人写信呢？

米勒　（不安地）听着，孩子！我要拆开这封信。

露意丝　随你的便吧，爸爸——可你什么也不会明白的。字母就像冷冰冰的死尸似的躺着，唯有爱情的眼睛才富于生气。

米勒　（念信）“你被出卖了，斐迪南——一个没有先例的阴谋扯碎了我俩的同心结，可怕的誓言又封住了我的嘴；你父亲到处安排有他的密探。然而，亲爱的，你要是有勇气的话——我还知道第三个地方，那儿誓言不再有约束力，任何密探也闯不进来。”（停住，严肃地凝视着她的脸）

露意丝　干吗这样瞅着我？念完呀，爸爸！

米勒　“可你必须鼓足勇气穿行黑暗的街道，在那儿给你光明的唯有你的露意丝和上帝——你只需带来你的爱，其他的一切希冀和渴望，你通通可以留在家里；在那儿，你只需要你的心。你要愿意——那就启程吧，在卡美尔派修道院的钟楼敲十二点的时候。你要胆怯——那就从你们男人的称谓前划去‘坚强’这个词，因为一个姑娘叫你蒙受了羞耻。”（米勒放下信，目光沉痛、呆滞地久久凝视着前方，好久才转过身来对着露意丝，嗓音低沉嘶哑地）什么第三个地方，孩子？

露意丝　你不知道它。你真的不知道吗，爸爸？——奇怪！这个地方说得很清楚，斐迪南会找到的。

米勒　唔！再讲清楚点！

露意丝　对它我偏偏想不起什么可爱的称呼。——你千万别害怕，爸爸，要是我说出难听的来。这个地方——这个情人们本该给它取一个最动听的名字的地方，呵，不知为什么他们却没想出好名字！这第三个地方哟，好爸爸——你可得让我说完呀——这第三个地方叫坟墓。

米勒　（歪歪倒倒地走向一把圈椅）我的上帝啊！

露意丝　（赶过去扶住他）可别这样，爸爸！仅仅是围绕这个称呼聚集起了许多恐惧的缘故——撇开这个称呼，在它里边摆放着新娘的寝床，床顶上铺展开了锦缎般的朝霞，还有年复一年的春天悬挂的五彩花环呐。只有大哭大叫的罪人才会骂死是一堆白骨；它其实是个甜蜜可爱的小男孩，容光焕发如世人画的小爱神，但却不像爱神似的刁钻古怪——死是一个沉静而乐于助人的精灵，它越过时间的鸿沟，伸出手臂迎接疲惫不堪的朝圣女子，为她的灵魂开启永恒的灿烂辉煌的仙宫，亲切地对她点着头，然后隐去。

米勒　你想干什么，我的女儿？——你想擅自戕害你的生命吗？

露意丝　别这么讲，爸爸。逃避一个容不下我的社会——提前到一个我迟早得去的地方——这难道也算是罪孽？

米勒　自杀是再可恶不过的了，孩子——是唯一无法追悔的罪孽，因为它将死亡与犯罪结合在一起。

露意丝　（呆立着）可怕呵！——不过不会这么快。我打算跳进河中，爸爸，我将在沉下去时祈求全能的上帝怜悯我。

米勒　这就是说，你要在赃物藏好后才来忏悔你的偷窃罪——孩子！孩子！当心啊，别愚弄上帝，当你最需要他的时候！呵，瞧你已经走得有多远，有多远！——你放弃了祈祷，仁慈的主已经收回他持有你的手。

露意丝　爱难道犯罪吗，爸爸？

米勒　如果你爱上帝，你就绝不会爱到犯罪的地步——你害得我头垂腰弯，我唯一的宝贝儿！深深地，深深地，也许已经接近坟墓。——得啦！我不想使你心情更加沉重，孩子！刚才说了点什么。我以为房里只我一个人。你已经听见了，我何必再保什么密呢？你曾是我崇拜的女神。听着，露意丝，只要你心中还有一点对父亲的体贴——你曾经是我的一切啊！现在你别再浪费你的财富了。我也可能失去一切啊！你瞧，我的头发已开始花白。对我来说，已经到了做父亲的该从儿女心中收回投资和红利的时候了。你想要剥夺我的这种权利吗？你想带上你父亲的全部财富一去不返吗？

露意丝　（异常激动地吻他的手）不，爸爸！我将带着对您的重债离开这个世界，到了永恒的彼岸再加倍偿还你。

米勒　注意啊，孩子，可别失算！（非常严肃和庄重地）在彼岸我们还可能重逢吗？——瞧，你脸色变得多么苍白！——我的露意丝自己也已明白过来，在那个世界我不可能再赶上她，因为我还不会像她似的急急忙忙地上那里去。（露意丝扑进他怀里，浑身战栗。他热烈地搂着她，用哀求的声调继续说）呵，孩子！孩子！我也许已经失去了你，走向死亡的女儿！记住我这做父亲的认真的话吧！我不可能时刻守着你。我可以搜走你的刀子，你却能用一根别针杀死自己。我可以防止你服毒，你却能用一串珍珠将自己勒死。——露意丝——露意丝——我还能做的，只是对你发出警告。——你愿意冒险尝试一下，让你那不可靠的幻想在时间与永恒之间的可怕小桥上，将你背弃吗？你愿在全能全知者的座前，鼓起勇气撒谎说“主啊，为了你的缘故，我来了”吗？——到那时，你有罪的眼睛将四处搜寻你的傀儡躯壳；你头脑中臆造的脆弱上帝也将像你一样，跟蛆虫似的在你的审判者脚下蜷曲着身子，在那进退失据的时刻揭穿你自以为是的亵渎神圣的假话，打掉你对永恒的慈悲的幻想——这样的慈悲，是一个罪人根本不可能乞求到的——到那时，你该怎么办啊？（加重语气，提高嗓门儿）你怎么办，不幸的孩子？（将她搂得更紧，呆呆地盯了她好一会儿，然后迅速离开她）现在我再不知道说什么了——（举起手臂）主啊，我不再替你照管这个灵魂！去吧，你想干什么干什么。去为你那高个儿青年做出牺牲，你的魔鬼会因此欢呼狂叫，你的天使却将退避三舍。——去呀！背起你的全部罪孽，并且将你这最后的也是最可怕的罪孽加上；要是你还嫌太轻，那就让我的诅咒给你凑足分量吧！——这儿是一把刀——戳穿你的心，还有——（同时号啕大哭，准备冲出门去）——这颗父亲的心！

露意丝　（赶紧追上去）等一等！等一等！我的爸爸！慈爱比暴君的愤怒更加专横！——叫我怎么办？我不能够啊！我该怎么办？

米勒　要是你感到那少校的亲吻，比你父亲的眼泪还要灼热——死去吧！

露意丝　（经过激烈的思想斗争，然后颇为坚定地说）爸爸！握住我的手！我愿——上帝啊！上帝啊！我这是干什么！我打算干什么？——爸爸，我发誓——我真该死，真该死！我这有罪的人，我偏想到哪边了呵！——爸爸，行啦！——斐迪南——上帝明鉴！——我这就彻底消除对他的记忆。（撕碎她那封信）

米勒　（大喜过望地冲上去搂住她的脖子）这才是我的女儿！——望着我！你摆脱了一个爱人，成全了一个幸福的父亲。（又是笑又是哭地搂着她）孩子！孩子！我真不配活到这样一天！上帝知道，我这坏老头怎么得到了你——我的天使！——我的露意丝，我的天国！——上帝呵，我不大懂得爱情，但放弃它必定是很痛苦的，这我还能理解。

露意丝　离开这个地方吧，爸爸——离开这座城市；在这儿我的女伴们会嘲笑我，我的好名声已经永远失去——走吧，走吧，远远地离开这个地方，在这里处处可以看见我失去了的幸福的痕迹——离开它，只要可能——

米勒　你愿上哪儿都行，我的女儿。世界无处不生长上帝赏赐的食粮，无处没有他的耳朵在聆听我拉琴。是的，让一切都成为过去吧！——我要让琴弦述说你哀痛的故事，我要唱一支赞美女儿的歌曲，她为敬重她的父亲而撕碎了自己的心——我们唱着这支歌挨家挨户乞讨；从那些感动得掉泪的人手里得来的面包，将别有一番滋味。

第二场

斐迪南和前场人物。

露意丝　（先看见斐迪南，惊叫一声，奔过去紧紧搂着父亲的脖子）上帝！他来啦！我完了。

米勒　哪儿？谁？

露意丝　（背转脸，指指少校，将父亲搂得更紧）他！他本人！——你回过头瞧瞧吧，爸爸——他要来杀我了。

米勒　（看见了斐迪南，往后退几步）怎么？您来了，男爵？

斐迪南　（慢慢走近，始终面对着露意丝，用审视的目光紧盯着她，过了一会儿才说）感到惊异的心地善良的小姐，多谢了！您的自白诚然可怕，却也直率而确切，省得我受痛苦折磨。——晚上好，米勒。

米勒　看在上帝分上！您到底要干什么，男爵？您来寒舍有何贵干？这样突然闯来究竟是什么意思？

斐迪南　可曾几何时，有人还把一天的光阴以秒计算，还把对我的思念挂在钟摆上以加快它的速率，还对我出现的一刹那急不可待得心儿怦怦跳动——怎么搞的，现在竟一下子成了突然闯来？

米勒　您走吧，您走吧，男爵——要是您心里还剩有一星半点儿人性——要是您还不想扼杀她，这个您说您爱她的女孩！我求您了，求您马上离开。只要您一踏进我的家，我们的幸福便完了。您给我家招来祸患，早先它却只有欢乐。您难道还不满意吗？我的独生女儿由于认识您而遭到不幸，您难道还要来拨弄她心上的伤口吗？

斐迪南　好个莫名其妙的父亲！我现在来，是要向令爱报告好消息！

米勒　大概是有了新的绝望的希望吧？——走呵，灾星！你那面孔已告诉人你没安什么好心。

斐迪南　实现我希望的机会终于到了！弥尔芙特夫人，我们爱情最可怕的障碍，此刻已逃离公国。我父亲同意了我的选择。命运认输了，遂了我俩的意。我们的幸福之星已经升起！——我来是兑现自己的诺言，领我的新娘去祭坛前举行婚礼呐！

米勒　你听见他了吗，女儿？你听见他奚落讥笑你的失望了吗？呵，真的，男爵！您这位诱惑者真叫惬意，干了坏事还可以卖弄小聪明。

斐迪南　你以为我在开玩笑吗？以我的名誉担保，不是的！我的话千真万确，就像我对露意丝的爱情；我视我的誓言为神圣，就像她遵守它一样。——我不知道还有什么更神圣的了——你还怀疑吗？在我美人儿的双颊上还没有快乐的红晕出现吗？这就怪了，真话在这儿难于取信，谎言肯定已成为家常便饭。你怀疑我的话，那这白纸黑字总该相信了吧。（把露意丝给侍卫长的信扔给她）

露意丝　（展开信，脸色惨白地倒下）

米勒　（未注意到露意丝，对少校）这是什么意思，男爵？我真不明白您！

斐迪南　（将他带到露意丝跟前）可我却十分清楚她！

米勒　（蹲到女儿身边）呵，上帝啊！我的孩子！

斐迪南　苍白得像死亡一样！——这样子才真叫我喜欢，您的女儿！她从来没有像现在这么漂亮过，您这虔诚的诚实的千金！——面孔像死尸一样——末日审判的嘘息能抹去任何诺言的涂漆表面，也吹掉了她脸上的脂粉；本来，凭着她的打扮，这妖精连光明天使也骗得过哟。——现在她的脸蛋儿再美不过！现在她第一次露出了真面目！让我来吻吻她吧。（准备向露意丝走去）

米勒　走开！滚！别来刺一个父亲的心，小子！我没能保护她不受你的调戏，却能保护她免遭你的虐待！

斐迪南　你想干什么，老头儿？我跟你没事儿。别掺和进这显然已经输了的赌博不好吗？——或者你比我想象的还要聪明一些？你已将六十岁的智慧投资到你女儿的风流营生中，并用拉客的勾当玷污了自己的白发？——呵！要是并非如此，不幸的老人啊，那就倒下死掉吧，还来得及！你还可以在咽气时甜蜜而陶醉地想：我曾是个幸福的父亲！——再过一会儿，你就得将这条毒蛇扔回它在地狱的老家，并且诅咒你所获得的这件礼物和它的赠予者，带着对上帝的亵渎走进坟墓里去。（对露意丝）说吧，倒霉的女人！这封信可是你写的？

米勒　（对露意丝，警告地）看在上帝分上，孩子！别忘了啊，别忘了啊！

露意丝　呵，这封信，爸爸……

斐迪南　它落进了不该落进的手里，是吗！——赞美天意的偶然，它完成了比自作聪明的理智更伟大的业绩，到末日审判时会比所有智者的机智更经得起考验——偶然吗，我说？——呵，即使是一只麻雀从天上掉下来，也有天意在起作用，一个魔鬼被揭露，又何尝不是这样呢？——我要求回答！——你写这封信了吗？

米勒　（在一旁哀求她）坚定些！坚定些，孩子！只要再说一声“是”，一切便过去了。

斐迪南　有趣！有趣！连父亲也骗了。所有人通通骗了！现在瞧啊，瞧她那德行，这可耻的女人。现在连她的舌头也不再听使唤，也不肯替她说出最后的谎话！向上帝发誓！和真实得可怕的主起誓！你写这封信了吗？

露意丝　（经历着极其痛苦的思想斗争，同父亲不断地交换眼色，然后坚定地、一了百了地）我写了！

斐迪南　（惊得呆住了）露意丝！——不！我拿灵魂担保，你在撒谎！——即使纯洁无邪的人，在严刑拷打下也会承认他不曾犯过的罪行。——我追问得太凶了，不是吗，露意丝！——你是因为我追问得太凶了才承认的，是吗？

露意丝　我承认事实。

斐迪南　不，我说。不！不！你没有写！根本不是你的笔迹！——就算像，难道模仿笔迹会比破坏心灵更困难吗？对我讲真话吧，露意丝！——或者不，不，别说实话！你可能会讲“是的”，你一讲我也就完了。——一句谎言，露意丝——一句谎言——无论怎样的都行啊，你只要又以天使般坦诚的神态对我讲出来，只要能说服我的耳朵，我的眼睛，只要能卑鄙地蒙骗我的心——呵，露意丝！就让一切的真理从此随着它飞到九霄云外去吧！就让善良正直从此对宫廷卑躬屈膝、俯首帖耳吧！（用畏葸和颤抖的声音）你写这封信了吗？

露意丝　上帝做证！可怕的真实的主做证，写了！

斐迪南　（呆了一会儿，表情极为沉痛）婆娘！婆娘！——你现在竟让我看这样一副嘴脸！——凭着它你就算答应给人家天堂，你甚至在地狱里也休想找到乐于光顾的人了。——你知不知道，你对我曾经是什么，露意丝！不可能！不会的！你不知道，你曾经是我的一切！一切啊！——一切，这是个平庸而无足轻重的字眼儿；可要围着它转一圈，上帝也会感觉吃力；各个宇宙体系的轨道，也完全在它里边——一切啊！可你却这么可恶地玩弄它——呵，太可怕了！

露意丝　你已经叫我承认了，瓦尔特先生。我自己诅咒了自己。这下您走吧！离开这所使您感到如此不幸的房子吧！

斐迪南　好！好！现在我平静下来了——流行过瘟疫的可怕地方也是平静的嘛，人家说——我也一样。（沉吟片刻之后）还有一点请求，露意丝——最后的请求！我头烧得厉害，需要凉一凉——愿意给我兑一杯柠檬汁吗？（露意丝下）

第三场

斐迪南和米勒。

两人互不搭理，各在房间的一侧踱来踱去。

米勒　（终于停下来，神情哀伤地打量着斐迪南）亲爱的男爵，我向您承认，我打心眼儿里为您难过，这也许能减轻一些您的气恼吧？

斐迪南　就算这样好了，米勒。（又走了几步）米勒，我几乎一点想不起来，当初我怎么走进了您的家——为的是什么事情？

米勒　怎么，少校先生？您不是想跟我学吹长笛吗？你一点儿记不起了？

斐迪南　（急忙抢过话头）我见到您的女儿。（又停了好一会儿）您说话不算话，朋友。我们原该演奏宁静的乐曲，打发我寂寞的时光，您却欺骗我，卖给我了蝎子。（见米勒已开始激动，赶紧说）不！别害怕，老人家。（感动地搂住他脖子）您没有责任。

米勒　（擦拭眼睛）全能全知的上帝清楚！

斐迪南　（重新踱来踱去，堕入忧郁的沉思）真怪啊，上帝竟这么莫名其妙地和咱们开玩笑。在一些几乎瞧不见的细线上，常常悬挂着可怕重荷——人怎么知道，咬这个苹果一口就吞食了死亡，嗯？——怎么知道？（越走越急，然后突然抓住米勒的手，异常激动地）我说老头儿啊，为跟您学一点儿笛子，我付出的代价可太大了——而您竟一无所获——您也会输掉——也许输掉一切。（抑郁地从米勒身边走开）该死的学吹长笛，永生永世不该产生这个念头！

米勒　（极力掩饰着感情）这柠檬汁也兑得太久了。我想，您要是不见怪，我去看一看？

斐迪南　不急，亲爱的米勒。（自言自语地）对父亲更是——您只管留下吧——我有什么要问您来着？——对了！——露意丝是您独生女儿？除了她您就没有孩子吗？

米勒　（亲切地）再没有了，少校——也不想再有。这丫头恰好占完我这颗父亲的心——我已把全部现存的爱倾注在女儿的身上。

斐迪南　（大为震动）嗨！——您还是去看看饮料好些，亲爱的米勒。（米勒下）

第五场

米勒走回来。斐迪南仍在房中。

米勒　饮料马上给您送到，男爵。可怜的丫头坐在外边哭得死去活来。她将在柠檬中掺进她的泪水送给您喝啊。

斐迪南　光是泪水还更好些！——我们刚才不是谈到音乐了吗，米勒？——（掏出一个钱包）我还欠你的债哩。

米勒　干什么？干什么？去您的吧，男爵！您把我当成什么人了？钱留在您手里挺好的，别让我难堪好不好！再说，上帝保佑，咱俩又不是从此不再见面。

斐迪南　谁知道呢？您只管收下吧。我说不定是死是活哟。

米勒　（笑起来）噢，原来这样，男爵！以您现在的处境，我想，是可能心一横倒下的。

斐迪南　有人确实横过心——您从未听说过年轻人倒下吗？青年男女，希望的孩子们，受骗父亲的空中楼阁，年岁的蛀虫都奈何不得的，却往往让一记雷击就打倒了！——您的露意丝也并非长生不死呵。

米勒　她是上帝赐予我的。

斐迪南　您听着——我告诉您，她并非长生不死。这个女儿是您的心肝宝贝儿。您全心全意眷恋她，疼爱她。可您当心，米勒。只有绝望的赌徒才会孤注一掷。哪个商人把全部财产都装在一艘船上，人家就叫他冒失鬼——听着，想一想我这警告。——可您为什么不收下这些钱呢？

米勒　怎么，先生？偌大的一袋钱？少爷您想到哪儿去啦？

斐迪南　还债呗——给！（将钱袋扔在桌上，从袋里滚出来几枚金币）我也不能永生永世守着这劳什子。

米勒　（惊愕）伟大的上帝，这是什么？听声音不像是银币！（走向桌子，发出惊呼）老天爷呀，您这是干啥，男爵？您以为您在什么地方，男爵？您搞的啥名堂，男爵？我只能说您在开玩笑！（将双手捧在一起）这儿确实是些个……要不就是我中了邪——要不……上帝诅咒我！我抓在手里的确实是上帝创造的金子啊，确实是硬邦邦、黄澄澄、圆溜溜的金圆！——不，魔鬼！我才不受你的诱惑呐！

斐迪南　您是酒喝多了怎么的，米勒？

米勒　（粗鲁地）见他妈的鬼！您快瞧瞧呀！——金子！

斐迪南　自然，事情是有点特别。

米勒　（沉默了一会儿又走向他，深有感触地）少爷，我告诉您我是一个老实正直的人，如果您想把我套起来，为您去干坏事的话——要知道，上帝明鉴，这么许多钱靠正当的营生是挣不来的。

斐迪南　（感动地）您放心吧，亲爱的米勒。您早就配得到这些钱了；上帝饶恕我，我是想用它们来报答您的一片好心啊。

米勒　（像疯了似的跳跳蹦蹦）这么说是我的啰！是我的啰！上帝明鉴，上帝恩典，是我的啰！（高叫着朝房门奔去）老婆！闺女！维克多莉亚！快来呀！（走回房中）可老天爷！我怎么会一下子得到这多得要命的财富？我凭什么挣来的？我该怎么回报？嗯？

斐迪南　不是靠您上的音乐课，米勒。——我给您这些钱，是要……（浑身打了个冷战）是要……（稍停，伤感地）偿付您女儿让我做了三个月的幸福美梦！

米勒　（抓住他的手紧紧握着）少爷啊！您要是个普通、平凡的市民——（加快语速）我闺女还不爱您，那我就要亲手宰了她，这丫头！（又走到钱袋旁，抑郁地）可现在我有了一切，您却一无所有。现在是不是又轮到我来花天酒地一番，嗯？

斐迪南　别担心，朋友！——我这就起程，去到那个我打算永远待下来的国度。在那儿，这些钱不再管用。

米勒　（眼睛死死盯着金币，兴奋地）这么说它们仍旧是我的？是我的？——不过您要走了我挺难过。——等着吧，看我现在会是个啥气派！看我现在会如何满面春风！（戴上帽子，大步流星地穿过房间）我要再到市场上去教音乐课，再抽三王牌的蹩脚烟，再坐三文钱的孬位子，就让魔鬼把我逮去好啦！（欲走）

斐迪南　等一等！别声张！把您的钱收起来吧！（郑重地）只是今晚上您还不能说出去。从今以后别再收学生啦，为了我的缘故。

米勒　（更加兴奋，紧紧抓住斐迪南的马夹，抑制不住内心的快乐）少爷啊！还有我女儿！（放开斐迪南）钱并非一切——不是的——我吃土豆也罢，吃野味也罢，饱总归是饱；我这件外套还蛮好嘛，只要上帝亲爱的阳光还没洞穿它的袖筒子！——破旧衣服我来穿好啦，可我闺女应该得到幸福。只要她的眼睛流露出什么心愿，她就应该得到满足……

斐迪南　（赶紧打断他）别讲了！呵，别……

米勒　（越发激动）我要让她从头开始学法语，学跳法国小步舞，学唱歌；让人家在报上读到关于她的报道；让她戴和枢密顾问千金的一样的漂亮帽子，穿各种各样我说不出名字的时髦衣裙；让远远近近的人们都谈论提琴师的女儿，让……

斐迪南　（激动得可怕地抓住米勒的手）别说啦！什么也别说啦，看在上帝分上，住口吧！只有今天，什么都别说；这就是我要求您给我的——唯一报答！

第六场

露意丝捧着柠檬汁上。前场人物。

露意丝　（眼睛哭得红红的，一边将杯子递给少校，一边声音颤抖地说）请只管吩咐，如果还不够浓的话！

斐迪南　（接过杯子去放在桌上，迅速将脸转向米勒）噢，我差点儿给忘了！——允许我求您办点儿事吗，亲爱的米勒！您乐意帮我个小忙吗？

米勒　万分乐意！您想要？……

斐迪南　人家等着我出席宴会。糟糕的是我心情坏透了。像这样子我完全不可能去见人。——您愿意去我父亲那儿代我表示一下歉意吗？

露意丝　（一惊，急忙抢过话头）我完全可以去走一趟。

米勒　去找宰相？

斐迪南　不见他本人。您只要在前厅里让一名侍从转达就行了。——带上我这只表作为证明。——等您回来时，我还在这儿。——您得等他回答。

露意丝　（惊恐地）干吗不可以我去呢？

斐迪南　（对正要动身的米勒）等一等，还有点儿事。这是一封给我父亲的信，今天傍晚封在给我的信里送来的——也许有什么要紧事——让侍从带给他吧。

米勒　没问题，男爵！

露意丝　（抱住父亲，惊恐到了极点）可是爸爸，所有这些我全能办好的呀！

米勒　你独自一人，天又这么黑，孩子。（下）

斐迪南　给你父亲照亮，露意丝。（在她端着灯送父亲出去时，奔到桌旁，把毒药倒进柠檬里）是啊，她该死！她该死！头顶的神明已对我首肯，道出了可怕的“是”字；复仇的天神也画了押；她的守护天使已将她抛弃……

第七场

斐迪南和露意丝。

露意丝端着灯慢慢走回来，把灯放在桌上，站在少校对面的另一侧，脸冲着地面，只是时不时地以怯生生的目光偷觑一下少校。他站在另一边，目光呆滞。长时间的沉默，预示紧张的一幕即将开始。

露意丝　您要乐意我伴奏，封·瓦尔特先生，我就弹一会儿钢琴。（打开琴盖）

斐迪南　（闷声不响，好一会儿不予回答）

露意丝　您还多赢我一盘棋哩。我们再下一次好吗，封·瓦尔特先生？

斐迪南　（又是一阵静默）

露意丝　唉，我好可怜啊！

斐迪南　（还是刚才的姿势）那是可能的。

露意丝　您心情这么糟，封·瓦尔特先生，不是我的错。

斐迪南　（脸朝一边冷笑两声）对我这样发痴发傻，你哪能有什么错？

露意丝　我明白了，我们现在不适合好下去。我承认，在您打发走我父亲的那一刻，我马上吃了一惊。——封·瓦尔特少爷，我猜想，这会儿我们两个人将同样难熬。你要是允许，我就去邀请我的几个熟人来吧。

斐迪南　噢，行啊，去吧。我也马上去邀几个我的熟人来。

露意丝　（愣愣地望着他）封·瓦尔特先生？

斐迪南　（非常辛辣地）以我的名誉起誓，在眼前的情况下没有谁能出更聪明的主意！这一来，令人厌烦的二重唱变成一阵子嘻嘻哈哈，失恋的苦恼也就从卖弄风情中得到了报偿。

露意丝　您情绪好些了吗，封·瓦尔特少爷？

斐迪南　再好不过！好得市场上的孩子们跟在我身后追，以为我是疯子！不，说真的，露意丝！你的榜样教训了我——你应该是我的老师。傻瓜才胡诌什么永远忠贞的爱情，老是一张面孔令人反感，变化无常才有滋有味儿——一言为定，露意丝！我奉陪到底——咱俩从一桩风流韵事跳到另一桩风流韵事，从一个泥潭滚向另一个泥潭——你朝东——我朝西。也许，在某一家妓院里会找回我失去了的宁静。——也许，在一阵快活的追逐之后，我和你成了两具腐朽的白骨，有朝一日又会不胜惊喜地相逢在一起，就像在喜剧里一样，彼此凭着同一母亲的任何一个孩子都不否认的血缘标志认出对方，致使厌恶与羞惭又变得和谐一致；这可是最最温柔的爱情也不可能的呀！

露意丝　呵，年轻人，年轻人！你已经是不幸的了，难道你还想让家人骂你咎由自取吗？

斐迪南　（咬牙切齿地喃喃道）我不幸？谁告诉你的？你这个女人太卑鄙了，自己已麻木不仁，又凭什么去衡量他人的感受呢？——不幸，她说？——哈！这个词儿简直可以从坟墓里唤醒我的愤懑！——她早已知道，我一定会不幸呐。——该死的东西！她明知如此，却仍然背叛了我，瞧这条毒蛇！原来还觉得有唯一一点可原谅的理由——你的自供将折断你的脖子——迄今为止我总以你的单纯来掩饰你的罪孽，不屑与你计较，让你差点儿逃脱我的报复。（急切地抓起杯子）原来你并不轻率——并不痴傻——你只是一个魔鬼而已！（喝柠檬汁）这柠檬汁淡而无味，就像你的灵魂——尝尝看！

露意丝　天啊！我害怕有这一幕，并非多虑？！

斐迪南　（以命令的口气）尝一尝！

露意丝　（勉强接过杯子，开始喝）

斐迪南　（一见她把杯子送到嘴边，立刻转过身，脸色刷地一下白了，同时跑到最里边的屋角去）

露意丝　这柠檬汁挺好嘛。

斐迪南　（未转过身来，浑身哆嗦）那你受用吧！

露意丝　（放下杯子）唉，您不知道，瓦尔特，您多么伤我的心。

斐迪南　哼！

露意丝　将来会有一个时间，瓦尔特……

斐迪南　（回到前面）噢，时间一到咱们就一了百了。

露意丝　到那时，今晚上的事会成为你良心的沉重负担——

斐迪南　（开始越走越急，越来越不安，同时扔掉挂在身上的绶带和佩剑）去你的吧，效忠殿下！

露意丝　我的上帝！您怎么啦？

斐迪南　又热又闹——希望舒服一点。

露意丝　喝柠檬汁吧！喝吧！喝了您会感觉凉快一点。

斐迪南　那倒一定会的。——瞧，婊子也有心眼儿好的时候！可仅此而已。

露意丝　（满含情意地扑进他怀里）你竟这么对你的露意丝吗，斐迪南？

斐迪南　（推开她）滚！滚！别让我再见到你这双温柔迷人的眼睛！我要死了，露出你狰狞的面目来吧，毒蛇；扑到我身上吧，害人精——尽管对我亮出你的毒牙，扭动身子高高直立起来，有多可憎就多可憎——只是别再装出天使的样子——别再装作天使！——太晚了——我必须踩死你，像踩死一条毒蛇，不然就会毫无希望。——怜悯一下你自己吧！

露意丝　呵！干吗非走这样的极端？

斐迪南　（从旁边端详着她）天上的雕塑家的美妙杰作！——谁能相信呢？——谁会相信呢？（抓住她的手，向上举起）造物主啊，我不想责难你——可你为什么偏偏将你的毒汁装进如此美好的躯壳？在那温暖的宜人的天国，罪恶能够繁衍滋生吗？——真叫奇怪哟！

露意丝　不得不听这样的话，而且保持沉默！

斐迪南　嗓音甜美悦耳——从断裂的琴弦上，怎么可能发出如此动人的乐音呢？（久久盯着她，目光已经陶醉）一切都这么美好——这么匀称——这么仙女似的圆满！——处处显示出造物主怡然自得的心境！上帝做证，仿佛大千世界之所以产生，仅仅是为了让造物主酝酿情绪，以便最后完成他这个杰作！——只可惜，上帝在塑造灵魂时失了手！怎么会呢？怎么可能让这么个令人憎恶的怪胎出生在人世上，而未受挑剔呢？（迅速离开她）或者他本来不想雕一个天使却雕成功了，因而赶忙给她凑上一副更坏的心肠，以为这样就能弥补错误了吧？

露意丝　好个花岗岩脑袋啊！他宁可指责上帝，也不肯承认自己冒失。

斐迪南　（痛哭着扑向露意丝，搂住她的脖子）最后一次，露意丝——最后一次，就像我俩初次接吻的那天，当时你嘴唇灼热，好不容易才轻轻唤出一声“斐迪南”，唤出第一声“亲爱的”！——呵，在那一瞬间，恰似不可言喻的无穷快乐的种子发芽了，开花了。——突然间，我们眼前出现一个天堂，美好得如同明媚的五月；黄金的世纪像一些新娘子，围绕着我们的灵魂欢呼雀跃！——那时候我真幸福啊！——呵，露意丝！露意丝！露意丝！你干吗要对我这样？

露意丝　您哭吧，您哭吧，瓦尔特！您理当对我表露您的悲哀，而没理由对我发泄您的怒气。

斐迪南　自欺欺人！这可不是悲哀的眼泪——不是那种温馨欢快地流入心灵创伤的甘露，不是那种能使滞塞的感情之轮重新转动的润滑油。只是零零落落的——冰冷冰冷的水滴——只是我爱情诀别时的战栗。（神情庄严得叫人害怕，同时把手抚在她头上）是为你的灵魂惋惜的眼泪，露意丝——是为上帝的一片好心惋惜的眼泪，他未能造出他杰作中的杰作——我觉得啊，整个宇宙都该戴上黑纱，都该为在它中间出了这样的事感到惊骇——人会堕落，乐园会失去，这是常情；可是，如果天使中间也流行起瘟疫来，那就只能让哀号声响彻整个大自然了！

露意丝　别逼我走上绝路，瓦尔特。我的灵魂足够坚强——可它必须承受一次人为的考验。瓦尔特，再说一句话，然后咱们分手。——可怕的命运扰乱了我们心灵的语言。要是我能够开口，瓦尔特，我会告诉你一些事情——我会的……可是呢，严酷的命运束缚住了我的舌头，还有我的爱情；即使你现在待我像个下贱的婊子，我也只好忍受。

斐迪南　你还舒服吗，露意丝？

露意丝　干吗问这个？

斐迪南　不这样我就替你感到遗憾，因为你将不得不带着这个谎言离开人世。

露意丝　我求您啦，瓦尔特……

斐迪南　（万分激动地）不！不！这样报复太凶狠！不，上帝保佑我！我不愿将她赶到另一个世界去——露意丝！你爱过侍卫长吗？你再不会走出这间房间了。

露意丝　您想问什么就问吧。我可什么也不再回答。（坐下）

斐迪南　（激动万分地跪在她脚下）露意丝，你爱过侍卫长吗？不等这一支蜡烛燃完——你就将站在——上帝面前！

露意丝　（惊骇得跳起来）耶稣啊！这是怎么的？……我难受得要命。（倒在椅子上）

斐迪南　已经感到难受？你们女人真是些猜不透的谜啊！你们娇弱的神经足以咬碎人类之根的罪恶；可是呢，一丁点儿砒霜就够把你们毒倒。

露意丝　毒药？毒药！我的上帝！

斐迪南　恐怕是喽。你的柠檬汁是地狱调制的。你用它冲死神干了杯。

露意丝　死！死！仁慈的主啊！柠檬汁有毒，喝了就会死！——怜悯我的灵魂吧，仁慈的上帝！

斐迪南　要紧就要紧在这儿。我也会同样地祈求他。

露意丝　可我的母亲……我的父亲……救世主啊！我可怜的绝望的父亲！难道已没救了吗？我年纪轻轻，已没救了！我现在一定要完了吗？

斐迪南　没救了，一定完了。——可是别紧张：咱俩一块儿走。

露意丝　斐迪南，你也一样！毒药，斐迪南！是你放的？上帝啊，原谅他吧！——仁慈的主啊，免除他的罪孽吧！

斐迪南　去了结你自己的账吧——我担心，情况不妙哩！

露意丝　斐迪南！斐迪南！——呵，我现在不能再沉默下去！——死亡——死亡消除了一切誓约——斐迪南，天地间没有比你更不幸的人啦！——我死得冤枉哟，斐迪南！

斐迪南　（骇异）她在说什么？——死到临头，人通常都不再撒谎的呀！

露意丝　我没撒谎——没撒谎——我一辈子仅仅就一次——唉！我怎么浑身发冷，哆嗦！——就撒过一次谎，就是在我写那封给侍卫长的信的时候。

斐迪南　哈！那封信！——赞美上帝！现在我又完全恢复了我的男子气概。

露意丝　（舌头渐渐不听使唤，手指开始痉挛）这封信——请您沉住气，准备听一句可怕的自白——是我违心地写的，句句遵照令尊大人的指示。

斐迪南　（呆若木鸡，久久地毫无生气，最后像遭了雷击似的突然倒下）

露意丝　可怕的误解呵——斐迪南——他们逼迫我——请原谅——你的露意丝宁肯死去啊！——可是我父亲——处于危险之中——他们搞的阴谋诡计。

斐迪南　（愤怒跳起）感谢上帝，我还没感到毒性发作。（拔出佩剑）

露意丝　（越来越虚弱）可悲啊！你打算干什么？他是你的父亲——

斐迪南　（怒不可遏地）凶手加上凶手的父亲！——他必须一块儿死，这样，人间的审判者才可能将怒火发泄在真正的罪人身上！（欲走出房间）

露意丝　救世主临终时会宽恕一切人——愿你和他也得到宽恕。（死去）

斐迪南　（很快转过身，正好看见她咽最后一口气，悲痛欲绝地倒在死者面前）等一等！等一等！别扔下我啊，我的天使！（抓起她的手来很快又放下）已经凉了啊，又凉又湿！她的灵魂已经离开！（又跳起来）我的露意丝的主啊！慈悲！对凶手中最卑劣的凶手发慈悲！这是她最后的祈愿呐！——连死后的她也多么美丽，多么动人！死神也受了感动，在掠过这和善的脸颊时倍加小心。——这温柔的容颜才不是毫无生气的面具哩，它抗拒住了死的侵袭。（过了一会儿）可怎么搞的？我为什么一点感觉没有？难道我青春的活力会拯救我吗？枉费心机啊！我自己不愿意！（说着抓起杯子）

最后一场

斐迪南、宰相、伍尔穆和众侍从。

宰相和他的一帮人惊惶失措地冲进房间，随后米勒和一些群众也跟进来。法庭的差役们集中站在房间最里边。

宰相　（手握着信）儿子，这是怎么啦？——我可永远不愿相信——

斐迪南　（把杯子扔在他脚下）那你就瞧吧，凶手！

宰相　（踉跄倒退。所有人都惊呆了。可怕的寂静）我的儿子啊！为什么你对我这么干？

斐迪南　（不正眼瞧他）噢，当然！我本该先听一听大政治家的意见，看这么做是否也符合他的安排？——真巧妙，真令人佩服，你们这个用嫉妒来拆散我俩同心结的阴谋，我承认！——出谋划策的肯定是位行家；遗憾的只是，被激怒的爱情不像你手中的玩偶，不会乖乖儿地听任摆布！

宰相　（目光四处搜寻）这里没有任何人为一位绝望的父亲哭泣吗？

米勒　（在后台呼喊）让我进去！看在上帝分上，让我进去！

斐迪南　这姑娘是位圣女——她该有另外的人照顾。（为米勒打开门。米勒、群众和法庭的差役一拥而入）

米勒　（惊恐万状）我的孩子！我的孩子！——（有人喊叫：“这儿服毒啦！这儿有人服毒啦！”）——我的女儿哟，你在哪里啊？

斐迪南　（把他领到宰相和露意丝的尸体之间）不是我的错。该感谢这儿这位！

米勒　（倒在女儿身边）救世主耶稣啊！

斐迪南　简单说几句，爸爸——言语对我来说已变得宝贵了……我好端端地被夺去了生命，被爸爸您！我怎样面对上帝呵，我直打哆嗦……可我从来不是坏蛋。我将遭到怎样的永劫，只好听天由命了——但愿不惩罚您！——然而我杀了人。（声音尖锐得可怕）这桩杀人罪，您该不会妄想我一个人背着去见上帝吧！这儿，我郑重地把更大、更丑恶的一半奉还给你，至于拿它怎么办，就是你自己的事了。（把父亲拽到尸体跟前）这儿，野蛮人，品尝品尝你狡诈的可怕果实吧：在这张脸上，歪歪扭扭地写着你的名字，行刑的天使将会认出来的呀！——这个形象，将在您入睡时扯下你床前的帷幔，把她冰冷的手伸向你！这个形象，将在你临终时站到你的灵魂前，挤掉你最后的祈祷！这个形象，将伫立在你的坟墓上，当你希望复活的时候——将站在上帝的旁边，当他审判你的时候！（即将昏厥，被侍从们扶住）

宰相　（手臂举向天空，恐怖地）别怪我！别怪我，上帝！——向这人索取他们的灵魂吧！（走向伍尔穆）

伍尔穆　（气愤地）向我？

宰相　该死的，向你！向你，魔鬼！——是你，是你定下的毒计。责任在你身上——我两手清白！

伍尔穆　在我身上？（一阵怪笑）有意思！有意思！这下我可知道魔鬼是怎么报恩的喽。——在我身上？愚蠢的流氓！难道他是我儿子，我是你主子不成？——责任在我身上？哈！一见这情形我骨髓全凉了！要我来负责任！——现在我算完了，可你也得一块儿完。走！走！咱们去大街小巷喊“杀人啦！杀人啦”！去把法官们都叫醒！法警，把我捆起来吧！从这里带走吧！我要揭露一些阴谋，叫听见的人浑身打冷战。（欲下）

宰相　（拦住他）他真的会吗，疯子？

伍尔穆　（拍拍宰相的肩）我会的，伙计！我会——我是疯了，真的——多亏了你嘛——现在我真要发发疯——我要和你手挽手地上断头台！——手挽手地下地狱！我真巴不得和你一道受诅咒啊，恶棍！（被带出房间）

米勒　（一直默默地把头埋在露意丝怀里，痛不欲生。这时突然站起来，将钱包掷到少校脚下）投毒犯，收回你造孽的金子吧！——你想拿它买下我的女儿是不是？（冲出房去）

斐迪南　（嗓音嘶哑）追上他！他绝望了——这钱得替他收起来——它是我可怕的报答。露意丝——露意丝——我来了——多保重！——让我在这座祭坛前离开人世吧——

宰相　（大梦初醒似的走向儿子）斐迪南——儿子！难道你不屑于再看一眼你悲惨的父亲吗？

斐迪南　（被放在露意丝身边）最后一瞥属于仁慈的上帝。

宰相　（痛苦不堪地跪在斐迪南跟前）造物和造物主全抛弃了我——再看我一眼，给我最后一点安慰，都不行吗？

斐迪南　（把手无力地伸给他）

宰相　（迅速站起身）他饶恕我了！（对其他人）现在把我抓起来吧！（下，法警们跟在他后面。幕落）

SCENE I.

MILLER-MRS. MILLER.

MILLER (walking quickly up and down the room). Once for all! The affair is becoming serious. My daughter and the baron will soon be the town-talk-my house lose its character-the president will get wind of it, and-the short and long of the matter is, I'll show the younker the door.

MRS MILLER. You did not entice him to your house-did not thrust your daughter upon him!

MILLER. Didn't entice him to my house-didn't thrust the girl upon him! Who'll believe me? I was master of my own house. I ought to have taken more care of my daughter. I should have bundled the major out at once, or have gone straight to his excellency, his papa, and disclosed all. The young baron will get off merely with a snubbing, I know that well enough, and all the blame will fall upon the fiddler.

MRS MILLER (sipping her coffee). Pooh! Nonsense! How can it fall upon you? What have people to do with you? You follow your profession, and pick up pupils wherever you can find them.

MILLER. All very fine, but please to tell me what will be the upshot of the whole affair? He can't marry the girl-marriage is out of the question, and to make her his-God help us! "Good-by t'ye!" No, no-when such a sprig of nobility has been nibbling here and there and everywhere, and has glutted himself with the devil knows what all, of course it will be a relish to my young gentleman to get a mouthful of sweet water. Take heed! Take heed! If you were dotted with eyes, and could place a sentinel for every hair of your head, he'll bamboozle her under your very nose; add one to her reckoning, take himself off, and the girl's ruined for life, left in the lurch, or, having once tasted the trade, will carry it on. (Striking his forehead.) Oh, horrible thought!

MRS MILLER. God in his mercy protect us!

MILLER. We shall want his protection. You may well say that. What other object can such a scapegrace have? The girl is handsome-well made-can show a pretty foot. How the upper story is furnished matters little. That's blinked in you women if nature has not played the niggard in other respects. Let this harum-scarum but turn over this chapter-Ho! Ho! His eyes will glisten like Rodney's when he got scent of a French frigate; then up with all sail and at her, and I don't blame him for it-flesh is flesh. I know that very well.

MRS MILLER. You should only read the beautiful billy-doux which the baron writes to your daughter. Gracious me! Why it's as clear as the sun at noonday that he loves her purely for her virtuous soul.

MILLER. That's the right strain! We beat the sack, but mean the ass's back. He who wishes to pay his respects to the flesh needs only a kind heart for a go-between. What did I myself? When we've once so far cleared the ground that the affections cry ready! Slap! The bodies follow their example, the appetites are obedient, and the silver moon kindly plays the pimp.

MRS MILLER. And then only think of the beautiful books that the major has sent us. Your daughter always prays out of them.

MILLER (whistles). Prays! You've hit the mark. The plain, simple food of nature is much too raw and indigestible for this maccaroni gentleman's stomach. It must be cooked for him artificially in the infernal pestilential pitcher of your novel-writers. Into the fire with the rubbish! I shall have the girl taking up with-God knows what all-about heavenly fooleries that will get into her blood, like Spanish flies, and scatter to the winds the handful of Christianity that cost her father so much trouble to keep together. Into the fire with them I say! The girl will take the devil's own nonsense into her head; amidst the dreams of her fool's paradise she'll not know her own home, but forget and feel ashamed of her father, the music-master; and, lastly, I shall lose a worthy, honest son-in-law who might have nestled himself so snugly into my connections.No! Damn it! (Jumps up in a passion.) I'll break the neck of it at once, and the major-yes, yes, the major! Shall be shown where the carpenter made the door. (Going.)

MRS MILLER. Be civil, Miller! How many a bright shilling have his presents——

MILLER (comes back, and goes up to her). The blood money of my daughter? To Beelzebub with thee, thou infamous bawd! Sooner will I vagabondize with my violin and fiddle for a bit of bread-sooner will I break to pieces my instrument and carry dung on the sounding-board than taste a mouthful earned by my only child at the price of her soul and future happiness. Give up your cursed coffee and snuff-taking, and there will be no need to carry your daughter's face to market. I have always had my bellyful and a good shirt to my back before this confounded scamp put his nose into my crib.

MRS MILLER. Now don't be so ready to pitch the house out of window. How you flare up all of a sudden. I only meant to say that we shouldn't offend the major, because he is the son of the president.

MILLER. There lies the root of the mischief. For that reason-for that very reason the thing must be put a stop to this very day!The president, if he is a just and upright father, will give me his thanks. You must brush up my red plush, and I will go straight to his excellency. I shall say to him-"Your excellency's son has an eye to my daughter; my daughter is not good enough to be your excellency's son's wife, but too good to be your excellency's son's strumpet, and there's an end of the matter. My name is Miller."

SCENE II.

Enter SECRETARY WORM.

MRS MILLER. Ah! Good morning, Mr. Seckertary! Have we indeed the pleasure of seeing you again?

WORM. All on my side-on my side, cousin Miller! Where a high-born cavalier's visits are received mine can be of no account whatever.

MRS MILLER. How can you think so, Mr. Seckertary? His lordship the baron, Major Ferdinand, certainly does us the honor to look in now and then; but, for all that, we don't undervalue others.

MILLER (vexed). A chair, wife, for the gentleman! Be seated, kinsman.

WORM (lays aside hat and stick, and seats himself). Well, well-and how then is my future-or past-bride? I hope she'll not be-may I not have the honor of seeing-Miss Louisa?

MRS MILLER. Thanks for inquiries, Mr. Seckertary, but my daughter is not at all proud.

MILLER (angry, jogs her with his elbow). Woman!

MRS MILLER. Sorry she can't have that honor, Mr. Seckertary. My daughter is now at mass.

WORM. I am glad to hear it-glad to hear it. I shall have in her a pious, Christian wife!

MRS MILLER (smiling in a stupidly affected manner). Yes-but, Mr.Seckertary——

MILLER (greatly incensed, pulls her ears). Woman!

MRS MILLER. If our family can serve you in any other way-with the greatest pleasure, Mr. Seckertary——

WORM (frowning angrily). In any other way? Much obliged! Much obliged!-Hm! Hm! Hm!

MRS MILLER. But, as you yourself must see, Mr. Seckertary——

MILLER (in a rage, shaking his fist at her). Woman!

MRS MILLER. Good is good, and better is better, and one does not like to stand between fortune and one's only child (with vulgar pride). You understand me, Mr. Seckertary?

WORM. Understand. Not exac-. Oh, yes. But what do you really mean?

MRS MILLER. Why-why-I only think-I mean-(coughs).Since then Providence has determined to make a great lady of my daughter——

WORM (jumping from his chair). What's that you say? what?

MILLER. Keep your seat, keep your seat, Mr. Secretary! The woman's an out-and-out fool! Where's the great lady to come from? How you show your donkey's ears by talking such stuff.

MRS MILLER. Scold as long as you will. I know what I know, and what the major said he said.

MILLER (snatches up his fiddle in anger). Will you hold your tongue?Shall I throw my fiddle at your head? What can you know? What can he have said? Take no notice of her clack, kinsman! Away with you to your kitchen! You'll not think me first cousin of a fool, and that I'm looking out so high for the girl? You'll not think that of me, Mr. Secretary?

WORM. Nor have I deserved it of you, Mr. Miller! You have always shown yourself a man of your word, and my contract to your daughter was as good as signed. I hold an office that will maintain a thrifty manager; the president befriends me; the door to advancement is open to me whenever I may choose to take advantage of it. You see that my intentions towards Miss Louisa are serious; if you have been won over by a fop of rank——

MRS MILLER. Mr. Seckertary! More respect, I beg——

MILLER. Hold your tongue, I say. Never mind her, kinsman. Things remain as they were. The answer I gave you last harvest, I repeat today. I'll not force my daughter. If you suit her, well and good;then it's for her to see that she can be happy with you. If she shakes her head-still better-be it so, I should say-then you must be content to pocket the refusal, and part in good fellowship over a bottle with her father. 'Tis the girl who is to live with you-not I.Why should I, out of sheer caprice, fasten a husband upon the girl for whom she has no inclination? That the evil one may haunt me down like a wild beast in my old age-that in every drop I drink-in every bit of bread I bite, I might swallow the bitter reproach:Thou art the villain who destroyed his child's happiness!

MRS MILLER. The short and the long of it is-I refuse my consent downright; my daughter's intended for a lofty station, and I'll go to law if my husband is going to be talked over.

MILLER. Shall I break every bone in your body, you millclack?

WORM (to MILLER). Paternal advice goes a great way with the daughter, and I hope you know me, Mr. Miller?

MILLER. Plague take you! 'Tis the girl must know you. What an old crabstick like me can see in you is just the very last thing that a dainty young girl wants. I'll tell you to a hair if you're the man for an orchestra-but a woman's heart is far too deep for a music-master. And then, to be frank with you-you know that I'm a blunt, straightforward fellow-you'll not give thank'ye for my advice. I'll persuade my daughter to no one-but from you Mr. Sec-I would dissuade her! A lover who calls upon the father for help-with permission-is not worth a pinch of snuff. If he has anything in him, he'll be ashamed to take that old-fashioned way of making his deserts known to his sweetheart. If he hasn't the courage, why he's a milksop, and no Louisas were born for the like of him. No! He must carry on his commerce with the daughter behind the father's back. He must manage so to win her heart, that she would rather wish both father and mother at Old Harry than give him up-or that she come herself, fall at her father's feet, and implore either for death on the rack, or the only one of her heart. That's the fellow for me! That I call love! And he who can't bring matters to that pitch with a petticoat may-stick the goose feather in his cap.

WORM (seizes hat and stick and hurries out of the room). Much obliged, Mr. Miller!

MILLER (going after him slowly). For what? For what? You haven't taken anything, Mr. Secretary! (Comes back.) He won't hear, and off he's gone. The very sight of that quill-driver is like poison and brimstone to me. An ugly, contraband knave, smuggled into the world by some lewd prank of the devil-with his malicious little pig's eyes, foxy hair, and nut-cracker chin, just as if Nature, enraged at such a bungled piece of goods, had seized the ugly monster by it, and flung him aside. No! Rather than throw away my daughter on a vagabond like him, she may-God forgive me!

MRS MILLER. The wretch!-But you'll be made to keep a clean tongue in your head!

MILLER. Ay, and you too, with your pestilential baron-you, too, must put my bristles up. You're never more stupid than when you have the most occasion to show a little sense. What's the meaning of all that trash about your daughter being a great lady? If it's to be cried out about the town tomorrow, you need only let that fellow get scent of it. He is one of your worthies who go sniffing about into people's houses, dispute upon everything, and, if a slip of the tongue happen to you, skurry with it straight to the prince, mistress, and minister, and then there's the devil to pay.

SCENE III.

Enter LOUISA with a book in her hand.

LOUISA. Good morning, dear father!

MILLER (affectionately). Bless thee, my Louisa! I rejoice to see thy thoughts are turned so diligently to thy Creator. Continue so, and his arm will support thee.

LOUISA. Oh! I am a great sinner, father! Was he not here, mother?

MRS MILLER. Who, my child?

LOUISA. Ah! I forgot that there are others in the world besides him-my head wanders so. Was he not here? Ferdinand?

MILLER (with melancholy, serious voice). I thought my Louisa had forgotten that name in her devotions?

LOUISA (after looking at him steadfastly for some time). I understand you, father. I feel the knife which stabs my conscience; but it comes too late. I can no longer pray, father. Heaven and Ferdinand divide my bleeding soul, and I fear-I fear-(after a pause). Yet no, no, good father. The painter is best praised when we forget him in the contemplation of his picture. When in the contemplation of his masterpiece, my delight makes me forget the Creator-is not that, father, the true praise of God?

MILLER (throws himself in displeasure on a chair). There we have it!Those are the fruits of your ungodly reading.

LOUISA (uneasy, goes to the window). Where can he be now? Ah!The high-born ladies who see him-listen to him——I am a poor forgotten maiden. (Startles at that word, and rushes to her father.)But no, no! Forgive me. I do not repine at my lot. I ask but little-to think on him-that can harm no one. Ah! That I might breathe out this little spark of life in one soft fondling zephyr to cool his check! That this fragile floweret, youth, were a violet, on which he might tread, and I die modestly beneath his feet! I ask no more, father! Can the proud, majestic day-star punish the gnat for basking in its rays?

MILLER (deeply affected, leans on the arm of his chair, and covers his face). My child, my child, with joy would I sacrifice the remnant of my days hadst thou never seen the major.

LOUISA (terrified.) How; how? What did you say? No, no! That could not be your meaning, good father. You know not that Ferdinand is mine! You know not that God created him for me, and for my delight alone! (After a pause of recollection.) The first moment that I beheld him-and the blood rushed into my glowing cheeks-every pulse beat with joy; every throb told me, every breath whispered,"'Tis he!” And my heart, recognizing the long-desired one, repeated “'Tis he!” And the whole world was as one melodious echo of my delight! Then-oh! Then was the first dawning of my soul! A thousand new sentiments arose in my bosom, as flowers arise from the earth when spring approaches. I forgot there was a world, yet never had I felt that world so dear to me! I forgot there was a God, yet never had I so loved him!

MILLER (runs to her and clasps her to his bosom). Louisa! My beloved, my admirable child! Do what thou wilt. Take all-all-my life-the baron- God is my witness-him I can never give thee! [Exit.

LOUISA. Nor would I have him now, father! Time on earth is but a stinted dewdrop in the ocean of eternity. ‘Twill swiftly glide in one delicious dream of Ferdinand. I renounce him for this life! But then, mother-then when the bounds of separation are removed-when the hated distinctions of rank no longer part us-when men will be only men-I shall bring nothing with me save my innocence! Yet often has my father told me that at the Almighty's coming riches and titles will be worthless; and that hearts alone will be beyond all price. Oh! Then shall I be rich! There, tears will be reckoned for triumphs, and purity of soul be preferred to an illustrious ancestry. Then, then, mother, shall I be noble! In what will he then be superior to the girl of his heart?

MRS. MILLER (starts from her seat). Louisa! The baron! He is jumping over the fence! Where shall I hide myself?

LOUISA (begins to tremble). Oh! Do not leave me, mother!

MRS MILLER. Mercy! What a figure I am. I am quite ashamed! I cannot let his lordship see me in this state!

[Exit.

SCENE IV.

LOUISA-FERDINAND. (He flies towards her-she falls back into her chair, pale and trembling. He remains standing before her-they look at each other for some moments in silence. A pause.)

FERDINAND. So pale, Louisa?

LOUISA (rising, and embracing him). It is nothing-nothing now that you are here-it is over.

FERDINAND (takes her hand and raises it to his lips). And does my Louisa still love me? My heart is yesterday's; is thine the same? I flew hither to see if thou wert happy, that I might return and be so too. But I find thee whelmed in sorrow!

LOUISA. Not so, my beloved, not so!

FERDINAND. Confess, Louisa! You are not happy. I see through your soul as clearly as through the transparent lustre of this brilliant. No spot can harbor here unmarked by me-no thought can cloud your brow that does not reach your lover's heart. Whence comes this grief? Tell me, I beseech you! Ah! Could I feel assured this mirror still remained unsullied, there'd seem to me no cloud in all the universe! Tell me, dear Louisa, what afflicts you?

LOUISA (looking at him with anxiety for a few moments). Ferdinand!Couldst thou but know how such discourse exalts the tradesman's daughter——

FERDINAND (surprised). What say'st thou? Tell me, girl! How camest thou by that thought? Thou art my Louisa! Who told thee thou couldst be aught else? See, false one, see, for what coldness I must chide thee! Were indeed thy whole soul absorbed by love for me, never hadst thou found time to draw comparisons! When I am with thee, my prudence is lost in one look from thine eyes: when I am absent in a dream of thee! But thou -thou canst harbor prudence in the sane breast with love! Fie on thee! Every moment bestowed on this sorrow was a robbery from affection and from me!

LOUISA (pressing his hand and shaking her head with a melancholy air). Ferdinand, you would lull my apprehensions to sleep; you would divert my eyes from the precipice into which I am falling.I can see the future! The voice of honor-your prospects, your father's anger-my nothingness. (Shuddering and suddenly drops his hands.) Ferdinand! A sword hangs over us! They would separate us!

FERDINAND (jumps up). Separate us! Whence these apprehensions, Louisa? Who can rend the bonds that bind two hearts, or separate the tones of one accord? True, I am a nobleman-but show me that my patent of nobility is older than the eternal laws of the universe-or my escutcheon more valid than the handwriting of heaven in my Louisa's eyes? “This woman is for this man?” I am son of the prime minister. For that very reason, what but love can soften the curses which my father's extortions from the country will entail upon me?

LOUISA. Oh! How I fear that father!

FERDINAND. I fear nothing-nothing but that your affection should know bounds. Let obstacles rise between us, huge as mountains, I will look upon them as a ladder by which to fly into the arms of my Louisa! The tempest of opposing fate shall but fan the flame of my affection dangers will only serve to make Louisa yet more charming. Then speak no more of terrors, my love! I myself-I will watch over thee carefully as the enchanter's dragon watches over buried gold. Trust thyself to me! Thou shalt need no other angel.I will throw myself between thee and fate- for thee receive each wound. For thee will I catch each drop distilled from the cup of joy, and bring thee in the bowl of love. (Embracing affectionately.) This arm shall support my Louisa through life. Fairer than it dismissed thee, shall heaven receive thee back, and confess with delight that love alone can give perfection to the soul.

LOUISA (disengaging herself from him, greatly agitated). No more! I beseech thee, Ferdinand! No more! Couldst thou know. Oh! Leave me, leave me! Little dost thou feel how these hopes rend my heart in pieces like fiends! (Going.)

FERDINAND (detaining her). Stay, Louisa! Stay! Why this agitation?Why those anxious looks?

LOUISA. I had forgotten these dreams, and was happy. Now-now-from this day is the tranquillity of my heart no more. Wild impetuous wishes will torment my bosom! Go! God forgive thee!Thou hast hurled a firebrand into my young peaceful heart which nothing can extinguish! (She breaks from him, and rushes from the apartment, followed by FERDINAND.)

SCENE V.

A Chamber in the PRESIDENT.'s House.

The PRESIDENT, with the grand order of the cross about his neck, and a star at his breast-SECRETARY WORM.

PRESIDENT. A serious attachment, say you? No, no, Worm; that I never can believe.

WORM. If your excellency pleases, I will bring proofs of my assertions.

PRESIDENT. That he has a fancy for the wench-flatters her-and, if you will, pretends to love her-all this is very possible-nay-excusable -but-and the daughter of a musician, you say?

WORM. Of Miller, the music-master.

PRESIDENT. Handsome? But that, of course.

WORM (with warmth). A most captivating and lovely blondine, who, without saying too much, might figure advantageously beside the greatest beauties of the court.

PRESIDENT (laughs). It's very plain, Worm, that you have an eye upon the jade yourself-I see that. But listen, Worm. That my son has a passion for the fair sex gives me hope that he will find favor with the ladies. He may make his way at court. The girl is handsome, you say; I am glad to think my son has taste. Can he deceive the silly wench by holding out honorable intentions-still better; it will show that he is shrewd enough to play the hypocrite when it serves his purpose. He may become prime minister-if he accomplishes his purpose! Admirable! That will prove to me that fortune favors him. Should the farce end with a chubby grandchild-incomparable! I will drink an extra bottle of Malaga to the prospects of my pedigree, and cheerfully pay the wench's lying-in expenses.

WORM. All I wish is that your excellency may not have to drink that bottle to drown your sorrow.

PRESIDENT (sternly). Worm! Remember that what I once believe, I believe obstinately-that I am furious when angered. I am willing to pass over as a joke this attempt to stir my blood. That you are desirous of getting rid of your rival, I can very well comprehend, and that, because you might have some difficulty in supplanting the son, you endeavor to make a cat's paw of the father, I can also understand-I am even delighted to find that you are master of such excellent qualifications in the way of roguery. Only, friend Worm, pray don't make me, too, the butt of your knavery.Understand me, have a care that your cunning trench not upon my plans!

WORM. Pardon me, your excellency! If even-as you suspect-jealousy is concerned, it is only with the eye, and not with the tongue.

PRESIDENT. It would be better to dispense with it altogether. What can it matter to you, simpleton, whether you get your coin fresh from the mint, or it comes through a banker? Console yourself with the example of our nobility. Whether known to the bridegroom or not, I can assure you that, amongst us of rank, scarcely a marriage takes place but what at least half a dozen of the guests-or the footmen-can state the geometrical area of the bridegroom's paradise.

WORM (bowing). My lord! Upon this head I confess myself a plebeian.

PRESIDENT. And, besides, you may soon have the satisfaction of turning the laugh most handsomely against your rival. At this very moment it is under consideration in the cabinet, that, upon the arrival of the new duchess, Lady Milford shall apparently be discarded, and, to complete the deception, form an alliance. You know, Worm, how greatly my influence depends upon this lady-how my mightiest prospects hang upon the passions of the prince.The duke is now seeking a partner for Lady Milford. Some one else may step in-conclude the bargain for her ladyship, win the confidence of the prince, and make himself indispensable, to my cost. Now, to retain the prince in the meshes of my family, I have resolved that my Ferdinand shall marry Lady Milford. Is that clear to you?

WORM. Quite dazzling! Your excellency has at least convinced me that, compared with the president, the father is but a novice. Should the major prove as obedient a son as you show yourself a tender father, your demand may chance to be returned with a protest.

PRESIDENT. Fortunately I have never yet had to fear opposition to my will when once I have pronounced, “It shall be so!” But now, Worm, that brings us back to our former subject! I will propose Lady Milford to my son this very day. The face which he puts upon it shall either confirm your suspicions or entirely confute them.

WORM. Pardon me, my lord! The sullen face which he most assuredly will put upon it may be placed equally to the account of the bride you offer to him as of her from whom you wish to separate him. I would beg of you a more positive test! Propose to him some perfectly unexceptionable woman. Then, if he consents, let Secretary Worm break stones on the highway for the next three years.

PRESIDENT (biting his lips). The devil!

WORM. Such is the case, you may rest assured! The mother-stupidity itself-has, in her simplicity, betrayed all to me.

PRESIDENT (pacing the room, and trying to repress his rage). Good!This very morning, then!

WORM. Yet, let me entreat your excellency not to forget that the major— is my master's son——

PRESIDENT. No harm shall come to him, Worm.

WORM. And that my service in ridding you of an unwelcome daughter-in-law——

PRESIDENT. Should be rewarded by me helping you to a wife? That too, Worm!

WORM (bowing with delight). Eternally your lordship's slave. (Going.)

PRESIDENT (threatening him). As to what I have confided to you, Worm! If you dare but to whisper a syllable——

WORM (laughs). Then your excellency will no doubt expose my forgeries!

[Exit.

PRESIDENT. Yes, yes, you are safe enough! I hold you in the fetters of your own knavery, like a trout on the hook!

Enter SERVANT.

SERVANT. Marshal Kalb——

PRESIDENT. The very man I wished to see. Introduce him.

[Exit SERVANT.

SCENE VI.

MARSHAL KALB, in a rich but tasteless court-dress, with Chamberlain's keys, two watches, sword, three-cornered hat, and hair dressed a la Herisson. He bustles up to the PRESIDENT, and diffuses a strong scent of musk through the whole theatre-PRESIDENT.

MARSHAL. Ah! Good morning, my dear baron! Quite delighted to see you again-pray forgive my not having paid my respects to you at an earlier hour-the most pressing business-the duke's bill of fare-invitation cards-arrangements for the sledge party today-ah!-besides it was necessary for me to be at the levee, to inform his highness of the state of the weather.

PRESIDENT. True, marshal! Such weighty concerns were not to be neglected!

MARSHAL. Then a rascally tailor, too, kept me waiting for him!PRESIDENT. And yet ready to the moment?

MARSHAL. Nor is that all! One misfortune follows at the heels of the other today! Only hear me!

PRESIDENT (absent). Can it be possible?

MARSHAL. Just listen! Scarce had I quitted my carriage, when the horses became restive, and began to plunge and rear-only imagine!-splashed my breeches all over with mud! What was to be done? Fancy, my dear baron, just fancy yourself for a moment in my predicament! There I stood! The hour was late! A day's journey to return-yet to appear before his highness in this-good heavens! What did I bethink me of? I pretended to faint! They bundle me into my carriage! I drive home like mad- change my dress-hasten back-and only think!-In spite of all this I was the first person in the antechamber! What say you to that?

PRESIDENT. A most admirable impromptu of mortal wit-but tell me, Kalb, did you speak to the duke?

MARSHAL (importantly). Full twenty minutes and a half.

PRESIDENT. Indeed? Then doubtless you have important news to impart to me?

MARSHAL (seriously, after a pause of reflection). His highness wears a Merde d'Oye beaver today.

PRESIDENT. God bless me!-and yet, marshal, I have even greater news to tell you. Lady Milford will soon become my daughter-in-law. That, I think will be new to you?

MARSHAL. Is it possible! And is it already agreed upon?

PRESIDENT. It is settled, marshal-and you would oblige me by forthwith waiting upon her ladyship, and preparing her to receive Ferdinand's visit. You have full liberty, also, to circulate the news of my son's approaching nuptials.

MARSHAL. My dear friend! With consummate pleasure! What can I desire more? I fly to the baroness this moment. Adieu! (Embracing him.) In less than three-quarters of an hour it shall be known throughout the town. [Skips off.

PRESIDENT (smiling contemptuously). How can people say that such creatures are of no use in the world? Now, then, Master Ferdinand must either consent or give the whole town the lie. (Rings-WORM enters.) Send my son hither. (WORM retires; the PRESIDENT walks up and down, full of thought.)

SCENE VII.

PRESIDENT-FERDINAND.

FERDINAND. In obedience to your commands, sir——

PRESIDENT. Ay, if I desire the presence of my son, I must command it- Ferdinand, I have observed you for some time past, and find no longer that open vivacity of youth which once so delighted me. An unusual sorrow broods upon your features; you shun your father; you shun society. For shame, Ferdinand! At your age a thousand irregularities are easier forgiven than one instant of idle melancholy. Leave this to me, my son! Leave the care of your future happiness to my direction, and study only to co-operate with my designs-come, Ferdinand, embrace me!

FERDINAND. You are most gracious today, father!

PRESIDENT. “Today,” you rogue? And your “today” with such a vinegar look? (Seriously.) Ferdinand! For whose sake have I trod that dangerous path which leads to the affections of the prince? For whose sake have I forever destroyed my peace with Heaven and my conscience? Hear me, Ferdinand-I am speaking to my son.For whom have I paved the way by the removal of my predecessor?A deed which the more deeply gores my inward feelings the more carefully I conceal the dagger from the world! Tell me, Ferdinand, for whose sake have I done all this?

FERDINAND (recoiling with horror). Surely not for mine, father, not for mine? Surely not on me can fall the bloody reflection of this murder? By my Almighty Maker, it were better never to have been born than to be the pretext for such a crime!

PRESIDENT. What sayest thou? How? But I will attribute these strange notions to thy romantic brain, Ferdinand; let me not lose my temper- ungrateful boy! Thus dost thou repay me for my sleepless nights? Thus for my restless anxiety to promote thy good? Thus for the never-dying scorpion of my conscience? Upon me must fall the burden of responsibility; upon me the curse, the thunderbolt of the Judge. Thou receivest thy fortune from another's hand-the crime is not attached to the inheritance.

FERDINAND (extending his right hand towards heaven). Here I solemnly abjure an inheritance which must ever remind me of a parent's guilt!

PRESIDENT. Hear me, sirrah! And do not incense me! Were you left to your own direction you would crawl through life in the dust.

FERDINAND. Oh! Better, father, far, far better, than to crawl about a throne!

PRESIDENT (repressing his anger). So! Then compulsion must make you sensible of your good fortune! To that point, which, with the utmost striving a thousand others fail to reach, you have been exalted in your very sleep. At twelve you received a commission;at twenty a command. I have succeeded in obtaining for you the duke's patronage. He bids you lay aside your uniform, and share with me his favor and his confidence. He spoke of titles-embassies-of honors bestowed but upon few. A glorious prospect spreads itself before you! The direct path to the place next the throne lies open to you! Nay, to the throne itself, if the actual power of ruling is equivalent to the mere symbol. Does not that idea awaken your ambition?

FERDINAND. No! My ideas of greatness and happiness differ widely from yours. Your happiness is but seldom known, except by the misery of others. Envy, terror, hatred are the melancholy mirrors in which the smiles of princes are reflected. Tears, curses, and the wailings of despair, the horrid banquet that feasts your supposed elect of fortune; intoxicated with these they rush headlong into eternity, staggering to the throne of judgment. My ideas of happiness teach me to look for its fountain in myself! All my wishes lie centered in my heart!

PRESIDENT. Masterly! Inimitable! Admirable! The first schooling I have received these thirty years! Pity that the brain at fifty should be so dull at learning! But-that such talent may not rust, I will place one by your side on whom you can practise your harlequinade follies at pleasure. You will resolve-resolve this very day-to take a wife.

FERDINAND (starting back amazed). Father!

PRESIDENT. Answer me not. I have made proposals, in your name, to Lady Milford. You will instantly determine upon going to her, and declaring yourself her bridegroom.

FERDINAND. Lady Milford! Father?

PRESIDENT. I presume she is not unknown to you!

FERDINAND (passionately). To what brothel is she unknown through the dukedom? But pardon me, dearest father! It is ridiculous to imagine that your proposal can be serious. Would you call yourself father of that infamous son who married a licensed prostitute?

PRESIDENT. Nay, more. I would ask her hand myself, if she would take a man of fifty. Would not you call yourself that infamous father's son?

FERDINAND. No! As God lives! That would I not!

PRESIDENT. An audacity, by my honor! Which I pardon for its excessive singularity.

FERDINAND. I entreat you, father, release me from a demand which would render it insupportable to call myself your son.

PRESIDENT. Are you distracted, boy? What reasonable man would not thirst after a distinction which makes him, as one of a trio, the equal and co-partner of his sovereign?

FERDINAND. You are quite an enigma to me, father! “A distinction,”do you call it? A distinction to share that with a prince, wherein he places himself on a level with the meanest of his subjects? (The PRESIDENT bursts into a loud laugh.) You may scoff-I must submit to it in a father. With what countenance should I support the gaze of the meanest laborer, who at least receives an undivided person as the portion of his bride? With what countenance should I present myself before the world? Before the prince? Nay, before the harlot herself, who seeks to wash out in my shame the brandmarks of her honor?

PRESIDENT. Where in the world couldst thou collect such notions, boy?

FERDINAND. I implore you, father, by heaven and earth! By thus sacrificing your only son you can never become so happy as you will make him miserable! If my life can be a step to your advancement, dispose of it. My life you gave me; and I will never hesitate a moment to sacrifice it wholly to your welfare. But my honor, father! If you deprive me of this, the giving me life was a mere trick of wanton cruelty, and I must equally curse the parent and the pander.

PRESIDENT (tapping him on the shoulder in a friendly manner). That's as it should be, my dear boy! Now I see that you are a brave and noble fellow, and worthy of the first woman in the dukedom. You shall have her. This very day you shall be affianced to the Countess of Ostheim.

FERDINAND (in new disorder). Is this, then, destined to be the hour of my destruction?

PRESIDENT (regarding him with an eye of suspicion). In this union, I imagine, you can have no objection on the score of honor?

FERDINAND. None, father, none whatever. Frederica of Ostheim would make any other the happiest of men. (Aside, in the greatest agitation.) His kindness rends in pieces that remnant of my heart which his cruelty left unwounded.

PRESIDENT (his eye still fixed upon him). I expect your gratitude, Ferdinand!

FERDINAND (rushes towards him and kisses his hands). Father, your goodness awakens every spark of sentiment in my bosom. Father!Receive my warmest thanks for your kind intentions. Your choice is unexceptionable! But I cannot-I dare not-pity me, father, I never can love the countess.

PRESIDENT (draws back). Ha! Ha! Now I've caught you, young gentleman! The cunning fox has tumbled into the trap. Oh, you artful hypocrite! It was not then honor which made you refuse Lady Milford? It was not the woman, but the nuptials which alarmed you! (FERDINAND stands petrified for a moment; then recovers himself and prepares to quit the chamber hastily.) Whither now? Stay, sir. Is this the respect due to your father? (FERDINAND returns slowly.) Her ladyship expects you. The duke has my promise! Both court and city believe all is settled. If thou makest me appear a liar, boy! If, before the duke-the lady-the court and city-thou shouldst make me appear a liar!-tremble, boy!-or when I have gained information of certain circumstances-how now? Why does the color so suddenly forsake your cheeks?

FERDINAND (pale and trembling). How? What? Nothing-it is nothing, my father!

PRESIDENT (casting upon him a dreadful look). Should there be cause.If I should discover the source whence this obstinacy proceeds!Boy! Boy! The very suspicion drives me distracted! Leave me this moment. 'Tis now the hour of parade. As soon as the word is given, go thou to her ladyship. At my nod a dukedom trembles; we shall see whether a disobedient son dare dispute my will! (Going, returns.) Remember, sir! Fail not to wait on Lady Milford, or dread my anger!

[Exit.

FERDINAND (awakens, as if from a dream). Is he gone? Was that a father's voice? Yes, I will go-I will see her-I will say such things to her-hold such a mirror before her eyes. Then, base woman, shouldst thou still demand my hand-in the presence of the assembled nobles, the military, and the people-gird thyself with all the pride of thy native Britain-I, a German youth, will spurn thee!

[Exit.

SCENE I.

A room in LADY MILFORD's house. On the right of the stage stands a sofa, on the left a pianoforte.

LADY MILFORD, in a loose but elegant negligee, is running her hand over the keys of the pianoforte as SOPHY advances from the window.

SOPHY. The parade is over, and the officers are separating, but I see no signs of the major.

LADY MILFORD (rises and walks up and down the room in visible agitation). I know not what ails me today, Sophy! I never felt so before-you say you do not see him! It is evident enough that he is by no means impatient for this meeting-my heart feels oppressed as if by some heavy crime. Go! Sophy, order the most spirited horse in the stable to be saddled for me-I must away into the open air where I may look on the blue sky and hear the busy hum of man. I must dispel this gloominess by change and motion.

SOPHY. If you feel out of spirits, my lady, why not invite company!Let the prince give an entertainment here, or have the ombre table brought to you. If the prince and all his court were at my beck and call I would let no whim or fancy trouble me!

LADY MILFORD (throwing herself on the couch). Pray, spare me.I would gladly give a jewel in exchange for every hour's respite from the infliction of such company! I always have my rooms tapestried with these creatures! Narrow-minded, miserable beings, who are quite shocked if by chance a candid and heartfelt word should escape one's lips! And stand aghast as though they saw an apparition; slaves, moved by a single puppet-wire, which I can govern as easily as the threads of my embroidery! What can I have in common with such insipid wretches, whose souls, like their watches, are regulated by machinery? What pleasure can I have in the society of people whose answers to my questions I know beforehand? How can I hold communion with men who dare not venture on an opinion of their own lest it should differ from mine!Away with them-I care not to ride a horse that has not spirit enough to champ the bit! (Goes to the window.)

SOPHY. But surely, my lady, you except the prince, the handsomest, the wittiest, and the most gallant man in all his duchy.

LADY MILFORD (returning). Yes, in his duchy, that was well said-and it is only a royal duchy, Sophy, that could in the least excuse my weakness. You say the world envies me! Poor thing! It should rather pity me! Believe me, of all who drink of the streams of royal bounty there is none more miserable than the sovereign's favorite, for he who is great and mighty in the eyes of others comes to her but as the humble suppliant! It is true that by the talisman of his greatness he can realize every wish of my heart as readily as the magician calls forth the fairy palace from the depths of the earth!He can place the luxuries of both Indies upon my table, turn the barren wilderness to a paradise, can bid the broad rivers of his land play in triumphal arches over my path, or expend all the hard-earned gains of his subjects in a single feu-de-joie to my honor. But can he school his heart to respond to one great or ardent emotion?Can he extort one noble thought from his weak and indigent brain? Alas! My heart is thirsting amid all this ocean of splendor;what avail, then, a thousand virtuous sentiments when I am only permitted to indulge in the pleasures of the senses.

SOFHY (regarding her with surprise). Dear lady, you amaze me! How long is it since I entered your service?

LADY MILFORD. Do you ask because this is the first day on which you have learnt to know me? I have sold my honor to the prince, it is true, but my heart is still my own-a heart, dear Sophy, which even yet may be worth the acceptance of an honorable man-a heart over which the pestilential blast of courtly corruption has passed as the breath which for a moment dims the mirror's lustre. Believe me my spirit would long since have revolted against this miserable thraldom could my ambition have submitted to see another advanced to my place.

SOPHY. And could a heart like yours so readily surrender itself to mere ambition?

LADY MILFORD (with energy). Has it not already been avenged?Nay, is it not even at this very moment making me pay a heavy atonement? (with emphasis laying her hand on SOPHY's shoulder)Believe me, Sophy, woman has but to choose between ruling and serving, but the utmost joy of power is a worthless possession if the mightier joy of being slave to the man we love be denied us.

SOPHY. A truth, dear lady, which I could least of all have expected to hear from your lips!

LADY MILFORD. And wherefore, Sophy? Does not woman show, by her childish mode of swaying the sceptre of power, that she is only fit to go in leading-strings! Have not my fickle humors-my eager pursuit of wild dissipation-betrayed to you that I sought in these to stifle the still wilder throbbings of my heart?

SOPHY (starting back with surprise). This from you, my lady?

LADY MILFORD (continuing with increasing energy). Appease these throbbings. Give me the man in whom my thoughts are centered-the man I adore, without whom life were worse than death. Let me but hear from his lips that the tears of love with which my eyes are bedewed outvie the gems that sparkle in my hair, and I will throw at the feet of the prince his heart and his dukedom, and flee to the uttermost parts of the earth with the man of my love!

SOPHY (looking at her in alarm). Heavens! My lady! Control your emotion——

LADY MILFORD (in surprise). You change color! To what have I given utterance? Yet, since I have said thus much, let me say still more-let my confidence be a pledge of your fidelity-I will tell you all.

SOPHY (looking anxiously around). I fear my lady-I dread it-I have heard enough!

LADY MILFORD. This alliance with the major-you, like the rest of the world, believe to be the result of a court intrigue-Sophy, blush not-be not ashamed of me-it is the work of-my love!

SOPHY. Heavens! As I suspected!

LADY MILFORD. Yes, Sophy, they are all deceived. The weak prince-the diplomatic baron-the silly marshal-each and all of these are firmly convinced that this marriage is a most infallible means of preserving me to the prince, and of uniting us still more firmly! But this will prove the very means of separating us forever, and bursting asunder these execrable bonds. The cheater cheated-outwitted by a weak woman. Ye yourselves are leading me to the man of my heart-this was all I sought. Let him but once be mine-be but mine-then, oh, then, a long farewell to all this despicable pomp!

SCENE II.

An old valet of the DUKE's, with a casket of jewels. The former.

VALET. His serene highness begs your ladyship's acceptance of these jewels as a nuptial present. They have just arrived from Venice.

LADY MILFORD (opens the casket and starts back in astonishment). What did these jewels cost the duke?

VALET. Nothing!

LADY MILFORD. Nothing! Are you beside yourself? (retreating a step or two.) Old man! You fix on me a look as though you would pierce me through. Did you say these precious jewels cost nothing?

VALET. Yesterday seven thousand children of the land left their homes to go to America-they pay for all.

LADY MILFORD (sets the casket suddenly down, and paces up and down the room; after a pause, to the VALET). What distresses you, old man? You are weeping!

VALET (wiping his eyes, and trembling violently). Yes, for these jewels.My two sons are among the number.

LADY MILFORD. But they went not by compulsion?

VALET (laughing bitterly). Oh! Dear no! They were all volunteers!There were certainly some few forward lads who pushed to the front of the ranks and inquired of the colonel at what price the prince sold his subjects per yoke, upon which our gracious ruler ordered the regiments to be marched to the parade, and the malcontents to be shot. We heard the report of the muskets, and saw brains and blood spurting about us, while the whole band shouted-“Hurrah for America!”

LADY MILFORD. And I heard nothing of all this! Saw nothing!

VALET. No, most gracious lady, because you rode off to the bear-hunt with his highness just at the moment the drum was beating for the march. 'Tis a pity your ladyship missed the pleasure of the sight-here, crying children might be seen following their wretched father-there, a mother distracted with grief was rushing forward to throw her tender infant among the bristling bayonets-here, a bride and bridegroom were separated with the sabre's stroke-and there, graybeards were seen to stand in despair, and fling their very crutches after their sons in the New World -and, in the midst of all this, the drums were beating loudly, that the prayers and lamentations might not reach the Almighty ear.

LADY MILFORD (rising in violent emotion). Away with these jewels-their rays pierce my bosom like the flames of hell.Moderate your grief, old man. Your children shall be restored to you. You shall again clasp them to your bosom.

VALET (with warmth). Yes, heaven knows! We shall meet again! As they passed the city gates they turned round and cried aloud: “God bless our wives and children-long life to our gracious sovereign.At the day of judgment we shall all meet again!”

LADY MILFORD (walks up and down the room in great agitation).Horrible! Most horrible!-And they would persuade me that I had dried up all the tears in the land. Now, indeed, my eyes are fearfully opened! Go-tell the prince that I will thank him in person! (As the valet is going she drops the purse into his hat.) And take this as a recompense for the truth you have revealed to me.

VALET (throws the purse with contempt on the table). Keep it, with your other treasures. [Exit.

LADY MILFORD (looking after him in astonishment). Sophy, follow him, and inquire his name. His sons shall be restored to him.(SOPHY goes. LADY MILFORD becomes absorbed in thought.Pause. Then to SOPHY as she returns.) Was there not a report that some town on the frontier had been destroyed by fire, and four hundred families reduced to beggary? (She rings.)

SOPHY. What has made your ladyship just think of that? Yes-such was certainly the fact, and most of these poor creatures are either compelled to serve their creditors as bondsmen, or are dragging out their miserable days in the depths of the royal silver mines.

Enter a SERVANT. What are your ladyship's commands?

LADY MILFORD (giving him the case of jewels). Carry this to my treasurer without delay. Let the jewels be sold and the money distributed among the four hundred families who were ruined by the fire.

SOPHY. Consider, my lady, the risk you run of displeasing his highness.

LADY MILFORD (with dignity). Should I encircle my brows with the curses of his subjects? (Makes a sign to the servant, who goes away with the jewel case.) Wouldst thou have me dragged to the earth by the dreadful weight of the tears of misery? Nay! Sophy, it is better far to wear false jewels on the brow, and to have the consciousness of a good deed within the breast!

SOPHY. But diamonds of such value! Why not rather give some that are less precious? Truly, my lady, it is an unpardonable act.

LADY MILFORD. Foolish girl! For this deed more brilliants and pearls will flow for me in one moment than kings ever wore in their richest diadems! Ay, and infinitely more beautiful!

SERVANT (enters.) Major von Walter!

SOPHY (running hastily to the help of LADY MILFORD, who seems fainting). Heavens, my lady, you change color!

LADY MILFORD. The first man who ever made me tremble. (To the SERVANT.) I am not well-but stay-what said the major?-how?O Sophy! I look sadly ill, do I not?

SOPHY. I entreat you, my lady, compose yourself.

SERVANT. Is it your ladyship's wish that I should deny you to the major?

LADY MILFORD (hesitating). Tell him-I shall be happy to see him. (Exit SERVANT.) What shall I say to him, Sophy? how shall I receive him? I will be silent-alas! I fear he will despise my weakness. He will-ah, me! what sad forebodings oppress my heart! You are going Sophy! stay, yet-no, no-he comes-yes, stay, stay with me——

SOPHY. Collect yourself, my lady, the major——

SCENE III.

FERDINAND VON WALTER. The former.

FERDINAND (with a slight bow). I hope I do not interrupt your ladyship?

LADY MILFORD (with visible emotion). Not at all, baron-not in the least.

FERDINAND. I wait on your ladyship, at the command of my father.

LADY MILFORD. Therein I am his debtor.

FERDINAND. And I am charged to announce to you that our marriage is determined on. Thus far I fulfil the commission of my father.

LADY MILFORD (changing color and trembling). And not of your own heart?

FERDINAND. Ministers and panders have no concern with hearts.

LADY MILFORD (almost speechless with emotion). And you yourself-have you nothing to add?

FERDINAND (looking at SOPHY). Much! My lady, much!

LADY MILFORD (motions to SOPHY to withdraw). May I beg you to take a seat by my side?

FERDINAND. I will be brief, lady.

LADY MILFORD. Well!

FERDINAND. I am a man of honor!

LADY MILFORD. Whose worth I know how to appreciate.

FERDINAND. I am of noble birth!

LADY MILFORD. Noble as any in the land!

FERDINAND. A soldier!

LADY MILFORD (in a soft, affectionate manner). Thus far you have only enumerated advantages which you share in common with many others. Why are you so silent regarding those noble qualities which are peculiarly your own?

FERDINAND (coldly). Here they would be out of place.

LADY MILFORD (with increasing agitation). In what light am I to understand this prelude?

FERDINAND (slowly, and with emphasis). As the protest of the voice of honor-should you think proper to enforce the possession of my hand!

LADY MILFORD (starting with indignation). Major von Walter! What language is this?

FERDINAND (calmly). The language of my heart-of my unspotted name-and of this true sword.

LADY MILFORD. Your sword was given to you by the prince.

FERDINAND. 'Twas the state which gave it, by the hands of the prince. God bestowed on me an honest heart. My nobility is derived from a line of ancestry extending through centuries.

LADY MILFORD. But the authority of the prince——

FERDINAND (with warmth). Can he subvert the laws of humanity, or stamp glory on our actions as easily as he stamps value on the coin of his realm? He himself is not raised above the laws of honor, although he may stifle its whispers with gold-and shroud his infamy in robes of ermine! But enough of this, lady!-It is too late now to talk of blasted prospects-or of the desecration of ancestry-or of that nice sense of honor-girded on with my sword-or of the world's opinion. All these I am ready to trample under foot as soon as you have proved to me that the reward is not inferior to the sacrifice.

LADY MILFORD (in extreme distress turning away). Major! I have not deserved this!

FERDINAND (taking her hand). Pardon me, lady-we are without witnesses. The circumstance which brings us together today-and only today-justifies me, nay, compels me, to reveal to you my most secret feelings. I cannot comprehend, lady, how a being gifted with so much beauty and spirit-qualities which a man cannot fail to admire-could throw herself away on a prince incapable of valuing aught beyond her mere person-and yet not feel some visitings of shame, when she steps forth to offer her heart to a man of honor!

LADY MILFORD (looking at him with an air of pride). Say on, sir, without reserve.

FERDINAND. You call yourself an Englishwoman-pardon me, lady, I can hardly believe you. The free-born daughter of the freest people under heaven-a people too proud to imitate even foreign virtues-would surely never have sold herself to foreign vices! It is not possible, lady, that you should be a native of Britain, unless indeed your heart be as much below as the sons of Britannia vaunt theirs to be above all others!

LADY MILFORD. Have you done, sir?

FERDINAND. Womanly vanity-passions-temperament-a natural appetite for pleasure-all these might, perhaps, be pleaded in extenuation-for virtue often survives honor-and many who once trod the paths of infamy have subsequently reconciled themselves to society by the performance of noble deeds, and have thus thrown a halo of glory round their evil doings-but if this were so, whence comes the monstrous extortion that now oppresses the people with a weight never before known? This I would ask in the name of my fatherland-and now, lady, I have done!

LADY MILFORD (with gentleness and dignity). This is the first time, Baron von Walter, that words such as these have been addressed to me-and you are the only man to whom I would in return have vouchsafed an answer. Your rejection of my hand commands my esteem. Your invectives against my heart have my full forgiveness, for I will not believe you sincere, since he who dares hold such language to a woman, that could ruin him in an instant-must either believe that she possesses a great and noble heart- or must be the most desperate of madmen. That you ascribe the misery of this land to me may He forgive, before whose throne you, and I, and the prince shall one day meet! But, as in my person you have insulted the daughter of Britain, so in vindication of my country's honor you must hear my exculpation.

FERDINAND (leaning on his sword). Lady, I listen with interest.

LADY MILFORD. Hear, then, that which I have never yet breathed to mortal, and which none but yourself will ever learn from my lips. I am not the low adventurer you suppose me, sir! Nay! Did I listen to the voice of pride, I might even boast myself to be of royal birth; I am descended from the unhappy Thomas Norfolk, who paid the penalty of his adherence to the cause of Mary, Queen of Scots, by a bloody death on the scaffold. My father, who, as royal chamberlain, had once enjoyed his sovereign's confidence, was accused of maintaining treasonable relations with France, and was condemned and executed by a decree of the Parliament of Great Britain. Our estates were confiscated, and our family banished from their native soil. My mother died on the day of my father's execution, and I-then a girl of fourteen-fled to Germany with one faithful attendant. A casket of jewels, and this crucifix, placed in my bosom by my dying mother, were all my fortune![FERDINAND, absorbed in thought, surveys LADY MILFORD with looks of compassion and sympathy.

LADY MILFORD (continuing with increased emotion). Without a name-without protection or property-a foreigner and an orphan, I reached Hamburg. I had learnt nothing but a little French, and to run my fingers over the embroidery frame, or the keys of my harpsichord. But, though I was ignorant of all useful arts, I had learnt full well to feast off gold and silver, to sleep beneath silken hangings, to bid attendant pages obey my voice, and to listen to the honeyed words of flattery and adulation. Six years passed away in sorrow and in sadness-the remnant of my scanty means was fast melting away-my old and faithful nurse was no more-and-and then it was that fate brought your sovereign to Hamburg. I was walking beside the shores of the Elbe, wondering, as I gazed on its waters, whether they or my sorrows were the deeper, when the duke crossed my path. He followed me, traced me to my humble abode, and, casting himself at my feet, vowed that he loved me.(She pauses, and, after struggling with her emotion, continues in a voice choked by tears.) All the images of my happy childhood were revived in hues of delusive brightness-while the future lowered before me black as the grave. My heart panted for communion with another-and I sank into the arms opened to receive me! (Turning away.) And now you condemn me!

FERDINAND (greatly agitated, follows her and leads her back). Lady!Heavens! What do I hear! What have I done? The guilt of my conduct is unveiled in all its deformity! It is impossible you should forgive me.

LADY MILFORD (endeavoring to overcome her emotion). Hear me on! The prince, it is true, overcame my unprotected youth, but the blood of the Howards still glowed within my veins, and never ceased to reproach me; that I, the descendant of royal ancestors, should stoop to be a prince's paramour! Pride and destiny still contended in my bosom, when the duke brought me hither, where SCENEs the most revolting burst upon my sight! The voluptuousness of the great is an insatiable hyena-the craving of whose appetite demands perpetual victims. Fearfully had it laid this country waste separating bridegroom and bride-and tearing asunder even the holy bonds of marriage. Here it had destroyed the tranquil happiness of a whole family-there the blighting pest had seized on a young and inexperienced heart, and expiring victims called down bitter imprecations on the heads of the undoers. It was then that I stepped forth between the lamb and the tiger, and, in a moment of dalliance, extorted from the duke his royal promise that this revolting licentiousness should cease.

FERDINAND (pacing the room in violent agitation). No more, lady! No more!

LADY MILFORD. This gloomy period was succeeded by one still more gloomy. The court swarmed with French and Italian adventurers-the royal sceptre became the plaything of Parisian harlots, and the people writhed and bled beneath their capricious rule. Each had her day. I saw them sink before me, one by one, for I was the most skilful coquette of all! It was then that I seized and wielded the tyrant's sceptre whilst he slumbered voluptuously in my embrace-then, Walter, thy country, for the first time, felt the hand of humanity, and reposed in confidence on my bosom. (A pause, during which she gazes upon him with tenderness.) Oh! 'That the man, by whom, of all others, I least wish to be misunderstood, should compel me to turn braggart and parade my unobtrusive virtues to the glare of admiration! Walter, I have burst open the doors of prisons-I have cancelled death-warrants and shortened many a frightful eternity upon the galleys. Into wounds beyond my power to heal I have at least poured soothing balsam. I have hurled mighty villains to the earth, and oft with the tears of a harlot saved the cause of innocence from impending ruin. Ah! Young man, how sweet were then my feelings! How proudly did these actions teach my heart to support the reproaches of my noble blood! And now comes the man who alone can repay me for all that I have suffered-the man, whom perhaps my relenting destiny created as a compensation for former sorrows-the man, whom with ardent affection, I already clasped in my dreams.

FERDINAND (interrupting her). Hold, lady, hold! You exceed the bounds of our conference! You undertook to clear yourself from reproach, and you make me a criminal! Spare me, I beseech you!Spare a heart already overwhelmed by confusion and remorse!

LADY MILFORD (grasping his hand). You must hear me, Walter!Hear me now or never. Long enough has the heroine sustained me; now you must feel the whole weight of these tears! Mark me, Walter! Should an unfortunate-impetuously, irresistibly attracted towards you-clasp you to her bosom full of unutterable, inextinguishable love-should this unfortunate-bowed down with the consciousness of shame-disgusted with vicious pleasures-heroically exalted by the inspiration of virtue-throw herself-thus into your arms (embracing him in an eager and supplicating manner); should she do this, and you still pronounce the freezing word “Honor!” Should she pray that through you she might be saved-that through you she might be restored to her hopes of heaven! (Turning away her head, and speaking in a hollow, faltering voice.) Or should she, her prayer refused, listen to the voice of despair, and to escape from your image plunge herself into yet more fearful depths of infamy and vice——

FERDINAND (breaking from her in great emotion). No, by heaven!This is more than I can endure! Lady, I am compelled-Heaven and earth compels me-to make the honest avowal of my sentiments and situation.

LADY MILFORD (hastening from him). Oh! Not now! By all that is holy I entreat you-spare me in this dreadful moment when my lacerated heart bleeds from a thousand wounds. Be your decision life or death-I dare not-I will not hear it!

FERDINAND. I entreat you, lady! I insist! What I have to say will mitigate my offence, and warmly plead your forgiveness for the past. I have been deceived in you, lady. I expected-nay, I wished to find you deserving my contempt. I came determined to insult you, and to make myself the object of your hate. Happy would it have been for us both had my purpose succeeded! (He pauses; then proceeds in a gentle and faltering voice.) Lady, I love!-I love a maid of humble birth-Louisa Miller is her name, the daughter of a music-master. (LADY MILFORD turns away pale and greatly agitated.) I know into what an abyss I plunge myself; but, though prudence bids me conceal my passion, honor overpowers its precepts. I am the criminal-I first destroyed the golden calm of Louisa's innocence-I lulled her heart with aspiring hopes, and surrendered it, like a betrayer, a prey to the wildest of passions.You will bid me remember my rank-my birth-my father-schemes of aggrandisement. But in vain-I love! My hopes become more fervent as the breach widens between nature and the mere conventions of society- between my resolution and worldly prejudices! We shall see whether love or interest is victorious.(LADY MILFORD during this has retired to the extreme end of the apartment, and covers her face with both hands. FERDINAND approaches her.) Have you aught to answer, lady?

LADY MILFORD (in a tone of intense suffering). Nothing! Nothing!But that you destroy yourself and me-and, with us yet a third.

FERDINAND. A third?

LADY MILFORD. Never can you marry Louisa; never can you be happy with me. We shall all be the victims of your father's rashness. I can never hope to possess the heart of a husband who has been forced to give me his hand.

FERDINAND. Forced, lady? Forced? And yet given? Will you enforce a hand without a heart? Will you tear from a maiden a man who is the whole world to her? Will you tear a maiden from a man who has centered all his hopes of happiness on her alone? Will you do this, lady? You who but a moment before were the lofty, noble-minded daughter of Britain?

LADY MILFORD. I will because I must! (earnestly and firmly). My passions, Walter, overcome my tenderness for you. My honor has no alternative. Our union is the talk of the whole city. Every eye, every shaft of ridicule is bent against me. 'Twere a stain which time could never efface should a subject of the prince reject my hand! Appease your father if you have the power! Defend yourself as you best may! My resolution is taken. The mine is fired and I abide the issue.

[Exit. FERDINAND remains in speechless astonishment for some moments; then rushes wildly out.

SCENE IV.

Miller's House. MILLER meeting LOUISA and MRS. MILLER.

MILLER. Ay! Ay! I told you how it would be!

LOUISA (hastening to him with anxiety). What, father? What?

MILLER (running up and down the room). My cloak, there. Quick, quick! I must be beforehand with him. My cloak, I say! Yes, yes!This was just what I expected!

LOUISA. For God's sake, father! Tell me?

MRS. MILLER. What is the matter, Miller? What alarms you?

MILLER (throwing down his wig). Let that go to the friezer. What is the matter, indeed? And my beard, too, is nearly half an inch long.What's the matter? What do you think, you old carrion. The devil has broke loose, and you may look out for squalls.

MRS. MILLER. There, now, that's just the way! When anything goes wrong it is always my fault.

MILLER. Your fault? Yes, you brimstone fagot! And whose else should it be? This very morning when you were holding forth about that confounded major, did I not say then what would be the consequence? That knave, Worm, has blabbed.

MRS. MILLER. Gracious heavens! But how do you know?

MILLER. How do I know? Look yonder! A messenger of the minister is already at the door inquiring for the fiddler.

LOUISA (turning pale, and sitting down). Oh! God! I am in agony!

MILLER. And you, too, with that languishing air? (laughs bitterly).But, right! Right! There is an old saying that where the devil keeps a breeding-cage he is sure to hatch a handsome daughter.

MRS. MILLER. But how do you know that Louisa is in question? You may have been recommended to the duke; he may want you in his orchestra.

MILLER (jumping up, and seizing his fiddlestick). May the sulphurous rain of hell consume thee! Orchestra, indeed! Ay, where you, you old procuress, shall howl the treble whilst my smarting back groans the base (Throwing himself upon a chair.) Oh! God in heaven!

LOUISA (sinks on the sofa, pale as death). Father! Mother! Oh! My heart sinks within me.

MILLER (starting up with anger). But let me only lay hands on that infernal quill-driver! I'll make him skip-be it in this world or the next; if I don't pound him to a jelly, body and soul; if I don't write all the Ten Commandments, the seven Penitential Psalms, the five books of Moses, and the whole of the Prophets upon his rascally hide so distinctly that the blue hieroglyphics shall be legible at the day of judgment-if I don't, may I——

MRS. MILLER. Yes, yes, curse and swear your hardest! That's the way to frighten the devil! Oh, dear! Oh, dear! Oh, gracious heavens! What shall we do? Who can advise us? Speak, Miller, speak; this silence distracts me! (She runs screaming up and down the room.)

MILLER. I will instantly to the minister! I will open my mouth boldly, and tell him all from beginning to end. You knew it before me, and ought to have given me a hint of what was going on! The girl might yet have been advised. It might still have been time to save her! But, no! There was something for your meddling and making, and you must needs add fuel to the fire. Now you have made your bed you may lie on it. As you have brewed so you may drink; I shall take my daughter under my arm and be off with her over the borders.

SCENE V.

MILLER, MRS. MILLER, LOUISA, FERDINND.

(All speaking together).

FERDINAND (rushes in, terrified, and out of breath). Has my father been here?

LOUISA (starts back in horror). His father? Gracious heaven!

MRS. MILLER (wringing her hands). The minister here? Then it's all over with us!

MILLER (laughs bitterly). Thank God! Thank God! Now comes our benefit!

FERDINAND (rushing towards LOUISA, and clasping her in his arms). Mine thou art, though heaven and hell were placed between us!

LOUISA. I am doomed! Speak, Ferdinand! Did you not utter that dreaded name? Your father?

FERDINAND. Be not alarmed! The danger has passed! I have thee again! Again thou hast me! Let me regain my breath on thy dear bosom. It was a dreadful hour!

LOUISA. What was a dreadful hour? Answer me, Ferdinand! I die with apprehension!

FERDINAND (drawing back, gazing upon her earnestly, then in a solemn tone). An hour, Louisa, when another's form stepped between my heart and thee-an hour in which my love grew pale before my conscience-when Louisa ceased to be all in all to Ferdinand!

[LOUISA sinks back upon her chair, and conceals her face.

(FERDINAND stands before her in speechless agitation, then turns away from her suddenly and exclaims). Never, never! Baroness, 'tis impossible! You ask too much! Never can I sacrifice this innocence at your shrine. No, by the eternal God! I cannot recall my oath, which speaks to me from thy soul-thrilling eyes louder than the thunders of heaven! Behold, lady! Inhuman father, look on this!Would you have me destroy this angel? Shall my perfidy kindle a hell in this heavenly bosom? (turning towards her with firmness).No! I will bear her to thy throne, Almighty Judge! Thy voice shall declare if my affection be a crime. (He grasps her hand, and raises her from the sofa.) Courage, my beloved!-thou hast conquered-and I come forth a victor from the terrible conflict!

LOUISA. No, no, Ferdinand, conceal nothing from me! Declare boldly the dreadful decree! You named your father! You spoke of the baroness! The shivering of death seizes my heart! 'Tis said she is about to be married!

FERDINAND (quite overcome, throws himself at her feet). Yes, and to me, dear unfortunate. Such is my father's will!

LOUISA (after a deep pause, in a tremulous voice, but with assumed resignation). Well! Why am I thus affrighted? Has not my dear father often told me that you never could be mine? But I was obstinate, and believed him not. (A second pause; she falls weeping into her father's arms.) Father, thy daughter is thine own again!Father, forgive me! 'Twas not your child's fault that the dream was so heavenly-the waking so terrible!

MILLER. Louisa! Louisa! O merciful heaven! She has lost her senses!My daughter! My poor child! Curses upon thy seducer! Curses upon the pandering mother who threw thee in his way!

MRS. MILLER (weeping on LOUISA's neck). Daughter, do I deserve this curse? God forgive you, major! What has this poor lamb done that you bring this misery upon her?

FERDINAND (with resolution). I will unravel the meshes of these intrigues. I will burst asunder these iron chains of prejudice. As a free-born man will I make my choice, and crush these insect souls with the colossal force of my love! [Going.

LOUISA (rises trembling from the sofa, and attempts to follow him). Stay, oh, stay! Whither are you going? Father! Mother! He deserts us in this fearful hour!

MRS. MILLER (hastens towards him, and detains him). The president is coming hither? He will ill-use my child! He will ill-use us all,-and yet, major, you are going to leave us.

MILLER (laughs hysterically). Leave us. Of course he is! What should hinder him? The girl has given him all she had. (Grasping FERDINAND with one hand, and LOUISA with the other.) Listen to me, young gentleman. The only way out of my house is over my daughter's body. If you possess one single spark of honor await your father's coming; tell him, deceiver, how you stole her young and inexperienced heart; or, by the God who made me! (thrusting LOUISA towards him with violence and passion) You shall crush before my eyes this trembling worm whom love for you has brought to shame and infamy!

FERDINAND (returns, and walks to and fro in deep thought). 'Tis true, the President's power is great-parental authority is a mighty word-even crimes claim respect when concealed within its folds.He may push that authority far-very far! But love goes beyond it.Hear me, Louisa; give me thy hand! (clasping it firmly). As surely as I hope for Heaven's mercy in my dying hour, I swear that the moment which separates these hands shall also rend asunder the thread that binds me to existence!

LOUISA. You terrify me! Turn from me! Your lips tremble! Your eyes roll fearfully!

FERDINAND. Nay, Louisa! Fear nothing! It is not madness which prompts my oath! 'Tis the choicest gift of Heaven, decision, sent to my aid at that critical moment, when an oppressed bosom can only find relief in some desperate remedy. I love thee, Louisa! Thou shalt be mine! 'Tis resolved! And now for my father!

[He rushes out, and is met by the PRESIDENT.

SCENE VI.

MILLER, MRS. MILLER, LOUISA, FERDINAND, PRESIDENT, with SERVANTS.

PRESIDENT (as he enters). So! Here he is! (All start in terror.)

FERDINAND (retiring a few paces). In the house of innocence!

PRESIDENT. Where a son learns obedience to his father!

FERDINAND. Permit me to——

PRESIDENT (interrupting him, turns to MILLER). The father, I presume?

MILLER. I am Miller, the musician.

PRESIDENT (to MRS. MILLER). And you, the mother?

MRS. MILLER. Yes, alas! Her unfortunate mother!

FERDINAND (to MILLER.) Father, take Louisa to her chamber-she is fainting.

PRESIDENT. An unnecessary precaution! I will soon arouse her. (To LOUISA.) How long have you been acquainted with the President's son?

LOUISA (with timidity). Of the President's son I have never thought.Ferdinand von Walter has paid his addresses to me since November last.

FERDINAND. And he adores her!

PRESIDENT (to LOUISA). Has he given you any assurance of his love?

FERDINAND. But a few minutes since, the most solemn, and God was my witness.

PRESIDENT (to his son angrily). Silence! You shall have opportunity enough of confessing your folly. (To LOUISA.) I await your answer.

LOUISA. He swore eternal love to me.

FERDINAND. And I will keep my oath.

PRESIDENT (to FERDINAND). Must I command your silence? (To LOUISA). Did you accept his rash vows?

LOUISA (with tenderness). I did, and gave him mine in exchange.

FERDINAND (resolutely). The bond is irrevocable——

PRESIDENT (to FERDINAND). If you dare to interrupt me again I'll teach you better manners. (To LOUISA, sneeringly.) And he paid handsomely every time, no doubt?

LOUISA. I do not understand your question.

PRESIDENT (with an insulting laugh). Oh, indeed! Well, I only meant to hint that-as everything has its price-I hope you have been more provident than to bestow your favors gratis-or perhaps you were satisfied with merely participating in the pleasure? Eh? How was it?

FERDINAND (infuriated). Hell and confusion! What does this mean?

LOUISA (to FERDINAND, with dignity and emotion). Baron von Walter, now you are free!

FERDINAND. Father! Virtue though clothed in a beggar's garb commands respect!

PRESIDENT (laughing aloud). A most excellent joke! The father is commanded to honor his son's strumpet!

LOUISA. Oh! Heaven and earth! (Sinks down in a swoon.)

FERDINAND (drawing his sword). Father, you gave me life, and, till now, I acknowledged your claim on it. That debt is cancelled.(Replaces his sword in the scabbard, and points to LOUISA.) There lies the bond of filial duty torn to atoms!

MILLER (who has stood apart trembling, now comes forward, by turns gnashing his teeth in rage, and shrinking back in terror). Your excellency, the child is the father's second self. No offence, I hope!Who strikes the child hits the father-blow for blow-that's our rule here. No offence, I hope!

MRS. MILLER. God have mercy on us! Now the old man has begun-we shall all catch it with a vengeance!

PRESIDENT (who has not understood what MILLER said). What?Is the old pander stirred up? We shall have something to settle together presently, Mr. Pander!

MILLER. You mistake me, my lord. My name is Miller, at your service for an adagio-but, as to ladybirds, I cannot serve you. As long as there is such an assortment at court, we poor citizens can't afford to lay in stock! No offence, I hope!

MRS. MILLER. For Heaven's sake, man, hold your tongue! Would you ruin both wife and child?

FERDINAND (to his father). You play but a sorry part here, my lord, and might well have dispensed with these witnesses.

MILLER (coming nearer, with increasing confidence). To be plain and above board-No offence, I hope-your excellency may have it all your own way in the Cabinet-but this is my house. I'm your most obedient, very humble servant when I wait upon you with a petition, but the rude, unmannerly intruder I have the right to bundle out-no offence, I hope!

PRESIDENT (pale with anger, and approaching MILLER). What?What's that you dare to utter?

MILLER (retreating a few steps). Only a little bit of my mind sir-no offence, I hope!

PRESIDENT (furiously). Insolent villain! Your impertinence shall procure you a lodging in prison. (To his servants). Call in the officers of justice! Away! (Some of the attendants go out. The PRESIDENT paces the stage with a furious air.) The father shall to prison; the mother and her strumpet daughter to the pillory!Justice shall lend her sword to my rage! For this insult will I have ample amends. Shall such contemptible creatures thwart my plans, and set father and son against each other with impunity? Tremble, miscreants! I will glut my hate in your destruction-the whole brood of you-father, mother, and daughter shall be sacrificed to my vengeance!

FERDINAND (to MILLER, in a collected and firm manner). Oh!Not so! Fear not, friends! I am your protector. (Turning to the PRESIDENT, with deference). Be not so rash, father! For your own sake let me beg of you no violence. There is a corner of my heart where the name of father has never yet been heard. Oh! Press not into that!

PRESIDENT. Silence, unworthy boy! Rouse not my anger to greater fury!

MILLER (recovering from a stupor). Wife, look you to your daughter! I fly to the duke. His highness' tailor-God be praised for reminding me of it at this moment-learns the flute of me-I cannot fail of success. (Is hastening off.)

PRESIDENT. To the duke, will you? Have you forgotten that I am the threshold over which you must pass, or failing, perish? To the duke, you fool? Try to reach him with your lamentations, when, reduced to a living skeleton, you lie buried in a dungeon five fathoms deep, where light and sound never enter; where darkness goggles at hell with gloating eyes! There gnash thy teeth in anguish; there rattle thy chains in despair, and groan, “Woe is me! This is beyond human endurance!”

SCENE VII.

Officers of Justice-the former.

FERDINAND (flies to LOUISA, who, overcome with fear, faints in his arms.) Louisa!-Help, for God's sake! Terror overpowers her![MILLER, catching up his cane and putting on his hat, prepares for defense. MRS. MILLER throws herself on her knees before the PRESIDENT.

PRESIDENT (to the officers, showing his star). Arrest these offenders in the duke's name. Boy, let go that strumpet! Fainting or not-when once her neck is fitted with the iron collar the mob will pelt her till she revives.

MRS. MILLER. Mercy, your excellency! Mercy! Mercy!

MILLER (snatching her from the ground with violence). Kneel to God, you howling fool, and not to villains-since I must to prison any way!

PRESIDENT (biting his lips.) You may be out in your reckoning, scoundrel! There are still gallows to spare! (To the officers.) Must I repeat my orders?

[They approach LOUISA-FERDINAND places himself before her.

FERDINAND (fiercely). Touch her who dare! (He draws his sword and flourishes it.) Let no one presume to lay a finger on her, whose life is not well insured. (To the PRESIDENT.) As you value your own safety, father, urge me no further!

PRESIDENT (to the officers in a threatening voice). At your peril, cowards! (They again attempt to seize LOUISA.)

FERDINAND. Hell and furies! Back, I say! (Driving them away.) Once more, father, I warn you-have some thought for your own safety!Drive me not to extremity!

PRESIDENT (enraged to the officers). Scoundrels! Is this your obedience? (The officers renew their efforts.)

FERDINAND. Well, if it must be so (attacking and wounding several of them), Justice forgive me!

PRESIDENT (exasperated to the utmost). Let me see whether I, too, must feel your weapon! (He seizes LOUISA and delivers her to an officer.)

FERDINAND (laughing bitterly). Father! Father! Your conduct is a galling satire upon Providence, who has so ill understood her people as to make bad statesmen of excellent executioners!

PRESIDENT (to the officers). Away with her!

FERDINAND. Father, if I cannot prevent it, she must stand in the pillory-but by her side will also stand the son of the president. Do you still insist?

PRESIDENT. The more entertaining will be the exhibition. Away with her!

FERDINAND. I will pledge the honor of an officer's sword for her. Do you still insist?

PRESIDENT. Your sword is already familiar with disgrace. Away!Away! You know my will.

FERDINAND (wrests LOUISA from the officer and holds her with one arm, with the other points his sword at her bosom.) Father, rather than tamely see my wife branded with infamy I will plunge this sword into her bosom. Do you still insist?

PRESIDENT. Do it, if the point be sharp enough!

FERDINAND (releases LOUISA, and looks wildly towards heaven).Be thou witness, Almighty God, that I have left no human means untried to save her! Forgive me now if I have recourse to hellish means. While you are leading her to the pillory (speaking loudly in the PRESIDENT's ear), I will publish throughout the town a pleasant history of how a president's chair may be gained! [Exit.

PRESIDENT (as if thunder-struck). How? What said he? Ferdinand!Release her instantly! (Rushes after his son.)

SCENE I.

Room at the President's. Enter PRESIDENT and WORM.

PRESIDENT. That was an infernal piece of business!

WORM. Just what I feared, your excellency. Opposition may inflame the enthusiast, but never converts him.

PRESIDENT. I had placed my whole reliance upon the success of this attempt. I made no doubt but if the girl were once publicly disgraced, he would be obliged as an officer and a gentleman to resign her.

WORM. An admirable idea!-Had you but succeeded in disgracing her.

PRESIDENT. And yet-when I reflect on the matter coolly-I ought not to have suffered myself to be overawed. It was a threat which he never could have meant seriously.

WORM. Be not too certain of that! There is no folly too gross for excited passion! You say that the baron has always looked upon government with an eye of disapprobation. I can readily believe it. The principles which he brought with him from college are ill-suited to our atmosphere. What have the fantastic visions of personal nobility and greatness of soul to do in court, where 'tis the perfection of wisdom to be great and little by turns, as occasion demands? The baron is too young and too fiery to take pleasure in the slow and crooked paths of intrigue. That alone can give impulse to his ambition which seems glorious and romantic!

PRESIDENT (impatiently). But how will these sagacious remarks advance our affairs?

WORM. They will point out to your excellency where the wound lies, and so, perhaps, help you to find a remedy. Such a character- pardon the observation-ought never to have been made a confidant, or should never have been roused to enmity. He detests the means by which you have risen to power! Perhaps it is only the son that has hitherto sealed the lips of the betrayer! Give him but a fair opportunity for throwing off the bonds imposed upon him by nature! only convince him, by unrelenting opposition to his passion, that you are no longer an affectionate father, and that moment the duties of a patriot will rush upon him with irresistible force! Nay, the high-wrought idea of offering so unparalleled a sacrifice at the shrine of justice might of itself alone have charms sufficient to reconcile him to the ruin of a parent!

PRESIDENT. Worm! Worm! To what a horrible abyss do you lead me!

WORM. Never fear, my lord, I will lead you back in safety! May I speak without restraint?

PRESIDENT (throwing himself into a seat). Freely, as felon with felon.

WORM. Forgive me, then. It seems to me that you have to ascribe all your influence as president to the courtly art of intrigue; why not resort to the same means for attaining your ends as a father?I well remember with what seeming frankness you invited your predecessor to a game at piquet, and caroused half the night with him over bumpers of Burgundy; and yet it was the same night on which the great mine you had planned to annihilate him was to explode. Why did you make a public exhibition of enmity to the major? You should by no means have let it appear that you knew anything of his love affair. You should have made the girl the object of your attacks and have preserved the affection of your son; like the prudent general who does not engage the prime of the enemy's force but creates disaffection among the ranks?

PRESIDENT. How could this have been effected?

WORM. In the simplest manner-even now the game is not entirely lost! Forget for a time that you are a father. Do not contend against a passion which opposition only renders more formidable. Leave me to hatch, from the heat of their own passions, the basilisk which shall destroy them.

PRESIDENT. I am all attention.

WORM. Either my knowledge of human character is very small, or the major is as impetuous in jealousy as in love. Make him suspect the girl's constancy-whether probable or not does not signify. One grain of leaven will be enough to ferment the whole mass.

PRESIDENT. But where shall we find that grain?

WORM. Now, then, I come to the point. But first explain to me how much depends upon the major's compliance. How far is it of consequence that the romance with the music-master's daughter should be brought to a conclusion and the marriage with Lady Milford effected?

PRESIDENT. How can you ask me, Worm? If the match with Lady Milford is broken off I stand a fair chance of losing my whole influence; on the other hand, if I force the major's consent, of losing my head.

WORM (with animation). Now have the kindness to listen to me. The major must be entangled in a web. Your whole power must be employed against his mistress. We must make her write a love-letter, address it to a third party, and contrive to drop it cleverly in the way of the major.

PRESIDENT. Absurd proposal! As if she would consent to sign her own death-warrant.

WORM. She must do so if you will but let me follow my own plan.I know her gentle heart thoroughly; she has but two vulnerable sides by which her conscience can be attacked; they are her father and the major. The latter is entirely out of the question; we must, therefore, make the most of the musician.

PRESIDENT. In what way?

WORM. From the description your excellency gave me of what passed in his house nothing can be easier than to terrify the father with the threat of a criminal process. The person of his favorite, and of the keeper of the seals, is in some degree the representative of the duke himself, and he who offends the former is guilty of treason towards the latter. At any rate I will engage with these pretences to conjure up such a phantom as shall scare the poor devil out of his seven senses.

PRESIDENT. But recollect, Worm, the affair must not be carried so far as to become serious.

WORM. Nor shall it. It shall be carried no further than is necessary to frighten the family into our toils. The musician, therefore, must be quietly arrested. To make the necessity yet more urgent, we may also take possession of the mother-and then we begin to talk of criminal process, of the scaffold, and of imprisonment for life, and make the daughter's letter the sole condition of the parent's release.

PRESIDENT. Excellent! Excellent! Now I begin to understand you!

WORM. Louisa loves her father-I might say even to adoration!The danger which threatens his life, or at least his freedom-the reproaches of her conscience for being the cause of his misfortunes-the impossibility of ever becoming the major's wife-the confusion of her brain, which I take upon myself to produce-all these considerations make our plan certain of success.She must be caught in the snare.

PRESIDENT. But my son-will he not instantly get scent of it? Will it not make him yet more desperate?

WORM. Leave that to me, your excellency! The old folks shall not be set at liberty till they and their daughter have taken the most solemn oath to keep the whole transaction secret, and never to confess the deception.

PRESIDENT. An oath! Ridiculous! What restraint can an oath be?

WORM. None upon us, my lord, but the most binding upon people of their stamp. Observe, how dexterously by this measure we shall both reach the goal of our desires. The girl loses at once the affection of her lover, and her good name; the parents will lower their tone, and, thoroughly humbled by misfortune, will esteem it an act of mercy, if, by giving her my hand, I reestablish their daughter's reputation.

PRESIDENT (shaking his head and smiling). Artful villain! I confess myself outdone-no devil could spin a finer snare! The scholar excels his master. The next question is, to whom must the letter be addressed- with whom to accuse her of having an intrigue?

WORM. It must necessarily be some one who has all to gain or all to lose by your son's decision in this affair.

PRESIDENT (after a moment's reflection). I can think of no one but the marshal.

WORM (shrugs his shoulders). The marshal! He would certainly not be my choice were I Louisa Miller.

PRESIDENT. And why not? What a strange notion! A man who dresses in the height of fashion-who carries with him an atmosphere of eau de mille fleurs and musk-who can garnish every silly speech with a handful of ducats-could all this possibly fail to overcome the delicacy of a tradesman's daughter? No, no, my good friend, jealousy is not quite so hard of belief. I shall send for the marshal immediately. (Rings.)

WORM. While your excellency takes care of him, and of the fiddler's arrest, I will go and indite the aforesaid letter.

PRESIDENT (seats himself at his writing-table). Do so; and, as soon as it is ready, bring it hither for my perusal.

[Exit WORM.

[The PRESIDENT, having written, rises and hands the paper to a servant who enters.

See this arrest executed without a moment's delay, and let Marshal von Kalb be informed that I wish to see him immediately.

SERVANT. The marshal's carriage has just stopped at your lordship's door.

PRESIDENT. So much the better-as for the arrest, let it be managed with such precaution that no disturbance arise.

SERVANT. I will take care, my lord.

PRESIDENT. You understand me? The business must be kept quite secret.

SERVANT. Your excellency shall be obeyed.

[Exit SERVANT.

SCENE II.

The PRESIDENT-MARSHALL KALB.

MARSHAL (hastily). I have just looked in, en passant, my dear friend!How are you? How do you get on? We are to have the grand opera Dido to-night! Such a conflagration!-A whole town will be in flames!-You will come to the blaze of course-eh?

PRESIDENT. I have conflagration enough in my own house, one that threatens the destruction of all I possess. Be seated, my dear marshal. You arrive very opportunely to give me your advice and assistance in a certain business which will either advance our fortunes or utterly ruin us both!

MARSHAL. Don't alarm me so, my dear friend!

PRESIDENT. As I said before, it must exalt or ruin us entirely! You know my project respecting the major and Lady Milford-you are not ignorant how necessary this union is to secure both our fortunes! Marshal, our plans threaten to come to naught. My son refuses to marry her!

MARSHAL. Refuses! Refuses to marry her? But, my goodness! I have published the news through the whole town. The union is the general topic of conversation.

PRESIDENT. Then you will be talked of by all the town as a spreader of false reports,-in short, Ferdinand loves another.

MARSHAL. Pooh! You are joking! As if that were an obstacle?

PRESIDENT. With such an enthusiast a most insurmountable one!

MARSHAL. Can he be mad enough to spurn his good-fortune? Eh?

PRESIDENT. Ask him yourself and you'll hear what he will answer.

MARSHAL. But, mon Dieu! what can he answer?

PRESIDENT. That he will publish to the world the crime by which we rose to power-that he will denounce our forged letters and receipts-that he will send us both to the scaffold. That is what he can answer.

MARSHAL. Are you out of your mind?

PRESIDENT. Nay, that is what he has already answered? He was actually on the point of putting these threats into execution; and it was only by the most abject submission that I could persuade him to abandon his design. What say you to this, marshal?

MARSHAL (with a look of bewildered stupidity). I am at my wits' end!

PRESIDENT. That might have blown over. But my spies have just brought me notice that the grand cupbearer, von Bock, is on the point of offering himself as a suitor to her ladyship.

MARSHAL. You drive me distracted! Whom did you say? Von Bock?Don't you know that we are mortal enemies? And don't you know why?

PRESIDENT. The first word that I ever heard of it!

MARSHAL. My dear count! You shall hear-your hair will stand on end! You must remember the famous court ball-it is now just twenty years ago. It was the first time that English country-dances were introduced-you remember how the hot wax trickled from the great chandelier on Count Meerschaum's blue and silver domino. Surely, you cannot have forgotten that affair!

PRESIDENT. Who could forget so remarkable a circumstance!

MARSHAL. Well, then, in the heat of the dance Princess Amelia lost her garter. The whole ball, as you may imagine, was instantly thrown into confusion. Von Bock and myself-we were then fellow-pages-crept through the whole saloon in search of the garter. At length I discovered it. Von Bock perceives my good-fortune-rushes forward-tears it from my hands, and, just fancy-presents it to the princess, and so cheated me of the honor I had so fortunately earned. What do you think of that?

PRESIDENT. 'Twas most insolent!

MARSHAL. I thought I should have fainted upon the spot. A trick so malicious was beyond the powers of mortal endurance. At length I recovered myself; and, approaching the princess, said,-“Von Bock, 'tis true, was fortunate enough to present the garter to your highness; but he who first discovered that treasure finds his reward in silence, and is dumb!”

PRESIDENT. Bravo, marshal! Admirably said! Most admirable!

MARSHAL. And is dumb! But till the day of judgment will I remember his conduct-the mean, sneaking sycophant! And as if that were not aggravation enough, he actually, as we were struggling on the ground for the garter, rubbed all the powder from one side of my peruke with his sleeve, and ruined me for the rest of the evening.

PRESIDENT. This is the man who will marry Lady Milford, and consequently soon take the lead at court.

MARSHAL. You plunge a dagger in my heart! But why must he? Why should he marry her? Why he? Where is the necessity?

PRESIDENT. Because Ferdinand refuses her, and there is no other candidate.

MARSHAL. But is there no possible method of obtaining your son's consent? Let the measure be ever so extravagant or desperate-there is nothing to which I should not willingly consent in order to supplant the hated von Bock.

PRESIDENT. I know but one means of accomplishing this, and that rests entirely with you.

MARSHAL. With me? Name it, my dear count, name it!

PRESIDENT. You must set Ferdinand and his mistress against each other.

MARSHAL. Against each other? How do you mean?-And how would that be possible.

PRESIDENT. Everything is ours could we make him suspect the girl.

MARSHAL. Ah, of theft, you mean?

PRESIDENT. Pshaw!-He would never believe that! No, no-I mean that she is carrying on an intrigue with another.

MARSHAL. And this other, who is he to be?

PRESIDENT. Yourself!

MARSHAL. How? Must I be her lover? Is she of noble birth?

PRESIDENT. What signifies that? What an idea!-she is the daughter of a musician.

MARSHAL. A plebeian?-That will never do!

PRESIDENT. What will never do? Nonsense, man! Who in the name of wonder would think of asking a pair of rosy cheeks for their owner's pedigree?

MARSHAL. But consider, my dear count, a married man! And my reputation at court!

PRESIDENT. Oh! That's quite another thing! I beg a thousand pardons, marshal; I was not aware that a man of unblemished morals held a higher place in your estimation than a man of power!Let us break up our conference.

MARSHAL. Be not so hasty, count. I did not mean to say that.

PRESIDENT (coldly.) No-no! You are perfectly right. I, too, am weary of office. I shall throw up the game, tender my resignation to the duke, and congratulate von Bock on his accession to the premiership. This duchy is not all the world.

MARSHAL. And what am I to do? It is very fine for you to talk thus!You are a man of learning! But I-mon Dieu! What shall I be if his highness dismisses me?

PRESIDENT. A stale jest!-A thing out of fashion!

MARSHAL. I implore you, my dearest, my most valued friend.Abandon those thoughts. I will consent to everything!

PRESIDENT. Will you lend your name to an assignation to which this Louisa Miller shall invite you in writing?

MARSHAL. Well, in God's name let it be so!

PRESIDENT. And drop the letter where the major cannot fail to find it.

MARSHAL. For instance, on the parade, where I can let it fall as if accidentally in drawing out my handkerchief.

PRESIDENT. And when the baron questions you will you assume the character of a favored rival?

MARSHAL. Mort de ma vie! I'll teach him manners! I'll cure him of interfering in my amours!

PRESIDENT. Good! Now you speak in the right key. The letter shall be written immediately! Come in the evening to receive it, and we will talk over the part you are to play.

MARSHAL. I will be with you the instant I have paid sixteen visits of the very highest importance. Permit me, therefore, to take my leave without delay. (Going.)

PRESIDENT (rings). I reckon upon your discretion, marshal.

MARSHAL (calls back). Ah, mon Dieu! You know me!

[Exit MARSHAL.

SCENE IV.

Room in MILLER's House. LOUISA and FERDINAND.

LOUISA. Cease, I implore you! I expect no more days of happiness.All my hopes are levelled with the dust.

FERDINAND. All mine are exalted to heaven! My father's passions are roused! He will direct his whole artillery against us! He will force me to become an unnatural son. I will not answer for my filial duty. Rage and despair will wring from me the dark secret that my father is an assassin! The son will deliver the parent into the hands of the executioner. This is a moment of extreme danger, and extreme danger alone could prompt my love to take so daring a leap! Hear me, Louisa! A thought, vast and immeasurable as my love, has arisen in my soul-thou, Louisa, and I, and Love! Lies not a whole heaven within this circle? Or dost thou feel that there is still something wanting?

LOUISA. Oh! Cease! No more! I tremble to think what you would say.

FERDINAND. If we have no longer a claim upon the world, why should we seek its approbation? Why venture where nothing can be gained and all may be lost? Will thine eyes sparkle less brightly reflected by the Baltic waves than by the waters of the Rhine or the Elbe? Where Louise loves me there is my native land! Thy footsteps will make the wild and sandy desert far more attractive than the marble halls of my ancestors. Shall we miss the pomp of cities? Be we where we may, Louisa, a sun will rise and a sun will set- scenes before which the most glorious achievements of art grow pale and dim! Though we serve God no more in his consecrated churches, yet the night shall spread her solemn shadows round us; the changing moon shall hear our confession, and a glorious congregation of stars join in our prayers! Think you our talk of love can ever be exhausted! Oh, no! One smile from

Louisa were a theme for centuries-the dream of life will be over ere I can exhaust the charms of a single tear.

LOUISA. And hast thou no duty save that of love?

FERDINAND (embracing her). None so sacred as thy peace of mind!

LOUISA (very seriously). Cease, then, and leave me. I have a father who possesses no treasure save one only daughter. Tomorrow he will be sixty years old-that he will fall a victim to the vengeance of the President is most certain!

FERDINAND (interrupting her). He shall accompany us. Therefore no more objections, my beloved. I will go and convert my valuables into gold, and raise money on my father's credit! It is lawful to plunder a robber, and are not his treasures the price for which he has sold his country? This night, when the clock strikes one, a carriage will stop at your door-throw yourself into it, and we fly!

LOUISA. Pursued by your father's curse! A curse, unthinking one, which is never pronounced in vain even by murderers-which the avenging angel hears when uttered by a malefactor in his last agony-which, like a fury, will fearfully pursue the fugitives from shore to shore! No, my beloved! If naught but a crime can preserve you to me, I still have courage to resign you!

FERDINAND (mutters gloomily). Indeed!

LOUISA. Resign you? Oh! Horrible beyond all measure is the thought.Horrible enough to pierce the immortal spirit and pale the glowing cheeks of joy! Ferdinand! To resign you! Yet how can one resign what one never possessed? Your heart is the property of your station. My claim was sacrilege, and, shuddering, I withdraw it!

FERDINAND (with convulsed features, and biting his underlip). You withdraw it!

LOUISA. Nay! Look upon me, dearest Ferdinand. Gnash not your teeth so bitterly! Come, let my example rouse your slumbering courage.Let me be the heroine of this moment. Let me restore to a father his lost son. I will renounce a union which would sever the bonds by which society is held together, and overthrow the landmarks of social order. I am the criminal. My bosom has nourished proud and foolish wishes, and my present misery is a just punishment.Oh! Leave me then the sweet, the consoling idea that mine is the sacrifice. Canst thou deny me this last satisfaction? (FERDINAND, stupefied with agitation and anger, seizes a violin and strikes a few notes upon it; and then tears away the strings, dashes the instrument upon the ground, and, stamping it to pieces, bursts into a loud laugh.)Walter! God in Heaven! What mean you? Be not thus unmanned!This hour requires fortitude; it is the hour of separation! You have a heart, dear Walter; I know that heart-warm as life is your love-boundless and immeasurable-bestow it on one more noble, more worthy-she need not envy the most fortunate of her sex! (Striving to repress her tears.) You shall see me no more! Leave the vain disappointed girl to bewail her sorrow in sad and lonely seclusion;where her tears will flow unheeded. Dead and gone are all my hopes of happiness in this world; yet still shall I inhale ever and anon the perfumes of the faded wreath! (Giving him her trembling hand, while her face is turned away.) Baron Walter, farewell!

FERDINAND (recovering from the stupor in which he was plunged). Louisa, I fly! Do you indeed refuse to follow me?

LOUISA (who has retreated to the further end of the apartment, conceals her countenance with her hands). My duty bids me stay, and suffer.

FERDINAND. Serpent! Thou liest-some other motive chains thee here!

LOUISA (in a tone of the most heartfelt sorrow). Encourage that belief.Haply it may make our parting more supportable.

FERDINAND. What? Oppose freezing duty to fiery love! And dost thou think to cheat me with that delusion? Some rival detains thee here, and woe be to thee and him should my suspicions be confirmed!

[Exit.

SCENE VI.

LOUISA and WORM.

WORM (approaches her). Good evening, miss.

LOUISA. Heavens! Who speaks! (Perceives him, and starts back in terror.) Ha! Dreadful! Dreadful! I fear some dire misfortune is even now realizing the forebodings of my soul! (To WORM, with a look of disdain.) Do you seek the president? He is no longer here.

WORM. 'Tis you I seek, miss!

LOUISA. I wonder, then, that you did not direct your steps towards the market-place.

WORM. What should I do there?

LOUISA. Release your betrothed from the pillory.

WORM. Louisa, you cherish some false suspicion——

LOUISA (sharply interrupting him). What is your business with me?

WORM. I come with a message from your father.

LOUISA (agitated). From my father? Oh! Where is my father?

WORM. Where he would fain not be!

LOUISA. Quick, quick, for God's sake! Oh! My foreboding heart!Where is my father!

WORM. In prison, if you needs must know!

LOUISA (with a look towards heaven). This, too! This, too! In prison, said you? And why in prison?

WORM. It is the duke's order.

LOUISA. The duke's?

WORM. Who thinking his own dignity offended by the insults offered to the person of his representative——

LOUISA. How? How? Oh ye Almighty Powers!

WORM. ——Has resolved to inflict the most exemplary punishment.

LOUISA. This was still wanting! This! Yes, in truth. I now feel that my heart does love another besides Ferdinand! That could not be allowed to escape! The prince's dignity offended? Heavenly Providence! Save, oh! Save my sinking faith! (After a moment's pause, she turns to WORM.) And Ferdinand?

WORM. Must choose between Lady Milford's hand and his father's curse and disinheritance.

LOUISA. Terrible choice!-And yet-yet is he the happier of the two.He has no father to lose-and yet to have none is misery enough!My father imprisoned for treason-my Ferdinand compelled to choose between Lady Milford's hand or a parent's curse and disinheritance! Truly admirable! For even villany so perfect is perfection! Perfection? No! Something is still wanting to complete that. Where is my mother?

WORM. In the house of correction.

LOUISA (with a smile of despair). Now the measure is full! It is full, and I am free-released from all duties-all sorrows-all joys!Released even from Providence! I have nothing more to do with it!(A dreadful pause.) Have you aught else to communicate? Speak freely-now I can hear anything with indifference.

WORM. All that has happened you already know.

LOUISA. But not that which is yet to happen! (Another pause, during which she surveys WORM from head to foot.) Unfortunate man! You have entered on a melancholy employment, which can never lead you to happiness. To cause misery to others is sad enough-but to be the messenger of evil is horrible indeed-to be the first to shriek the screech-owl's song, to stand by when the bleeding heart trembles upon the iron shaft of necessity, and the Christian doubts the existence of a God-Heaven protect me! Wert thou paid a ton of gold for every tear of anguish which thou must witness, I would not be a wretch like thee! What is there yet to happen?

WORM. I know not.

LOUISA. You pretend not to know? This light-shunning embassy trembles at the sound of words, but the spectre betrays itself in your ghastly visage. What is there yet to happen? You said the duke will inflict upon him a most exemplary punishment. What call you exemplary?

WORM. Ask me no more.

LOUISA. Terrible man! Some hangman must have schooled thee! Else thou hast not so well learned to prolong the torture of thy victim before giving the finishing stroke to the agonized heart! Speak!What fate awaits my father? Death thou canst announce with a laughing sneer-what then must that be which thou dost hesitate to disclose? Speak out! Let me at once receive the overwhelming weight of thy tidings! What fate awaits my father?

WORM. A criminal process.

LOUISA. But what is that? I am an ignorant, innocent girl, and understand but little of your fearful terms of law. What mean you by a criminal process?

WORM. Judgment upon life or death.

LOUISA (firmly). Ah! I thank you.[Exit hastily by a side door.

WORM (alarmed). What means this? Should the simpleton perchance- confusion! Surely she will not-I must follow her.I am answerable for her life. (As he is going towards the door, LOUISA returns, wrapped in a cloak.)

LOUISA. Your pardon, Mr. Secretary, I must lock the door.

WORM. Whither in such haste?

LOUISA (passing him). To the duke.

WORM (alarmed, detains her). How? Whither?

LOUISA. To the duke. Do you not hear? Even to that very duke whose will is to decide upon my father's life or death. Yet no?-'Tis not his will that decides, but the will of wicked men who surround his throne. He lends naught to this process, save the shadow of his majesty, and his royal signature.

WORM (with a burst of laughter). To the duke!

LOUISA. I know the meaning of that sneering laugh-you would tell me that I shall find no compassion there. But though I may meet (God preserve me!) with nothing but scorn-scorn at my sorrows-yet will I to the duke. I have been told that the great never know what misery is; that they fly from the knowledge of it. But I will teach the duke what misery is; I will paint to him, in all the writhing agonies of death, what misery is; I will cry aloud in wailings that shall creep through the very marrow of his bones, what misery is; and, while at my picture his hairs shall stand on end like quills upon the porcupine, will I shriek into his affrighted ear, that in the hour of death the sinews of these mighty gods of earth shall shrivel and shrink, and that at the day of judgment beggars and kings shall be weighed together in the same balance(Going.)

WORM (ironically). By all means go to the duke! You can really do nothing more prudent; I advise you heartily to the step. Only go, and I give you my word that the duke will grant your suit.

LOUISA (stopping suddenly). What said you? Do you yourself advise the step? (Returns hastily). What am I about to do? Something wicked surely, since this man approves it-how know you that the prince will grant my suit?

WORM. Because he will not have to grant it unrewarded.

LOUISA. Not unrewarded? And what price does he set on his humanity?

WORM. The person of the fair suppliant will be payment enough!

LOUISA (stopping for a moment in mute dismay-in a feeble voice). Almighty God!

WORM. And I trust that you will not think your father's life over-valued when 'tis purchased at so gracious a price.

LOUISA (with great indignation). True, oh! True! The great are entrenched from truth behind their own vices, safely as behind the swords of cherubim. The Almighty protect thee, father! Your child can die-but not sin for thee.

WORM. This will be agreeable news for the poor disconsolate old man. “My Louisa,” Says he, “has bowed me down to the earth;but my Louisa will raise me up again.” I hasten to him with your answer. (Affects to be about to depart.)

LOUISA (flies after him and holds him back). Stay! Stay! One moment's patience! How nimble this Satan is, when his business is to drive humanity distracted! I have bowed him to the earth! I must raise him up again! Speak to me! Counsel me! What can I, what must I do?

WORM. There is but one means of saving him!

LOUISA. What is that means?

WORM. And your father approves of it——

LOUISA. My father? Oh! Name that means.

WORM. It is easy for you to execute.

LOUISA. I know of nothing harder than infamy!

WORM. Suppose you were to release the major from his engagement?

LOUISA. Release him! Do you mock me? Do you call that a choice to which force compelled me?

WORM. You mistake me, dear girl! The major must resign you willingly, and be the first to retract his engagement.

LOUISA. That he will never do.

WORM. So it appears. Should we, do you think, have had recourse to you were it not that you alone are able to help us?

LOUISA. I cannot compel him to hate me.

WORM. We will try! Be seated.

LOUISA (drawing back). Man! What is brooding in thy artful brain?

WORM. Be seated. Here are paper, pens, and ink. Write what I dictate.

LOUISA (sitting down in the greatest uneasiness). What must I write?To whom must I write?

WORM. To your father's executioner.

LOUISA. Ah! How well thou knowest to torture souls to thy purpose.(Takes a pen.)

WORM (dictating to her). “My dear Sir (LOUISA writes with a trembling hand.) three days, three insupportable days, have already passed-already passed-since last we met.”

LOUISA (starts, and lays down her pen). To whom is the letter?

WORM. To your father's executioner.

LOUISA. Oh! My God!

WORM. “But for this you must blame the major-the major-who watches me all day with the vigilance of an Argus.”

LOUISA (starting up). Villany! Villany beyond all precedent! To whom is the letter?

WORM. To your father's executioner.

LOUISA (paces to and fro, wringing her hands). No, no, no! This is tyrannical! Oh Heaven! If mortals provoke thee, punish them like mortals; but wherefore must I be placed between two precipices?Wherefore am I hurled by turns from death to infamy, from infamy to death? Wherefore is my neck made the footstool of this blood-sucking fiend? No; do what thou wilt, I will never write that!

WORM (seizing his hat). As you please, miss! It rests entirely on your own pleasure!

LOUISA. Pleasure, say'st thou? On my own pleasure? Go, barbarian!Suspend some unfortunate over the pit of hell; then make your demands, and ask your victim if it be his pleasure to grant your request! Oh! Thou knowest but too well that the bonds of nature bind our hearts as firmly as chains! But all is now alike indifferent.Dictate! I cease to think! Artifices of hell, I yield to ye! (She resumes her seat at the table.)

WORM. “With the vigilance of an Argus.” Have you written it?

LOUISA. Proceed, proceed!

WORM. “The president was here yesterday. It was amusing to see how warm the poor major was in defence of my honor.”

LOUISA. Excellent! Excellent! Oh! Admirable! Quick! Quick, go on!

WORM. “I had recourse to a swoon-a swoon-that I might not laugh aloud”——

LOUISA. Oh, Heavens!

WORM. “But the mask which I have worn so long is becoming insupportable-insupportable. Oh! if I could but rid myself of him.”

LOUISA (rises, and walks a few turns with her head bent down, as if she sought something upon the floor: then returns to her place, and continues to write). “Rid myself of him.”

WORM. “He will be on duty tomorrow-observe when he leaves me, and hasten to the usual place.” Have you written “the usual place”?

LOUISA. Everything, everything!

WORM. “To the usual place, to meet your devotedly attached Louisa.”

LOUISA. Now then, the address?

WORM. “To Marshal von Kalb.”

LOUISA. Eternal Providence! A name as foreign to my ear as these scandalous lines are to my heart! (She rises, and for some moments surveys the writing with a vacant gaze. At length she hands it to WORM, speaking in a voice trembling and exhausted.) Take it, Sir! What I now put into your hands is my good name. It is Ferdinand-it is the whole joy of my life! You have it, and now I am a beggar——

WORM. Oh! Not so! Despair not, dear girl! You inspire me with the most heartfelt pity! Perhaps-who knows? I might even now overlook certain parts of your conduct-yes! Heaven is my witness, how deeply I compassionate your sorrows!

LOUISA (giving him a piercing look). Do not explain yourself! You are on the point of asking something more terrible than all.

WORM (attempting to kiss her hand). What if I asked this little hand?Would that be terrible, Louisa?

LOUISA (with great indignation). Yes! For I should strangle you on the bridal night: and for such a deed I would joyfully yield my body to be torn on the rack! (She is going, but comes hurriedly back.) Is all settled between us, sir? May the dove be released?

WORM. A trifle yet remains, maiden! You must swear, by the holy sacrament, to acknowledge this letter for your free and voluntary act.

LOUISA. Oh God! Oh God! And wilt thou grant thine own seal to confirm the works of hell? (WORM leads her away.)

SCENE II.

FERDINAND (hastily reading the letter, at one moment seeming petrified with astonishment, at the next pacing the room with fury).Impossible! Quite impossible! A form so heavenly cannot hide so devilish a heart. And yet!-And yet! Though all the angels of heaven should descend on earth and proclaim her innocence-though heaven and earth, the Creator and the created, should, with one accord, vouch for her innocence-it is her hand, her own hand!Treachery, monstrous, infernal treachery, such as humanity never before witnessed! This, then, was the reason she so resolutely opposed our flight! This it was-Oh, God! Now I awake from my dream! Now the veil is lifted! This, then, is why she surrendered with so much seeming heroism her claims on my affection, and all but cheated me with her saint-like demeanor! (He traverses the chamber rapidly, and then remains for some moments in deep thought.) To fathom my heart to its very core! To reciprocate every lofty sentiment, every gentle emotion, every fiery ebullition! To sympathize with every secret breathing of my soul! To study me even in her tears! To mount with me to the sublimest heights of passion-to brave with me, undaunted, each fearful precipice! God of heaven! And was all this deceit? Mere grimace? Oh, if falsehood can assume so lovely an appearance of truth why has no devil yet lied himself back into heaven?

When I unfolded to her the dangers which threatened our affection, with what convincing artifice did the false one turn pale! With what overpowering dignity did she repulse my father's licentious scoffs! Yet at that very moment the deceiver was conscious of her guilt! Nay, did she not even undergo the fiery ordeal of truth?Forsooth, the hypocrite fainted! What must now be thy language, sensibility, since coquettes faint? How wilt thou vindicate thyself, innocence?-for even strumpets faint?

She knows her power over me-she has seen through my very heart! My soul shone conspicuous in my eyes at the blush of her first kiss. And that she should have felt nothing! Or perhaps felt only the triumph of her art; whilst my happy delirium fancied that in her I embraced a whole heaven, my wildest wishes were hushed!No thought but of her and eternity was present to my mind. Oh, God! And yet she felt nothing? Nothing? But that her artifice had triumphed! That her charms were flattered! Death and vengeance!Nothing, but that I was betrayed!

SCENE III.

FERDINAND, the MARSHAL.

MARSHAL (tripping into the room). I am told, my dear baron, that you have expressed a wish——

FERDINAND (muttering to himself). To break your rascally neck.(Aloud.) Marshal, this letter must have dropped out of your pocket on parade. (With a malicious smile.) And I have been the fortunate finder.

MARSHAL. You?

FERDINAND. By a singular coincidence! Now, balance thy account with heaven!

MARSHAL. You quite alarm me, baron!

FERDINAND. Read it, sir, read it! (Turning from him.) If I am not good enough for a lover perhaps I may do for a pimp. (While the MARSHAL reads, FERDINAND goes to the wall and takes down the pistols.)

KALB (throws the letter upon the table, and rushes off). Confusion!

FERDINAND (leads him back by the arm). Wait a little, my dear marshal! The intelligence contained in that letter appears to be agreeable! The finder must have his reward. (Showing him the pistols.)

MARSHAL (starts back in alarm). Have you lost your senses, baron?

FERDINAND (in a terrible voice). I have more than enough left to rid the world of such a scoundrel as you! Choose one of these instantly! (He forces a pistol into the MARSHAL's hand, and then draws out his handkerchief.) And now take the other end of this handkerchief! It was given me by the strumpet herself!

MARSHAL. What, shoot over the handkerchief? Baron, are you mad? What can you be thinking of?

FERDINAND. Lay hold of it, I say! Or you will be sure to miss your aim, coward! How the coward trembles! You should thank God, you pitiful coward, that you have a chance for once of getting something in your empty brain-box. (The MARSHAL takes to his heels.) Gently, gently! I'll take care of that. (Overtakes him and bolts the door.)

MARSHAL. Surely you will not fight in the chamber?

FERDINAND. As if you were worth the trouble of a walk beyond the boundaries! The report, my dear fellow, will be louder, and, for the first time, you will make some noise in the world. Now, then, take hold!

MARSHAL (wiping his forehead). Yet consider, I entreat. Would you risk your precious life, young and promising as you are, in this desperate manner?

FERDINAND. Take hold, I say! I have nothing more to do in this world!

MARSHAL. But I have much, my dearest, most excellent friend!

FERDINAND. Thou, wretch-thou? What hast thou to do, but to play the stop-gap, where honest men keep aloof! To stretch or shrink seven times in an instant, like the butterfly on a pin? To be privy registrar in chief and clerk of the jordan? To be the cap-and-bell buffoon on which your master sharpens his wit? Well, well, let it be so. I will carry you about with me, as I would a marmot of rare training. You shall skip and dance, like a tamed monkey, to the howling of the damned; fetch, carry, and serve; and with your courtly arts enliven the wailings of everlasting despair!

MARSHAL. Anything you please, dear major! Whatever you please!Only take away the pistols!

FERDINAND. How he stands there, poor trembling wretch! There he stands, a blot on the sixth day of creation. He looks as if he were a piratical counterfeit of the Almighty original. Pity, eternal pity! that an atom of brains should lie wasting in so barren a skull!That single atom bestowed upon a baboon might have made him a perfect man, whereas it is now a mere useless fragment. And that she should share her heart with a thing like this! Monstrous!Incredible! A wretch more formed to wean from sin than to excite it!

MARSHAL. Praised be Heaven! He is getting witty.

FERDINAND. I will let him live! That toleration which spares the caterpillar shall be extended to him! Men shall look on him in wonder, and, shrugging their shoulders, admire the wise dispensation of Providence, which can feed its creatures with husks and scourings; which spreads the table for the raven on the gallows, and for the courtier in the slime of majesty. We wonder at the wisdom of Providence, which even in the world of spirits maintains its staff of venomous reptiles for the dissemination of poison. (Relapsing into rage.) But such vermin shall not pollute my rose; sooner will I crush it to atoms (seizing the MARSHAL and shaking him roughly), thus-and thus-and thus——

MARSHAL. Oh! God, that I were away from here! Hundreds of miles away in the asylum for maniacs at Paris! Anywhere but near this man!

FERDINAND. Villain! If she be no longer pure! Villain! If thou hast profaned where I worshipped! (with increased fury). If thou hast polluted, where I believed myself the god! (Pausing suddenly; then in a solemn terrible voice.) It were better for thee, villain, to flee to hell, than to encounter my wrath in heaven! Confess! To what extent has your unhallowed love proceeded?

MARSHAL. Let me go! I will confess everything.

FERDINAND. Oh! It must be more rapturous even to be her licentious paramour than to burn with the purest flame for any other! Would she surrender her charms to unlicensed pleasure she might dissolve the soul itself to sin, and make voluptuousness pass for virtue(pressing his pistol against the MARSHAL's breast). To what extremities have you proceeded? Confess this instant or I fire!

MARSHAL. There is nothing at all in it, I assure you! There is not a syllable of truth in the whole business! Have but a moment's patience! You are deceived, indeed you are!

FERDINAND (furiously). And dare you remind me of that, villain? To what extremities have you proceeded? Confess, or you are a dead man!

MARSHAL. Mon Dieu! My God! You mistake my words! Only listen for a moment. When a father——

FERDINAND (still more enraged). No doubt! He threw his daughter into your arms? And how far have you proceeded? Confess, or I will murder you!

MARSHAL. You rave! You will not listen! I never saw her! I don't know her! I know nothing at all about her!

FERDINAND (drawing back). You never saw her? You don't know her? Know nothing at all about her? Louisa is lost to me forever on thy account, and yet in one breath hast thou denied her thrice. Go, wretch, go (he gives him a blow with the pistol, and thrusts him out of the chamber); powder were thrown away on such a miscreant.

[Exit MARSHAL.

SCENE IV.

FERDINAND (after a long silence, during which his countenance declares him to be agitated by some dreadful idea). Forever lost? Yes, false unfortunate, both are lost! Ay, by the Almighty God! if I am lost, thou art so too. Judge of the world, ask her not from me! She is mine. For her sake I renounced the whole world-abandoned all thy glorious creation. Leave me the maid, great Judge of the world! Millions of souls pour out their plaints to thee-turn on them thine eye of compassion, but leave me, almighty Judge-leave me to myself. (Clasping his hands in agony.) Can the bountiful, the munificent Creator be covetous of one miserable soul, and that soul the worst of his creation? The maiden is mine! Once I was her god, but now I am her devil!

(Fixes his eyes with terrible expression.)

An eternity passed with her upon the rack of everlasting perdition!Her melting eye-balls riveted on mine! Our blazing locks entwined together! Our shrieks of agony dissolving into one! And then to renew to her my vows of love, and chant unceasingly her broken oaths! God! God! The union is dreadful-and eternal! (As he is about to rush off, the PRESIDENT meets him.)

SCENE V.

FERDINAND, the PRESIDENT.

FERDINAND (starting back). Ha! My father.

PRESIDENT. I am glad to meet with you, Ferdinand! I come to bring you some pleasant news-something that will certainly surprise you, my dear son. Shall we be seated?

FERDINAND (after gazing upon him for some time with a vacant stare).My father! (Going to him with emotion, and grasping his hand.) My father! (Kissing it, and falling at his feet.) Oh, father!

PRESIDENT. What is the matter? Rise, my son. Your hand burns and trembles!

FERDINAND (wildly). Forgive my ingratitude, father! I am a lost man! I have misinterpreted your kindness! Your meaning was so truly-truly paternal! Oh! You had a prophetic soul! Now it is too late! Pardon! Pardon! Your blessing, my dear father!

PRESIDENT (feigning astonishment). Arise, my son! Recollect that your words to me are riddles!

FERDINAND. This Louisa, dear father! Oh! You understand mankind!Your anger was so just, so noble, so truly the zeal of a father! Had not its very earnestness led you to mistake the way. This Louisa!

PRESIDENT. Spare me, dear boy! Curses on my severity! Come to entreat your forgiveness——

FERDINAND. Forgiveness from me! Curse me rather. Your disapproval was wisdom! Your severity was heavenly mercy! This Louisa, father——

PRESIDENT. Is a noble, a lovely girl! I recall my too rash suspicions!She has won my entire esteem!

FERDINAND (starting up). What? You, too? Father, even you? And is she not, father, the very personification of innocence? And is it not so natural to love this maiden?

PRESIDENT. Say, rather, 'twere a crime not to love her.

FERDINAND. Incredible! Wonderful! And you, too, who can so thoroughly see through the heart! And you, who saw her faults with the eyes of hatred! Oh, unexampled hypocrisy! This Louisa, father!

PRESIDENT. Is worthy to be my daughter! Her virtues supply the want of ancestry, her beauty the want of fortune. My prudential maxims yield to the force of your attachment. Louisa shall be yours!

FERDINAND. Naught but this wanting! Father, farewell! (Rushes out of the apartment.)

PRESIDENT (following him). Stay, my son, stay! Whither do you fly?

SCENE VI.

A magnificent Saloon in LADY MILFORD's House.

Enter LADY MILFORD and SOPHIA.

LADY MILFORD. You have seen her then? Will she come?

SOPHIA. Yes, in a moment! She was in dishabille, and only requested time to change her dress.

LADY MILFORD. Speak not of her. Silence! I tremble like a criminal at the prospect of beholding that fortunate woman whose heart sympathizes thus cruelly with my own. And how did she receive my invitation?

SOPHIA. She seemed surprised, became thoughtful, fixed her eyes on me steadfastly, and for a while remained silent. I was already prepared for her excuses, when she returned me this answer with a look that quite astonished me; “tell your mistress that she commands what I myself intended to request tomorrow.”

LADY MILFORD. Leave me, Sophia! Pity me! I must blush if she is but an ordinary woman-despair if she is more!

SOPHIA. But, my lady! It is not in this spirit that a rival should be received! Remember who you are! Summon to your aid your birth, your rank, your power! A prouder soul should heighten the gorgeous splendor of your appearance.

LADY MILFORD (in a fit of absence). What is the simpleton babbling about?

SOPHIA (maliciously). Or, is it, perhaps, by chance that today, in particular, you are adorned with your most costly brilliants? By chance that you are today arrayed in your most sumptuous robes?That your antechamber is crowded with guards and pages; and that the tradesman's daughter is to be received in the most stately apartment of the palace?

LADY MILFORD (angry and nettled). This is outrageous! Insupportable!Oh that woman should have such argus-eyes for woman's weakness!How low, how irretrievably low must I have fallen when such a creature has power to fathom me!

LADY MILFORD, SOPHIA, a SERVANT.

SERVANT (entering). Ma'mselle Miller waits.

LADY MILFORD (to SOPHIA). Hence with you! Leave the room instantly! (Imperiously, as the latter hesitates.) Must I repeat my orders? (SOPHIA retires-LADY MILFORD takes a few turns hastily.) So; 'tis well that I have been excited! I am in the fitter mood for this meeting. (To the SERVANT.) Let her approach.

[Exit SERVANT. LADY MILFORD throws herself upon the sofa, and assumes a negligent but studied attitude.

SCENE VII.

LADY MILFORD, LOUISA.

LOUISA enters timidly, and remains standing at a great distance from LADY MILFORD, who has turned her back towards her, and for some time watches her attentively in the opposite looking-glass. After a pause ——

LOUISA. Noble lady, I await your commands.

LADY MILFORD (turning towards LOUISA, and making a slight and distant motion with her head.) Oh! Are you there? I presume the young lady-a certain—— Pray what is your name?

LOUISA (somewhat sensitively). My father's name is Miller. Your ladyship expressed a wish to see his daughter.

LADY MILFORD. True, true! I remember. The poor musician's daughter, of whom we were speaking the other day. (Aside, after a pause.) Very interesting, but no beauty! (To LOUISA.) Come nearer, my child. (Again aside.) Eyes well practised in weeping. Oh! How I love those eyes! (Aloud.) Nearer-come nearer! Quite close! I really think, my good child, that you are afraid of me!

LOUISA (with firmness and dignity). No, my lady-I despise the opinion of the multitude!

LADY MILFORD (aside). Well, to be sure! She has learnt this boldness from him. (To LOUISA.) You have been recommended to me, miss! I am told that you have been decently educated, and are well disposed. I can readily believe it; besides, I would not, for the world, doubt the word of so warm an advocate.

LOUISA. And yet I remember no one, my lady, who would be at the trouble to seek your ladyship's patronage for me!

LADY MILFORD (significantly). Does that imply my unworthiness, or your humility?

LOUISA. Your words are beyond my comprehension, lady.

LADY MILFORD. More cunning than I should have expected from that open countenance. (To LOUISA.) Your name is Louisa, I believe? May I inquire your age?

LOUISA. Sixteen, just turned.

LADY MILFORD (starting up). Ha! There it is! Sixteen! The first pulsation of love! The first sweet vibration upon the yet unsounded harp! Nothing is more fascinating. (To LOUISA.) Be seated, lovely girl-I am anxious about you. (To herself.) And he, too, loves for the first time! What wonder, if the ruddy morning beams should meet and blend? (To LOUISA, taking her hand affectionately.) 'Tis settled: I will make your fortune. (To herself.) Oh! There is nothing in it: nothing, but the sweet transient vision of youth! (To LOUISA, patting her on the cheek.) My Sophy is on the point of leaving me to be married: you shall have her place. But just sixteen? Oh! It can never last.

LOUISA (kissing her hand respectfully). Receive my thanks, lady, for your intended favors, and believe me not the less grateful though I may decline to accept them.

LADY MILFORD (relapsing into disdain and anger). Only hear the great lady! Girls of your station generally think themselves fortunate to obtain such promotion. What is your dependence, my dainty one? Are these fingers too delicate for work?-Or is it your pretty baby-face that makes you give yourself these airs?

LOUISA. My face, lady, is as little of my own choice as my station!

LADY MILFORD. Perhaps you believe that your beauty will last forever? Poor creature! Whoever put that into your head-be he who he may-has deceived both you and himself! The colors of those cheeks are not burnt in with fire: what your mirror passes off upon you as solid and enduring is but a slight tinselling, which, sooner or later, will rub off in the hands of the purchaser. What then, will you do?

LOUISA. Pity the purchaser, lady, who bought a diamond because it appeared to be set in gold.

LADY MILFORD (affecting not to hear her). A damsel of your age has ever two mirrors, the real one, and her admirer. The flattering complaisance of the latter counterbalances the rough honesty of the former. What the one proclaims frightful pock-marks, the other declares to be dimples that would adorn the Graces. The credulous maid believes only so much of the former as is confirmed by the latter, and hies from one to the other till she confounds their testimonies, and concludes by fancying them to be both of one opinion. Why do you stare at me so?

LOUISA. Pardon me, lady! I was just then pitying those gorgeous sparkling brilliants, which are unconscious that their possessor is so strenuous a foe to vanity.

LADY MILFORD (reddening). No evasion, miss. Were it not that you depend upon personal attractions, what in the world could induce you to reject a situation, the only one where you can acquire polish of manners and divest yourself of your plebeian prejudices?

LOUISA. And with them, I presume, my plebeian innocence!

LADY MILFORD. Preposterous objection! The most dissolute libertine dares not to disrespect our sex, unless we ourselves encourage him by advances. Prove what you are; make manifest your virtue and honor, and I will guarantee your innocence from danger.

LOUISA. Of that, lady, permit me to entertain a doubt! The palaces of certain ladies are but too often made a theatre for the most unbridled licentiousness. Who will believe that a poor musician's daughter could have the heroism to plunge into the midst of contagion and yet preserve herself untainted? Who will believe that Lady Milford would perpetually hold a scorpion to her breast, and lavish her wealth to purchase the advantage of every moment feeling her cheeks dyed with the crimson blush of shame? I will be frank, lady!-While I adorned you for some assignation, could you meet my eye unabashed? Could you endure my glance when you returned? Oh! Better, far better, would it be that oceans should roll between us-that we should inhabit different climes! Beware, my lady!-hours of temperance, moments of satiety might intrude; the gnawing worm of remorse might plant its sting in your bosom, and then what a torment would it be for you to read in the countenance of your handmaid that calm serenity with which virtue ever rewards an uncorrupted heart! (Retiring a few steps.) Once more, gracious lady, I entreat your pardon!

LADY MILFORD (extremely agitated). Insupportable, that she should tell me this! Still more insupportable, that what she tells is true!(Turning to LOUISA, and looking at her steadfastly.) Girl! Girl!This artifice does not blind me. Mere opinions do not speak out so warmly. Beneath the cloak of these sentiments lurks some far dearer interest. 'Tis that which makes my service particularly distasteful-which gives such energy to your language. (In a threatening voice.) What it is I am determined to discover.

LOUISA (with calm dignity). And what if you do discover it? Suppose the contemptuous trampling of your foot should rouse the injured worm, which its Creator has furnished with a sting to protect it against misusage. I fear not your vengeance, lady! The poor criminal extended on the rack can look unappalled even on the dissolution of the world. My misery is so exquisite that even sincerity cannot draw down upon me any further infliction! (After a pause.) You say that you would raise me from the obscurity of my station. I will not examine the motives of this suspicious favor.I will only ask, what could induce you to think me so foolish as to blush at my station? What could induce you to become the architect of my happiness, before you knew whether I was willing to receive that happiness at your hands? I had forever renounced all claims upon the pleasures of the world. I had forgiven fortune that she had dealt with me so niggardly. Ah! Why do you remind me of all this. If the Almighty himself hides his glory from the eyes of his creatures, lest the highest seraph should be overwhelmed by a sense of his own insignificance, why should mortals be so cruelly compassionate? Lady, lady! Why is your vaunted happiness so anxious to excite the envy and wonder of the wretched? Does your bliss stand in need of the exhibition of despair for entertainment?Oh! Rather grant me that blindness which alone can reconcile me to my barbarous lot! The insect feels itself as happy in a drop of water as though that drop was a paradise: so happy, and so contented! till some one tells it of a world of water, where navies ride and whales disport themselves! But you wish to make me happy, say you? (After a pause, she advances towards LADY MILFORD, and asks her suddenly.) Are you happy, lady? (LADY MILFORD turns from her hastily, and overpowered. LOUISA follows her, and lays her hand upon her bosom.) Does this heart wear the smile of its station? Could we now exchange breast for breast, and fate for fate-were I, in childlike innocence, to ask you on your conscience-were I to ask you as a mother- would you really counsel me to make the exchange?

LADY MILFORD (greatly excited, throwing herself on the sofa).Intolerable! Incomprehensible! No, Louisa, no! This greatness of thought is not your own, and your conceptions are too fiery, too full of youth, to be inspired by your father. Deceive me not! I detect another teacher——

LOUISA (looking piercingly at her). I cannot but wonder, my lady, that you should have only just discovered that other teacher, and yet have previously shown so much anxiety to patronize me!

LADY MILFORD (starting up). 'Tis not to be borne! Well, then, since I cannot escape you, I know him-know everything-know more than I wish to know! (Suddenly restraining herself, then continuing with a violence which by degrees increases to frenzy.) But dare, unhappy one!-Dare but still to love, or be beloved by him! What did I say? Dare but to think of him, or to be one of his thoughts! I am powerful, unhappy one!- Dreadful in my vengeance! As sure as there is a God in heaven thou art lost forever!

LOUISA (undaunted). Past all redemption, my lady, the moment you succeed in compelling him to love you!

LADY MILFORD. I understand you-but I care not for his love! I will conquer this disgraceful passion. I will torture my own heart; but thine will I crush to atoms! Rocks and chasms will I hurl between you. I will rush, like a fury, into the heaven of your joys. My name shall affright your loves as a spectre scares an assassin. That young and blooming form in his embrace shall wither to a skeleton. I cannot be blest with him- neither shalt thou. Know, wretched girl;that to blast the happiness of others is in itself a happiness!

LOUISA. A happiness, my lady, which is already beyond your reach!Seek not to deceive your own heart! You are incapable of executing what you threaten! You are incapable of torturing a being who has done you no wrong-but whose misfortune it is that her feelings have been sensible to impressions like your own. But I love you for these transports, my lady!

LADY MILFORD (recovering herself). Where am I? What have I done? What sentiments have I betrayed? To whom have I betrayed them? Oh, Louisa, noble, great, divine soul, forgive the ravings of a maniac! Fear not, my child! I will not injure a hair of thy head!Name thy wishes! Ask what thou wilt! I will serve thee with all my power; I will be thy friend- thy sister! Thou art poor; look (taking off her brilliants), I will sell these jewels-sell my wardrobe-my carriages and horses-all shall be thine-grant me but Ferdinand!

LOUISA (draws back indignantly). Does she mock my despair?-Or is she really innocent of participation in that cruel deed? Ha!Then I may yet assume the heroine, and make my surrender of him pass for a sacrifice! (Remains for a while absorbed in thought, then approaches LADY MILFORD, seizes her hand, and gazes on her with a fixed and significant look.) Take him, lady! I here voluntarily resign the man whom hellish arts have torn from my bleeding bosom! Perchance you know it not, my lady! but you have destroyed the paradise of two lovers; you have torn asunder two hearts which God had linked together; you have crushed a creature not less dear to him than yourself, and no less created for happiness; one by whom he was worshipped as sincerely as by you;but who, henceforth, will worship him no more. But the Almighty is ever open to receive the last groan of the trampled worm. He will not look on with indifference when creatures in his keeping are murdered. Now Ferdinand is yours. Take him, lady, take him! Rush into his arms! Drag him with you to the altar! But forget not that the spectre of a suicide will rush between you and the bridal kiss. God be merciful! No choice is left me! (Rushes out of the chamber.)

SCENE VIII.

LADY MILFORD alone, in extreme agitation, gazing on the door by which LOUISA left. At length she recovers from her stupor.

LADY MILFORD. What was that? What preys so on my heart? What said the unhappy one? Still, O heaven, the dreadful, damning words ring in my ears! “Take him! Take him!” What should I take, unfortunate? The bequest of your dying groan-the fearful legacy of your despair? Gracious heaven! Am I then fallen so low? Am I so suddenly hurled from the towering throne of my pride that I greedily await what a beggar's generosity may throw me in the last struggle of death? “Take him! Take him!” And with what a tone was it uttered!-With what a look! What! Amelia! Is it for this thou hast overleaped the bounds of thy sex? For this didst thou vaunt the glorious title of a free-born Briton, that thy boasted edifice of honor might sink before the nobler soul of a despised and lowly maiden? No, proud unfortunate! No! Amelia Milford may blush for shame-but shall never be despised. I, too, have courage to resign. (She walks a few paces with a majestic gait.) Hide thyself, weak, suffering woman! Hence, ye sweet and golden dreams of love! Magnanimity alone be now my guide. These lovers are lost, or Amelia must withdraw her claim, and renounce the prince's heart. (After a pause, with animation.) It is determined! The dreadful obstacle is removed-broken are the bonds which bound me to the duke-torn from my bosom this raging passion. Virtue, into thy arms I throw myself. Receive thy repentant daughter.Ha! How happy do I feel! How suddenly relieved my heart, and how exalted! Glorious as the setting sun, will I this day descend from the pinnacle of my greatness; my grandeur shall expire with my love, and my own heart be the only sharer of my proud exile!(Going to her writing-table with a determined air.) It must be done at once-now, on the spot-before the recollection of Ferdinand renews the cruel conflict in my bosom! (She seats herself, and begins to write).

SCENE IX.

LADY MILFORD, an ATTENDANT, SOPHIA, afterwards the MARSHAL, and then SERVANTS.

SERVANT. Marshal von Kalb is in the ante-chamber, and brings a message from his highness.

LADY MILFORD (not hearing him in the eagerness of writing). How the illustrious puppet will stare! The idea is singular enough, I own, the presuming to astonish his serene numskull. In what confusion will his court be thrown! The whole country will be in a ferment.

SERVANT and SOPHIA. Marshal von Kalb, my lady!

LADY MILFORD (turning round). Who? The marshal? So much the better! Such creatures were designed by nature to carry the ass'panniers.

[Exit SERVANT.

SOPHIA (approaching anxiously). If I were not fearful, my lady, that you would think it presumption. (LADY MILFORD continuing to write eagerly.) Louisa Miller rushed madly to the hall-you are agitated-you speak to yourself. (LADY MILFORD continues writing.) I am quite alarmed. What can have happened? (The MARSHAL enters, making repeated bows at LADY MILFORD's back; as she takes no notice of him, he comes nearer, stands behind her chair, touches the hem of her dress, and imprints a kiss on it, saying in a tremulous voice.) His serene highness——

LADY MILFORD (while she peruses hastily what she has written). He will tax me with black ingratitude! “I was poor and forsaken! He raised me from misery! From misery.” Detestable exchange! Annul my bond, seducer! The blush of my eternal shame repays my debt with interest.

MARSHAL (after endeavoring in vain to catch her eye). Your ladyship seems somewhat absent. I take the liberty of permitting myself the boldness (very loud)-his serene highness, my lady, has sent me to inquire whether you mean to honor this evening's gala with your presence, or the theatre?

LADY MILFORD (rising, with a laugh). One or the other, sweet sir.In the meantime take this paper to your duke for his dessert. (To SOPHIA.) Do you, Sophia, give directions to have my carriage brought to the door without delay, and call my whole household together in this saloon.

SOPHIA (goes out in great astonishment). Heavens! What do I forebode? What will this end in?

MARSHAL. You seem excited, my lady!

LADY MILFORD. The greater the chance of my letting you into a little truth. Rejoice, my Lord Marshal! There is a place vacant at court. A fine time for panders. (As the MARSHAL throws a look of suspicion upon the paper.) Read it, read it! 'Tis my desire that the contents should be made public. (While he reads it, the domestics enter, and range themselves in the background.)

MARSHAL (reading). “Your highness-an engagement, broken by you so lightly, can no longer be binding on me. The happiness of your subjects was the condition of my love. For three years the deception has lasted. The veil at length falls from my eyes! I look with disgust on favors which are stained with the tears of your subjects. Bestow the love which I can no longer accept upon your weeping country, and learn from a British princess compassion to your German people. Within an hour I shall have quitted your dominions. JOANNA NORFOLK”

SERVANTS (exclaiming to each other in astonishment). Quitted the dominions!

MARSHAL (replaces the letter upon the table in terror). God forbid, my dear and most excellent lady! The bearer of such a letter would be as mad as the writer!

LADY MILFORD. That is your concern, you pink of a courtier! Alas!I am sorry to know that you, and such as you, would choke even in the utterance of what others dare to do. My advice is that you bake the letter in a venison pasty, so that his most serene highness may find it on his plate!

MARSHAL. God preserve me! What presumption! Ponder well, I entreat you. Reflect on the disgrace which you will bring down upon yourself, my lady!

LADY MILFORD (turning to the assembled domestics, and addressing them in the deepest emotion). You seem amazed, good people; and anxiously awaiting the solution of this riddle? Draw nearer, my friends! You have served me truly and affectionately; have looked into my eyes rather than my purse. My pleasure was your study, my approbation your pride! Woe is me, that the remembrance of your fidelity must be the record of my unworthiness! Unhappy fate, that the darkest season of my life should have been the brightest of yours! (Her eyes suffused with tears.) We must part, my children.Lady Milford has ceased to exist, and Joanna of Norfolk is too poor to repay your love. What little wealth I have my treasurer will share among you. This palace belongs to the duke. The poorest of you will quit it far richer than his mistress! Farewell, my children!(She extends her hand, which they all in turn kiss, with marks of sorrow and affection.) I understand you, my good people! Farewell!Forever farewell! (Struggling with her feelings.) I hear the carriage at the door. (She tears herself away, and is hurrying out when the MARSHAL arrests her progress.) How, now? Pitiful creature, art thou still there?

MARSHAL (who all this while has been gazing in vacant astonishment at the letter). And must I be the person to put this letter into the most august hands of his most serene highness?

LADY MILFORD. Pitiful creature, even thou! Thou must deliver into his most august hands, and convey to his most august ears, that, as I cannot go barefoot to Loretto, I will support myself by the labor of my hands, that I may be purified from the disgrace of having condescended to rule him. (She hurries off-the rest silently disperse.)

SCENE I.

Twilight; a room in MILLER's house.

LOUISA sits silent and motionless in a dark corner of the room, her head reclining upon her hand. After a long pause, MILLER enters with a lantern, the light of which he casts anxiously round the chamber, without observing LOUISA, he then puts his hat on the table, and sets down the lantern.

LOUISA, MILLER.

MILLER. She is not here either. No, she is not here! I have wandered through every street; I have sought her with every acquaintance; I have inquired at every door! No one has seen my child! (A silence of some moments.) Patience, poor unhappy father! Patience till morning; then perhaps the corpse of your only one may come floating to shore. Oh, God in heaven! What though my heart has hung too idolatrously upon this daughter, yet surely the punishment is severe! Heavenly Father! Surely it is severe! I will not murmur, Heavenly Father; but the punishment is indeed severe! (Throws himself sorrowfully into a chair.)

LOUISA (without moving from her seat). Thou dost well, wretched old man! Learn betimes to lose.

MILLER (starts up eagerly). Ah! Art thou there, my child? Art thou there? But wherefore thus alone, and without a light?

LOUISA. Yet am I not alone. When all things around me are dark and gloomy then have I the companionship which most I love.

MILLER. God defend thee, my child! The worm of conscience alone wakes and watches with the owl; none shun the light but criminals and evil spirits.

LOUISA. And eternity, father, which speaks to the soul in solitude!

MILLER. Louisa, my child! What words are these?

LOUISA (rises, and comes forward). I have fought a hard fight-you know it, father! But God gave me the strength! The fight is over!Father, our sex is called timid and weak; believe it no more! We tremble at a spider, but the black monster, corruption, we hug to our arms in sport! This for your edification, father. Your Louisa is merry.

MILLER. I had rather you wept. It would, please me better.

LOUISA. How I will outwit him, father! How I shall cheat the tyrant!Love is more crafty than malice, and bolder-he knew not that, the man of the unlucky star! Oh! They are cunning so long as they have but to do with the head; but when they have to grapple with the heart the villains are at fault. He thought to seal his treachery with an oath! Oaths, father, may bind the living, but death dissolves even the iron bonds of the sacrament! Ferdinand will learn to know his Louisa. Father, will you deliver this letter for me? Will you do me the kindness?

MILLER. To whom, my child?

LOUISA. Strange question! Infinitude and my heart together had not space enough for a single thought but of him. To whom else should I write?

MILLER (anxiously). Hear me, Louisa! I must read this letter!

LOUISA. As you please, father! But you will not understand it. The characters lie there like inanimate corpses, and live but for the eye of love.

MILLER (reading). “You are betrayed, Ferdinand! An unparalleled piece of villany has dissolved the union of our hearts; but a dreadful vow binds my tongue, and your father has spies stationed upon every side. But, if thou hast courage, my beloved, I know a place where oaths no longer bind, and where spies cannot enter.”(MILLER stops short, and gazes upon her steadfastly.)

LOUISA. Why that earnest look, father? Read what follows.

MILLER. “But thou must be fearless enough to wander through a gloomy path with no other guides than God and thy Louisa. Thou must have no companion but love; leave behind all thy hopes, all thy tumultuous wishes-thou wilt need nothing on this journey but thy heart. Darest thou come; then set out as the bell tolls twelve from the Carmelite Tower. Dost thou fear; then erase from the vocabulary of thy sex's virtues the word courage, for a maiden will have put thee to shame.” (MILLER lays down the letter and fixes his eyes upon the ground in deep sorrow. At length he turns to LOUISA, and says, in a low, broken voice) Daughter, where is that place?

LOUISA. Don't you know it, father? Do you really not know it? 'Tis strange! I have described it unmistakably! Ferdinand will not fail to find it.

MILLER. Pray speak plainer!

LOUISA. I can think of no pleasing name for it just now! You must not be alarmed, father, if the name I give it has a terrible sound. That place——Oh! Why has no lover invented a name for it! He would have chosen the softest, the sweetest-that place, my dear father-but you must not interrupt me-that place is-the grave!

MILLER (staggering to a seat). Oh, God!

LOUISA (hastens to him, and supports him). Nay, father, be not alarmed! These are but terrors which hover round an empty word!Take away the name and the grave will seem to be a bridal-bed over which Aurora spreads her golden canopy and spring strews her fairest flowers. None but a groaning sinner pictures death as a skeleton; to others he is a gentle, smiling boy, blooming as the god of love, but not so false-a silent, ministering spirit who guides the exhausted pilgrim through the desert of eternity, unlocks for him the fairy palace of everlasting joy, invites him in with friendly smiles, and vanishes forever!

MILLER. What meanest thou, my child? Surely, thou wilt not lay guilty hands on thine own life?

LOUISA. Speak not thus, father! To quit a community from which I am already rejected, to fly voluntarily to a place from which I cannot much longer be absent, is that a sin?

MILLER. Suicide is the most horrible of sins, my child. 'Tis the only one that can never he repented, since death arrives at the moment the crime is committed.

LOUISA (stands motionless with horror). That is dreadful! But my death will not be so sudden, father. I will spring into the river, and while the waters are closing over me, cry to the Almighty for mercy and forgiveness!

MILLER. That is to say, you will repent the theft as soon as the treasure is secure! Daughter! Daughter! Beware how you mock your God when you most need his help! Oh! You have gone far, far astray! You have forgotten the worship of your Creator, and he has withdrawn his protecting hand from you!LOUISA. Is it, then, a crime to love, father?

MILLER. So long as thou lovest God thou wilt never love man to idolatry. Thou hast bowed me down low, my only one! Low! Very low! Perhaps to the grave! Yet will I not increase the sadness of thy heart. Daughter! I gave vent to my feelings as I entered. I thought myself alone! Thou hast overheard me! And why should I longer conceal the truth. Thou wert my idol! Hear me, Louisa, if there is yet room in thy heart for a father's feelings. Thou wert my all!Of thine own thou hast nothing more to lose, but I have my all at stake! My life depends on thee! My hairs are turning gray, Louisa;they show that the time is drawing nigh with me when fathers look for a return of the capital invested in the hearts of their children.Wilt thou defraud me of this, Louisa? Wilt thou away and bear with thee all the wealth of thy father?

LOUISA (kissing his hand in the deepest emotion). No, father, no! I go from this world deeply in your debt, and will repay you with usury in the world to come.

MILLER. Beware, my child, lest thy reckoning should be false! (very earnestly and solemnly). Art thou certain that we shall meet in that world to come? Lo! How the color fades from thy cheek! My child must feel that I can scarcely overtake her in that other world if she hurries there before me. (LOUISA throws herself shuddering into his arms, he clasps her warmly to his bosom, and continues in a tone of fervent adjuration.) Oh! Louisa! Louisa! Fallen, perhaps already lost, daughter! Treasure in thy heart the solemn counsels of a father! I cannot eternally watch over thee! I may snatch the dagger from thy hands; but thou canst let out life with a bodkin. I may remove poison from thy reach; but thou canst strangle thyself with a necklace. Louisa! Louisa! I can only warn thee. Wilt thou rush boldly forward till the perfidious phantom which lured thee on vanishes at the awful brink of eternity? Wilt thou dare approach the throne of the Omniscient with the lie on thy lips? “At thy call am I here, Creator!” While thy guilty eyes are in search only of their mortal idol! And when thou shalt see this perishable god of thine own creation, a worm like thee, writhing at the Almighty's feet; when thou shalt hear him in the awful moment give the lie to thy guilty daring, and blast thy delusive hopes of eternal mercy, which the wretch implores in vain for himself; what then! (Louder and more fervently.) What, then, unhappy one? (He clasps her still closer to his bosom, and gazes upon her with wild and piercing looks; then suddenly disengages himself.) I can do no more! (Raising his right hand towards heaven.) Immortal Judge, I can do no more to save this soul from ruin! Louisa, do what thou wilt. Offer up a sacrifice at the altar of this idolized youth that shall make thy evil genius howl for transport and thy good angels forsake thee in despair. Go on! Heap sin upon sin-add to them this, the last, the heaviest-and, if the scale be still too light throw in my curse to complete the measure. Here is a knife; pierce thy own heart, and(weeping aloud and rushing away), and with it, thy father's!

LOUISA (following and detaining him). Stay! Stay! Oh! Father, father!-To think that affection should wound more cruelly than a tyrant's rage! What shall I?-I cannot!-What must I do?

MILLER. If thy lover's kisses burn hotter than thy father's tears-then die!

LOUISA (after a violent internal struggle, firmly). Father! Here is my hand! I will-God! God! What am I doing! What would I?-Father, I swear. Woe is me! Criminal that I am where'er I turn! Father, be it so! Ferdinand. God, look down upon the act! Thus I destroy the last memorial of him. (Tearing the letter.)

MILLER (throwing himself in ecstasy upon her neck). There spoke my daughter! Look up, my child! Thou hast lost a lover, but thou hast made a father happy. (Embracing her, and alternately laughing and crying.) My child! My child! I was not worthy to live so blest a moment! God knows how I, poor miserable sinner, became possessed of such an angel! My Louisa! My paradise! Oh! I know but little of love; but that to rend its bonds must be a bitter grief I can well believe!

LOUISA. But let us hasten from this place, my father! Let us fly from the city, where my companions scoff at me, and my good name is lost forever-let us away, far away, from a spot where every object tells of my ruined happiness-let us fly if it be possible!

MILLER. Whither thou wilt, my daughter! The bread of the Lord grows everywhere, and he will grant ears to listen to my music.Yes! We will fly and leave all behind. I will set the story of your sorrows to the lute, and sing of the daughter who rent her own heart to preserve her father's. We will beg with the ballad from door to door, and sweet will be the alms bestowed by the hand of weeping sympathy!

SCENE II.

The former; FERDINAND.

LOUISA (who perceives him first, throws herself shrieking into MILLER's arms). God! There he is! I am lost!

MILLER. Who? Where?

LOUISA (points, with averted face, to the MAJOR, and presses closer to her father). 'Tis he! 'Tis he! Himself! Look round, father, look round!-He comes to murder me!

MILLER (perceives him and starts back). How, baron? You here?

FERDINAND (approaches slowly, stands opposite to LOUISA, and fixes a stern and piercing look upon her. After a pause, he says). Stricken conscience, I thank thee! Thy confession is dreadful, but swift and true, and spares me the torment of an explanation! Good evening, Miller!

MILLER. For God's sake! Baron, what seek you? What brings you hither? What means this surprise?

FERDINAND. I knew a time when the day was divided into seconds, when eagerness for my presence hung upon the weights of the tardy clock, and when every pulse-throb was counted until the moment of my coming. How is it that I now surprise?

MILLER. Oh, leave us, leave us, baron! If but one spark of humanity still linger in your bosom; -if you seek not utterly to destroy her whom you profess to love, fly from this house, stay not one moment longer. The blessing of God deserted us when your foot first crossed its threshold. You have brought misery under a roof where all before was joy and happiness. Are you not yet content?Do you seek to deepen the wound which your fatal passion has planted in the heart of my only child?

FERDINAND. Strange father, I have come to bring joyful tidings to your daughter.

MILLER. Perchance fresh hopes, to add to her despair. Away, away, thou messenger of ill! Thy looks belie thy words.

FERDINAND. At length the goal of my hopes appears in view! Lady Milford, the most fearful obstacle to our love, has this moment fled the land. My father sanctions my choice. Fate grows weary of persecuting us, and our propitious stars now blaze in the ascendant-I am come to fulfil my plighted troth, and to lead my bride to the altar.

MILLER. Dost thou hear him, my child? Dost thou hear him mock at thy cheated hopes? Oh, truly, baron! It is so worthy of the deceiver to make a jest of his own crime!

FERDINAND. You think I am jesting? By my honor I am not! My protestations are as true as the love of my Louisa, and I will keep them as sacred as she has kept her oaths. Nothing to me is more sacred. Can you still doubt? Still no joyful blush upon the cheek of my fair bride? 'Tis strange! Falsehood must needs be here the current coin, since truth finds so little credit. You mistrust my words, it seems? Then read this written testimony. (He throws LOUISA her letter to the MARSHAL. She opens it, and sinks upon the floor pale as death.)

MILLER (not observing this). What can this mean, baron? I do not understand you.

FERDINAND. (leads him to LOUISA). But your daughter has understood me well.

MILLER (throws himself on his knees beside her). Oh, God! My child!

FERDINAND. Pale as a corpse! 'Tis thus your daughter pleases me the best. Your demure and virtuous daughter was never half so lovely as with that deathlike paleness. The blast of the day of judgment, which strips the varnish from every lie, has wafted the painted colors from her cheek, or the juggler might have cheated even the angels of light. This is her fairest countenance. Now for the first time do I see it in its truth. Let me kiss it. (He approaches her.)

MILLER. Back! Away, boy! Trifle not with a father's feelings. I could not defend her from your caresses, but I can from your insults.

FERDINAND. What wouldst thou, old man? With thee I have naught to do. Engage not in a game so irrevocably lost. Or hast thou, too, been wiser than I thought? Hast thou employed the wisdom of thy sixty years in pandering to thy daughter's amours, and disgraced those hoary locks with the office of a pimp? Oh! if it be not so, wretched old man, then lay thyself down and die. There is still time. Thou mayest breathe by last in the sweet delusion, “I was a happy father!” Wait but a moment longer and thine own hand will dash to her infernal home this poisonous viper; thou wilt curse the gift, and him who gave it, and sink to the grave in blasphemy and despair. (To LOUISA.) Speak, wretched one, speak! Didst thou write this letter?

MILLER (to LOUISA, impressively). For God's sake, daughter, forget not! Forget not!

LOUISA. Oh, father-that letter!

FERDINAND. Oh! That it should have fallen into the wrong hands.Now blessed be the accident! It has effected more than the most consummate prudence, and will at the day of judgment avail more than the united wisdom of sages. Accident, did I say? Oh!Providence directs, when a sparrow falls, why not when a devil is unmasked? But I will be answered! Didst thou write that letter?

MILLER (to LOUISA, in a tone of entreaty). Be firm, my child, be firm!But a single “Yes,” and all will be over.

FERDINAND. Excellent! Excellent! The father, too, is deceived! All, all are deceived by her! Look, how the perfidious one stands there;even her tongue refuses participation in her last lie. I adjure thee by that God so terrible and true-didst thou write that letter?

LOUISA (after a painful struggle, with firmness and decision). I did!

FERDINAND (stands aghast). No! As my soul liveth, thou hast lied.Even innocence itself, when extended on the rack, confesses crime which it never committed-I ask too passionately. Is it not so, Louisa? Thou didst but confess, because I asked passionately?

LOUISA. I confessed the truth!

FERDINAND. No, I tell thee! No! No! Thou didst not write that letter! It is not like thy hand! And, even though it were, why should it be more difficult to counterfeit a writing than to undo a heart? Tell me truly, Louisa! Yet no, no, do not! Thou mightest say yes again, and then I were lost forever. A lie, Louisa! A lie! Oh! If thou didst but know one now-if thou wouldst utter it with that open angelic mien-if thou wouldst but persuade mine ear and eye, though it should deceive my heart ever so monstrously! Oh, Louisa! Then might truth depart in the same breath-depart from our creation, and the sacred cause itself henceforth bow her stiff neck to the courtly arts of deception.

LOUISA. By the Almighty God! By Him who is so terrible and true! I did!

FERDINAND (after a pause, with the expression of the most heartfelt sorrow). Woman! Woman! With what a face thou standest now before me! Offer Paradise with that look, and even in the regions of the damned thou wilt find no purchaser. Didst thou know what thou wert to me, Louisa? Impossible! No! Thou knewest not that thou wert my all-all! 'Tis a poor insignificant word! But eternity itself can scarcely circumscribe it. Within it systems of worlds can roll their mighty orbs. All! And to sport with it so wickedly. Oh,'tis horrible.

LOUISA. Baron von Walter, you have heard my confession! I have pronounced my own condemnation! Now go! Fly from a house where you have been so unhappy.

FERDINAND. 'Tis well! 'Tis well! You see I am calm; calm, too, they say, is the shuddering land through which the plague has swept.I am calm. Yet ere I go, Louisa, one more request! It shall be my last. My brain burns with fever! I need refreshment! Will you make me some lemonade?

[Exit LOUISA.

SCENE III.

FERDINAND and MILLER.

They both pace up and down without speaking, on opposite sides of the room, for some minutes.

MILLER (standing still at length, and regarding the MAJOR with a sorrowful air). Dear baron, perhaps it may alleviate your distress to say that I feel for you most deeply.

FERDINAND. Enough of this, Miller. (Silence again for some moments.) Miller, I forget what first brought me to your house.What was the occasion of it?

MILLER. How, baron? Don't you remember? You came to take lessons on the flute.

FERDINAND (suddenly). And I beheld his daughter! (Another pause.)You have not kept your faith with me, friend! You were to provide me with repose for my leisure hours; but you betrayed me and sold me scorpions. (Observing MILLER's agitation.) Tremble not, good old man! (falling deeply affected on his neck)-The fault was none of thine!

MILLER (wiping his eyes). Heaven knows, it was not!

FERDINAND (traversing the room, plunged in the most gloomy meditation). Strange! Oh! Beyond conception strange, are the Almighty's dealings with us! How often do terrific weights hang upon slender, almost invisible threads! Did man but know that he should eat death in a particular apple! Hem! Could he but know that! (He walks a few more turns; then stops suddenly, and grasps MILLER's hand with strong emotion.) Friend, I have paid dearly for thy lessons-and thou, too, hast been no gainer- perhaps mayst even lose thy all. (Quitting him dejectedly.) Unhappy flute-playing, would that it never entered my brain!

MILLER (striving to repress his feelings). The lemonade is long in coming. I will inquire after it, if you will excuse me.

FERDINAND. No hurry, dear Miller! (Muttering to himself.) At least to her father there is none. Stay here a moment. What was I about to ask you? Ay, I remember! Is Louisa your only daughter? Have you no other child?

MILLER (warmly). I have no other, baron, and I wish for no other. That child is my only solace in this world, and on her have I embarked my whole stock of affection.

FERDINAND (much agitated). Ha! Pray see for the drink, good Miller![Exit MILLER.

SCENE IV.

FERDINAND alone.

FERDINAND. His only child! Dost thou feel that, murderer? His only one! Murderer, didst thou hear, his only one? The man has nothing in God's wide world but his instrument and that only daughter!And wilt thou rob him of her?

Rob Him? Rob a beggar of his last pittance? Break the lame man's crutch, and cast the fragments at his feet? How? Have I the heart to do this? And when he hastens home, impatient to reckon in his daughter's smiles the whole sum of his happiness; and when he enters the chamber, and there lies the rose-withered-dead-crushed-his last, his only, his sustaining hope. Ha! And when he stands before her, and all nature looks on in breathless horror, while his vacant eye wanders hopelessly through the gloom of futurity, and seeks God, but finds him nowhere, and then returns disappointed and despairing! Great God! And has not my father, too, an only son? An only child, but not his only treasure. (After a pause.) Yet stay! What will the old man lose? She who could wantonly jest with the most sacred feelings of love, will she make a father happy? She cannot! She will not! And I deserve thanks for crushing this viper ere the parent feels its sting.

SCENE V.

MILLER returning, and FERDINAND.

MILLER. You shall be served instantly, baron! The poor thing is sitting without, weeping as though her heart would break! Your drink will be mingled with her tears.

FERDINAND. 'Twere well for her were it only with tears! We were speaking of my lessons, Miller. (Taking out a purse.) I remember that I am still in your debt.

MILLER. How? What? Go along with you, baron! What do you take me for? There is time enough for payment. Do not put such an affront on me; we are not together for the last time, please God.

FERDINAND. Who can tell? Take your money. It is for life or death.

MILLER (laughing). Oh! For the matter of that, baron! As regards that I don't think I should run much risk with you!

FERDINAND. You would run the greatest. Have you never heard that youths have died. That damsels and youths have died, the children of hope, the airy castles of their disappointed parents? What is safe from age and worms has often perished by a thunderbolt. Even your Louisa is not immortal.

MILLER. God gave her to me.

FERDINAND. Hear me! I say to you your Louisa is not immortal. That daughter is the apple of your eye; you hang upon her with your whole heart and soul. Be prudent, Miller! None but a desperate gamester stakes his all upon a single cast. The merchant would be called a madman who embarked his whole fortune in one ship.Think upon this, and remember that I warned you. But why do you not take your money?

MILLER. How, baron, how? All that enormous purse? What can you be thinking of?

FERDINAND. Upon my debt! There! (Throws a heavy purse on the table; some gold drops out.) I cannot hold the dross to eternity.

MILLER (astonished). Mercy on us! What is this? The sound was not of silver! (Goes to the table and cries out in astonishment.) In heaven's name, baron, what means this? What are you about? You must be out of your mind! (Clasping his hands.) There it lies! Or I am bewitched. 'Tis damnable! I feel it now; the beauteous, shining, glorious heap of gold! No, Satan, thou shalt not catch my soul with this!

FERDINAND. Have you drunk old wine, or new, Miller?

MILLER (violently). Death and furies! Look yourself, then. It is gold!FERDINAND. And what of that?

MILLER. Let me implore you, baron! In the name of all the saints in heaven, I entreat you! It is gold!

FERDINAND. An extraordinary thing, it must be admitted.

MILLER (after a pause; addressing him with emotion). Noble sir, I am a plain, straightforward man-do you wish to tempt me to some piece of knavery?-For, heaven knows, that so much gold cannot be got honestly!

FERDINAND (moved). Make yourself quite easy, dear Miller! You have well earned the money. God forbid that I should use it to the corruption of your conscience!

MILLER (jumping about like a madman). It is mine, then! Mine indeed! Mine with the knowledge and consent of God! (Hastening to the door.) Daughter, wife, hurrah, come hither! (Returning.)But, for heaven's sake, how have I all at once deserved this awful treasure? How am I to earn it? How repay it, eh?

FERDINAND. Not by your music lessons, Miller! With this gold do I pay you for (stops suddenly, and shudders)-I pay you-(after a pause, with emotion)-for my three months' unhappy dream of your daughter!

MILLER (taking his hand and pressing it affectionately). Most gracious sir! Were you some poor and low-born citizen, and my daughter refused your love, I would pierce her heart with my own hands. (Returning to the gold in a sorrowful tone.) But then I shall have all, and you nothing- and I should have to give up all this glorious heap again, eh?

FERDINAND. Let not that thought distress you, friend. I am about to quit this country, and in that to which I am journeying such coin is not current.

MILLER (still fixing his eyes in transport on the money). Mine, then, it remains? Mine? Yet it grieves me that you are going to leave us. Only just wait a little and you shall see how I'll come out! I'll hold up my head with the best of them. (Puts on his hat with an air, and struts up and down the room.) I'll give my lessons in the great concert-room, and won't I smoke away at the best puyke varinas-and, when you catch me again fiddling at the penny-hop, may the devil take me!

FERDINAND. Stay, Miller! Be silent, and gather up your gold.(Mysteriously.) Keep silence only for this one evening, and do me the favor henceforward to give no more music lessons.

MILLER (still more vehemently grasping his hand, full of inward joy).And my daughter, baron! My daughter! (Letting go.) No, no!Money does not make the man-whether I feed on vegetables or on partridges, enough is enough, and this coat will do very well as long as the sunbeams don't peep in at the elbows. To me money is mere dross. But my girl shall benefit by the blessing; whatever wish I can read in her eyes shall be gratified.

FERDINAND (suddenly interrupting him). Oh! Silence! Silence!

MILLER (still more warmly). And she shall learn to speak French like a born native, and to dance minuets, and to sing, so that people shall read of her in the newspapers; and she shall wear a cap like the judge's daughter, and a kidebarri [meaning, no doubt, Cul de Paris, a bustle], as they call it; and the fiddler's daughter shall be talked of for twenty miles round.

FERDINAND. (seizing his hand in extreme agitation). No more! No more! For God's sake be silent! Be silent but for this one night; 'tis the only favor I ask of you.

SCENE VI.

LOUISA with a glass of lemonade; the former.

LOUISA (her eyes swelled with weeping, and trembling voice, while she presents the glass to FERDINAND). Tell me, if it be not to your taste.

FERDINAND (takes the glass, places it on the table, and turns to MILLER). Oh! I had almost forgotten! Good Miller, I have a request to make. Will you do me a little favor?

MILLER. A thousand with pleasure! What are your commands?

FERDINAND. My father will expect me at table. Unfortunately I am in very ill humor. 'Twould be insupportable to me just now to mix in society. Will you go to my father and excuse my absence?

LOUISA (terrified, interrupts him hastily). Oh, let me go!

MILLER. Am I to see the president himself?

FERDINAND. Not himself. Give your message to one of the servants in the ante-chamber. Here is my watch as a credential that I sent you. I shall be here when you return. You will wait for an answer.

LOUISA (very anxiously). Cannot I be the bearer of your message?

FERDINAND (to MILLER, who is going). Stay-one thing more! Here is a letter to my father, which I received this evening enclosed in one to myself. Perhaps on business of importance. You may as well deliver it at the same time.

MILLER (going). Very well, baron!

LOUISA (stopping him, and speaking in a tone of the most exquisite terror). But, dear father, I could do all this very well! Pray let me go!

MILLER. It is night, my child! And you must not venture out alone![Exit.

FERDINAND. Light your father down, Louisa. (LOUISA takes a candle and follows MILLER. FERDINAND in the meantime approaches the table and throws poison into the lemonade). Yes!She must die! The higher powers look down, and nod their terrible assent. The vengeance of heaven subscribes to my decree. Her good angels forsake her, and leave her to her fate!

SCENE VII.

FERDINAND and LOUISA.

LOUISA re-enters slowly with the light, places it on the table, and stops on the opposite side of the room, her eyes fixed on the ground, except when she raises them to him with timid, stolen glances. He stands opposite, looking steadfastly on the earth-a long and deep silence.

LOUISA. If you will accompany me, Baron von Walter, I will try a piece on the harpsichord! (She opens the instrument. FERDINAND makes no answer. A pause.)

LOUISA. You owe me a revenge at chess. Will you play a game with me, Baron von Walter? (Another pause.)

LOUISA. I have begun the pocketbook, baron, which I promised to embroider for you. Will you look at the design? (Still a pause.)

LOUISA. Oh! I am very wretched!

FERDINAND (without changing his attitude). That may well be!

LOUISA. It is not my fault, Baron von Walter, that you are so badly entertained!

FERDINAND (with an insulting laugh). You are not to blame for my bashful modesty——

LOUISA. I am quite aware that we are no longer fit companions. I confess that I was terrified when you sent away my father. I believe, Baron von Walter, that this moment is equally insupportable to us both. Permit me to ask some of my acquaintances to join us.

FERDINAND. Yes, pray do so! And I too will go and invite some of mine.

LOUISA (looking at him with surprise). Baron von Walter!

FERDINAND (very spitefully). By my honor, the most fortunate idea that in our situation could ever enter mortal brain? Let us change this wearisome duet into sport and merriment, and by the aid of certain gallantries, revenge ourselves on the caprices of love.

LOUISA. You are merry, Baron von Walter!

FERDINAND. Oh! Wonderfully so! The very street-boys would hunt me through the market-place for a merry-andrew! In fact, Louisa, your example has inspired me-you shall be my teacher. They are fools who prate of endless affection-never-ending sameness grows flat and insipid-variety alone gives zest to pleasure. Have with you, Louisa, we are now of one mind. We will skip from amour to amour, whirl from vice to vice; you in one direction, I in another. Perhaps I may recover my lost tranquillity in some brothel. Perhaps, when our merry race is run, and we become two mouldering skeletons, chance again may bring us together with the most pleasing surprise, and we may, as in a melodrama, recognize each other by a common feature of disease-that mother whom her children can never disavow. Then, perhaps, disgust and shame may create that union between us which could not be effected by the most tender love.

LOUISA. Oh, Walter! Walter! Thou art already unhappy-wilt thou deserve to be so?

FERDINAND (muttering passionately through his teeth). Unhappy?Who told thee so? Woman, thou art too vile to have any feelings of thine own; how, then, canst thou judge of the feelings of others?Unhappy, did she say?-Ha! That word would call my anger from the grave! She knew that I must become unhappy. Death and damnation! She knew it, and yet betrayed me! Look to it, serpent!That was thy only chance of forgiveness. This confession has condemned thee. Till now I thought to palliate thy crime with thy simplicity, and in my contempt thou hadst well nigh escaped my vengeance (seizing the glass hastily). Thou wert not thoughtless, then- thou wert not simple-thou wert nor more nor less than a devil! (He drinks.) The drink is bad, like thy soul! Taste it!

LOUISA. Oh, heavens! 'Twas not without reason that I dreaded this meeting.

FERDINAND (imperiously). Drink! I say.

[LOUISA, offended, takes the glass and drinks. The moment she raises the cup to her lips, FERDINAND turns away with a sudden paleness, and recedes to the further corner of the chamber.]

LOUISA. The lemonade is good.

FERDINAND (his face averted and shuddering.) Much good may it do thee!

LOUISA (sets down the glass). Oh! Could you but know, Walter, how cruelly you wrong me!

FERDINAND. Indeed!

LOUISA. A time will come, Walter——

FERDINAND (advancing). Oh! We have done with time.

LOUISA. When the remembrance of this evening will lie heavy on your heart!

FERDINAND (begins to walk to and fro more vehemently, and to become more agitated; he throws away his sash and sword.) Farewell the prince's service!

LOUISA. My God! What mean you!

FERDINAND. I am hot, and oppressed. I would be more at ease.

LOUISA. Drink! Drink! It will cool you.

FERDINAND. That it will, most effectually. The strumpet, though, is kind-hearted! Ay, ay, so are they all!

LOUISA (rushing into his arms with the deepest expression of love). That to thy Louisa, Ferdinand?

FERDINAND (thrusting her from him). Away! Away! Hence with those soft and melting eyes! They subdue me. Come to me, snake, in all thy monstrous terrors! Spring upon me, scorpion! Display thy hideous folds, and rear thy proud coils to heaven! Stand before my eyes, hateful as the abyss of hell e'er saw thee! But not in that angel form! Take any shape but that! 'Tis too late. I must crush thee like a viper, or despair! Mercy on thy soul!

LOUISA. Oh! That it should come to this!

FERDINAND (gazing on her). So fair a work of the heavenly artist! Who would believe it? Who can believe it? (Taking her hand and elevating it.) I will not arraign thy ordinations, Oh! Incomprehensible Creator! Yet wherefore didst thou pour thy poison into such beauteous vessels? Can crime inhabit so fair a region? Oh! 'Tis strange! 'Tis passing strange!

LOUISA. To hear this, and yet be compelled to silence!

FERDINAND. And that soft, melodious voice! How can broken chords discourse such harmony? (Gazing rapturously upon her figure.) All so lovely! So full of symmetry! So divinely perfect!Throughout the whole such signs that'twas the favorite work of God! By heaven, as though all mankind had been created but to practise the Creator, ere he modelled this his masterpiece! And that the Almighty should have failed in the soul alone? Is it possible that this monstrous abortion of nature should have escaped as perfect? (Quitting her hastily.) Or did God see an angel's form rising beneath his chisel, and balance the error by giving her a heart wicked in proportion?

LOUISA. Alas for this criminal wilfulness! Rather than confess his own rashness, he accuses the wisdom of heaven!

FERDINAND (falls upon her neck, weeping bitterly). Yet once more, my Louisa! Yet once again, as on the day of our first kiss, when you faltered forth the name of Ferdinand, and the first endearing“Thou!” Trembled on thy burning lips. Oh! A harvest of endless and unutterable joys seemed to me at that moment to be budding forth. There lay eternity like a bright May-day before our eyes;thousands of golden years, fair as brides, danced around our souls.Then was I so happy! Oh! Louisa! Louisa! Louisa! Why hast thou used me thus?

LOUISA. Weep, Walter, weep! Your compassion will be more just towards me than your wrath.

FERDINAND. You deceive yourself. These are not nature's tears! Not that warm delicious dew which flows like balsam on the wounded soul, and drives the chilled current of feeling swiftly along its course. They are solitary ice-cold drops! The awful, eternal farewell of my love! (With fearful solemnity, laying his hand on her head.) They are tears for thy soul, Louisa! Tears for the Deity, whose inexhaustible beneficence has here missed its aim, and whose noblest work is cast away thus wantonly. Oh methinks the whole universe should clothe itself in black, and weep at the fearful example now passing in its centre. 'Tis but a common sorrow when mortals fall and Paradise is lost; but, when the plague extends its ravages to angels, then should there be wailing throughout the whole creation!

LOUISA. Drive me not to extremities, Walter. I have fortitude equal to most, but it must not be tried by a more than human test. Walter!One word, and then-we part forever. A dreadful fatality has deranged the language of our hearts. Dared I unclose these lips, Walter, I could tell thee things! I could——but cruel fate has alike fettered my tongue and my heart, and I must endure in silence, even though you revile me as a common strumpet.

FERDINAND. Dost thou feel well, Louisa?

LOUISA. Why that question?

FERDINAND. It would grieve me shouldst thou be called hence with a lie upon thy lips.

LOUISA. I implore you, Walter——

FERDINAND (in violent agitation). No! No! That revenge were too satanic! No! God forbid! I will not extend my anger beyond the grave! Louisa, didst thou love the marshal? Thou wilt leave this room no more!

LOUISA (sitting down). Ask what you will. I shall give no answer.

FERDINAND (in a solemn voice). Take heed for thy immortal soul!Louisa! Didst thou love the marshal? Thou wilt leave this room no more!

LOUISA. I shall give no answer.

FERDINAND (throwing himself on his knees before her in the deepest emotion). Louisa! Didst thou love the marshal? Before this light burns out-thou wilt stand-before the throne of God!

LOUISA (starting from her seat in terror). Merciful Jesus! What was that? And I feel so ill! (She falls back into her chair.)

FERDINAND. Already? Oh, woman, thou eternal paradox! Thy delicate nerves can sport with crimes at which manhood trembles;yet one poor grain of arsenic destroys them utterly!

LOUISA. Poison! Poison! Oh! Almighty God!

FERDINAND. I fear it is so! Thy lemonade was seasoned in hell!Thou hast pledged death in the draught!

LOUISA. To die! To die! All-merciful God! Poison in my drink! And to die! Oh! Have mercy on my soul, thou Father in heaven!

FERDINAND. Ay, be that thy chief concern: I will join thee in that prayer.

LOUISA. And my mother! My father, too! Saviour of the world! My poor forlorn father! Is there then no hope? And I so young, and yet no hope? And must I die so soon?

FERDINAND. There is no hope! None!-You are already doomed!But be calm. We shall journey together.

LOUISA. Thou too, Ferdinand? Poison, Ferdinand! From thee! Oh!God forgive him! God of mercy, lay not this crime on him!

FERDINAND. Look to your own account. I fear it stands but ill.

LOUISA. Ferdinand! Ferdinand! Oh! I can be no longer silent. Death-death absolves all oaths. Ferdinand! Heaven and earth contain nothing more unfortunate than thou! I die innocent, Ferdinand!

FERDINAND (terrified). Ah! What do I hear? Would she rush into the presence of her Maker with a lie on her lips?

LOUISA. I lie not! I do not lie! In my whole life I never lied but once!Ugh! What an icy shivering creeps through my veins! When I wrote that letter to the marshal.

FERDINAND. Ha! That letter! Blessed be to God! Now I am myself again!

LOUISA (her voice every moment becomes more indistinct. Her fingers tremble with a convulsive motion). That letter. Prepare yourself for a terrible disclosure! My hand wrote what my heart abhorred.It was dictated by your father! (Ferdinand stands like a statue petrified with horror. After a long silence, he falls upon the floor as if struck by lightning.) Oh! That sorrowful act!——Ferdinand-I was compelled- forgive me-thy Louisa would have preferred death-but my father-his life in danger! They were so crafty in their villany.

FERDINAND (starting furiously from the ground). God be thanked! The poison spares me yet! (He seizes his sword.)

LOUISA (growing weaker by degrees). Alas! What would you? He is thy father!

FERDINAND (in the most ungovernable fury). A murderer-the murderer of his son; he must along with us that the Judge of the world may pour his wrath on the guilty alone. (Hastening away).

LOUISA. My dying Redeemer pardoned his murderers, -may God pardon thee and thy father! (She dies.)

FERDINAND (turns quickly round, and perceives her in the convulsions of death, throws himself distractedly on the body). Stay!Stay! Fly not from me, angel of light! (Takes her hand, but lets it fall again instantly.) Cold! Cold and damp! Her soul has flown!(Starting up suddenly.) God of my Louisa! Mercy! Mercy for the most accursed of murderers! Such was her dying prayer! How fair, how lovely even in death! The pitying destroyer has touched gently on those heavenly features. That sweetness was no mask-the hand of death even has not removed it! (After a pause.) But how is this? Why do I feel nothing. Will the vigor of my youth save me?Thankless care! That shall it not. (He seizes the glass.)

SCENE VIII.

FERDINAND, the PRESIDENT, WORM, and SERVANTS, who all rush in alarm into the room. Afterwards MILLER, with a crowd, and OFFICERS of justice, who assemble in the background.

PRESIDENT (an open letter in his hand). My son! What means this? I never can believe——

FERDINAND (throwing the glass at his feet). Convince thyself, murderer! (The PRESIDENT staggers back. All stand speechless. A dreadful pause.)

PRESIDENT. My son! Why hast thou done this?

FERDINAND (without looking at him). Why, to be sure I ought first to have asked the statesman whether the trick suited his cards.Admirably fine and skilful, I confess, was the scheme of jealousy to break the bond of our hearts! The calculation shows a master-mind;'twas pity only that indignant love would not move on wires like thy wooden puppets.

PRESIDENT (looking round the circle with rolling eyes). Is there no one here who weeps for a despairing father?

MILLER (calling behind the SCENEs). Let me in! For God's sake, let me in!

FERDINAND. She is now a saint in heaven! Her cause is in the hands of another! (He opens the door for MILLER, who rushes in, followed by officers of justice and a crowd of people.)

MILLER (in the most dreadful alarm). My child! My child! Poison, they cry-poison has been here! My daughter! Where art thou?

FERDINAND (leading him between the PRESIDENT and LOUISA's corpse). I am innocent. Thank this man for the deed.

MILLER (throwing himself on the body). Oh, Jesus!

FERDINAND. In few words, father!-They begin to be precious to me. I have been robbed of my life by villanous artifice-robbed of it by you! How I may stand with God I tremble to think, but a deliberate villain I have never been! Be my final judgment what it will, may it not fall on thee! But I have committed murder! (In a loud and fearful voice.) A murder whose weight thou canst not hope that I should drag alone before the judgment-seat of God. Here I solemnly bequeath to thee the heaviest, the bloodiest part; how thou mayst answer it be that thy care! (Leading him to LOUISA.)Here, barbarian! Feast thine eyes on the terrible fruits of thy intrigues! Upon this face thy name is inscribed in the convulsions of death, and will be registered by the destroying angel! May a form like this draw thy curtain when thou sleepest, and grasp thee with its clay-cold hand! May a form like this flit before thy soul when thou diest, and drive away thy expiring prayer for mercy!May a form like this stand by thy grave at the resurrection, and before the throne of God when he pronounces thy doom! (He faints, the servants receive him in their arms.)

PRESIDENT (extending his arms convulsively towards heaven). Not from me, Judge of the world. Ask not these souls from me, but from him! (Pointing to WORM.)

WORM (starting). From me?

PRESIDENT. Accursed villain, from thee! From thee, Satan! Thou gavest the serpent's counsel! Thine be the responsibility; their blood be not on my head, but on thine!

WORM. On mine! On mine! (laughing hysterically.) Oh! Excellent!Now I understand the gratitude of devils. On mine, thou senseless villain! Was he my son? Was I thy master? Mine the responsibility?Ha! By this sight which freezes the very marrow in my bones!Mine it shall be! I will brave destruction, but thou shalt perish with me. Away! Away! Cry murder in the streets! Awaken justice! Bind me, officers! Lead me hence! I will discover secrets which shall make the hearer's blood run cold. (Going.)

PRESIDENT (detaining him). Surely, madman, thou wilt not dare?

WORM (tapping him on the shoulder). I will, though,-comrade, I will!I am mad, 'tis true; but my madness is thy work, and now I will act like a madman! Arm in arm with thee will I to the scaffold! Arm in arm with thee to hell! Oh! How it tickles my fancy, villain, to be damned with thee! (The officers carry him off.)

MILLER (who has lain upon LOUISA's corpse in silent anguish, starts suddenly up, and throws the purse before the MAJOR's feet.)Poisoner, take back thy accursed gold! Didst thou think to purchase my child with it? (Rushes distractedly out of the chamber.)

FERDINAND (in a voice scarcely audible). Follow him! He is desperate. The gold must be taken care of for his use; 'tis the dreadful acknowlegment of my debt to him. Louisa! I come!Farewell! On this altar let me breathe my last.

PRESIDENT (recovering from his stupor). Ferdinand! My son! Not one last look for a despairing father? (FERDINAND is laid by the side of LOUISA.)

FERDINAND. My last must sue to God for mercy on myself.

PRESIDENT (falling down before him in the most dreadful agony). The Creator and the created abandon me! Not one last look to cheer me in the hour of death! (FERDINAND stretches out his trembling hand to him, and expires.)

PRESIDENT (springing up). He forgave me! (To the OFFICERS.)Now, lead on, sirs! I am your prisoner.

[Exit, followed by the OFFICERS; the curtain falls.

译序

英国女作家玛丽·雪莱（Mary Shelley，1797—1851）是19世纪欧洲杰出的浪漫主义诗人珀西·雪莱的妻子。她的父亲威廉·哥德文（William Godwin，1756—1836）是享有盛名的思想家，母亲玛丽·沃尔斯顿克拉弗特（Mary Wollstonecraft，1759—1797）是著名的女权运动领袖。雪莱因思想激进而被牛津大学开除之后，追随哥德文并常到其家中请教，与玛丽相爱。两人冲破了重重阻碍而结合，从1816年起流亡国外。1822年雪莱在意大利溺水而亡后，玛丽返回英国，从事雪莱诗作的整理出版工作，并创作了几部长篇小说和大量短篇小说。

《弗兰肯斯坦》全名为《弗兰肯斯坦，或现代普罗米修斯》（Frankenstein，or the Modern Prometheus），1816年写于瑞士。玛丽·雪莱创作这部小说的起因本身就是一个有趣的故事：雪莱和玛丽在瑞士与当时也流亡在此的另一位英国浪漫主义诗人拜伦比邻而居，朝夕相处。在阴雨天的傍晚，他们围炉而坐，偶然读到几本德国的鬼怪故事，不禁兴味盎然，约定每人写一部有关超自然事件的小说。玛丽冥思苦想而难以下笔，一天夜里，她做了一个神秘而恐怖的梦，觉得豁然开朗，便以其为基础逐步发展成为现在的这部小说。拜伦和雪莱虽然因去阿尔卑斯山旅行而未能履约，但拜伦将他写出的开头部分用在了其他作品里，雪莱则不仅给玛丽以热情鼓励，本书的序言实际上也是他的手笔。

单纯从这则文坛逸事看，本书的产生似乎只是一个偶然现象，但实际上是有着非常深刻的原因的。18世纪末到19世纪初，欧洲流行着所谓的“哥特式小说”，常常描写离奇、神秘和恐怖的事件，一时蔚成风气。《弗兰肯斯坦》显然受到了它的影响。从更深广的方面来看，当时正值资本主义发展以及随之而来的生产力和科学技术突飞猛进的时期，许多思想家和文学家觉察到在社会的一时表面繁荣之下掩盖着深刻危机，开始对18世纪的启蒙理性主义产生怀疑，试图从人性、伦理、情感等角度进行批判性的反思。哥特式小说和当时的感伤主义文学都是这一思潮的产物，波澜壮阔的19世纪浪漫主义文学也是以此为思想基础的。因此，本书就其风格而言，可以说是一部哥特式小说，从它以创造生命的科学实验为情节来看，可以说是一部科学幻想小说（事实上它也被公认为西方文学史上的第一部科幻小说，被誉为科幻文学的开山之作），但其主题的重大、思想内蕴的丰富、对人性剖析的深刻、心理分析和景物描写的出色，却远非一般的哥特式小说或科幻小说所能比拟。

小说的主人公弗兰肯斯坦怀着探索生命奥秘、造福人类的良好愿望创造了一个“人”。正因为如此，作者引用古希腊神话中普罗米修斯创造人类、为人类盗取天火并教给人类各种技艺的典故，为小说加了一个副标题“现代普罗米修斯”。普罗米修斯受到了大神宙斯的惩罚，而弗兰肯斯坦则受到他自己行为的报复。他所创造的“人”不仅给他自身带来了可怕的灾难，而且使人类面临着巨大的危险，弗兰肯斯坦尤其对后一点忧虑不安，才必欲毁灭自己的创造物而后已。在作者看来，科学技术的发展并不必然地给人类带来福祉，假如我们对客观规律缺乏正确而深入的认识，无视人类与自然界的和谐关系，不同时致力于社会组织结构的改善和人类自身素质的提高，弗兰肯斯坦式的悲剧有可能变成现实。两个世纪过去了，科学技术已取得了玛丽·雪莱所未能预料的巨大进展，但20世纪生态环境的恶化、运用高科技手段的大规模战争、核泄漏、电脑病毒乃至近来引起普遍关注的生物“克隆”技术等等，都有力地证明了本书提出的问题是多么具有预见性。

弗兰肯斯坦创造的“怪物”便体现了科学技术的这一异化力量，但是作者并未以漫画式的手法将他处理成单纯的“恶”的象征。他虽然形体丑陋，面目狰狞，却具有正常的知觉和丰富的感情，渴望友谊、爱情和幸福，希望得到人类的理解和接纳；他为此做过种种努力，但总是受到拒斥、唾弃和伤害，内心充满孤独和痛苦；随着他对人类的所作所为有所了解，他发现人间处处是贫穷、压迫、欺诈和杀戮，不禁深感失望；他最后希望能有一个异性同类作为伴侣，到远离人类的地方去过隐遁生活，又遭到弗兰肯斯坦的拒绝。因此，“善”才转变为“恶”，他才对弗兰肯斯坦实施复仇，并对整个人类充满了憎恶和仇恨。用他自己的话来说，就是“堕落的天使变成了狠毒的魔鬼”。和弗兰肯斯坦一样，他也是一个悲剧性的形象，在小说结尾的时候，他自愿前往北极冰海焚身自杀，便是最后对人类提出的悲愤抗议。这一悲剧提醒人类自省自惕，从社会制度和伦理价值角度进行自我审视，从而大大地深化了小说的主题。

小说从这个角度出发，对弗兰肯斯坦和“怪物”的性格进行了集中刻画，成功地运用了心理描写、情感抒发和对话等手法，表现出了形象塑造的高超艺术技巧。小说的景物描写也十分出色，尤其是日内瓦湖的绮丽风光和阿尔卑斯山的宏伟景色，不仅如诗如画，而且情景交融，令人叹为观止。在叙述方式上，小说采用了大故事套小故事的框架式结构，第一层次是探险家沃尔顿在给姐姐的信中讲述遇见弗兰肯斯坦的事，第二层次是弗兰肯斯坦向沃尔顿叙述自己的遭遇，第三层次是“怪物”对弗兰肯斯坦讲他的经历，最后，在第三层次中又包含着费利克斯一家的故事等等。这种结构方式显得别致精巧，如层层剥笋，步步深入。我们从小说中不仅能得到深刻的思想启迪，也能获得充分的艺术享受。

伍厚恺

序言

这部小说所根据的事件，按照达尔文博士和德国某些生理学家提出的假设，并非是不可能发生的。对于这样一种想象的产物，我丝毫也没有认为实有其事，可是，在以之作为一部幻想作品的基础时，我也并不认为自己仅仅是在编织一连串的超自然恐怖事件而已。故事引人入胜，在于其情节摆脱了纯粹的鬼怪魔法故事的种种弊端。它由于自身展示的场景的新奇而受到欢迎，而且，无论作为物质事实是多么的不可能，它却为想象力提供了一个新的视点，以便比实际事件的普通关系更广泛地、更强有力地描绘出人类的激情。

我就这样努力地保存人类天性种种基本要素的真实性，同时又毫无顾忌地在这些要素的组合上进行创新。希腊的悲剧史诗《伊利亚特》，莎士比亚的《暴风雨》和《仲夏夜之梦》，特别是弥尔顿的《失乐园》，都符合这一法则。一个最谦卑的小说家，试图通过他的劳动使别人或者使自己得到娱乐，可以并非冒昧地在散文作品中运用诗的“破格”，或者说运用一种法则，在成就最高的诗歌中，因为应用这种法则而描绘出了如此众多的人类情感的精妙组合。

我的故事所依据的情景源于随意闲谈的启发。写作的初衷，部分是为了有所消遣，部分是以此作为未经考验的智力的一种锻炼手段。在写作过程中又掺进了其他一些动机。无论小说中所包含的情感或人物体现出怎样的道德倾向，对于它影响读者的方式，我当然是绝不会漠然视之的。不过，我在这方面主要的关注点，一直局限于避免现今小说削弱道德意义的效果，并专注于展示家庭感情的温馨亲切和普遍美德的崇高卓越。从主人公的性格和处境之中自然流露出来的观点，绝不应被视为是我本人的一贯信念；也不能理所当然地从后面的篇章中推论说，我对任何派别的任何学说怀有偏见。

对于作者而言，这部小说还有一个富于特殊兴味之处，那就是故事的创作开始于一个风景宏伟的地区，这也是书中主要场景之所在，同时它又是在与我永远怀念的人们的相互交往中动笔的。我是在日内瓦郊外度过1816年的夏季的。那个季节寒冷多雨，傍晚时分我们总是聚在熊熊燃烧的炉火边，偶尔读读碰巧落在手里的一些德国鬼怪故事来作消遣。这些故事激起了我们加以戏谑性模仿的欲望。两位朋友（任何一位写的故事都会远比我希望自己所能写出的更受大众的欢迎）和我本人一致约定，每个人都要根据某种超自然事件写出一个故事来。

然而天气突然转晴了，两位朋友撇下我到阿尔卑斯山去旅行，置身于壮丽风景中，浑然忘却了他们关于鬼怪的幻想。下面的故事便成了唯一完成了的作品。

1817年9月，马洛

第一封信
致萨维尔夫人

你将高兴地听到，你怀着那样凶险的预兆来看待的一项事业，在开始的时候并未发生任何灾难。我在昨天到达这里，我的第一个任务是要让我亲爱的姐姐确信我安康，并对我事业的成功增进信心。

我现在已经置身于远离伦敦的遥远的北方了。当我行走在圣彼得堡街头的时候，我感觉到寒冷的北风拂弄着我的面颊，它使我精神振奋、充满喜悦。你理解这种感情吗？这风是从我即将前往的那些地方吹来的，它让我事先品尝一下冰天雪地的滋味。在这蕴含成功希望的北风的鼓舞下，我的白日梦变得愈加炽热而生动了。我即使试图让自己相信北极乃是天寒地冻的荒凉之地，也是徒劳，它在我的想象之中总是充满美丽和欢乐的地方。在那里，玛格丽特，太阳永远不会沉落，它那个大圆盘只是紧贴地平线，放射着永恒的光辉。在那里——我的姐姐，请允许我对以前的航海家们给予几分信任——在那里并没有冰雪风霜。我们在平静的海面航行，也许会漂到一块陆地上，其奇异美丽要超过我们居住的地球上迄今已发现的任何地方。它的物产和风貌可能是无与伦比的，正像那些未经发现的孤独天体上的情景无疑是无与伦比的一样。在一个充满永恒光辉的国度，还有什么你以为是见不到的呢？我会在那里发现吸引磁针的神奇的力量，还会校正成千次天体观察的结果，只需有这次航行便可以将其中那些看来古怪的现象永远变得合情合理了。我强烈的好奇心，将因为看到人类从未造访过的这个世界的一部分而得到满足，我也许会踏上一块从来不曾印上人类足迹的土地。就是这一切使我心醉神迷，它们足以让我克服一切关于危险和死亡的恐惧，并引诱我欢欣鼓舞地开始这一次艰难竭蹶的航程，就像一个孩子登上了一条小舟，和度假的小伙伴们一道，沿着家乡的河流溯源探险一样。即便是我这一切推测猜想都纯属子虚乌有吧，你也无法否认，我将在北极附近探索出一条通往某些国家的新航线，而现在要到达那里必须花费好几个月时间。我将弄清磁力的奥秘，假如这个奥秘可能弄清的话，也只有通过我这样的事业才能实现，这样，我将为整个人类直至子孙万代带来不可估量的益处。

这些思考已经驱散了我开始写信时的那种热切不安的情绪，我感到内心燃起了一种使我崇高激越的热情，因为要使头脑镇静清醒莫过于心中怀有一个坚定不移的目标——在这一点上，灵魂可以使它的心智之眼专注如一。这次探险是我早年梦寐以求的事情。我曾经满腔热情地阅读过许多航海故事，它们记载着期盼穿越环绕北极的海洋而抵达北太平洋的种种航行。你也许还记得，我们的好托马斯叔叔的全部藏书就是一部记载所有航海探险的历史。我对受教育是漫不经心的，但我却十分热衷于读书。这几卷书就是我夜以继日所做的功课，而我把它们读得烂熟，就越发增强了我的遗憾，在我还小的时候，知道了父亲的遗训是禁止叔叔允许我从事航海生涯，这种遗憾就产生了。

当我第一次读到那些诗人的作品时，他们奔放的情感使我心醉神迷、如登天庭，原来那些幻想便黯然消退了。我也成了一个诗人，在我自己创造的天国里生活了一年，我想象自己或许也能在供奉着荷马和莎士比亚大名的圣殿里占据一席之地。你很清楚我是失败了，而且失望又让我心情多么沉痛。但就是在那个时候，我继承了堂兄的财产，我的心思又转回到早年癖好的轨道上来了。

自从我下定决心要进行目前这次航行以来，已有六个年头过去了。即使是现在，我还能记起自己刚刚决心献身于这项伟大事业的那个时刻。一开始我训练自己的身体以适应艰苦处境。我跟随捕鲸者数次远航到北海，我自愿忍受严寒、饥饿、干渴和睡眠不足，在白天我干活常常比一般水手还要苦，到了晚上又专心致志地学习数学、医药理论，以及航海冒险家可以从中获得最大实效的那些自然科学学科。有两次我真的在一艘格陵兰捕鲸船上被雇用做了二副，而且因恪尽职守得到赞扬。当船长邀我做船上仅次于他的大副，并以最大的热忱请求我留下的时候，我得承认，我是感到有点儿自豪了；船长认为我的工作干得是那样的卓有成效。

现在，亲爱的玛格丽特，难道我不配去实现某个伟大的目标吗？我的一生本可以在舒适奢华中度过，但我更愿意获取荣誉，而无视财富在我人生道路上设置的种种诱惑。啊，我多么希望有鼓励的话语来支持我的选择！我的勇气和决心是坚定不移的，不过我的希望时明时暗，我的情绪也常常低落下去。我即将出发开始一次漫长而艰难的航程，种种突发事件需要我百折不挠：这要求我不但要鼓舞别人的斗志，有时还要在别人情绪消沉的时候支撑起自己的精神。

眼下是在俄罗斯旅行的最佳时期。人们驾着雪橇在雪上飞驰；这样的滑行真惬意，在我看来，它远比坐在英国的公共马车里行进更令人愉快。如果你身上裹着裘皮衣服，也不会觉得太冷的——我现在已经穿上这样的服装了，因为在甲板上走动着，和动也不动地一坐几个钟头是大有区别的，这样坐着身体没有任何活动，难保血液不会真的在血管里凝结起来呢。我可没有在圣彼得堡与阿尔汉格尔斯克(1)之间的驿道上丢掉性命的打算。

我将在两三个星期之后动身去阿尔汉格尔斯克；我打算在那儿租上一艘船，只要为船主付保险金，这事是很容易办到的，再在惯于捕鲸的人当中招募够必要的船员。我准备一直等到6月再启航。至于什么时候回来呢？啊，亲爱的姐姐，我怎么能够回答这个问题呢？假如我成功了，那我们将会过很多、很多月，或许很多、很多年之后才能相见。假如我失败了，你就会很快再见到我的，或者永远也见不到我了。

再见了，我亲爱的、顶好的玛格丽特。愿上天赐福给你，也保佑我，这样我就可以一次又一次地证明我感激你对我的爱和关心了。

你亲爱的弟弟 罗·沃尔顿

17××年12月11日，圣彼得堡

————————————————————

(1) 阿尔汉格尔斯克（Arkhangelsk，原文作Archangel），俄罗斯北部城市。

第二封信
致萨维尔夫人

被包围在这儿的冰天雪地里，时间过得是多么缓慢啊！不过，我已经朝着我的事业迈开第二步了。我租到了一艘船，正忙着招募船员。现在已经招募到的看来都是些靠得住的人，肯定都具有无所畏惧的勇气。

不过我还有一个需要至今没有得到满足，我现在感到最严重的不幸便是缺乏了这个东西。我没有一个朋友，玛格丽特：当我因成功的热情而兴高采烈的时候，没有谁和我共享欢乐；如果失望来袭击我，也没有谁在沮丧中尽力给我支持。是的，我可以在纸上倾诉我的思绪，但这对于传达情感而言只是一个聊胜于无的办法。我希望有一个与我情投意合的伙伴，他的眼睛和我的眼睛可以做无言的交流。你也许会认为我太多情和好幻想，亲爱的姐姐，但我确实痛感需要一个朋友。我身边没有这样一个人，他既温和又勇敢，既富于教养又胸怀博大，志趣和我一致，可以赞同或者修正我的计划。有了这样的一个朋友，将会给你可怜的弟弟的缺点带来怎样的补益啊！我办起事来过于热切，遇到困难又太缺乏耐心。但对我来说更大的不幸是我的教育全靠自修：我一生中的最初十四年里都在野地里游荡胡闹，除了托马斯叔叔的航海书籍以外什么也没读过。那些年头过后我知道了我国的那些著名的诗人，可是也只是在我确信自己无力从中获取最重要的教益时，我才意识到有必要了解一些我国语言之外的更多的语言。我现在已经二十八岁了，而事实上我在学识上还不如许多十五岁的中学生。我确实想得比较多，我的白日梦也愈加海阔天空、壮丽辉煌，可是它们缺乏的是（就像画家们所说的）——“协调”。我迫切需要有一个朋友，他要有足够的见识，不至于觉得我耽于幻想而鄙薄我，还要对我有足够的感情，会尽力校正我的思想。

好了，这些都是于事无补的抱怨。在茫茫大海上我当然是找不到什么朋友的，即使在阿尔汉格尔斯克这儿，在商人和水手中间，也是不会找到什么朋友的。不过，甚至在这些粗犷的心胸里，也仍然搏动着某些并未与人性的渣滓同流合污的情感。比如我的副手，就是一个具有出色的勇气和事业心的人。他狂热地渴求荣誉，或者用更为确切的话来说，是一个渴盼在职业上大展宏图的人。他是一个英国人，怀有民族的和职业的偏见，缺乏教养上的陶冶，但仍然保持着人性中某些最高尚的禀赋。我最初是在一艘捕鲸船上认识他的：我发现他在这个城市里还没有工作，没费什么周折就雇了他来协助我的事业。

船长是一个性情极好的人，他在船上素以态度温和、纪律宽大著称。这一事实，再加上他那众所周知的正直品德和无畏勇气，使得我非常希望能雇用他。我的青年时代在孤独中流逝，我一生中最好的岁月是在温柔的、女性的抚育下度过的，这使得我的性格的根基变得如此温柔文雅，以致我对船上司空见惯的残暴行为怀有不可抑制的厌恶心理：我从不相信这种行为是必要的。所以当我听说有一个著名的海员，他既心地善良，又能得到水手们的尊敬和服从的时候，便因为能够请他为我工作而感到特别幸运。我是在一种颇富浪漫色彩的情况下，从一个受过他的救命之恩的女士口中第一次听说他的。下面就是关于他的简短的故事。若干年前，他爱上了一个家境小康的俄国女子。他已经攒下了一笔数额可观的奖金，姑娘的父亲同意了他们的婚事。在约定的婚礼之前，他有一次去看她，而她却泪如涌泉，扑跪在他的脚下请求他的宽恕，同时坦陈自己爱着另一个男人，可是因为他穷，父亲绝不会同意他们结合。我的慷慨大度的朋友要这位恳求者放心；当他获悉她的心上人的姓名之后便立即放弃了自己的婚事。他已经用自己那笔钱购置了一处农场，计划在那里度过余生，可是他却把整个农场赠送给了他的情敌，还用奖金的剩余部分添置了牲口，然后亲自去请求姑娘的父亲同意她和她的情人结为夫妻。老人却坚决予以拒绝，认为自己在道义上对我的朋友负有责任。当我的朋友发现老人的想法无可动摇的时候，便离开了祖国，直到他听见他过去的未婚妻如愿以偿地结了婚以后才回国。你会惊叹说：“一个多么高尚的人啊！”他的确是这样的一个人，不过他完全没有受过什么教育：他就像个土耳其人一样沉默寡言，还有某种愚昧无知、大大咧咧的神气，这固然使他的行为显得更加令人惊讶，但也减弱了他本来应该博得的兴趣和同情。

不过不要因为我稍稍抱怨了一下，或者我对闻所未闻的艰难劳作进行了一点自我安慰，就以为我的决心发生了动摇。我的决心和命运一样的坚定不移，我的航行眼下只是暂时推延，只待天气允许便会启程。今年冬天一直是可怕的严寒，但春天可以期望会很好，而且大家认为会来得特别早，因此我启航的时间也许比预期的要来得快。我不会鲁莽从事的，你是了解我的，相信一旦有他人的安全托付给我照料的时候，我会做到慎重小心、考虑周到的。

我无法向你形容我展望即将开始的事业前景时是怎样的感觉。我在做出发前的准备时，那种半是欣喜半是疑惧的战栗不安的心情，是无法用语言传达给你的。我即将前往那个“迷雾冰雪之地”的未经探索过的地区，不过我是绝不会杀死信天翁的，所以你也不要为我的安全担惊受怕，难道我会像那个“老水手”一样形容枯槁、满怀忧伤地回来见你吗？你一定会笑我引用了这个故事(1)，不过我要向你披露一个秘密。我常常把自己对于海洋那种危险和神秘的眷恋，以及对它的炽烈的热情，归因于当代最富想象力的诗人的那部作品。在我的灵魂中有某种我不能理解的东西在起作用。我干起事来很勤奋——很刻苦——我是一个坚韧不拔、埋头苦干的工匠。可是除此之外我又热爱奇妙的东西，相信奇妙的事情，它们掺和进我的一切计划之中，这便驱使我越出人们所走的常规之路，甚至走向了我即将去探索的那片茫茫大海和人类未曾涉足之地。

不过还是回到更为亲切的关怀之情上来吧。在我穿越广袤的海洋，绕过非洲或美洲最南端的海岬之后，还会再见到你吗？我真不敢期望这样的成功，然而我又不忍看到与此相反的情景。在目前请利用每一个机会继续给我写信，在将来我最需要你的信来支撑起自己的精神的时候，我可以再来读它们。我深深地爱你。万一你再也得不到我的消息，就亲切地怀念我吧。

罗伯特·沃尔顿

17××年3月28日，阿尔汉格尔斯克

————————————————————

(1) 前文所引为英国诗人柯勒律治（Samuel Taylor Coleridge，1772—1834）的长诗《老水手行》（The Rime of the Ancient Mariner，1798）。诗中写一次出海远航，老水手杀死了引航的信天翁，遭遇可怕的灾难，最后老水手虔诚忏悔才死里逃生。

第四封信
致萨维尔夫人

我们遇到了如此奇怪的一件事，我没法制止自己把它记下来，尽管在这封信到你手中之前，很可能你已经见到我了。

上个星期一（7月31日），我们差不多被冰块包围了，船的四周全挤着冰，几乎没留一点船只可以通过的余地。我们的处境有些危急，特别是又有浓密的大雾包裹着我们的时候。我们因此只好顶风停船，希望气层和天气会发生变化。

大约两点钟时分，雾散了，我们看见四面八方都延伸着宽阔而不规则的冰原，仿佛没有尽头似的。我的一些伙伴们发出了呻吟，我的心里也充满了焦急的思虑，开始变得警觉起来，就在这时候有一种奇怪的景象突然吸引了我们的注意力，转移开了我们对自己处境的忧虑。我们觉察到有一辆固定在狗拉雪橇上的低矮的车，正在离我们半英里的地方向北驶去。有一个身形像人但显然更巨大的生物，正坐在雪橇上驾驭着那些狗。我们用望远镜看着那个旅行者疾速地前进着，直到消失在远处崎岖起伏的冰原尽头。

这番景象激起了我们无限的惊异。我们相信自己距离任何陆地都有好几百英里，可是这个怪物的出现却又似乎表明，陆地实际上并不是我们所料想的那样遥远。但因为被冰块紧紧围住，我们尽管极其注意地观察，也无法追寻到他的去向。

在发生这件事之后大约两个小时，我们听到了海底发出的啸声，不到天黑，冰层碎裂了，我们的船解除了囚禁。不过我们还得停在原地等到天亮，害怕在黑暗中会撞上冰层化开以后四处漂浮着的大冰块。我利用这段时间休息了几个小时。

第二天早晨天一亮，我就走到甲板上去，却发现所有的水手都急匆匆地挤到船的一侧，好像正在和海上的什么人谈着话。事实上，船舷下面有一辆雪橇，样子和我们先前见过的相似，它是停在一个大冰块上，在夜里漂到我们跟前来的。只有一条狗还活着，不过雪橇上坐着一个人，水手们正在劝说他到船上来。他并不像前一个旅行者那样仿佛是某个荒岛上的未开化的野人，而是一个欧洲人。我走上甲板的时候，船长说：“这是我们的队长，他是不会让你在大海上死掉的。”

陌生人看见我，便用英语说起话来，只不过带有一种外国腔调。“在我登上您的船之前，”他说，“请先告诉我你们的船开往何处好吗？”

你可以想象到，当我听到一个处在毁灭边缘的人竟向我提出这样一个问题的时候，会有多么的惊讶，我原本料想我的船对他来说应当是无比宝贵的，即使用世上最珍贵的财富来交换他也不会答应哩。不过我还是回答他说，我们正在前往北极探险的航行途中。

他听到这个回答显得很满意，同意到船上来。天啊！玛格丽特，你要是看到这个非要如此才肯为自己的安全向我们屈服的人，你真会感到无限的惊奇。他的四肢几乎冻僵，他的躯体因为劳累和折磨而变得瘦骨嶙峋。我从来没有见过一个人落到如此悲惨的境地。我们试图把他抬进船舱里去，可是他刚一离开新鲜空气就昏了过去。我们只好又把他抬回甲板上，用白兰地擦他的身体，还硬给他灌下了少量的酒，借此让他苏醒过来。他一显出复苏的迹象，我们就用毯子把他裹住，把他放到厨房火炉的烟囱旁边。他一步步地慢慢恢复过来了，还喝了一点儿汤，这可使他大有起色了。

就像这样过了两天，他才有力气讲话。我常常担心他所受的折磨会使他丧失了理解力。当他恢复到一定程度的时候，我把他搬到我的船舱里来，并在我的职务允许的时候全力照料他。我从来没有见过比他更能引起我的兴趣的人了：他的眼睛通常带有一种狂热的，甚至是疯狂的神情，但有的时候，当有人对他做出好意的举动，或者为他提供了任何微不足道的服务时，他的表情又会豁然开朗，仿佛闪耀着一种我从未见过的仁慈而亲切的光彩。不过总的说来他显得既忧郁又绝望，有时候他还咬牙切齿，仿佛难于忍受那压迫着他的痛苦重负似的。

我的客人稍微恢复了一些的时候，要把那些想向他提出一千个问题的人们打发开去，我真是花了很大的力气。不过从他身心的状况来看，要复原显然取决于彻底的休息，我不愿让他受到他们那些毫无意义的好奇心的折磨。不过，有一次我的副手问了他，为什么他会乘坐这样奇怪的一种交通工具，在冰上跑到这么远的地方来？

他的脸上顿时罩上了浓重的荫翳。他回答说：“为了找寻一个逃离我的人。”

“你追寻的人是不是和你用同样的方式在旅行？”

“是的。”

“那么我想我们见过他，因为就在救起你来的前一天，我们看到有几只狗拉着一辆雪橇，上面坐着一个人，横跨过冰原。”

这句话引起了陌生人的注意，他问了许许多多的问题，全都有关那个魔鬼——他这样称呼他——行进的路线。过后不久，当他单独和我待在一起的时候，他说：“毫无疑问，我激起了你以及那些好心人的好奇心。不过你很体贴人，并不向我提问。”

“理所当然。假如我用好奇的探询来打扰你，那我确实是太没道理，也太残酷了。”

“不过你把我从不同寻常的危险处境中救了出来，你仁慈地让我恢复了生命。”

紧接着他便问我，我是否认为碎裂的冰块已经撞毁了那另一辆雪橇？我回答说，我没有任何把握做出答复，因为冰层直到临近半夜才开裂，而那个旅行者在此之前可能就已经到达了某个安全的地方。不过关于这一点我也不能肯定。

从这个时候起，一种新的生命之灵使陌生人正在衰竭的躯体焕发了生机。他表示出最热切的渴望，要到甲板上去，去守望那辆曾经出现过的雪橇。但我劝说他继续留在船舱里，因为他还太虚弱，受不了凛冽刺骨的冷空气。我答应派人去替他守望，只要有任何新物体出现，就会立即通知他的。

这就是到今天为止我的日志中记录的有关这个奇异事件的情况。陌生人的身体渐渐地恢复了健康，但他非常沉默寡言，而且每当有除我之外的任何人走进他的船舱，他就会显得神情不安。不过他的态度却是那样的讨人喜欢和温文尔雅，水手们都对他很感兴趣，尽管他们很少和他交谈。至于我本人，则开始对他怀有一种兄弟般的爱意，他那始终如一的深重的悲哀使我心中充满了同情和怜悯。他在境况顺利的日子里一定是个性格高尚的人，即使是眼下遭难的时候，他也依然是如此具有吸引力，如此和蔼可亲。

亲爱的玛格丽特，我曾经在一封信里说过，在茫茫大海上我是不会找到任何朋友的，然而我现在找到了一个人，在他的精神被痛苦击垮之前，我很高兴有他做我的知心兄弟。

如果有任何新的事件值得记录，我将继续在日志中不时记下有关这个陌生人的情况。

罗·沃

17××年8月15日

我对我的客人的感情与日俱增。他将我的钦敬和怜悯这两种情感都激发到了惊人的程度。我怎么能够眼看着如此高尚的一个人被痛苦摧毁而不感到彻心的悲痛呢？他是这样的温和，又是这样的聪明；他的心智是如此富于修养；他说起话来虽然措辞考究，却滔滔不绝，富于非凡的雄辩力。

现在他已经从病弱状态中大大地恢复过来了，还不停地走到甲板上去，显然是去守望在他之前的那辆雪橇。不过他虽然怏怏不乐，却并非一心只想着自己的痛苦，而是对别人的计划也怀着很浓的兴趣。他经常和我交谈我的计划，这项计划我已经毫无保留地告诉了他。他注意倾听我讲述自己必然成功的所有有利论据，以及我为了确保成功而采取的种种措施的每一点细节。他对我所表露的同情引得我禁不住把心里话和盘托出，我倾诉了我灵魂中那燃烧的激情，还带着令我兴奋的狂热谈到，我将乐于牺牲我的财产、我的生命、我的一切希望，来促成我的事业。为了获得我所寻求的知识，为了我将要获得并将传之于后世的对人类的自然之敌的统治权，付出一个人的生死，只不过是付出了一个渺小的代价而已。就在我说着这番话的时候，一片浓重的阴霾蒙住了我朋友的面容。开始时我感觉到他在极力抑制着自己的感情，他用双手掩住了眼睛。当我看见泪水从他的指缝间不断地涌流——他不停起伏的胸中迸发出一声呻吟的时候，我的声音颤抖得再也说不出话来了。我停住了——他最后说话了，声音断断续续的——“不幸的人哪！你难道和我一样疯狂吗？你难道也喝了那种迷魂汤吗？请听我讲——让我把自己的故事告诉你，你会把你唇边盛着苦酒的杯子摔得粉碎！”

你可以想象到，他的这几句话强烈地激起了我的好奇心。但是这阵突然发作的痛苦攫住了陌生人，摧垮了他虚弱的体力，必须有好几个小时的休息和平静的谈话才能使他恢复镇静。

当他控制住了情感的强烈爆发之后，他似乎为自己屈从于感情冲动而鄙视自己。在克服了阴郁的绝望情绪之后，他又再度引我谈论有关自己的事情。他问起我早年的经历。故事很快就讲完了，可是这唤醒了我的种种思绪。我谈起我希望找到一个朋友——我渴盼和一个朋友的心灵发生比迄今为止所有过的更为亲密无间的契合，我表示自己确信，一个人假如不曾享受到这种恩赐，就不能称许自己幸福。

“我同意你的看法，”陌生人回答道，“如果没有一个比我们更聪明、更美好、更可爱的人——一个朋友理应如此——没有他来帮助我们矫正我们软弱而有缺陷的性格，我们就是未曾完成的生物，只不过被塑造了一半而已。我曾经有一个朋友，他是人类中最高尚的人，因此我有资格来评判有关友谊的问题。你有希望，眼前有整个世界，绝没有理由灰心丧气。然而我——我已经失去了一切，再也不能重新开始生活了。”

他在说这番话的时候，面容上显露出一种安于不幸而听天由命的神情，这深深地打动了我。可是他沉默了，随即回到了他自己的船舱里。

即使他的情绪是如此沮丧，但谁也不如他那样对自然之美怀有深切的感受。繁星密布的天穹，大海，以及这些奇妙的地区所展示出的每一种景象，似乎仍然具有一种使他的心灵升华而超脱尘世的力量。这样的一个人具有双重的生存方式，他可能会受痛苦的折磨，被沮丧失望的情绪压倒，然而，当他退回到自己的内心世界中去的时候，他又像一个头绕光环的神灵，在这片光辉中绝没有悲伤或愚蠢敢于侵入。

你会笑我在谈起这个神灵般的流浪者时所表现出的热情吧？要是你见到他，就不会笑话我了。你从书籍中博采知识，教养优越，而且远离尘世，因此你评判别人也多少有些挑剔，可是正是这一点，更能使你欣赏这个奇妙的人所具有的不同寻常的优点。有时候我极力要去发现到底他具有什么样的品质，才使他大大地超越了我迄今为止所认识的任何人。我相信那是一种出于直觉的辨识力，一种既敏捷而又绝不会失误的判断力，一种深入事物根源的无比清晰准确的洞察力，再加上流畅的表达力，以及抑扬顿挫如抚慰灵魂的音乐般的语调。

17××年8月13日

昨天陌生人对我说：“沃尔顿队长，你也许不难看出，我曾经遭遇过无可比拟的巨大不幸。我一度下定了决心，要让有关那些灾祸的记忆随着我的死亡而归于消灭。可是你使我改变了自己的决定。你正像我曾经做过的那样，追求着知识与智慧，而我却热切地希望在你的愿望实现的时候，它不会像我所经受的那样，成为噬伤你的毒蛇。我不知道讲述自己的灾难是否对你有所裨益，不过，当我想到你正走着和我同样的道路，正面临着把我弄成今天这副模样的相同的危险时，我猜想你也许会从我的故事中吸取出适当的教训。要是你在事业上获得了成功，它可以指导你的行动，万一你失败了，它也可以安慰你。请你准备好倾听通常会被视为不可思议的一连串事件吧。要是我们处在静谧祥和的自然环境中，我或许会担心你将不肯相信我，也许还会嘲笑我，但在这蛮荒而神秘之地，许多事情都似乎成为可能的了，而对于那些并未领略过千变万化的大自然的伟力的人们来说，这一切都只会引得他们发笑罢了——我也毫不怀疑我的故事所包含的事件都具有真实的证据，在一步步进展中它将证明这一点。”

你很容易想象到，他主动提出做这番交谈，我是多么高兴。不过我又不忍心他因为诉说自己的不幸遭遇而再度经受痛苦。我觉得自己之所以怀着最急迫的心情要想听他准备讲述的故事，部分是源于好奇心理，部分则是出于自己想改变他的命运的强烈愿望。我在回答他的时候表示了这些想法。

“谢谢你的同情，”他回答说，“不过这是没用的。我的生命即将结束了。我只等待着发生一件事，然后我将安息。我理解你的感情，”他觉察到我想打断他的话，便接着说，“可是你错了，我的朋友，如果你允许我这样称呼你的话。什么力量也不能改变我的命运。请听我的故事吧，你将明白我的命运是怎样的无可挽回了。”

然后他告诉我，第二天我闲下来的时候他将开始讲述他的故事。我衷心地感谢他的这番许诺。我决定每天晚上当自己没有紧迫事务缠身的时候，尽可能按照他的原话把他白天讲述的事情记下来。万一我忙得没有时间，至少也要做些笔记。这些记录无疑会给你带来极大的乐趣。而对于我来说，我认识他，听过他亲口讲述，在将来的某一天，我又会带着怎样的兴味和同情来重读这些记录啊！甚至就在此刻，当我开始这项工作的时候，他那洪亮饱满的声音还在我的耳中回响，他那光彩奕奕的眼睛还带着忧郁的温情注视着我，我还看见他那瘦削的手举起来做着活泼的手势，而他的面容则闪耀着来自心灵内部的光辉。他的故事一定是奇异而痛苦的，而那吞没了正在航道上行驶的英勇的船舶，并把它损毁到这般地步的风暴，一定是令人惊怖的！

17××年8月19日

第一章　家世

就出生地而言，我是个日内瓦人，我的家族是那个共和国最显赫的家族之一。我的祖辈许多年来一直担任着顾问和市政官，我的父亲则承担过几项公共职务，声誉卓著。他受到所有人的尊敬，大家都知道他为人正直，对公共事务倾心关注，毫不懈怠。他的青年时代始终被国家公务所占据，各种各样的原因使他不可能早早结婚，直到生命的顶峰已过，他才做了丈夫和父亲。

鉴于父亲结婚的情况足以说明他的性格，我不能不加以叙述。他最知心的朋友中有一位是个商人，他因为屡遭不幸，家境从富足堕入贫困。这个人名叫波福，他性情高傲，不愿卑躬屈膝，要他在自己曾因富贵而显赫一时的国家里过贫穷和默默无闻的生活，他感到不堪忍受。因此，当他以最体面的方式偿付了债务之后，便和女儿退隐到了琉森市，在那里过着隐姓埋名和苦不堪言的生活。我父亲以最真诚的友谊爱着波福，对他落入这种不幸的境遇深感痛心。无谓的自傲心理导致他的朋友采取了这样一个配不上他们之间感情的行动，他感到痛惜。他刻不容缓地极力要找到他们，希望能够说服他凭借自己的信誉和帮助来重建家业。

波福采取了有效的措施使自己隐匿起来，父亲足足花了十个月的时间才探知到他的住处。这一发现使他欣喜异常，他急匆匆地赶往坐落在路斯附近一条简陋小街上的那所房屋。可是，当他走进屋子的时候，面对的只是悲惨和绝望。波福从破败的家产中只保住了很小的一笔钱，不过它倒是足以维持几个月的生活开支，在这段时间里，他希望能在一家商行里找到一分体面的工作。然而这段光阴结果却是毫无作为地浪费掉了。一旦有空闲来进行思考的时候，他的不幸便显得越发深重、越发痛心，到最后痛苦紧紧地攫住了他的心，以至于他在三个月以后缠绵病榻，再也无法进行任何努力了。

他的女儿极其体贴细心地照料他，可是她又绝望地眼看着那一小笔钱飞快地减少，却指望不到有任何的接济。不过卡罗琳·波福具有卓绝不凡的精神，她勇气倍增地支撑着自己来对付逆境。她找低微的活计来干，她编织草帽，她还用其他种种办法来挣得一点微薄的工钱，勉强维持着生活。

几个月就像这样过去了。她父亲的病情更严重了，她的时间更得用来照料他，她赖以谋生的收入日益减少。到了第十个月，她父亲在她的怀抱中去世，撇下她一个孤女，只能做一个乞丐。这个最后的打击使她完全崩溃了。当我的父亲进屋的时候，她正跪在波福的棺材边哀声痛哭。他就像一个保护神似的来到可怜的姑娘身旁，而她则把自己完全交给他来照顾。父亲在给朋友送葬之后，把她带到了日内瓦，送到一个亲戚家照料。这事过去两年以后，卡罗琳做了他的妻子。

我父母的年龄有相当大的差距，但这种情况却似乎使他们愈加倾心相爱。我父亲那正直的胸怀中存在着一种正义感，这使得他必然会高度赞许强烈的爱情。或许他在早年曾经恋爱过，因为发现所爱的人并不值得他爱而饱受痛苦，所以更珍视经受过磨难考验的有价值的东西。在他对我母亲的依恋之情里表现出某种感激和敬慕，这与一般老年丈夫对年轻妻子的溺爱完全不同，因为激发起这种爱的力量是父亲对母亲的美德的崇敬，以及要在某种程度上补偿她所经受过的不幸的强烈愿望，而正是因为这一点，他对母亲的态度便含有一种无法表达的慈爱之情。他做每一件事都顺从她的意愿，符合她的习惯。他努力保护她，就像园丁保护他美丽的奇花异草不受暴风的伤害一样，他还尽一切可能，让她的生活环绕着可以在她温柔而宽厚的心中激起欢乐的事物。她的健康，以及她素来坚韧而宁静的精神气质，都因她所经受的苦难而受到了损害。在他们婚前两年时间里，我父亲就逐渐放弃了他担任的所有公职。结婚以后，他们随即动身旅行，希望意大利那温暖宜人的气候，以及在那片神奇土地的旅行和变化无穷的景物和乐趣，有利于我母亲虚弱身体的康复。

他们又从意大利到了德国和法国。我是他们的长子，就出生在那不勒斯，还是个婴儿时就随他们四处漫游。好几年里我是他们唯一的孩子。尽管他们彼此倾心相爱，但他们又从爱情的源泉里汲取了无穷无尽的爱来倾注到我的身上。我母亲温柔的爱抚，我父亲凝视着我的时候那充满慈爱的欢乐的微笑，这便是我人生之初最早的印象。我是他们的玩具和偶像，但绝不仅此——我是他们的孩子，是上天赐予他们的天真无邪却又幼弱无助的生命，他们要抚育我健康成长，我未来的命运就在他们手中，根据他们如何对我尽责任，我或者走向幸福，或者通往不幸。他们深深意识到他们对于自己赋予生命的孩子肩负着怎样的责任，再加上他们两个人都富于活泼而温柔的性情，可以想象，我幼年生活的每时每刻都接受着关于耐心、仁爱和自我克制的教育，但引导我的却是一条温柔的丝带，我只觉得一切都充满了欢乐。

在很长时间里我都是他们唯一的关怀对象。母亲非常渴望能有一个女儿，可是我一直是他们的独生子。在我五岁的时候，他们去意大利边界那一带短途旅游，在科摩河畔度过了一周。出于仁慈的天性，他们常常去穷人的茅屋造访。这对于我母亲来说，不仅仅是一种责任，更是一种需要，一种强烈感情——她想起自己受过的苦难，自己又是如何得到解救的——现在轮到她来做穷苦人的保护天使了。在一次散步的时候，山谷的沟壑里一所破茅屋那孤零零的凄惨模样吸引了他们的注意力，同时茅屋周围还聚集着一群衣不蔽体的孩子，更足以说明这家人贫穷到了极点。有一天，当我父亲独自一人去了米兰的时候，母亲就带上我去访问这户人家。她看到一个农民和他的妻子，都是吃苦耐劳却又被忧虑和劳累压垮了的人，正在把很少一点的食物分发给五个饥饿的孩子。孩子当中有一个特别引起了母亲的注意。她看起来属于和其他孩子不同的血统。其他四个都是黑眼睛、身板坚韧的小流浪儿，这个孩子身体却很单薄，相貌秀美。她的头发是明亮耀眼的金色，尽管衣衫破烂，头上却仿佛戴着尊荣的冠冕。她的额头长得明净而饱满，蓝色的眼睛晶莹明澈，她的嘴唇和脸型是那样富于感情和充满甜美，谁见了也不能不觉得她气质不凡，仿佛是来自天堂，处处都像一个天使。

那农妇觉察到我母亲目不转睛地盯着这个可爱的女孩，眼里充满惊奇和赞赏，便急切地讲述了她的身世。女孩并不是她的孩子，而是米兰的一个贵族的女儿。她的母亲是个德国人，在生养她的时候死去。这个婴儿托付给了这个好人家抚养，而当时他们的境况还很好。他们结婚不久，最大的孩子也才刚刚出世。这个受托养的女孩的父亲，是在缅怀意大利古老光荣的精神熏陶之下成长起来的意大利人——激进党的一个成员，为了祖国的自由而竭力奋斗。他成了软弱的祖国的牺牲品。他到底是死了呢，还是仍在奥地利的地牢里苟延残喘，这可谁也不知道。他的财产被没收了，他的孩子则成了一个孤儿和乞丐。她继续留在她的养父母身边，在他们这粗陋的家中奇葩独放，比一朵在黑叶荆棘丛中的庭园玫瑰还要美丽。

当父亲从米兰归来的时候，他发现我正在别墅的大厅里和一个比画中天使还要美的孩子一起玩耍——她的面容似乎放射着光辉，她的体态和动作比山上的小羚羊还要轻捷。天使的出现很快就被解释清楚了。母亲得到了父亲的许可，说服了她的农民保护人把抚养孩子的责任转让给了她。他们本来很喜欢这个可爱的孤儿，有她住在自己家中就好像是他们的一种福分，不过现在天意使她得到了这样强有力的保护，那么再让她继续处于贫穷和匮乏之中，对她来说也就不公平了。他们请教了乡村教士，其结果是伊丽莎白·拉文查住进了我父母亲的房子——成了我的比妹妹还亲的妹妹——成了我一切活动和游乐的美好的、备受敬慕的伴侣。

每个人都喜欢伊丽莎白。大家都对她怀着热烈的，几乎是崇敬般的爱，而当我也分享这种情感的时候，则感到是我的骄傲和欢乐。在她被接到我家的前一天晚上，我母亲曾开玩笑地对我说：“我有一件珍贵的礼物要送给我的维克多——明天他就会得到它。”第二天，当她把她许诺的礼物伊丽莎白带来给我的时候，我却以孩子气的认真劲儿把她的话当了真，认为伊丽莎白就是属于我的——该由我来保护、爱和珍惜。人们对她的一切赞美，我都当作是对属于我的东西的赞美来加以接受。我们之间亲昵地以表兄妹称呼。她与我的关系是用任何词语、用任何表达方式都无法描绘的——她是我的比妹妹还亲的妹妹，从那时起直到她死去，她都是只属于我的。

第四章　狂热的工作

从那一天起，自然哲学，特别是在最广泛的意义上的化学，几乎成了我唯一的学习内容。我满怀热情地阅读现代研究者们在这些课题上撰写的著作，它们是那样的天才横溢和慎思明辨。我去听大学里科学家的演讲，发展与他们的关系。我甚至发现克伦普先生也颇具健全的思想和真实学问，的确，那是与令人不快的相貌和态度结合在一起的，但并不因为这一点就影响了它们的价值。沃德曼先生则成了我真正的朋友。他温文尔雅，丝毫也不武断。他对我的教导坦率而真诚，绝无一点迂腐的空谈。他用尽各种方法为我铺平学习知识的道路，把最深奥难解的问题阐述得清楚明白，让我易于理解。开始时，我的研究工作还是起伏波动、犹豫不决的，但随着我进行下去而渐渐获得了力量，不久我就变得那样的热诚和急切，以致当星星在晨曦中消失的时候，我往往还在实验室里工作着。

因为我如此专心致志地工作，所以不难想象我的进步是很快的。我的热忱确实使学生们惊讶，而我对知识的掌握也引起了老师们的惊奇。克伦普教授常常带着顽皮的微笑问我，科讷利乌斯·阿格里帕进展得如何啊？沃德曼教授则对我的进步表示由衷的欣喜。两年光阴就这样度过了，在此期间我没有回过一次日内瓦，而是全身心地投入到我希望能有所发现的研究工作之中。只有体验过这一切的人，才能想象到科学那迷人的魅力。在其他的学科中，你最多只能走到前人已经到达的那样远，再也没有更多的东西可以了解，然而在科学的探求中总不断有发现和奇迹。一个才智平平的人，只要专注于一种研究，也一定会成为这种研究里博大精深的专家。我呢，因为坚持不懈地努力要在一种研究目标上有所成就，而且全身心地投入到里面，所以进展非常迅速，到了两年的末尾，我便在某些化学仪器的改进方面有了一些发现，这使我在大学里获得了人们高度的尊重和敬佩。当我到达这一点的时候，建立在英戈尔施塔特教授们的课程基础上的有关自然哲学的理论和实践，我已经了如指掌，这样，我继续住在这里，已无助于我学业的进步，于是我考虑返回亲友的身边，回家乡去。就在这时候却发生了一件事，使我滞留在当地。

特别吸引我的注意力的现象之一，是人类身体的构造，而且包括任何具有生命的动物的构造。我常常问自己，生命的本源到底从何而来？这是一个大胆的问题，并且是一个从来就被视为神秘莫测的问题，可是，如果不是因为胆怯和漫不经心限制了我们的探究，我们本来应该接近了解许许多多事物的边缘了。我在心里翻来覆去地思考着这些情况，最后决定要更加注重研究与生理学有关的那些自然哲学的分支。要不是我被一种几乎不可思议的热情所激励的话，我进行的这项研究本来会是枯燥乏味、近乎不堪忍受的。要考察生命的起源，首先必须追溯到死亡。我已经熟悉了解剖学，可是这还不够，我还得观察人体的自然衰朽和腐坏的过程。在我接受教育的时候，父亲曾特别小心不让我的心灵受到半点超自然的恐怖事物的影响。在我的回忆中，我从来未曾因听了一个迷信故事而吓得发抖，也未曾害怕过什么鬼魂的显灵。黑暗绝不会使我胡思乱想，教堂墓地对我来说只不过是一个容纳尸体的地方，人体失去了生命，也就从美和力量的住所变成了蛆虫的食粮。现在我却要去考察人体这种腐坏的原因和过程，不得不日日夜夜待在墓穴和停尸房里。我的注意力现在集中在人类优雅感情最不堪承受的每一桩事物上。我目睹人的美好的形体是怎样衰败和腐烂的，我看到死亡后的腐败取代了青春焕发的富于生气的容颜，我眼看到蛆虫怎样盘踞着无比珍奇的人的眼睛和大脑。我驻足观察，考究和分析从生到死和从死到生的变化中所表现出来的因果关系的一切细微环节，直到在黑暗中突然迸射出一道光明，照亮了我的思想——这是一道如此辉煌和奇妙、却又是如此单纯的光明，当我被这道光明所展现的无限前景照得目眩头晕时，我不禁感到惊奇：曾经有这么多富于天才的人物向这一学科进行过探索，然而偏偏只有我一个人发现了如此惊人的秘密。

请记住，我并不是在记叙一个狂人的奇思异想。在天空照耀的太阳也不会比我所说的更真实。这件事也许只有出现某种奇迹才会发生，然而我的发现的一个个阶段却都是清清楚楚、完全可能的。经过了许多日日夜夜令人难以置信的劳作和疲惫，我才成功地发现了生殖和生命的起因。不，不仅如此，我还能够给无生命的物质赋予生命。

获得这一发现时最初体验到的惊奇，很快就为欢乐和狂喜所代替。经过了如此漫长的艰巨的劳作，突然到达自己欲望的顶峰，这正是对我的辛苦操劳的最完美的报偿。不过这个发现是如此伟大和令人惊愕，所以逐渐通向这一点的一步步过程都被淡忘了，我眼里只看到结果。从开天辟地起最有智慧的人所研究和渴望的东西，现在就在我的掌握之中。这可不像魔法里的情景，它不是猛然一下就展现在我的面前：我所获得的知识并非把已经完成了的事物展示在我面前，而只是在我确定了研究目标的时候指引我朝这个方向奋斗。我就像一个被埋葬在死人墓穴里的阿拉伯人，只是凭借着一丝微弱闪烁、似乎不可捉摸的光线，才找到一条走向生命的通道。

我从你急切的神态，以及你眼中流露出来的惊奇与希冀看出，我的朋友，你希望我告诉你我所了解的秘密是什么。耐心地听到故事结束吧，到那时你就会很容易理解我为什么对此要有所保留。我不愿意把你，像我当年那样毫无警惕而满腔热忱，引向毁灭和不可避免的不幸。从我身上汲取教训吧，即使不把我的话当作信条，至少要把我当作例证，要懂得获取知识是多么危险，而那些相信自己的家乡就是整个世界的人，比起那些渴望超越自己本性的人来，不知要幸福多少倍哩。

当我发现自己手中握有如此惊人的力量时，对于如何使用这种力量，我犹豫了很长时间。虽说我已经掌握了赋予生命的本领，然而要准备一个接受生命的躯体，包括它的繁复细微的纤维、肌肉和血管，这项工作还是面临着难以想象的困难和劳苦。起初我感到疑虑，到底是尝试创造一个像我自己一样的生命呢，还是创造一个结构较为简单的生物。但是我取得的第一次成功使我欢欣鼓舞，不容我再怀疑自己有能力将生命赋予一个像人一样复杂和奇妙的生物。我所掌握的材料看来还难以满足一项如此艰巨的事业的需要，可是我并不怀疑我最后会获得成功。我做好了准备去对付千万次的挫折，我的工作可能会不断地受挫，最终结果也可能并不完美。然而，当我想到在科学和机械学方面日新月异的进展时，我就倍受鼓舞，希望自己目前的尝试至少可以为将来的成功奠定基础。我也并不认为自己的计划因为过于庞大和复杂便是不切实际的。正是怀着这样一些想法，我开始了创造人的工作。因为人体的器官非常细微精致，这大大阻碍了我的进度，于是我决定，与起初的意图相反，我要让这个人具有庞大的体型，那就是说，大约八英尺高，全身按比例放大。在做出了这个决定以后，又花费了几个月的时间，成功地收集和整理好我的材料，然后我就开始了。

在渴望成功的最初的热情中，那旋风般的推动着我前进的复杂感情，是谁也无法想象的。生和死，对我来说乃是一种虚构出来的界限，我首先便要打破这种界限，让光明的洪流倾泻进我们这个黑暗的世界。一个新的物种将把我当作它的创造者和源头而感恩戴德，许多幸福而卓越的生命将把自己的存在归功于我的赐予。任何做父亲的，都不会像我这样完全有权利要求自己的孩子感激自己。按照这样的思路继续下去，我想，既然我能将生命赋予无生命的物质，那么随着时间的推移，我或许能（虽然我现在发现这是不可能的）在显然已经被死亡腐蚀了的躯体上复活生命。

当我以持续不懈的热情进行着我的事业时，就是这些想法在支撑着我的精神。我的脸颊因为用功而变得苍白，我的身体由于闭门不出而日渐衰弱。有时候，就在稳操胜券的当口，我失败了。然而我死死抱定希望，也许第二天，或者下一个钟头，就会成功了。对我所献身的事业充满希望，这就是我心中独自怀抱的秘密。当我半夜三更还在紧张急迫、屏息凝神地探索着自然最深处的奥秘时，唯有月亮在凝视着我。当我涉足于亵渎神明的墓穴的湿泥中，或者为了激活那毫无生命的泥土而折磨活着的动物时，谁能想象到我秘密的劳作所含的种种恐怖呢？现在想到那些情景，我的四肢便要发抖，不免头晕目眩。但在当时，却有一种不可抗拒的、几乎是疯狂的冲动驱使我往前走。要不是心里怀着这一个追求，我似乎就丧失了灵魂和任何感觉。这种感受实际上只是瞬间的心神恍惚，只要异常的刺激停止了作用，我回到惯常的状态以后，便觉得前所未有的敏锐。我从停尸房里收集骨头，我用亵渎神灵的手指去触摸人体的巨大秘密。被走廊和楼梯与其他房间分隔开来的一个单独的房间，或者说是房子顶部的一间斗室，被我当作了进行污秽的创造的工作室。因为专注于我的工作的细微操作，我的眼珠也从眼眶里鼓出来了。解剖室和屠宰场为我提供了许多材料，我身上的人性常常使我厌恶自己的工作，但是我仍然被不断增强的渴盼心理激励着，渐渐把我的工作做到接近完成。

当我这样全身心地专注于这项工作的时候，夏季的几个月过去了。这是最美丽的季节，大地从来没有赐予过人如此丰盛的收成，葡萄也从来没有生长出如此丰富的果实，可是我的眼睛对大自然的魅力却毫无感觉。这种使我无视周围景物的心境，也使我忘记了相距那么远、那么长的时间里未曾见面的亲友。我明白我的沉默会让他们不安，我也清楚地记得父亲说过的话：“我知道，你感觉愉快的时候，是会深情地想念我们的，我们将会定期收到你的来信。你应该原谅我，假如你的来信中断了，我就会据此认为你同样也忽视了在其他方面的责任。”

因此，我非常明白父亲会有怎样的心情，可是我没法让思想离开我的工作，它虽然令人厌恶，却不可抗拒地牢牢控制住了我的想象力。我似乎在这样希望，暂时把关系个人亲情的一切推延一下，等到我把那桩吞没了我天性中的所有习性的伟大事业完成以后再说。

那时我认为，父亲要是把我忽视通信看作我的罪过或者错误，那他是不公正的。可是现在我相信了，父亲觉得我并不是完全无可指责，那是有道理的。一个完美的人应当时时保持镇静和平的心态，绝不能让热情或者转瞬即逝的欲望扰乱了内心的宁静。我认为就这条原则而言，对知识的追求也并不例外。假如你所进行的研究有削弱你的感情的倾向，会破坏你对不可能掺和杂质的纯朴快乐的体味，那么，这种研究当然是不合法的，也就是说，不适宜于人类的头脑。如果始终遵守这条原则，如果谁也不允许任何事业来干扰他家庭感情的宁静的话，希腊就不会受奴役了，恺撒就不会损害他的国家了，美洲就会以和平渐进的方式被发现了，而墨西哥和秘鲁帝国也就不会被摧毁了。

不过我没注意到，我在故事最有趣的地方大谈道德教训了，你的表情在提醒我继续讲下去。

父亲在他的来信里半句也没有责备我，只是注意到了我的沉默，比过去更加详尽地询问了我做了些什么事情。冬天，春天和夏天，在我辛苦劳作的时候过去了，但我并未去观看鲜花和渐渐长大的绿叶——这些景象过去总是带给我无比的乐趣——我太深地沉浸在自己的工作中了。还没等到我的工作趋于结束的时候，当年的树叶便已枯萎，而眼前一天天愈加明白地显示出，我的事业进展得多么顺利。不过，我的热情也受到了焦虑情绪的影响，我与其说是一个从事于自己心爱的工作的艺术家，倒不如说像一个注定要在矿坑里干苦活的奴隶，或者是干任何其他有害身心的行当的人。每天夜里我都要承受一种慢性热病的折磨，我神经紧张到十分痛苦的程度：坠落一片树叶也会让我惊恐，我还躲避着我的伙伴们，仿佛自己犯了什么罪似的。有时候，我觉察到自己的惨状而感到恐慌，只有一心达到目的的动力在支撑着我。我的工作就要结束了，我相信锻炼和娱乐会驱走这些出现不久的病症，我向自己许诺，当我的创造完成以后，我既要锻炼，又要娱乐。

第五章　新生命的诞生

就在11月一个阴郁的夜晚，我看到了自己艰苦工作的成果。怀着焦急得近乎痛苦的心情，我拿起了身边的创造生命的工具，以便把生命的火花注入躺在我脚下的那个毫无生气的东西里。已经是子夜一点钟了，雨水凄厉地敲打得窗玻璃滴答作响，蜡烛也几乎燃尽了，凭借着半明半暗的莹莹烛光，我看见那个创造物睁开了浑浊呆滞的发黄的眼睛，它艰难地呼吸着，四肢开始痉挛地动弹起来。

我怎么能够描述出自己面临这一巨大灾变时的心情？或者说，我怎么能够描绘出自己备尝艰辛、殚精竭虑地创造出来的这个丑八怪？他的肢体是合乎比例的，我也曾经精心选材使它的相貌美丽。美丽！——天啊！他那黄色的皮肤几乎无法掩盖住下面的肌肉和血管，他的头发乌黑发亮，长长地飘垂着，他的牙齿白得像珍珠，可是这些鲜明的色彩和那湿漉漉的眼睛之间——那对眼睛几乎和安放它们的那暗白色的眼窝是同一种颜色，和他那皱缩的皮肤以及直挺挺的黑嘴唇之间，却恰好构成了吓人的对照。

人生中的种种偶然变故，和人性中的感情比起来还不算多么变化无常。我艰辛工作了差不多两年之久，唯一的目的是将生命力灌注到没有生命的躯体中去。为了这个目的，我剥夺了自己的休息和健康。我怀着毫无节制的热忱渴望着实现它。可是现在我完成了工作，而美丽的梦想却幻灭了，心里充满了令我窒息的恐惧和憎恶。我无法忍受自己创造出来的那个东西的模样，便冲出了工作室，回到卧室里长时间地徘徊踱步，没法安定下来睡觉。到后来疲乏终于替代了先前的烦乱，我和衣倒在床上，努力使自己能有一点忘却的时刻。然而这也是徒劳：我的确睡着了，可是狂乱的梦魇骚扰着我。我觉得自己看见了伊丽莎白，她容光焕发，正在英戈尔施塔特的街道上走着。我既高兴又惊奇，拥抱了她，可是当我在她的唇上印着第一个吻的时候，她的嘴唇却变成了死似的灰白，她的容貌似乎也改变了，我觉得自己手臂中抱着的是我死去的母亲的尸体，一块裹尸布包裹在她的身上，我看见吃死尸的蛆虫在绒布的褶皱里爬动着。我恐怖地从梦中惊醒，冷汗布满了我前额，我的牙齿打战，手脚都痉挛着。这时候月光透过百叶窗照射进来，借着它朦胧昏黄的光线，我又看见了那个丑八怪——我所创造出来的可悲的怪物。他揭起床帘，他的眼睛，如果可以叫作眼睛的话，正紧盯着我。他的嘴巴张着，喃喃地发出某种模糊不清的声音，同时皱着脸颊龇牙咧嘴地笑。他也许说了话，不过我没听见。他伸出了一只手，好像要阻拦我，但我逃掉了，急忙冲下了楼。我躲在这所房子附属的园子里，后半夜我一直留在那里，极度焦虑不安地来回走动，注意倾听着，听见一点声音就害怕是那个由我可悲地给予生命的活死尸逼近了。

啊！没有一个人能忍受他那副容貌带来的恐怖。就是一个复活了的木乃伊，也不会比这个丑八怪更骇人了。我在尚未完工的时候曾经仔细观看过他，他那时也很丑陋，可是当那些肌肉和关节一旦能够活动的时候，他就变成了一个甚至连但丁(1)也无法想象出来的怪物了。

我非常凄惨地度过了那个夜晚。有时候，我的脉搏跳动得又急又猛，以至于我感到每一根血管都在突突发颤；有时候，我又因为倦怠和极度衰弱而几乎跌倒在地上。和这种恐惧感混杂在一起，我还感到失望的苦痛。在如此长的时期里作为我的支撑和安慰的梦想，现在却变成了我的地狱。变化是多么的迅速，崩溃是何等的彻底！

阴郁而潮湿的清晨终于到来了，我通宵未眠的发痛的眼睛望见了英戈尔施塔特的教堂，看见了它那白色的尖塔和大钟，大钟正指着6点。看门人打开了我通宵当作避难所的园子的大门，于是我走进了街道，迈开急匆匆的步伐，仿佛要躲避在每个街角都可能出现在我眼前的那个丑恶的家伙。我的确曾壮起胆子想回到自己住的房间里去，可是我又觉得似乎在被什么力量推着往前走，尽管倾盆大雨从乌黑而阴郁的天空洒泼下来，湿透了我的全身。

就像这样，我继续走了一段时间，极力用体力的活动来减轻精神上的重负。我穿越过一条条街道，简直弄不清自己身在何处，或者在做什么。我的心由于满怀恐惧而发颤，我步履踉跄地急匆匆往前走，不敢向周围望上一眼——

像一个人，在冷寂的路上，
满怀恐惧地往前走，
回头看一眼，再向前，
却再也不敢回头；
因为他明白，
有个可怕的鬼正紧跟在他身后。(2)

我这样继续走，终于来到一家旅店的对面，在这旅店前面常常停着各式各样的驿车和马车。我停住了脚步，不知道是为什么，但是我在原处站了好几分钟，眼睛紧盯着从街的另一头向我驶来的一辆公共马车。当它驶近的时候，我发现那是一辆瑞士的驿车，它正好停在了我站立的地方，而且车门一打开，我竟看见了亨利·克莱瓦尔，而他一看见我便马上跳下车来。“我亲爱的弗兰肯斯坦，”他喊道，“看到你我多么高兴！我一下车，你就在这儿，是多么的幸运啊！”

没有什么能比见到克莱瓦尔更快乐的了。他的到来使我想起了我的父亲、伊丽莎白以及那所有的令我眷恋的家庭生活情景。我紧握住他的手，在一瞬间忘掉了自己的恐惧和不幸。突然地，而且是我许多个月以来第一次，我感到了平静和无忧无虑的欢乐。因此我向我的朋友表示了最衷心的欢迎，然后我们就朝我的学院走去。克莱瓦尔继续谈了一会儿有关我们共同的朋友的事，也谈到了他幸运地被准许到英戈尔施塔特来。“你完全想得到，”他说，“要说服我的父亲相信，并不是所有必要的知识都包括在崇高的簿记艺术中，该是多么的困难。而且说老实话，我担保他到最后一刻也并不相信哩，因为他对我不厌其烦的请求所给予的千篇一律的回答，老是《威克菲尔牧师传》(3)里那个荷兰教师的同一句话——‘我不懂希腊文，但我每年有一万弗罗林(4)，我不懂希腊文也吃得挺开心。’不过，他对我的爱还是最终克服了他对学问的厌弃，允许我到这个知识之邦来做一次探险旅行。”

“看到你使我感到了最大的快乐，不过请你告诉我，我的父亲、弟弟们和伊丽莎白怎么样。”

“非常的好，也非常的快乐，只是因为很少接到你的来信而感到有点不安。顺便说一下，为了他们的缘故，我本人还想责备你几句呢——不过，我亲爱的弗兰肯斯坦，”他接着说，停了片刻，仔细端详着我的脸，“我刚才没注意到，你看起来好像病得很重啊，这么消瘦和苍白，你瞧上去似乎接连几夜没睡过觉似的。”

“你猜对了。最近我一直专心致志地忙着一件工作，没法让自己得到充足的睡眠，就像你见到的这样。不过我希望，真诚地希望，所有这类工作都就此结束，我终于获得了自由。”

我全身剧烈地颤抖着，我不敢去想，更不敢提及前一天晚上发生的事情。我加快步伐向前走，于是我们很快就到了学院。这时我才想起，而这个想法使我发起抖来，那就是我留在家里的那个东西或许还在，还活生生的，走来走去。我害怕见到那个怪物，但我更害怕亨利会见到他。因此我请求他在楼下等一会儿，立即冲上楼梯到自己的房间去。我的手已经放在了门锁上了，而心里还没有镇定下来。于是我停了停，一阵冷战袭遍了我的全身。我用力把门打开，就像孩子以为门后有个鬼魂在等着的时候常做的那样，但是什么也没有出现。我胆战心惊地走进去：房间里没有人，卧室里也没有那个丑陋吓人的不速之客。我简直不敢相信这样的好运会落到自己的头上，不过，当我确证我的敌人真的已经跑掉了的时候，我高兴得直拍手，然后跑下楼去叫克莱瓦尔。

我们上楼进了房间，仆人立即送来了早餐，可是我还不能镇定住自己。控制着我的不仅仅是高兴，我由于极度的神经过敏而感到身上阵阵地刺痛，脉搏也在剧烈地跳动。我不能在同一个地方安定一秒钟，我跳过一把又一把椅子，拍着手，大声地笑。克莱瓦尔起初以为我异乎寻常的兴奋是因他到来而高兴，不过当他更留意地观察了我之后，他看出在我的眼神里有一种他无法解释的狂乱，我那高声的、放纵的、毫无感情的大笑使他既害怕又吃惊。

“我亲爱的维克多，”他叫道，“看在上帝分上，这是怎么回事啊？别再这样笑了。你病得多重啊！这到底是什么原因？”

“不要问我，”我喊道，用手蒙住了眼睛，因为我觉得我看到了那个恐怖的妖怪悄悄溜进了房间，“‘他’能告诉你——啊，救救我！救救我！”我想象怪物抓住了我，我发疯似的挣扎，然后猛然昏倒在地上。

可怜的克莱瓦尔！他会有怎样的感觉？他怀着那么快乐的心情期盼着的会面，竟会如此奇怪地变成了一种苦涩。可是我并没有目睹他的痛苦，因为我已经人事不省了，很长很长时间里我都没能恢复知觉。

一种神经性的热病就此开始，它使得我在几个月时间里卧床不起。在那些日子里，亨利是我唯一的看护。后来我才明白，亨利知道我父亲年纪太大，不宜做这样的长途旅行，而我的病又会使伊丽莎白伤心，所以他向他们隐瞒了我的病情，以免他们痛苦。他也知道，对我来说再没有比他自己更和蔼、更细心的看护了。他坚信我会康复，所以他一点也不怀疑自己这样做非但不是坏事，反而是对他们做了力所能及的最好的事情。

但我确实是病得非常重，只是因为我的朋友的无微不至和毫不懈怠的照料，才挽救了我的生命。我所创造的那个妖魔的形象一直浮现在我眼前，在我乱七八糟的呓语中也不断地提到他。我的话无疑使得亨利吃惊：他起初相信那是我受到扰乱的想象力在胡思乱想，可是我老是重复不断地谈同一件事，这使得他不得不考虑，我的神志错乱一定起因于某种异乎寻常的可怕事件。

我终于好起来了，不过恢复得非常缓慢，而且频繁发作的病情反复也让我的朋友惊恐和痛苦。我还记得自己第一次能够以愉快的心情观看外部事物时的情景，我看到落叶已经不见了，遮掩着我的窗户的树木已经发出了嫩芽。那是一个奇妙的春天，这个季节对我的康复大有裨益。我觉得自己的心中，欢乐和爱的感情在复苏，我的忧郁消失了，没过多久，我就变得和过去未被致命的激情袭击之前同样地振奋了。

“最亲爱的克莱瓦尔，”我感叹道，“你对我是多么友爱，多么好。这整整一个冬天，你没能像你打算的那样埋头钻研，却完全消磨在我的病室里。我怎么才能报偿你呢？我严厉自责，因为我的缘故而让你失望，不过你是会原谅我的。”

“只要你不再烦恼不安，尽快地恢复健康，你就完全报偿我了。既然你现在情绪很好，我想我可以给跟你谈一件事情，行吗？”

我发抖了。谈一件事情！那会是什么？他会提到我简直想也不敢想的那个东西吗？

“请你放心，”克莱瓦尔看见我变了脸色，便说，“要是这会使你不安，我就不提它了。不过，如果你的父亲和表妹收到一封你的亲笔信的话，他们会非常高兴的。他们还不知道你病得多么严重，你长时间的沉默一定使他们担心了。”

“就是这事吗，我亲爱的亨利？你怎么会觉得我的心思不会首先飞向那些我所爱的、而且是那么值得我爱的亲人们呢？”

“如果这就是你现在的心情，我的朋友，那么你或许会很高兴读一读在这儿搁了几天的一封信。我相信它是你的表妹写给你的。”

————————————————————

(1) 但丁（Dante Alighieri，1265—1321），意大利诗人，他在《神曲》的《地狱篇》里描绘了许多可怕的形象。

(2) 引自英国诗人柯勒律治的长诗《老水手行》。

(3) 《威克菲尔牧师传》（Vicar of Wakesfield），英国作家哥尔德斯密斯（Oliver Goldsmith，1728—1774）的著名小说。

(4) 弗罗林（florin），荷兰金币名。

第六章　亲情和友谊

于是克莱瓦尔把下面这封信放到了我的手中。它是我的伊丽莎白写来的——

我最亲爱的表哥——你病了，病情很重，即使亲爱的好亨利不断地写信来，也不能使我对你放心。你被医生禁止写信——禁止握笔，不过即使你的只言片语，亲爱的维克多，对平息我们的挂虑也是必要的。很长时间以来，我总以为每一班邮车会带来你的一封短信，我也一直劝阻叔叔启程到英戈尔施塔特来。我要避免他在这样漫长的旅途中经受种种不便甚至危险，可是我又那样时时遗憾自己不能亲自这样做！我在心中想象，在病床前照料你的任务，竟交给了一个只想赚钱的老看护，她绝不会猜想到你的愿望，也不会以你可怜的表妹的细心和真情来照看你。不过这一切已经过去了，克莱瓦尔写信来告诉我们，你确实一天天在康复。我热切地希望，你很快就会用你的亲笔信来证实这个消息。

愿你恢复健康——然后回到我们身边。你会有一个幸福而欢乐的家，有真心爱你的亲人。你的父亲身体康健，他一心只想见到你——确证你已经完全恢复，这样他那慈祥的面容上就不会有一缕愁云了。看到我们的欧内斯特大有长进，你会多么高兴啊！他现在十六岁了，充满了朝气和活力。他渴望成为一个真正的瑞士人，到国外去服役，不过我们不能和他分手，至少要等到他哥哥回到我们身边才行。叔叔对他想到遥远的国家从事军事生涯并不乐意，可是欧内斯特绝没有你那种专注用功的毅力。他把学习看作令人讨厌的枷锁——他的光阴都消耗在了野外，不是爬山，就是划船。我担心他会变成一个游手好闲的人，除非我们让步，同意他去从事他自己选择的职业。

自从你离开我们之后，除了我们可爱的弟弟们在长大以外，一切都没有多大改变。蔚蓝的湖水，皑皑的雪山，它们都永远不变。我想，我们安宁的家和我们满足的心也是被同样不变的规律所支配的。我那些琐碎的事务占据了我的时间，也让我得到了乐趣，看到周围的人都露出快乐和亲切的笑脸，我努力做的任何事情就得到了回报。你离家以后，我们小小的家庭里只有一个变化。你还记得于斯丁·莫里兹是怎样进入我们家的吗？也许你记不起了，所以我要用几句话讲讲她的故事。她的母亲莫里兹太太是个拖着四个孩子的寡妇，于斯丁是她的第三个孩子。这个女孩一直最得她父亲的宠爱，可是她的母亲出于一种奇怪的反常心理，却不能容忍她，在莫里兹先生去世以后待她很坏。我婶婶注意到了这种情况，在于斯丁十二岁的时候，说服她的母亲让她住到了我们家。由于我们国家的共和制度，人们的生活方式比周围那些君主制大国更为纯朴和快乐。所以，不同阶层的居民们之间的差别不是那样显著，较低阶层的人既不像其他国家的贫民那样穷困，也不是那样被人看不起，他们的生活方式也更加文雅，更有道德。一个日内瓦的仆人，和一个法国或英国的仆人绝不是一回事。于斯丁就这样被我们的家庭接纳，学习一个仆人的职责。这种地位在我们这个幸运的国家里，并不意味着无知愚昧，或者是牺牲了个人的尊严。

你也许还记得，于斯丁是你非常喜欢的人。我还记得你有一次说，如果你心情不好，只要于斯丁看你一眼，你的烦恼就会消散，而理由则和阿里奥斯托谈到安杰丽嘉的美丽时是一样的(1)——她看起来是那样心地坦率和快乐。婶婶对她很有感情，所以让她受的教育比最初打算的要更优越。这一恩惠获得了充分的报偿，于斯丁是世界上最知恩图报的孩子了，我倒不是说她有什么口头的表白，我从来没有听见她说过半个字，可是你能从她的眼神里看出，她几乎崇拜着她的女恩人。尽管她性格活泼，在许多方面还有欠细致周到，可是她对婶婶的一举一动却极为留心。她把婶婶当作尽善尽美的典范，努力模仿她的言谈举止，以至于直到现在于斯丁还常常让我想起婶婶来。

在亲爱的婶婶去世的时候，大家都过于沉浸在自己的悲痛之中，所以没怎么注意可怜的于斯丁，而于斯丁在婶婶病中一直满怀忧虑地以爱心照料着她。可怜的于斯丁患了重病，可是还有更多的磨难在等待着她。

她的兄弟姐妹一个接一个死去了，她的母亲除了这个被她忽视的女儿之外，就没有任何子女了。这个女人的良心感到了不安，她开始考虑，受她宠爱的孩子去世乃是上天对她偏心的惩罚。她是个罗马天主教徒，我相信，听她忏悔的神父也使她坚信了自己的想法。所以，在你去了英戈尔施塔特之后几个月，于斯丁就被她那悔悟了的母亲领回去了。可怜的姑娘！她离开我们家的时候哭了。自从婶婶去世以后，她变了许多，悲伤使得她过去活泼欢快的性格变得温和而柔顺了。住在母亲的家里也难以使她重新快乐起来。那个可怜的女人在悔恨的心境中变得情绪波动，有时候她哀求于斯丁宽恕她的冷酷无情，但更多的时候是把子女的死怪罪到于斯丁身上。长期的烦躁终于使得莫里兹太太身体衰竭了，起初她越来越暴躁易怒，而现在她则永远安息了。她是在寒潮第一次侵袭的时候去世的。于斯丁又回到我们这里了。说真的，我很疼爱她。她很聪明很温柔，而且非常漂亮，正像我前面说过的，她的神态和表情一直使我想起我亲爱的婶婶。

我亲爱的表哥，我还得说几句有关心爱的小威廉的话。我真希望你能见到他。就他的年龄而言，他的个子是挺高的，长着一双充满甜美笑意的蓝眼睛，黑色的睫毛，卷曲的头发。他的脸颊泛着健康的红晕，微笑的时候便出现两个小酒窝。他已经有一两个小“妻子”了，不过路易莎·毕伦是他最喜欢的，那是一个五岁的漂亮小姑娘。

现在，亲爱的维克多，我敢说你一定希望听听有关日内瓦的那些好人们的闲言碎语吧。漂亮的曼斯菲尔小姐即将和一个年轻的英国人约翰·梅尔本先生结婚，已经接待了很多祝贺的客人。她的丑姐姐曼侬去年秋天嫁给了一个富有的银行家杜维亚先生。你的要好的同学路易·马努瓦，在克莱瓦尔离开日内瓦以后碰到了好几件倒霉事。不过他已经恢复了情绪，据说就要娶一位非常活泼漂亮的法国女人塔弗尼尔夫人了。她是个寡妇，而且比马努瓦要大得多，但是她很受人们崇拜，每个人都喜欢她。

我越写心情就越好，亲爱的表哥，可是当我要结束的时候，忧虑又重回心头。写信吧，最亲爱的维克多——哪怕一行——哪怕一个字，都将使我们快乐。万分感激亨利的好心，他的爱意，以及他写的那么多封信，我们真诚地感谢他。再见！我的表哥，保重自己。再有，我请求你，写信来！

伊丽莎白·拉文查

17××年3月18日，日内瓦

“亲爱的，亲爱的伊丽莎白！”我念完她的来信后叫道，“我马上就写信，以免他们心里焦虑。”我写了信，而这件费力的工作竟使我疲惫不堪。不过我已经开始康复了，恢复的情况很正常。两个礼拜以后，我就能够离寓所外出了。

我身体复原之后首先要做的一件事，就是把克莱瓦尔介绍给大学里的几位教授。做这件事使我经受了某种折磨，对我精神上所受的创伤很不适宜。就从那个结束了工作、开始了不幸的致命的夜晚起，我甚至对自然哲学这个名称也感到强烈的反感。尽管我的健康已经恢复到相当程度，可是一旦见到化学仪器，神经性症状的一切痛苦便会再度发作。亨利看出了这一点，把我所有的仪器都从我的眼前搬走了。他还让我迁了住所，因为他发觉我对过去当作实验室的那个房间很讨厌。但是当我去拜访那些教授的时候，克莱瓦尔的这些关心就完全无济于事了。沃德曼先生仁慈而热情地夸奖我在科学上取得了惊人的进步，那简直是在折磨我。他很快就发现了我不喜欢这个话题，但他猜不到真正的原因，便把我的感情归结为谦虚，并把话题从我的进步转到了科学本身上来，正如我明白看出的那样，他是想引我谈话。可是我能怎么办呢？他的用意是要让我高兴，然而他却在折磨我。我感到他仿佛细心地把一件件刑具展示在我眼前，这些刑具是以后用来慢慢地、残酷地把我处死的。他的话语使我剧痛，可是我却不敢表示出自己的痛苦。克莱瓦尔的眼睛和感觉总是能很快地觉察到别人的感情，他便借口自己在这方面完全无知，推开了这个话题，于是谈话也就转到一般的问题上去了。我从内心感激我的朋友，不过我没有说出来。我清楚地看出他感到很惊奇，可是他从来就不会试图让我吐露心里的秘密。而我虽然怀着敬慕和尊重相互交织的感情爱着他，但仍然没法说服自己把这件时常浮现于记忆中的事向他坦露，我害怕把详情讲给另一个人听只会更加深它在我心头的印象。

克伦普先生并不是同样的温和。我当时处在几乎是不堪承受的敏感状况下，所以他那刺耳的、毫不掩饰的颂扬比沃德曼先生好意的称赞更使我痛苦。“真是活见鬼！”他嚷道，“嗨，克莱瓦尔先生，我敢说他已经胜过了我们大家。嗬，你尽管不相信好了，不过这是真的。一个年轻人，几年前还像信奉福音书一样坚定地信奉科讷利乌斯·阿格里帕，现在可是大学里的拔尖人物了，要是不快些把他拉下来的话，我们大家都要丢脸啦——唉，唉，”他看见我脸上露出痛苦的表情，又接着说，“弗兰肯斯坦先生很谦逊，这在一个年轻人身上是一种美好的品德。年轻人对自己的估价应该低一些才好，你知道，克莱瓦尔先生，我在年轻的时候就是这样，不过这种品德很快就会被消磨掉的。”

克伦普先生现在开始吹嘘起自己来，而这正好愉快地使谈话从令我烦恼的话题转移开了。

克莱瓦尔对我在自然科学方面的兴趣从来没有产生过共鸣，他对文学的追求与我所从事的研究完全不同。他到大学来，怀着使自己成为精通东方语言的大师的打算，希望借此为自己确定的人生计划开辟出一个领域。他决心要追求光荣的事业，便把目光投向东方，认为这可以为他的进取精神提供施展的天地。波斯语、阿拉伯语、梵语吸引了他的注意力，而我也很容易地被引向了同样的学习内容。无所事事的生活素来是我厌恶的，现在既然我希望摆脱自己的忧思，而且憎恶我过去的研究，所以和我的朋友共同学习使我感到极大的解脱，同时我在东方学者的著作中不仅获得了教益，也得到了安慰。我和克莱瓦尔不同，我并不试图对东方的各种语系获得一种批判性的知识，因为我除了暂时消遣而外没有别的用意。我的阅读只求理解其中蕴含的意义，而我的劳动得到了报偿。东方作家们的忧郁情调对人有抚慰作用，他们的欢乐则能振奋精神，其感人的程度是我在研读其他国家的作家时所从未体验过的。在你阅读东方作家的著作时，生活仿佛就是温煦的太阳和玫瑰园——仿佛就是一个爱而不得的女子的笑靥蹙眉，那团火焰简直要烧毁你的心。这与希腊和罗马的勇武的英雄诗歌是多么的不同！

夏季便在这样的学习中度过了，而我返回日内瓦的行期定在了秋末，可是因为几件意外的事故耽误，冬季和雪天又来临了，道路阻塞难行，我的行期又被推延到次年春季。这样的耽误使我很痛苦，因为我渴望着见到我的故乡和我心爱的亲友。我回家的日子所以被延误这么久，只是因为不愿意在克莱瓦尔与当地人熟识之前把他单独撇在陌生的地方。不过这个冬天倒是过得很快乐，而且虽然春天比通常时候来得晚，可是当它来临的时候，美丽的景色已足以补偿它的姗姗来迟了。

5月已经开始了，我每天都在盼着来信，以便确定我动身的日子，这时亨利建议到英戈尔施塔特的周围去做一次徒步旅行，也算我向自己住过这么久的国家做个人的告别。对这个建议我欣然赞同，我本来就喜欢体育锻炼，过去常在祖国的山川风光中进行这类性质的漫游时，克莱瓦尔总是我最好的伴侣。

我们在漫游中度过了两个礼拜，我的身体和精神都早已恢复了，而我所呼吸的宜人的空气，我们旅行途中所接触到的自然界的种种见闻，以及和我的朋友的谈话，更使我的身心获得了新的力量。以前，我的研究曾使得我和伙伴们疏于交往，让我变得很不合群，可是克莱瓦尔唤回了我心中的美好感情，他重新教会了我去爱大自然的景物，爱儿童欢乐的笑脸。多好的朋友！他多么诚挚地爱着我，又是多么真诚地极力要提高我的精神境界，直到它能达到与他相同的高度！一种自私的追求一直在束缚和限制着我，直到他的慷慨和爱心温暖了我，开阔了我心胸，我又重新变成了几年前那个幸福的人，爱所有的人，也被所有的人爱，再也没有任何苦恼和忧虑。心情一愉快，没有生命的自然界也就显示出了赋予我最大欢乐的力量。静谧的天空和青翠的田野使我心旷神怡。现在这个季节真是奇妙，春天的鲜花在树篱间盛开，夏季的花朵也在含苞欲放。前一年折磨我的思想现在已不再来骚扰我了，过去我尽管竭力要摆脱它们，它们仍然以不可抵御的力量重压着我。

亨利因为我的欢乐而感到高兴，并且真诚地和我的感情交融共鸣。他一方面表达着充满自己心灵的种种感受，另一方面也努力让我愉快起来。每当这个时候，他的智能真是令人惊叹，他的谈话充满了想象力，他常常模仿波斯和阿拉伯作家的风格，虚构出富于神奇幻想和激情的故事。有时候，他又背诵我最喜欢的诗，或者引我争论一些问题，而他支持自己的观点时总是极富独创性。

我们在一个礼拜天的下午回到了学院，农民们正在跳舞，我们遇见的每个人都显得喜气扬扬。我自己也兴高采烈，满怀欢乐地蹦跳着往前走。

————————————————————

(1) 阿里奥斯托（Ludovic Ariosto，1474—1533），意大利著名诗人。安杰丽嘉是其传奇体叙事诗《疯狂的奥尔兰多》（0rlando Furioso）中的女主人公。

第七章　灾祸初起

回到房间，我看到了父亲写来的这封信——

我亲爱的维克多——你或许已经不耐烦地等待着一封确定你回家日期的信吧。我最初很想只写上几行，只是提一提我希望在哪一天能见到你而已。可是那将是一种残酷的仁慈，我不敢这样做。当你期望着受到愉快和欢乐的迎接的时候，却相反看到眼泪和悲惨，我的儿子，你将震惊到何等程度呢？而我，维克多，又怎样来叙述我的不幸呢？分离并不能使你对我们的欢乐和悲伤麻木不仁，我又怎么能给我长期远离的儿子增加痛苦？我希望让你对这个悲惨的消息预先有所准备，可是我又明白这是不可能的，即使现在你的目光扫过这页信纸，寻找将要给你带来噩耗的字句时，也不可能先有准备。

威廉死了！——那个可爱的孩子，他的笑容曾经使我的心欢乐而温暖，他是那么的温顺，那么的快活！维克多，他是被人杀死的！

我不愿试图来安慰你，我只想简单地讲一讲事情的经过：

上个礼拜四（5月7日），我，我的侄女，还有你的两个弟弟，到普兰帕莱去散步。傍晚时分天气温暖而晴朗，我们比平时走得远一些。等我们想到返回的时候，天已经快黑了；那时我们发现走在前面的威廉和欧内斯特不见了。因此我们就坐下来休息，等他们回来。欧内斯特很快回来了，并问我们是否见到了他的弟弟。他说，他一直在和威廉一起玩，后来威廉跑到一边去藏了起来，他四处找也找不到，随后又等了他很久，但他始终没有回来。

他的述说使我们很惊恐，于是我们就继续寻找他，直到夜幕降临，这时候伊丽莎白猜想他也许已经回了家。但他并不在家。我们又回头再找，还带着火把，因为我一想到可爱的孩子迷了路，在夜晚的潮气和露水里毫无掩蔽，就没法安心，伊丽莎白也是焦急到了极点。大约到清晨五点，我找到了心爱的孩子，头天晚上见到他时还是那么活泼健康，现在却脸色青黑、一动不动地瘫卧在草地上：他的脖子上还留着凶手的指印。

他被抬回了家，我脸上显而易见的痛苦表情向伊丽莎白暴露了秘密。她非常想见一见尸体。我一开始试图阻拦她，但她坚持要看，闯进了停放尸体的房间，急匆匆地查验了受害孩子的脖子，然后紧握着双手高喊道：“啊，上帝啊！是我害死了我亲爱的小男孩！”

她昏过去了，我们费了极大的劲才使她恢复了知觉。当她醒过来以后，只是一味地哭泣和叹气。她告诉我，那天傍晚威廉曾缠着她，要戴她项上挂着的那个你母亲的非常珍贵的小肖像。肖像现在不见了，无疑就是这副肖像的诱惑驱使凶手干下了这桩事。我们目前还没有发现有关凶手的任何线索，不过我们要找到他的努力是绝不会停息的，然而怎么做也不会使我心爱的威廉死而复生了！

回来吧，亲爱的维克多；只有你才能安慰伊丽莎白。她现在不停地哭泣，并且毫无道理地责备自己导致了威廉的死亡；她的话简直刺穿了我的心。我们都很伤心，我的儿子，难道这不会更促使你回来安慰我们大家吗？你亲爱的母亲！唉，维克多！我现在要说，感谢上帝，她没有活着目睹她心爱的小儿子惨不忍睹地死去！

回来吧，维克多，不要抱着向凶手复仇的想法，而要怀着平和温柔的感情，这样才能疗治我们心头的创伤，而不会使它们更加恶化。我的好孩子，怀着仁慈和对爱你的人们的情意，不要带着对敌人的仇恨，走进这哀伤之家吧。

你亲爱的、伤心的父亲，阿尔丰斯·弗兰肯斯坦

17××年5月12日，日内瓦

克莱瓦尔在我读信的时候一直注意着我的神情，他吃惊地观察到，我由开始接到亲人的消息时的欢乐转变为了绝望。我把信扔到桌子上，用双手捂住了脸。

“我亲爱的弗兰肯斯坦，”他察觉到我在痛苦地哭泣，便高声说道，“难道你总是要不快乐才好吗？我亲爱的朋友，发生什么事了？”

我示意他拿起那封信，自己则极其烦乱地在房间里走来走去。当他读到我不幸的消息时，眼泪不禁夺眶而出。

“我没法安慰你，我的朋友，”他说，“你的灾难是无法弥补的。你打算怎么办？”

“即刻回日内瓦，亨利，跟我一道去找马车。”

在路上，克莱瓦尔努力要说几句话来安慰我，可是他只能表达他由衷的同情。“可怜的威廉！”他说，“可爱的讨人喜欢的孩子，现在他和他那天使般的母亲安息在一起了！谁见过这个年幼而美丽的孩子那聪明快乐的模样，都一定会为他的夭折而流泪的！死得那样的惨，竟被凶手给掐死了！要多么残忍的凶手才忍心摧残这样富于童年生气的无辜的孩子！可怜的小家伙！我们只有一个安慰，他的亲人们在为他哀悼和哭泣，然而他却已安息。那阵剧痛结束了，他的苦难永远终止了。一片草泥覆盖了他美好的躯体，他从此便再没有任何痛苦。他不再是怜悯的对象了，我们应该把怜悯留给仍然活着的可怜的人们。”

我们匆匆走过大街小巷的时候，克莱瓦尔这样说着。这些话深深地印在我的脑海里，后来我在孤独寂寞时又想起它们来。不过在当时，马车一到我就急忙上了车，向我的朋友告别了。

我的旅途是十分阴郁的。一开始，我盼望快快赶路，因为我渴望安慰我亲爱的哀伤的亲人们，和他们分担痛苦，可是当我渐渐接近故乡的时候，又减慢了速度。我几乎承受不了涌入心头的那许多复杂的感情。我一路上看见了青年时代所熟悉的种种景物，而我差不多有六年光景没有再见到它们了。在这段时光里，发生了多么大的变化啊！一件突如其来的灾难性的事变发生了，可是还有上千种细微的事件可能渐渐地导致其他许多改变，尽管它们是悄无声息地进行着，却不会减轻其决定性作用。恐惧压倒了我，我不敢再往前走，我惧怕着千百种使我战栗的不可名状的灾祸，虽然我没法说清楚它们是什么。

在这种痛苦的心态下，我在洛桑滞留了两天。我凝视着湖面，湖水波澜不兴，周围一片宁静，皑皑雪山，那“大自然的宫殿”，丝毫没有改变。静谧的如仙境般美丽的景色渐渐使我恢复了平静，于是我又继续着回日内瓦的旅程。

道路沿着湖边伸延着，越是接近故乡，道路越窄。我更加清晰地看见了尤拉山的坡脊，还有璀璨的勃朗峰。我像一个小孩子似的哭起来。“亲爱的山啊！我的美丽的湖啊！你们怎样来欢迎这个游子呢？你们的峰峦明净清晰，天穹和湖水碧蓝而宁静。这是在预示着和平呢，还是在嘲弄着我的不幸？”

我的朋友啊，我担心这样细细诉说到家前的种种情况，会使自己变得令人生厌了，可是那些日子还算是相对幸福的，现在我还怀着愉快的心情想念着它们。我的祖国，我亲爱的祖国！除了本国的同胞，还有谁能说得出我在重睹你的溪流、你的山峦，尤其是你可爱的湖水时心里的欢乐呢？

然而，当我越来越接近家门的时候，忧伤和恐惧又再度压倒了我。周围夜色沉沉，当我难以看清那黑黝黝的群山时，便更觉心情阴郁。眼前好像是一幅昭示着灾祸的广袤而黯淡的图景，而我则朦胧地预见到自己命中注定要成为最不幸的人。唉！我的预见是正确的，只是在一点上不准确，那就是尽管我想象和惧怕着种种苦难，也没能设想出我注定将承受的痛苦的百分之一。

当我抵达日内瓦附近地区的时候，天已经黑尽了，城门已经关闭了，我不得不在色歇隆度过当夜，这是离城半里格(1)的一个村子。天空很宁静。我因为不能入睡，便决定去看一看可怜的威廉被杀害的那个地方。由于无法从城中穿过，我只好坐小船渡过湖泊去普兰帕莱了。就在这短短的航途中，我看到了闪电在勃朗峰顶飞舞时那美丽之极的景象。当时暴风雨似乎在迅速地逼近，我登上了湖岸，爬上了一座小山，这样我就可以观察到暴风雨的发展过程。它在往前行进，天空乌云密布，不久我就感觉到大滴的雨点慢慢落了下来，而风暴的威力正在迅疾地增长着。

我离开坐处，继续往前走，尽管黑暗每分钟都变得更浓重，风暴变得更强劲，惊雷在我头上以可怕的轰鸣炸响。雷声在萨拉维、尤拉山和萨瓦的阿尔卑斯山那一带引起了回响。跳跃闪烁的电光晃得我眼花缭乱，它把湖面照得雪亮，使湖水看起来就像一片宽阔无边的燃烧的火海，接着在瞬刻之间，一切又变为漆黑，直到我的眼睛从方才的闪光中恢复视力为止。就像时常在瑞士发生的情况那样，暴风雨总是在天空的各个部分同时出现。最猛烈的风暴在城市的正北方，处于贝尔里芙海角和科佩村之间的那部分湖面上。另一场风暴正以微弱的闪电照亮着尤拉山，还有一场风暴则在湖东高耸的摩尔山上酝酿着，它将山峰笼罩在黑雾中，间或又让山峰显露出来。

我一面观看着如此美丽却又如此可怕的暴风雨，一面疾速地往前走。天空中那场壮丽的大自然的战争使我精神激奋，我紧握着双手，高声喊道：“威廉，可爱的小天使！这就是你的葬礼，这就是你的挽歌！”正在我说这些话的时候，我察觉到在阴暗处有一个身影，正从附近的树丛背后偷偷地溜出来。我伫立不动，凝神观看，我绝不会弄错。一道电光照亮了那个物体，向我清楚地显现了它的形状。它那庞大的体型，畸形的相貌，非人的丑陋，瞬刻之间就告诉了我，这就是我赐予生命的那个怪物，那个肮脏的魔鬼。他在这里干什么？他会不会是（我想到这一点就不寒而栗）杀害我弟弟的凶手？这个念头刚一掠过我的脑际，我就对它确信无疑。我的牙齿颤抖得格格作响，我被迫靠在一棵树上支撑着自己。那个身影迅速地从我面前掠过，在黑暗之中隐没了。只要还算具有人的躯壳的任何东西，也不至于去毁灭那个可爱的孩子啊。他就是那个凶手！我绝不怀疑这一点。单凭这个念头出现在我的脑际，就不可辩驳地证明了这是事实。我想到过跟踪这个魔鬼，但那将是徒劳无益的，因为又一道闪电掠过，我发现他正攀缘在与普兰帕莱南边相邻的几乎是垂直的萨拉维山的悬崖上。他很快地爬到了山顶，接着就消失了。

我待在原地一动也不动。雷声停了，不过雨还在下，周围全被一片无法穿透的黑暗包裹着。我的脑海里历历展现着我迄今一直努力要忘却的种种事件：我创造生命所经历的一系列过程；我的亲手创造物活生生地出现在我床前；他的不辞而别。从他最初获得生命的那个夜晚算起，差不多有两年时间过去了。这是不是他犯下的第一个罪行？唉！我竟然放纵一个以残害生命和制造不幸为乐事的、堕落的怪物到这世界上来。难道不是他杀害了我的弟弟吗？

没有谁能想象到我在露天度过的又冷又湿的后半夜里，我内心所承受的剧痛。我丝毫没有感觉到气候的恶劣，我的想象中疾速地掠过罪恶和绝望的景象。我在想着我释放到人间来的这个生物，是我赋予他意志和力量来实行恐怖的目的，例如现在他干下的这种行径，而这简直就等于我自己是一个吸血鬼，是从坟墓中释放出我自己的鬼魂，迫使它去毁灭我的所有亲人。

天亮了，于是我迈步走向城里。城门已经打开，我急忙朝父亲的房子走去。我一开始想到的是披露我所知道的有关凶手的情况，这样可以让人们立即进行追捕。但当我考虑到自己将不得不讲出那个故事，便只好作罢了。我自己制造了一个东西，我还赋予它生命，我还在半夜三更的时候、在险峻高山的悬崖上碰见了它。除了这完全不能令人置信而外，我也想起了在我的创造物出世的时候，自己曾经患过神经性热病，所以在讲述这个故事时更会显得像发高热时的胡言乱语。我很清楚，假如别的任何人向我讲述类似的事情，我也会把它视为精神错乱的疯话。此外，即使是亲友们信任我，被我说服去抓捕它，那个怪物的奇异的特性也是能够使它逃脱的。那么，跟踪追捕又有什么用呢？谁能够逮住有本领爬上萨拉维山的悬崖峭壁的怪物呢？这番考虑使我拿定了主意，决定保持沉默。

大约在清晨五点，我走进了父亲的房子。我告诉仆人别打搅家里人，然后走进书房去等候他们在通常的时间起床。

六年时光过去了，除了一道无法抹去的痕迹以外，这六年就像是一场梦，现在我又站在离家去英戈尔施塔特之前最后一次拥抱父亲的同一个地方了。亲爱的、可敬的父亲！他仍然在我身边。我凝视着立在壁炉上的母亲的肖像。这是按照父亲的意愿绘制的纪念性的主题画，画着卡罗琳·波福怀着绝望的痛苦跪在她父亲的灵柩旁。她的服装朴素，她的脸颊苍白，可是她有一种尊严而美丽的神态，不容人产生怜悯的感情。在这幅画像下面是一幅威廉的小画像，当我看到它时，不由得泪流满面。就在这时候，欧内斯特进来了，他听说我到家了，就急忙来迎接我。他见到我时显示出一种含着哀伤的快乐。“欢迎你，我最亲爱的维克多，”他说，“啊！我真希望你在三个月前回来，那时你会看到我们全都愉快而欢乐！现在你回来是要和我们分担无法减轻的悲痛了。不过我希望有你在家可以使父亲振作起来，他似乎正在不幸的重压下消沉下去；你的劝解也将使可怜的伊丽莎白停止她那毫无补益的痛苦的自责——可怜的威廉！他是我们的宝贝和我们的骄傲！”

无法自制的泪水从我弟弟的眼中流下来，致命的剧痛袭遍了我的全身。以前，我所想象的只是我这凄凉之家的悲惨情景，而现实对于我来说却是一场新的、同样可怕的灾祸。我极力让欧内斯特安静下来，我更仔细地询问有关父亲和我称为表妹的她的情况。

“她是我们当中最需要安慰的人，”欧内斯特说，“她指责自己是导致弟弟死亡的原因，这使得她非常痛苦。不过自从凶手被发现以后——”

“凶手被发现了！天啊！那怎么可能？谁能试图追上他？这是不可能的事——倒不如去追赶风，或者用一根草去挡住山溪。我也见到了他，他昨晚还没被抓住！”

“我不明白你的意思，”弟弟回答说，声音很惊讶，“不过发现了凶手却使我们更加彻底的不幸了。起初谁也不相信，现在尽管有了充分的证据，伊丽莎白仍然还是不相信。的确，谁能相信于斯丁·莫里兹，那样的和气，那样的爱我们全家，在突然间竟可能犯下如此可怕、如此令人震惊的罪行呢？”

“于斯丁·莫里兹！可怜的、可怜的姑娘，她被指控了吗？不过这是冤枉的，谁都知道这一点，谁也不相信，的确不相信，对吧，欧内斯特？”

“一开始谁也不相信，可是发现了一些情况，几乎迫使我们不得不信，而且她本人的举止又是如此惊慌，这就使得证据更加确凿，我担心事情已经是无可怀疑的了。不过她今天就要受审判，到那时你就可以听到所有的情况。”

他说，在发现可怜的威廉被害的那天早晨，于斯丁病了，而且有好几天都卧床不起。在这段时间里，一个仆人偶尔翻检她在凶杀发生的当晚穿过的衣服，在她的衣服口袋里发现了我母亲的肖像，这幅肖像被判定为诱使凶手杀人的东西。仆人即刻把它给另一个仆人看了，后者没有给家里任何人说半个字，便径直去见了地方行政官，根据他们的做证，于斯丁被关押起来。在依据事实受到指控的情况下，可怜的姑娘又表现得极其惊慌，于是在很大程度上更加证实了人们的怀疑。

这真是一个奇怪的故事，不过它并没有动摇我的信念，于是我诚挚地回答道：“你们都弄错了，我知道谁是凶手。于斯丁，可怜的、善良的于斯丁，是无辜的。”

就在这时候，父亲进来了。我看到愁容深深地印在他的脸上，但他努力要高高兴兴地欢迎我。在我们相互致以哀伤的问候以后，本来可以不谈我们的灾难而转向其他的话题，可是欧内斯特却大声地说：“天哪，爸爸！维克多说他知道谁是杀死可怜的威廉的凶手。”

“我们也知道了，这很不幸，”父亲回答道，“因为说真的，我宁愿永远被蒙在鼓里，也不愿在我如此珍爱的人身上发现这样深重的堕落和忘恩负义。”

“我亲爱的父亲，你错了，于斯丁是无辜的。”

“如果她是无辜的，上帝便不会让她蒙受罪名。今天她就要受审判了，我希望，我真诚地希望，她会被无罪开释。”

这番话使我平静下来。我坚信不仅于斯丁，而且任何人在这桩罪行中都是无辜的。因此，我丝毫也不担心会有任何偶然的证据足以证实她的罪名。我的故事不能当众宣布，其骇人听闻的程度会使一般人视为疯子的胡言乱语。除了我这个创造者以外，除非亲眼看见，谁会相信世界上存在着这个代表我自己的狂妄无知、并由我释放到人世上来作恶的活生生的创造物呢？

伊丽莎白很快就来到我们中间。自从我最后见到她以来，时光已使她有了改变，它赋予了她远远超越了童年时代之美的一种妩媚。她依然具有那种爽朗，那种活泼，但又糅合进了一种更富于情感和智慧的神态。她怀着强烈的感情欢迎我。“亲爱的表哥，你的到来，”她说，“使我充满了希望。也许你会找出什么办法来证明我可怜的于斯丁是无罪的。唉！假如连她都被认为有罪，那么谁还是安全的呢？我相信她的清白，就像我相信自己的清白一样确凿无疑。厄运给了我们双倍的打击，我们不仅失去了可爱的男孩，这个我所挚爱的可怜的姑娘又将被更可怕的命运夺走。如果她被定了罪，我将再也没有欢乐了。可是她不会被定罪的，我敢肯定不会。这样，即使是在我的小威廉惨死之后，我还可以再度快乐起来。”

“她是清白的，我的伊丽莎白，”我说，“这将得到证明，一点也别担心，坚信她会被无罪开释，让你的情绪振奋起来吧。”

“你是多么仁慈和宽宏大量啊！别的人个个都相信她有罪，这使我伤心，因为我知道那是绝不可能的。看到别人如此顽固地抱着偏见，我丧失了希望，毫无信心了。”她哭着说。

“亲爱的侄女，”父亲说，“擦干你的眼泪吧。如果她像你所相信的那样是无辜的，那么就信任我们法律的公正，并相信我会用行动去制止哪怕是最微小的有失公正的事情。”

————————————————————

(1) 里格（league），长度单位，约合五公里。

第八章　又一个牺牲者

我们度过了惨淡的几个钟头，直到十一点审讯开始。父亲和家里其他人都必须作为证人出庭，我陪伴着他们来到法庭。在这对正义进行可悲的嘲弄的过程中，我经受着活生生的折磨。我的好奇心和不法手段所产生的后果，是否会导致两个与我血肉相同的人的死亡，即将被决定了。一个是充满天真和欢乐的笑盈盈的孩子，另一个将更加悲惨地被杀害，她将名誉扫地，让人们永远怀着恐惧记住这件事。于斯丁是一个优秀的姑娘，她的许多好品质本会让她生活得很幸福，而如今一切都将埋没在一堆耻辱的坟墓里了，然而这却是因我而起的！有一千次，我真愿意坦白承认自己应当对于斯丁蒙受的罪名承担责任，可是当事情发生的时候我还没有回家，这样的声明会被当作疯子的胡言乱语，并不能替因我而受难的于斯丁开脱。

于斯丁的外表显得很镇静。她穿着丧服，她本来就很可爱的容貌，因为她内心严肃的感情而更显示出优雅之美。她对自己的清白无辜表现出很强的自信，虽然被千百个人注视和咒骂，她也不曾颤抖。尽管换一种情况，她的美可能会激起人们的慈爱之心，可是到场观看的人们一旦想到她被指控犯下的滔天大罪，慈爱便从心头消失了。她显得很平静，但她的平静显然是自我强制的结果，因为她的惊慌曾被看作有罪的证据，所以她打起精神做出勇敢的样子。走进法庭的时候，她向四周环顾，很快就发现了我们坐的地方。当她看见我们时，泪水似乎使她的视线模糊了，不过她很快就控制住了自己，那种带着忧伤的深情的神态，似乎足以证明她绝对是清白无辜的。

审讯开始了。律师提出对她的指控以后，几个证人被传出庭。好几件事实奇怪地凑合在一起，对她很不利，而任何人要是不像我这样有确凿证据认定她无罪的话，都会感到震惊的。凶杀发生的那天晚上，她整夜不在家，第二天快天亮的时候，一个赶集的女人就在发现孩子尸体不远的地方见到过她。那个女人问她在那儿干什么，而她的神情显得很古怪，只做了语无伦次、含糊不清的回答。她是在八点左右回到家里的。有个人问她那天夜里到什么地方去了，她回答说自己一直在寻找孩子，还急切地询问是否听到了有关孩子的什么消息。当她见到孩子的尸体时，便突然歇斯底里地哭喊起来，随后在床上躺了好几天。接着，法庭出示了仆人在她衣袋里找到的那幅肖像。当伊丽莎白用颤抖的声音证实了，那就是她在孩子失踪前一个小时挂在他脖子上的同一幅肖像时，一阵充满恐惧和义愤的低语声响遍了法庭。

于斯丁被传到庭前来为自己辩护。在审讯进行的过程中，她的神情随时在变化。她强烈地表现出惊讶、恐惧和痛苦。有时候，她是在强力抑制着眼泪，可是当法庭要她做辩护的时候，她打起了精神，用尽管不很稳定却很清晰的声音讲了起来。

“上帝知道，”她说，“我是完全清白的。不过我并不奢望我的辩护能开脱我的罪名，我只能坦诚地、简单地解释那些被引用来控告我的事实，以此证明我的无辜。我希望假如有任何细节显得令人难以置信和怀疑，自己的一贯品行能够使法官们做出有利于我的理解。”

然后她述说道，在凶杀案发生的那天傍晚，她得到了伊丽莎白的允许，待在离日内瓦大约一里格的谢讷村的姑母家里。九点钟左右，在她回来的路上，她遇见了一个男人，问她是否见到过一个失踪的孩子。她听到这个情况后感到吃惊，便花了几个钟头来寻找那个孩子。那时日内瓦的城门关闭了，她只好在一个农舍附属的谷仓里度过了后半夜，她和农舍的主人很熟悉，但不愿叫醒他们。她大部分时间里没阖眼，到快天亮的时候，她相信自己睡着了几分钟，后来有脚步声惊动了她，她就醒了。天已黎明，她便离开了过夜的地方，好继续去寻找我的弟弟。如果她曾走近过他的尸体躺着的地方，那她实际上并不知道。至于那个赶集的女人问她的时候她显得不知所措，那也没什么可奇怪的，因为她刚过了一个不眠之夜，而且可怜的威廉的命运还未弄清。关于那幅肖像，她无法解释。

“我知道，”那不幸的牺牲者继续说，“这种情况对于我来说是多么的严重和生死攸关，可是我又无力将它解释清楚，在我说自己对此一无所知的时候，我只好去猜想是否有这样的可能性，也许有人把那幅肖像放到了我的衣袋里。不过在这里我又被阻挡住了。我相信自己在世界上绝没有一个仇敌，任何人也绝不会恶毒得这样将我横加摧残。是不是凶手把肖像放在那里的？我想他不会有机会这样做，即使我假定他有机会，那他为什么在偷窃了珠宝之后，又这么快地把它丢掉呢？

“我把自己的理由提交法官们公平裁断，然而我看不出有多大的希望。我请求让一些证人来证明我的品格。如果他们的证言还不足以压倒加之于我身上的罪名，那么我就只好被判有罪了，尽管我可以用我灵魂得救的希望来担保我的清白。”

几位证人被传出庭，他们认识她很多年了，也称赞过她，可是他们以为她真的犯了罪，出于害怕和憎恶而变得畏怯了，不愿意站出来做证。伊丽莎白看到这最后的对策——于斯丁优美的性格和无可指责的行为，也不能拯救她了，这时尽管非常激动，仍然要求向法庭陈词。

“我是那个被杀害的不幸的孩子的表姐，”她说，“甚至可以说是他的姐姐，因为自他出生以来，甚至在他出生之前很久，我就受到他的父母的教育，和他的父母生活在一起。所以，在这样的场合下我出庭做证，可能会被视为不合时宜，但是当我看到与我们血肉相连的一个同胞，因为虚伪朋友的怯懦而濒于毁灭的时候，我希望能获准讲话，从而可以谈谈我对她品格的了解。我和被告非常熟悉。我和她在同一所房子里一起生活了五年，后来在另一时期又一起生活了将近两年。在以上所有的时间里，在我看来，她是一个最亲切、最好心的人了。我的婶婶弗兰肯斯坦夫人最后病危的时候，是她以最大的爱和关心照料着她，后来，她又伺候她那长年卧病的母亲，其行为激起了所有知道她的人一致的称赞。在此之后，她再度回到我叔叔的家，在这里她受到全家所有人的爱。她对现已死去的那个孩子怀有深厚的感情，对待他就像一个最慈爱的母亲。至于我，我会毫不犹豫地说，尽管所有的证据都对她不利，但我相信她、信任她的绝对清白无辜。没有任何动机诱惑她去做这样一件事，说到那个作为首要物证的小玩意儿，如果她真的想要它，我本来就会很乐意送给她的，因为我是如此珍爱和器重她。”

随着伊丽莎白简洁而有力的呼吁，响起了一片赞许的窃窃私语声，不过那是被她的宽宏大量的出面干预激起的，而并非是对可怜的于斯丁的同情。对于斯丁，公众却产生了新的普遍义愤，指责她为最无耻的忘恩负义者。伊丽莎白讲话的时候，于斯丁一直痛哭着，但她一言不发。在整个审讯过程中，我的焦虑和痛苦达到了极点。我深信于斯丁的清白无辜，我明白这一点。是不是那个魔鬼杀害了我的弟弟（这我没有片刻的怀疑），又出于恶魔的戏谑而将这个无辜者置于死地和身败名裂呢？我再也承受不了自己这可怕的处境了，当我觉察到大家的说话声和法官们的表情实际上已表明他们判处了我那不幸的牺牲者时，我在剧烈痛苦中冲出了法庭。被告所经受的折磨和我受的折磨并不等同，她有自己的清白无辜作为精神支持，而悔恨的毒牙却撕啮着我的胸膛，而且再也不会放松了。

我纯粹在痛苦中度过了一夜。早晨我去了法庭，我的嘴唇和喉咙像有火在烤着。我不敢询问那个生死攸关的问题，但主管官员认识我，他猜到了我的来意。已经投过票了，全是黑票，于斯丁被定了罪。

即使现在我也无法描述我当时的感受。过去我也体验过恐惧感，我也曾努力给予妥帖的表述，可是语言确实无法传达我当时心如刀绞的绝望。我找到的那个人还补充说，于斯丁已经承认自己有罪了。“这一点，”他评论道，“在如此显而易见的案情里已经并不多么需要了，不过我还是为此而高兴。说真的，我们法官谁也不愿意凭间接证据定罪，不管那是多么的确凿无疑。”

这是一个奇怪而料想不到的消息，这是什么意思？难道我的眼睛会欺骗我？难道我真的疯了，正如假使我披露我怀疑的对象后全世界都会相信我疯了那样？我急忙赶回家中，伊丽莎白急切地要求知道最后结果。

“我的表妹，”我回答道，“正如你可能料想的那样做了判决，所有的法官都宁可判十个无辜者死刑，也不愿让一个罪人逃脱。可是她自己认罪了。”

对坚信于斯丁无辜的可怜的伊丽莎白来说，这是一个可怕的打击。“啊！”她说，“我怎么能再相信人类的善良呢？于斯丁，我就像自己的姐妹那样爱她和尊重她，她怎么能装出纯洁无瑕的笑容，背地里却背叛我们呢？她那温顺的目光似乎绝不可能隐藏着残忍和狡诈，然而她却犯下了杀人罪。”

不久，我们听说那个可怜的牺牲者表示希望见一见我的表妹。父亲希望她不要去，不过他说，还是让她自己的判断和情感去做决定。“好，”伊丽莎白说，“我去，虽然她是有罪的。维克多，请你陪着我，我不能单独去。”这个主意对我而言简直是折磨，可是我没法拒绝。

我们走进阴暗的牢房，看见于斯丁坐在牢房远端的草堆上，她的双手上着镣铐，头枕在双膝上。她看见我们进来，就站了起来，当我们和她单独在一起的时候，她跪倒在伊丽莎白的脚下，痛苦地哭起来。我的表妹也哭了。

“啊！于斯丁！”她说，“你为什么要把我最后的安慰也夺走呢？我本来相信你是无辜的，我原来虽然非常伤心，但也没有现在这样痛苦啊。”

“难道你也相信我是那么、那么坏吗？难道你也和我的敌人一道来毁灭我，判定我是凶手吗？”她的声音被啜泣哽咽住了。

“站起来，我可怜的姑娘，”伊丽莎白说道，“假如你是清白的，为什么要下跪？我并不是你的敌人中的一个，我本来相信你无罪，尽管有一件件证据，直到我听说你自己已经承认有罪为止。告诉我，那个消息是假的。请相信，亲爱的于斯丁，除了你亲口认罪，再没有任何力量能动摇我对你的信任。”

“我的确认了罪，不过我的认罪是假话。我认罪是为了可能获得赦免，可是现在欺骗压在我的心上，比我所有别的罪过都沉重。上帝宽恕我！自从我被定罪以后，我的忏悔神父缠住了我，他恐吓我，威胁我，直到我几乎认为自己就是他所说的那个魔鬼了。他威胁说，假如我继续顽固不化，将在我的最后时刻受到开除教籍和地狱烈火的惩罚。亲爱的小姐，我得不到任何支持，所有的人都把我看作注定要身败名裂、永陷地狱的坏人。我能怎么办呢？我在不幸的时刻只好求助于撒谎，而现在我才真正感到不幸。”

她停了停，哭泣着，然后继续讲下去——“我亲爱的小姐，我一想到你会相信，你在天国的婶婶那么器重的、你也那么钟爱的于斯丁竟会犯下只有魔鬼才会干的罪行，就充满了恐惧。亲爱的威廉！亲爱的、上帝赐福的孩子！我很快就要在天堂再见到你了，在那里我们都将幸福。这给了我安慰，虽然我即将承受耻辱和死亡。”

“啊，于斯丁！原谅我曾有片刻怀疑了你。为什么你要认罪呢？不过，不要悲哀，亲爱的姑娘。不要害怕。我将公开声明，我将证明你无罪。我会用我的眼泪和祈求去溶化你的敌人的铁石心肠。你不能死！——你，我童年的游伴，我的伴侣，我的妹妹，竟死在绞架上！不！不！在这样可怕的灾祸之后，我也绝对活不了了。”

于斯丁悲伤地摇了摇头。“我并不怕死，”她说，“剧烈的痛苦已经过去了。上帝使我摆脱了软弱，赐给我勇气去忍受最坏的命运。我离开的是一个悲惨而痛苦的世界。如果你能记得我，把我看作一个蒙冤定罪的人，我就甘愿屈从那等待着我的命运了。像我这样吧，亲爱的小姐，以忍耐去顺从上天的意志吧！”

在他们谈话的时候，我退到了牢房的一个角落里，在那里我可以掩饰住控制我心灵的可怕的痛苦。绝望了！谁敢说出那件事？那可怜的牺牲者，明天就要跨过生与死的可怕界限了，也不像我这样感到深切而剧烈的痛苦。我咬紧牙齿，把它们磨来磨去，同时发出了一声呻吟，那是从我的灵魂深处发出来的。于斯丁吃了一惊。当她看清是谁的时候，她便走近我，说道：“亲爱的先生，谢谢你好心地来看我。我希望，你并不相信我有罪吧？”

我无力回答。“是的，”伊丽莎白说，“他比我更相信你是无辜的，因为甚至当他听说你已经认罪了的时候，他也不肯置信。”

“我真诚地感激他。在这最后的时刻，我对那些仁慈地想着我的人们怀着最真诚的谢意。对于我这样一个可怜的人来说，别人的感情是多么的甜蜜啊！它使我的不幸减轻了一多半。既然我的清白得到了你，亲爱的小姐，还有你的表哥的承认，我感到我似乎能够平静地去死了。”

这个可怜的受难者就这样极力安慰着别人和她自己。她确实获得了她所想要的安于天命。可是我呢，我这真正的凶手，心中却永远有自责的毒虫在咬啮，我将既无希望，也无安慰。伊丽莎白也在哭泣，也在伤心，但她的痛苦是清白的，它就像一片飘过明月的浮云，有一阵会遮住月亮的光亮，但不能使它黯然失色。痛楚和绝望穿透了我的心房，我的心里有一座地狱，什么也无法使它消灭。我们和于斯丁一起待了几个小时，伊丽莎白极不忍心和她分别。“我真希望自己和你一起死，”她哭喊道，“我不能在这个充满痛苦的世界上活下去。”

于斯丁一面极力抑制住苦涩的泪水，一面强装出高兴的样子。她拥抱着伊丽莎白，带着不能完全抑制的感情说：“永别了，可爱的小姐，最亲爱的伊丽莎白，我心爱的唯一的朋友。愿上天慷慨地赐福于你，保佑你，但愿这是你一生中经受的最后的不幸！活下去，要快乐，同时让别人快乐。”

第二天于斯丁死了。伊丽莎白令人心碎的雄辩没能感动法官，不能使他们改变对这个圣徒般的受难者的有罪认定。我的激烈而愤慨的请求对他们也毫无作用。当我得到他们冷漠的回答，听到这些人粗暴无情的推理时，我事先打算做的声明便从口边化为乌有了。如果我吐露真相，便相当于我宣布自己是个疯子，而绝不可能推翻对可怜的牺牲者的判决。她作为一个杀人犯死在了绞刑架上！

我从自己内心所受的苦刑转而考虑我的伊丽莎白深沉而无言的痛苦。这也是我造成的！还有父亲的愁苦，不久前还喜气扬扬的家庭如今的凄凉——这一切都是我这双应受三重诅咒的手造成的！你们哭泣吧，不幸的人们，然而这还不是你们最后的眼泪！你们还将在葬礼上痛哭，你们悲悼的哭声还将一次又一次地响起！弗兰肯斯坦，你们的儿子，你们的亲人，你们多年的、极其钟爱的朋友，他本愿为了你们洒尽每一滴热血——他不会想到、也不会感到欢乐，除非欢乐也反映在你们的面容上——他本愿让空中响彻他的祝福，并把一生用来为你们服务——可是，他却叫你们哭泣——叫你们流淌无尽的眼泪。假如无情的命运就此得到满足，假如在坟墓的宁静未曾接续到你们可悲的痛苦之前，毁灭就此停住，他将感到超乎希望之外的幸福！

我的灵魂说着这样的预言。当时我正被悔恨、恐惧和绝望撕裂着，看着我所爱的人在威廉和于斯丁的坟头——我亵渎神明的妖术最初的不幸牺牲者的坟头——枉自悲伤着。

第九章　逃避痛苦

对人的精神来说最痛苦的，莫过于在一系列迅速发生的事变激发起感情之后，接着却是无所作为和听天由命的死一般的平静，从而使心灵既无希望，也无恐惧。于斯丁死了，她安息了，而我却活着。血还在我的血管里畅快地流着，但绝望和悔恨的重负却压迫着我的心，没有办法减轻。我无法阖眼入睡，我像鬼魂一样游荡，因为我已经犯下了许多难以形容的可怕的罪孽，以后（我让自己相信）还将犯更多的、多得多的罪孽。然而我的心里是充溢着仁慈以及对美德的热爱的。我怀着造福于人的目的开始生活，渴望着有一天能够实现我的目标，让自己成为人类的有用之材。现在一切都被毁掉了。我本应该享有良心的宁静，能让自己以满足的心情来回顾过去，并由此获得对未来的新的希望，可是现在悔恨和内疚却攫住了我，把我向一座充满着语言无法形容的痛苦折磨的地狱里驱赶。

这种心情摧残着我的健康，而我的健康或许根本就没有从第一次打击中完全恢复过来。我躲避着不见任何人，任何欢乐或愉快的声音对我都是折磨，我唯一的安慰是孤独——深沉的、黑暗的、死一般的孤独。

父亲怀着痛苦注意到了我的性情和习惯中的这种明显的改变，并根据他自己坦然的良心和清白的生活，竭力找理由来激励我，唤起我的勇气去驱散笼罩着我的愁云。“维克多，难道你认为，”他说，“我就不痛苦吗？没有谁比我更爱你弟弟了（他说着说着不禁热泪盈眶），可是我们应该避免以过度忧伤的表现去加重活着的人的痛苦，这难道不是一种责任吗？这也是你对自己应尽的责任，因为过分的哀痛会阻碍你进步和获得欢乐，甚至会使你疏于日常事务，而缺少了这些任何人便不适合在社会中生活。”

这番忠告虽然很好，却完全不适合我的情况。要是在我的感情里，悔恨没有掺杂进它的苦涩，恐惧没有混入它的惊慌的话，我本应是第一个掩藏起自己的伤痛去安慰亲友的人。现在，我只有以绝望的神情来回答我的父亲，并尽力不在他跟前露面。

大约就在这个时候，我们迁回了在贝尔里芙的房子。这一改变对我来说是特别相宜。日内瓦的城门定时在十点关闭，超过那个时刻就不能继续在湖上流连了，这使我非常厌倦在日内瓦城里的生活。现在我自由了。我常常在晚上家人就寝以后划着船，在湖上度过许多钟头。有时候，我扬起帆，让风推着前进；有时候，我把船划到湖心之后，便让船随意飘荡，任自己沉浸在悲凉的思绪中。在周围的一切都归于平静的时分，我是唯一的在这片美丽如仙境的环境中不能安宁的东西——如果我除开那些蝙蝠，或者那些当我靠岸时才能听见它们刺耳的断续鸣叫声的青蛙——这时候，我常常想一头扎进这片宁静的湖里，这样湖水就可以淹没我，并永远淹没掉我的灾难。可是当我想到英勇的而又受着苦难的伊丽莎白，她是我所钟爱的、我的生命与之紧密相连的，我便克制住了自己。我也想到父亲和活着的一个弟弟，难道我要卑鄙地扔下他们，听任他们毫无防备地暴露在我放纵于他们之中的那个魔鬼的毒手之下吗？

每当这些时候，我就苦涩地哭泣起来，并希冀精神能够再归于平静，从而可以给予他们安慰和快乐。然而这是不可能的。悔恨熄灭了一切希望。我是那无可更改的灾祸的根源，我每时每刻生活在担忧中，唯恐我创造出来的那个妖魔会再干出什么新的邪恶勾当。我有一种朦胧的感觉，一切还没有结束，那个魔鬼还会犯下某种惊人的罪行，其剧烈的程度几乎会掩没我们对过去灾难的记忆。我将永远担惊受怕，只要我所爱的事物还存在着。我对这个魔鬼的憎恶简直到了难以设想的程度。一想到他，我就咬牙切齿、眼里冒火，渴望着毁掉这个自己轻率地制造成的生命。一想到他的罪恶和毒辣行径，我的仇恨和复仇意志便冲破了任何节制。我愿意跋涉到安第斯山的峰顶，只要我能在那儿把他摔到山脚下面去。我希望再见到他，这样就可以打碎他的脑袋来尽量发泄我的憎恨，并为威廉和于斯丁复仇。

我们的家成了丧宅。父亲的健康由于近来的可怕事件而深受影响。伊丽莎白悲哀而消沉，日常进行的活动不再使她感兴趣，任何欢乐在她看来都是对死者的亵渎，她认为，永远的哀伤和眼泪是她对被摧残毁灭的无辜者应有的祭品。她不再是那个童年时与我在湖畔流连、欢悦地谈论我们未来前景的快乐的人了。让我们弃绝人世的最初的痛苦已经降临到她身上了，它那吞没光明的力量已经扑灭了她可爱的笑容。

“我亲爱的表哥，”她说，“我一想起于斯丁·莫里兹的惨死，就觉得眼中的世界和世间的事物再也不是从前的模样了。从前，对于书上读到的或从旁人那里听到的罪恶和不公，我总是看作古代的传说，或者虚构出来的邪恶，至少，它们距离我们很远，我们从理性上熟悉它们，而难以去进行想象。可是如今不幸降临到家里来了，我感到人仿佛就是些嗜饮彼此的鲜血的魔鬼。不过我这样想肯定是不公平的。人人都相信那个可怜的姑娘是有罪的。要是她真的犯下了她为此而被处死的罪行，那么她肯定是最堕落无耻的人了。为了一点珠宝，便谋害了她的恩人和朋友的儿子，一个从襁褓中就由她抚育、好像亲生孩子一样被她钟爱的孩子！我不能赞同对任何一个人处以死刑，不过我当然也应该想到，像这样的人确实不配继续留在人类的社会里。可是，她是无辜的。我知道，我感觉得到，她是无辜的。你和我意见一致，这更坚定了我的看法。唉！维克多，当虚假看起来像真实的时候，谁还能够保证自己会享有某种幸福呢？我觉得自己仿佛走在悬崖的边缘上，成千上万的人正朝我这里挤过来，拼命要把我推到深渊底下去。威廉和于斯丁被谋害了，凶手却逍遥法外，他自由地在世上走来走去，或许还受到人们的尊敬。不过即使我因相同的罪行而被送上绞架，也不愿和这样一个卑鄙的家伙交换位置。”

我怀着最剧烈的痛苦听着她的这番话。我，虽然不是在行动上，但在实际上，就是那个真正的凶手。伊丽莎白从我的面容上看出了我的痛楚，便亲切地握住我的手说：“我亲爱的朋友，你得让自己平静下来。这些事变影响了我，上帝知道有多深，但我还不像你那样沮丧。你脸上的神情有时表现出绝望，有时又蕴含着复仇，这使我不禁颤抖。亲爱的维克多，消除掉这些阴郁的感情吧。想想你身边的亲友，他们把自己全部的希望都集中在你的身上了。难道我们失去了使你快乐起来的力量了吗？啊！只要我们相爱——只要我们互相忠诚，我们就可以在这块和平而美丽的土地上，在你的祖国，获得恬静的幸福——还有什么能够扰乱我们的宁静呢？”

我当作命运最高恩典加以珍视的伊丽莎白的这一席话，还不足以驱走潜伏在我心中的那个魔鬼吗？甚至在她说话的时候，我也紧紧贴近了她，仿佛我感到恐惧。我唯恐就在这个时候，那个毁灭者已经走近了，要把她从我身边劫走。

就像这样，无论是友谊的温情，还是世上或天堂的美丽事物，都无法从悲苦中拯救出我的灵魂，即使是爱的话语也无能为力。我被一团愁云包裹着，任何有益的影响力都没法穿透它。一头负伤的麋鹿拖着虚弱的肢体，躲到无人的树丛中，在那里凝视着射穿它身体的箭，然后死去——这就是我的写照。

有时我尚能设法抵御压倒我的阴郁的绝望情绪，但有时心灵中旋风般的激烈情感驱赶着我，我不得不借助于体力活动或者环境的改变，以求解脱我不堪承受的感情。正是在这种心态萌动之时，我突然离家出走，迈步向附近的阿尔卑斯山的峡谷走去，企求在山景的雄伟和永恒中忘却我自己，以及我作为人所具有的短暂的痛苦。我的漫游的目的地是萨姆尼山谷。我在少年时代常到那里去。从那时起六年时光流逝了，我是劫后余生——然而蛮荒的、不朽的景物却毫无改变。

我骑马走了开始的一部分路程，后来我雇了一匹骡子，因为它在崎岖的山路上走得更稳，最不容易受伤。天气很晴朗。当时大约是8月中旬，离于斯丁的死差不多两个月，我的一切痛苦就是从她死去的那个不幸的日子开始的。当我越来越深入阿尔弗峡谷的时候，我便明显感到精神上的重压减轻了。在我四周的顶上耸立着巨大的山峦和绝壁——岩石间急流奔腾咆哮，瀑布从天飞坠，都展示着如万能之主一般的强大威力——万能之主创造和统治着自然的元素，在这里显露出最为摄人心魄的形象，于是，我对任何不如这般强大的事物都不会再害怕，也不会屈服了。而且，我攀登得越高，峡谷便越显出宏伟而令人惊叹的特色。坍塌的古堡高挂在松林覆盖的山峦峭壁上，还有急流飞湍的阿尔弗河，树林中疏落显露的农舍，一起构成了美妙绝伦的风景。而巍峨的阿尔卑斯山更为它增添了崇高壮丽，那些洁白发亮的金字塔形和圆拱形的峰顶高高耸立，俯瞰万物，仿佛是属于另一个世界，是另一种生灵的居所。

我跨过了贝利西埃桥，在这里河流形成的峡谷展现在我的眼前，然后我就开始攀登耸立在河谷上方的山冈。不久，我就进入了萨姆尼峡谷。这个峡谷与我刚刚通过的塞弗克斯峡谷相比更为奇妙和宏伟，但没有它那样美丽如画。它的四周紧紧围绕着高耸的皑皑雪峰，不过我再也见不到坍塌的城堡和肥沃的田野了。巨大的冰川逼近了道路，我听到雪崩发出的雷霆般的轰鸣，看见了它移动时激起的烟雾。勃朗峰，那恢宏壮丽的勃朗峰，从周围的尖峰中高高跃起，它那巨大无朋的圆拱形峰顶巍巍俯瞰着下面的峡谷。

在旅途中，那久已丧失了的令人震颤的欢悦感又常常袭上我的心头。道路的某一处转弯，突然看到似曾相识的某个景物，都使我想起那些消逝了的、与无忧无虑的童年时代相联系的时光。风儿以抚慰的声调在我耳畔悄声细语，慈母般的大自然劝我别再哭泣。可是接着，这种仁慈亲切的影响力又停止了作用——我感到自己又被愁苦束缚住了，重又沉浸在悲痛的思绪中。然后我就驱赶骡子快跑，这样极力来忘掉世界，忘掉恐惧，尤其是忘掉自己——或者以更近乎拼死挣扎的方式，我从骡子背上跳下来，扑倒在草地上，被恐惧和绝望彻底压倒。

我终于抵达了萨姆尼村。在经受了身心的极度疲惫之后，我精疲力竭了。我在窗前伫立了短暂的时间，遥望着苍白的闪电在勃朗峰上空飞舞，倾听着阿尔弗河水在下方河床里喧哗奔腾。这催人入睡的声响对我过于敏锐的感觉而言起到了一种催眠曲的作用：当我的头落到了枕上，睡意就袭来了，我感觉到它的到来，我赞美这忘却的赐予者。

第十章　相遇在阿尔卑斯山

第二天我整天都在山谷里漫游。我站在阿尔弗河源头的旁边，它发源于一座冰山，而那座冰山正缓缓地滑下山岗的顶峰，即将堵住峡谷。我的前面是茫茫群山直立的峭壁，冰山形成的冰墙高高地悬挂在我的顶上，有几棵衰败的松树零零散散地长在四周。在这大自然君主的壮丽的接待厅里一派庄严的肃静，只有潺潺流水声，巨大的碎裂石块的坠落声，雪崩的雷鸣般的轰响声，回响在群山之间的冰层的断裂声，才偶尔打破这一片沉寂。那厚厚累积的冰层由于永恒不变的法则在阒无声息地起作用，不时总在融化和迸裂，仿佛它们只不过是那些自然法则手中的玩物而已。这种种崇高宏伟的景象给了我心灵所能接受的最大的安慰。它们使我所有的渺小情感得以升华，尽管它们并没有消除我的痛苦，但使它减轻了，平和了。在某种程度上，它们使我的思想从一个月以来无法排遣的忧思中转移开去了。晚上我回去寝息，我的睡梦仿佛也有白天所见的壮丽景象相伴。它们簇拥在我的周围，那洁白无瑕的皑皑雪峰，那熠熠发光的峰峦尖顶，那松林，那乱石峥嵘的河谷，那翱翔于云间的鹰隼——它们都聚集在我的身边，祝我内心安宁。

第二天早晨我醒来的时候，它们又消隐到什么地方去了呢？一切振奋心灵的景象都随梦境消失，深沉的忧郁又笼罩了我的每一缕思绪。滂沱大雨倾注着，浓雾遮蔽了群山的峰顶，使我看不清那些伟岸的朋友们的面孔。然而我仍要穿过它们那浓雾的纱幕，到它们云遮雾罩的隐居地去寻找它们。大雨和风暴对我来说又算得了什么？我的骡子被牵到了门前，而我决定去攀登蒙坦维峰。我还记得我第一次见到宏大的、不停移动的冰川时心灵的反应。它使我充满了一种崇高的狂喜之情，从而让我的灵魂长上了翅膀，从这个昏暗的世界高飞到光明和欢乐的处所。的确，每当见到大自然中令人敬畏和宏伟壮丽的事物时，我的思想常常变得庄严肃穆，我忘却了人世转眼即逝的忧烦。我决定不要向导独自前行，因为我对那条路非常熟悉，而且有其他人在场也会破坏风景那种孤寂的壮美。

上山的路十分险峻，不过沿山崖开凿出了蜿蜒曲折的小道，倒可以让你登上直立的峭壁。这是一派惊人的凄凉景象。处处都可见冬季雪崩后遗留下来的痕迹，地上散布着凌乱破碎的树木，有的已完全被摧毁了，有的则弯折了，斜靠着突出的山崖，或者横依在别的树上。随着你攀登得越来越高，小道便常常为雪沟横断，从上面还不断有石头滚落下来。乱石中有一块尤其危险，因为即使是最轻微的声响，甚至高声说话，也会产生空气的振动，足以使得它飞坠下来击碎你的脑袋。这里的松树并不高大繁茂，但它们显得很阴沉，给这派景色添加了一种凛冽肃杀之气。我俯瞰脚下的河谷，茫茫雾气正从穿过峡谷的河面上冉冉升起，并浓密地环绕在对面群山的周围，山顶全都被稠密如一的云团所遮蔽，而这时大雨又从乌黑的天空倾注而下，更加重了我从周围景物里得到的那种阴郁的印象。唉！人为什么要夸口自己具有比野蛮之物更为优越的情感呢，这只不过使他们成为更受束缚的生命。假如推动我们的力量仅限于饥、渴和生之欲望，我们或许可以说自己近乎自由了，可是现在，一阵风吹过，偶然的只言片语，或者这只言片语所表达的情景，都会使我们心生感慨。

我们休憩，梦境毒害我们的睡眠。
我们起身，缠绵思绪污染了白日。
我们感觉，想象，推理；大笑或哭泣，
或耽于哀伤，或摒弃忧虑；
全都一样：因为无论欢乐或痛苦，
到头来都必然消逝。
人的昨日绝不同于明日；
万事不可永存，变易本是常理！

当我攀登到了峰顶的时候，已经接近正午了。我坐在俯瞰冰海的一块岩石上休息了一会儿。一片雾气遮盖了冰海和它周围的群山。不久，一阵微风吹散了云雾，我便下山向冰川上走去。冰川的表面坑洼不平，有的地方就像不平静的海波层层涌起，有的地方又很低，散布着陷落很深的裂隙。冰面大约有一里格宽，而我差不多花了两个小时才横穿过去。对面的那座山是一片光秃秃的峭壁。正对着我所站立的位置的侧面，耸立着蒙坦维峰，距此有一里格远，而在蒙坦维峰的上方则高耸着勃朗峰，宏伟而庄严。我伫立在山崖的一个凹陷处，凝望着这一派奇妙而雄伟的景象。那片海洋，或者不如说是那条茫茫的冰河，在毗邻的群山之间曲折盘旋，群山高耸入云的峰顶就直立在冰河的凹陷处。山顶那冰封的晶莹峰巅在云端泻下的阳光里熠熠闪光。我那不久前还充满忧伤的心，现在满溢着近乎欢乐的感情。我高声呼喊着——“漫游的精灵们啊，假如你们真的在漫游，而不是安卧在狭窄的坟墓里，就请让我享受这微小的快乐吧，要不然就把我当作你们的同伴，带我离开这人世的欢乐吧。”

我正说着的时候，突然看到离我不远处有一个人影，正以超人的速度向我走来。他飞跃过我刚才小心翼翼地走过的冰缝，当他走近时，看得出他的身型也显得比常人高大。我心里发慌，眼前腾起了一片雾，一阵头晕目眩，不过一股寒冷的山风使我很快就镇定下来了。当那个东西走得更近的时候，我看出来（多么庞大和可憎的怪物！）他就是我创造的那个丑恶的家伙。我因为愤怒和恐惧而浑身发抖，决心等着他靠近，然后与他进行生死搏斗。他逼近了，他的表情中带着剧烈的痛楚，又混杂着轻蔑和敌意，而他那非人的丑陋又使这种神情可怕得让人不敢看一眼。不过我几乎没有注意到这一点，愤怒和仇恨最初使我简直说不出话来，但我恢复了镇定，为的是以具有强烈厌恶和蔑视的话语来把他压倒。

“魔鬼，”我高声说道，“你敢靠近我吗？你不怕我凶狠的复仇的手臂砸碎你那可恶的脑袋吗？滚开，邪恶的毒虫！再不就待着，好让我把你踩成烂泥！啊！消灭了你那可恶的生命，但愿那些被你残暴杀害的牺牲者能够复活！”

“我料想到你会这样对待我，”恶魔说，“所有的人都恨可怜虫，我比世上的任何生灵都更不幸，那一定是多么的招人憎恨啊！可是你，我的创造者，也来憎恶和唾弃我，而你是和你的创造物紧紧连在一起的，只有消灭我们之中的一个，才能割断这种联系。你打算杀死我。你怎么敢这样戏弄生命呢？你尽到你对我的责任，那么我也会尽我对你以及对人类中其他人的责任。如果你同意我的条件，我就让他们和你得到安宁，假如你拒绝，我将满足死神的胃口，直到它餍足了你剩余的亲友的鲜血为止。”

“可恶的怪物！你真是个魔鬼！地狱的酷刑也不足以惩罚你的罪恶。令人作呕的妖怪！你责怪我创造了你，那么，来吧，我要扑灭自己轻率赐予的生命之火。”

我简直无法控制自己的怒火，我被拼死决战的愤怒所驱使，猛地向他扑去。

他不费吹灰之力就躲过了我，然后说道：“冷静些！在你把仇恨发泄到我这虔诚的脑袋上之前，请先听我讲几句。难道我受的罪还不够，你还要来雪上加霜吗？生命，虽然只不过是在累积痛苦，但对我来说还是可贵的，我一定要捍卫它。记住，你把我造得比你本人更为强大，我的体型比你高大，我的关节比你柔韧。不过我不会起意跟你作对的。我是你的创造物，我甚至会对我生来的主人和君王温和而柔顺，只要你履行你对我应尽的责任。啊，弗兰肯斯坦，不要对别人都那么公平，却偏偏亏待我一个，你对我最应该公正，甚至宽厚和仁爱。记住，我是你的创造物，我应该是你的亚当(1)啊；不过我倒不如说是那个被贬谪的天使，被你无缘无故地逐出乐园(2)。我到处都看见幸福，而只有我一个被不可挽回地排除在外。我本来是仁慈而善良的，是苦难使我变成了魔鬼。让我幸福吧，我将重新变得善良。”

“滚开！我不听你讲。你和我之间没有任何共同点，我们是敌人。滚开，再不然就让我们决一死战，你我当中必死一个。”

“我怎么才能感动你呢？难道任何恳求都不能让你友善地看一眼你的创造物，这个正在哀求你的仁慈和同情的生命吗？相信我，弗兰肯斯坦，我本来是仁慈的，我的灵魂燃烧着爱和人性，可是我现在不是孤独的、孤苦伶仃的吗？你，我的创造者，也来嫌恶我，那么我还能对你那些并不欠我什么的同类抱什么希望呢？他们唾弃我，憎恨我。荒凉的山岭和阴郁的冰川是我的避难所。我已经在这里游荡了许多天了，冰窟是我唯一不害怕的地方，它们成了我的栖身之地，也是人类唯一不吝惜的处所。我向凄冷的天穹欢呼，因为它比你的同类对我更宽厚。要是众多的人类知道了我的存在，他们一定也会像你所做的那样，武装起来消灭我。那么，我不应该憎恨那些憎恶我的人吗？我绝不和敌人妥协。我是不幸的，他们也得分担我的不幸。不过，你有能力补偿我，从而免除他们的灾难，这场灾难将仅仅因为你而变得极其巨大，不仅你和你的家人，而且有成百上千的人，都要被卷入这狂暴灾难的旋风之中。请你动动恻隐之心，不要蔑视我吧。请听听我的故事——听完以后，唾弃或者同情，听凭你来评判我该得到什么好了。不过你要听我说。按照人类的法律，罪人不管怎样罪大恶极，也能在判罪以前为自己辩护的。听我说，弗兰肯斯坦。你指控我是杀人凶手，而你呢，却心安理得地要毁灭你的创造物。啊，赞美人类的永恒正义吧！可是我并不要求你饶恕——听我讲完，然后，只要你办得到，只要你愿意，就毁灭你亲手创造的作品吧。”

“你为什么要唤起我的记忆，”我回答道，“让我不寒而栗地想起自己就是那些不幸的根源和制造者？可恶的魔鬼，我诅咒你第一次看见天光的那个日子！我诅咒（尽管我是在诅咒自己）那双造出你的手！你已经使我变得不可言喻的悲惨。你已经使我无力去考虑自己到底对你是公正还是不公正。滚开！别让我再看见你那可憎的样子。”

“我这样就可以使你得到解脱，我的创造者，”他说，并把他可憎的双手放到我的眼前。我猛地把它们摔开，“这样，我就可以使你不再看到你所憎恨的形象了。可是你仍然可以听我说话，给我以同情。凭我原来具有的美德，我要求你做到这一点。听听我的故事吧，这个故事又长又离奇，而这儿的气温不适宜你那纤弱的感情，到山上的小屋里去。太阳还高挂在天上，在它降落到那边雪封的峭壁背后，照亮另一个世界以前，你就会听完我的故事，然后做出你的决定。到底我是永远离开人世，过一种无害于人的生活呢，还是成为你的同类的祸根和使你本人迅速毁灭的力量，就完全取决于你了。”

他一边说，一边在冰原上引路，我跟在他的后面。我心事重重，没有搭理他。不过我一面向前走，一面掂量着他提出的种种理由，决定至少也得听听他的故事。我部分出于好奇，此外同情心也坚定了我的决心。我至今为止都认为是他杀害了我的弟弟，所以我急切地想要证实或者否定这个看法。而且，我也是第一次感到一个创造者对他的创造物应尽怎样的责任，在怨恨他作恶之前，我应该首先让他快乐。这些想法促使我同意了他的要求。于是，我们跨过了冰原，爬上了对面的岩石。空气很寒冷，雨又开始下起来，我们进了小屋，那魔鬼兴高采烈，而我却心情沉重，情绪抑郁。不过我答应听他讲，我坐在我那可憎的同伴燃起的火堆旁，他便开始讲他的故事。

————————————————————

(1) 据《圣经》，亚当是上帝创造的第一个人。

(2) 据《圣经》，魔鬼撒旦本是大天使，被上帝贬至下界。

第十一章　初识人类

“我回忆自己生命的开始阶段，感到相当的困难，那段时期一切事情都显得混乱和模糊。一团奇异而复杂的感觉攫住了我，在同一时刻里，我开始了看，感觉，听，嗅，确实过了很长一段时间，我才知道分辨不同感官的作用。我记得，有一道强烈的光压迫着我的神经，以致我不得不闭着眼睛。接着黑暗就吞没了我，使我不安。可是我几乎还没来得及感受到这一点，光亮又淹没了我，我现在设想，那是我又睁开了眼睛。我走起来，我相信是在往下走，但是我立即发现感觉发生了巨大的改变。在这之前，黑暗的、不透光的物体包围着我，触摸不到，也看不清，而现在我发现自己能够自由走动，再没有什么障碍是我不能越过或者绕开的。光亮对我的压迫力越来越大，而且我走动的时候，热力使我感到疲惫，于是我就寻找一个能获得荫凉的地方。这个地方就是英戈尔施塔特近郊的森林。在那里，我躺在一条小溪旁休息，消除疲劳，直到我感觉受到了饥饿和口渴的折磨。这使我从接近休眠的状态中醒了过来，后来我就吃了一些悬挂在树枝上和落到地上的浆果。我用溪水来解渴，然后又躺到地上，被睡意所征服。

“当我醒来的时候，天已经黑了，我又感到寒冷，并且仿佛出于本能，发现自己如此孤单而感到有些害怕。在离开你的寓所之前，我因为感到冷曾在身上披了几件衣服，可是它们并不足以为我抵挡夜间的寒露。我是个可怜的、无助的、凄惨的倒霉蛋，我什么也不懂，什么也辨不清，我只觉得痛楚从四面八方袭来，便坐下来哭泣。

“不久，有一道柔和的光布满了天空，并给我一种愉快的感觉。我跳起来，看见一团发光的东西从树林间升起。(1)我带着惊奇凝望着它。它移动得很慢，但它为我照亮了路，我又走出去寻找浆果。我还是觉得冷，这时候我在一棵树下发现了一件宽大的斗篷，于是我把它披在身上，在地上坐下来。我的脑子里没有任何明晰的思想，一切都是混沌不清的。我感觉到光亮、饥饿、口渴、黑暗，数不清的声音在我耳中鸣响，各种各样的气味从四面扑来。我唯一能够清楚辨别的东西就是那个亮晃晃的月亮，于是我就高兴地目不转睛地盯着它。

“白天和黑夜经过了几次交换以后，夜晚的那个圆球就变得很小了，而这时候我也开始能区分开我的各种感觉了。我渐渐地看清楚了供我饮用的那条清澈的小溪，看清楚了用枝叶为我遮阴的树木。当我第一次发现，那种常常传到我耳中的悦耳的声音，是从一只有时会挡住我眼前光线的长翅膀的小动物的喉咙里发出的，我可真是高兴。我也开始更精确地观察围绕在我身边的各种形体，感知那覆盖在我头上的发光的屋顶的边界在哪里。有时候，我还尝试模仿鸟儿那动听的歌声，不过我做不到。有时候，我想用自己的方式来表达感情，可是我吐出的那种粗糙而含混的声音吓得我又赶快闭口。

“在一个夜晚，月亮消失了，后来又以变小了的形状再次出现，在这段时间里我仍然留在森林里。到这时候，我的感觉已经变得清晰起来，我的头脑每天都接受着更多的新概念。我的眼睛开始习惯光亮了，可以看出物体真正的形状，我能区分昆虫和草叶，而且逐渐能分辨各种草之间的差别。我发现麻雀只能发出刺耳的叫声，而乌鸦和画眉的鸣啼则甜美而动人。

“有一天，当我冷得难受的时候，我发现了流浪的乞丐留下的一堆火，并因为体验到火的温暖而喜不自禁。在欣喜中我把手插进了还在燃烧的余烬，但接着我就痛得大叫一声，急忙把手缩了回来。我想，多么奇怪啊，同一种原因却会产生这样截然不同的效果！我仔细查看那火的材料，高兴地发现是由木头构成的。我迅速地捡了一些树枝来，可是它们都是潮湿的，燃不起来。我对此感到很苦恼，静静地坐着看那火是怎么燃烧的。我放在火边的那些湿木头被烤干了，自己就燃了，我就思忖起这一点来。我用手去摸不同的树枝，找到了原因，便急忙捡了一大堆木头，这样我就可以烤干它们，以后就有许多生火的东西了。当夜晚渐渐来临时，也带来了睡眠，我非常担心我的火会熄灭。我小心翼翼地用干木头和干树叶盖在火上，再在上面放上湿的树枝，然后我在地上铺开斗篷，躺在上面，睡着了。

“到早晨我才醒来，首先关心的是那堆火。我揭开上层的覆盖物，一阵微风很快就把它吹成了熊熊大火。我观察到了这个现象，就用树枝编成了一把扇子，在余烬快要熄灭的时候，就用它来扇火。当黑夜再度降临的时候，我高兴地发现火能够产生热，也能够产生光，发现这一点对我的食物很有用，因为我找到过旅行者遗留下来的一些火烤过的残余食物，它们比我从树上采摘的浆果滋味好得多。因此，我也试着用同样的方式处理我的食物，把它们放到火上去烤。我发现用这个办法破坏了浆果的味道，而坚果和根茎的味道却大有改善。

“然而，食物变得越来越稀少了，为了寻找几个橡树子来缓和饥饿的痛苦，我常常要花上一天的时间，而且一无所获。当我发现了这一点，便决定离开我现在的住所，另找一个地方，在那里能够更容易地满足我为数不多的需求。在这次迁移过程中，特别伤心的是我丢掉了偶然获得的火种，而且不知道怎样才能重新燃起火来。我花了好几个钟头来认真考虑如何解决这个难题，可是我仍不得不放弃所有重新得到火的尝试。我用斗篷把自己裹起来，穿过树林向日落的方向走去。我这样游荡了三天，终于发现了一片旷野。前一夜刚刚下过了一场大雪，原野白茫茫一片，景象阴郁，而且我发现脚被地上那种又冷又湿的东西冻得发僵。

“大约在早晨七点钟，我极想得到一点食物和一个栖身之地。终于，我看到在一处高地上有个小茅屋，它无疑是为了某个牧羊人的生活方便而盖的。这是我从未见过的东西，我非常好奇地观察它的结构。看见门开着，我就走了进去。屋里有个老人坐在火炉边，正在上面准备他的早餐。他听见声响便转过身来，一看到我就大声尖叫，跑出茅屋，飞跑着穿过了原野，其速度似乎超过了他那衰弱身体的可能限度。他的模样，和我以前见过的任何东西都不同，他的飞跑则使我吃惊。但我被那所茅屋的样子迷住了，这里雨雪不能穿透，地面是干燥的，那时它对我来说显得如此精美恢宏，就像‘万魔殿’对于经受了火湖的磨难之后的地狱群魔那样。(2)我贪婪地吞下牧羊人剩下的早餐，其中有面包、奶酪、牛奶和酒，不过酒我并不喜欢。后来，我被疲劳所征服，便躺在一个草堆上睡着了。

“我醒来的时候已经到中午了，太阳照耀在雪白的地上，我被太阳的温暖所诱惑，决定继续我的旅行。我把吃剩下的那个农民的早餐装在我找到的一个口袋里，然后横跨田野走了几个钟头，直到日落时分，我来到了一个村子。这里显得多么的神奇啊！茅屋，整洁的农舍，堂皇的房屋，轮番地引起我的赞叹。园子里的蔬菜，一些农舍的窗台上放着的牛奶和奶酪，令我馋涎欲滴。我走进了一所最漂亮的农舍，可是还没等我的脚跨过门槛，那些孩子们就尖叫起来，有一个女人晕了过去。整个村子都骚动了，有的人在逃窜，有的人攻击我，石块和其他飞掷过来的武器直打得我鼻青脸肿，我这才逃到了旷野中，战战兢兢地躲进了一个低矮的窝棚，里面空空如也，和我刚才在村子里见到的那些宫殿相比，它简直是一幅破烂模样。不过这间窝棚却毗邻着一座整洁舒适的农舍，但是在刚才那番惨痛教训之后，我却不敢走进去了。我的这个藏身之地是用木头搭成的，低矮得我只能勉强直坐在里面。可是并没有铺上木板，只是泥土地面，好在地是干燥的；尽管有风从无数的缝隙里吹进来，我却觉得这是一个可以避雪挡雨的舒适的避难所。

“我就在这里隐居了，我躺下来，庆幸自己找到了一个栖身之地，不管多么简陋，总可以躲避严酷的冬天，更能够逃避人类的野蛮行为。

“天一放亮，我就从我的窝里爬出来，想观察一下紧连着的那间农舍，看看自己是不是能够在这个窝棚里继续待下去。窝棚靠着农舍的后部，它的两侧一面是个猪圈，另一面是一池清水。有一面是敞开着的，我就是从这一面爬进来的。现在我把每一个可能让人发觉我的缝隙都用石块和木头堵起来，同时在自己想出去的时候又可以搬动它们。我需要的光亮完全是从猪圈那边透过来的，这对于我来说已经足够了。

“我这样安排好了我的住所，又在地面上铺上一层干净的稻草，就悄悄地躲起来，因为我看到远处有个人影，而我对头天晚上所受的待遇印象太深，不敢让自己落在他的手里。不过，我先就偷了一大块粗面包来做我当天的食物，还有一个杯子，可以用来饮用窝棚旁边流过的清水，这比我用手捧水喝要方便得多了。地面被稍微垫起来了，所以相当的干燥，而且窝棚挨着农舍的烟囱，还算暖和。

“这样装备起来以后，我就决定在这间棚子里住下去，一直住到有什么情况使我改变主意时为止。这里和我以前栖身的地方相比，真可谓是天堂了，那荒凉的森林里只有滴着雨水的树枝，湿漉漉的土地。我愉快地吃起了早餐，并打算搬开一个木板取点水喝，这时我听到了一阵脚步声，我从一个缝隙往外看，看见一个年轻女人头顶着一只水桶从窝棚前经过。这个姑娘年轻而文雅，和我从那以后所见过的其他村姑和农家女仆不一样。可是她的衣着很破旧，只穿着一条蓝色的粗布裙子和一件亚麻布上衣，她那金黄色的头发编成了辫子，但没有任何装饰，她显得从容不迫，但神情忧伤。接着我就看不见她了。大约一刻钟以后，她又顶着桶回来了，桶里现在装着一些牛奶。她走路的时候，好像有点承负不了那个木桶的重量似的，一个年轻男人迎过来，他的面容显得更加郁郁寡欢。他忧郁地说了一点什么，便从她头上接下了木桶，把它提进农舍去。她跟在他后面，然后他们就消失了。不久，我又看见了那个年轻男人，手里拿着一些工具，穿过了屋后的田野，那个姑娘也在忙碌，有时候在屋里，有时候在院子里。

“我仔细检查我的住所时，发现农舍的窗户有一扇原来就开在窝棚这面，现在却被木板给封死了。在一个窗格上有一条小得几乎无法察觉的细缝，刚好眼睛可以透过它张望。透过这个缝隙，可以看到一个小房间，墙壁刷得洁白，收拾得很整洁，但是家具非常少。在一个角落里，靠近火炉边，坐着一个老人，忧伤地用双手托着头。年轻姑娘正在整理着屋子，不过她马上从一个抽屉里拿出了一件东西用手把弄起来，并在老人身边坐下，老人则拿起了一件乐器开始弹奏，那声音比画眉和夜莺的叫声更美妙。这个情景，即使是对于我这个以前从未见过任何美景的可怜虫来说，也是太可爱了！农舍老主人那银白的头发和慈祥的面容使我肃然起敬，而那个姑娘温柔的举止也激起了我爱慕。老人弹奏着一支美妙的哀伤曲调，我发觉那曲调引得他那和蔼可亲的同伴掉下眼泪，而老人却没注意到，直到她哭出了声音。于是他说了一些话，美丽的姑娘放下了她的活计，跪倒在他的脚下。他把她扶起来，而且他是那样充满慈爱和温情地笑着，竟使我感到一种特别的、不可抗拒的激情：这是痛苦和快乐的混合物，是我过去无论从饥饿寒冷还是温暖饱足里都从来没有体验过的。于是我从窗口走开了，我承受不了这种感情。

“这件事过去没多久，那个年轻男子回来了，还扛着一捆木头。姑娘到门口去迎接他，帮他卸下木头，然后拿了一些木头进了屋子，把它们放到了炉火上。然后，她和那个青年走到农舍的一个角落，青年拿出了一大块面包和一片奶酪来给她看。她似乎很高兴，便走进了菜园去拿了一些块茎和植物，先放到水里，然后再放到火炉上。后来她继续干她的活计，而年轻人则进了菜园，好像是忙着挖掘和拔起什么东西的根茎。他这样干了大约一个钟头以后，姑娘也来和他一起干，后来他们就一道进了屋子。

“在这段时间里，老人一直在郁郁沉思着，不过，当他的两个同伴出现的时候，他就换上了一副比较快乐的表情，然后他们就坐下来吃饭。饭很快就吃完了。年轻女子又忙着收拾屋子，老人靠在那个青年的手臂上，在屋子前面的阳光中走了几分钟。再没有什么能比得上这两个优美的人之间的那种对照的美了。一个是老人，满头银发，脸上洋溢着慈爱，一个是青年，身材修长优雅，面容俊美匀称，不过他的眉目神态却表现出极度的忧伤和沮丧。老人回到了屋子里，青年拿起了几件和早晨不同的工具，横跨田野走了。

“夜晚很快就来临了，可是使我极为惊奇的是，农舍的主人有办法拿蜡烛来延长时光，我还高兴地发现，太阳沉落并没有结束我观察我的人类邻人的乐趣。晚上，年轻姑娘和她的同伴还做了各种我不能理解的事情，老人又拿起了早晨曾发出过令我入迷的美妙声音的乐器。他一结束弹奏，青年就开始弄出一些单调的声音，不是用乐器弹奏，而是用口，它们既不像老人的乐器上发出的声音那样和谐悦耳，也不像鸟儿的歌唱。我后来知道他是在朗读，不过当时我还一点不懂关于词句和字母的科学。

“那家人像这样度过了不长的一段时间后，就熄灭了烛光，走开了，我想是去睡觉了。”

————————————————————

(1) 原注：指月亮。

(2) 英国诗人弥尔顿（John Milton，1608—1674）在长诗《失乐园》（Paradise Lost）里写撒旦在火湖里召集群魔反叛上帝，建“万魔殿”（Pandemonium）。

第十二章　可爱的一家

“我躺在草堆上，但我无法入睡。我想着白天发生的那些事情。给我印象最深的是这些人的温和的举止，我真想加入到他们当中去，可是我不敢。前晚受到的那些野蛮村民的对待，我记得太清楚了，所以我拿定主意，不管我今后会采取什么我以为是正确的行动，在目前我还是静静地待在我的窝棚里，细心观察，设法找出影响人类行为的动机是什么。

“第二天早晨太阳还没升起，农舍的主人们就起床了。年轻女人收拾屋子和准备早餐，年轻男人吃过饭以后就离开了。

“这一天和前一天按照同样的方式度过了。年轻男人一直在屋外干活，姑娘在屋里做各种各样的杂事。那个老人，我不久就发现他的眼睛是瞎的，用弹奏乐器或沉思来打发他的时光。两个年轻人对他们可敬的长辈表现出的那种爱和尊敬，简直没有什么可以相比。他们对他温柔地尽着无微不至的爱和责任，而老人则用他慈祥的微笑来报答他们。

“他们并不完全快乐。年轻男人常常和他的同伴走到一边去，好像在哭泣。我可看不出他们有任何理由不高兴，不过我还是深深地被这件事所感动。假如这样可爱的人也会痛苦，那么像我这样不完美的、孤孤单单的生命，活得悲惨也就不算奇怪了。可是这些优美的生命为什么会不快乐呢？在我看来，他们有一所可爱的房子和种种享受，寒冷时有温暖的炉火，饥饿时有精美的食物，他们穿着极好的衣服，更愉快的是，他们能彼此做伴，互相交谈，每天大家都以亲切慈爱的态度相待。他们的眼泪意味着什么呢？他们的眼泪难道真的在表示痛苦吗？起先，我不能解答这些问题，不过坚持观察和时间的流逝为我解释清楚了许多开始时像谜一样的事情。

“过了相当长的一段时间，我才了解到使这个可爱的家庭烦恼不安的一个原因是贫穷，他们非常痛苦地承受着这个灾难的折磨。他们的营养完全依靠园子里的蔬菜，还有一头母牛的奶，而在冬天母牛产的奶非常少，因为主人几乎找不到食物来喂养它。我相信，他们常常忍受着饥饿的剧烈痛苦，特别是那两个年轻人，有好多次，他们把食物放到那个老人的面前，一点也没有留下给自己。

“这种好心肠深深地打动了我。在夜间，我已经习惯于偷一点他们储藏的食物来满足自己的需要，可是当我发现这样做是在给他们制造痛苦时，我就停止了偷窃，而是从邻近的树林里采集浆果、坚果和根茎来食用。

“我还发现自己能够通过另一种办法来帮助他们劳动。我了解到年轻人每天都要花很长时间去为家里弄柴火，于是到了夜晚，我就常常拿起他的工具——它们的使用方法我很快就学会了，随后给他们家弄回足够烧好几天的柴火。

“我还记得自己第一天这样做过之后，年轻女人早晨打开了门，看见外面有一大堆木柴，显得非常吃惊。她高声说了几个字，年轻男人便到她这儿来了，他也露出了吃惊的表情。我高兴地注意到，他那天就没有到森林里去了，而是整天修补房子和种菜园。

“渐渐地，我发现了一桩更重要的事情。我发现这些人有一种办法，能通过清晰的声音来交流他们的经验和感情。我察觉到他们说的那些字，常常使听的人头脑里或面容上产生快乐或者痛苦，笑容或者悲哀。这真是一种神奇的学问，我热切地渴望要了解它。不过我为了这个目的而做出的每一步努力都受到了挫折。他们发声很快，而且他们说出的字与可见的事物没有任何明显的联系，我找不到任何线索来解开声音和事物的连接之谜。不过经过我的苦心琢磨，在窝棚里又待了好几轮月亮形状变化的时间，我终于了解了他们的谈话中最常说到的一些东西的名称。我学会了并且能使用‘火’‘牛奶’‘面包’‘柴火’这些字。我还学会说小屋主人们的名字。年轻人和他的同伴每个人都有几个名字，而老人只有一个，那就是‘父亲’。那个姑娘叫‘姐姐’，或者‘阿加莎’，那个青年叫‘费利克斯’，‘弟弟’，或者‘儿子’。当我懂得了给每一个声音所分配的意思，并且自己也能发出它们来的时候，那种快乐简直是无法形容的。我还可以分辨出几个其他的字，不过还不能了解和运用它们，例如‘好’‘亲爱的’‘不快活’。

“就这样我度过了那个冬季。小屋主人们温柔的态度和美丽的形象为我所喜爱，当他们不快活的时候，我也感到沮丧，当他们高兴的时候，我又和他们一起快乐。除了他们以外，我很少见到其他人类，即使有什么人偶尔走进那间农舍，他们粗鲁的态度和粗俗的举动只能使我更感到我的朋友们品行优秀。我可以觉察到，老人常常极力鼓励他的孩子们——我有时听到他这样称呼他们——要抛开忧愁。他总是以一种快乐的语气和慈爱的表情讲话，这甚至让我也感到愉快起来。阿加莎很恭敬地听着，她的眼里有时涌满了泪水，于是她就尽量让人不察觉地把泪水擦掉。不过在一般情况下，在她听完了她父亲的教诲之后，表情和声调会变得更快活些。费利克斯就不一样。在这几个人当中他是最忧伤的，即使我的毫无经验的感官，也能感觉到他似乎比他的朋友们更痛苦。不过，如果说他的面容更忧愁的话，他的声音却比他的姐姐显得更快活，特别是当他对老人说话的时候。

“我可以举出无数的事例来，它们虽然都微不足道，却能表明这些可爱的村民有怎样的性情。在贫困和匮乏的生活中，费利克斯会高兴地给姐姐带来雪地上刚刚冒出来的第一朵小花。清晨在她起床以前，他就扫干净了她去奶棚的小路上的积雪，从井里汲了水，从屋外的棚子里拿来了柴火，在那里，使他一直感到惊讶的是，总是有看不见的手给他们增添着储存。我相信，白天他是去给附近的农民干活，因为他常常出门，晚饭时才回家，却没有带回任何柴火。其他时间他就在菜园里劳动，在霜冻的日子里没有多少活干，他就给老人和阿加莎念书。

“起初，念书这事使我极为迷惑不解，不过慢慢地我就发现，他念书的时候发出的许多声音和他说话的时候是一样的。因此我就猜想，他在纸上看到了他懂得的一些代表说话的符号，于是我也热切地渴望懂得这些符号，可是，既然我连那些符号所代表的声音也不明白，怎么可能懂得这些符号呢？然而我在这门学问里已经有明显的进步，只不过尽管我集中注意力，理解力还不足以跟上他们的任何谈话罢了。我很容易看出，虽然我渴望让小屋主人知道我，但在我没有首先掌握好他们的语言之前，不能做这种尝试。懂得了语言，也许能使他们不在乎我那畸形的外貌，因为我始终看到自己的形体和他们相比构成了鲜明的对照。

“我赞赏小屋主人们那完美的形体——他们的优雅，美丽，以及精美的皮肤。当我在清澈的池水中照见自己的时候，我是多么的惊骇啊！一开始我吓得跳了起来，不敢相信那映在水中的镜像就是我自己。等我完全确信自己真的就是那个怪物的时候，心里充满了沮丧和屈辱的极度痛苦。唉！我当时还不完全懂得这可悲的丑陋会发生致命的作用。

“随着太阳渐渐变得温暖起来，白天变得越来越长，积雪溶化了，我看见了光秃秃的树木和黑油油的土地。从这个时候起，费利克斯就更加忙碌了，那种处于饥饿边缘的令人伤心的迹象也消失了。他们的食物，正如我后来发现，是粗糙的，却是有益于健康的，现在食物也很充足了。他们修整了菜园，里面长出了几种新的蔬菜。随着季节的变化，他们的生活也逐日显示出舒适的迹象。

“如果没有下雨——我发现当天上落下水的时候，他们就这样称呼它——每天中午，老人便靠在儿子手臂上散步。时常都会下雨，不过一阵大风会很快吹干地面，这个季节变得比以前要愉快得多了。

“我在窝棚里的生活始终如一。早晨，我注意着主人们的活动，当他们各自忙着干活的时候，我就睡觉。一天剩余的时间，我用来观察我的朋友们。当他们回房睡觉的时候，如果有月亮，或者有星光，我就到树林里去，为自己采集食物，为小屋主人捡柴火。回来的时候，只要有必要，我就清扫小路上的积雪，还干些我看到费利克斯干过的事情。我后来发现，由看不见的手为他们干的这些活儿，令他们大为惊讶。在这种情况下，有一两次我听见他们说什么‘善良的精灵’‘真奇妙’，不过我当时还不懂这些字的意义。

“我的思想现在变得更活跃了，而且我渴望了解这些可爱的人心里的动机和感情，我想弄清楚费利克斯为什么显得那样痛苦，阿加莎又为什么显得那样悲哀。我想（愚蠢的可怜虫！）我也许能够让这些应该快乐的人重新得到快乐。当我睡觉或者在外边的时候，那个可敬的失明的父亲、温柔的阿加莎和优秀的费利克斯的形象时常掠过我的眼前。我把他们看作比自己更优越的生命，他们将作我未来命运的主宰者。我在想象中勾画出上千的画面，设想自己怎么出现在他们面前，他们又将怎样接待我。我想象他们会感到厌恶，直到我用温柔的态度和劝慰的话语首先赢得他们的好感，然后再博得他们的爱。

“这些想法使我感到振奋，并使我以新的热情去学习语言的技艺。我的发音器官的确很粗糙，不过还算柔韧，尽管我的声音很不像他们的语调那样如柔和的音乐，但我到底能基本清楚地像自己理解的那样发出声来。这就像驴子和哈巴狗，温顺的驴子尽管模样很粗鲁，但它的心是好的，应该受到更好的待遇，而不应挨鞭打和咒骂。

“春天快意的骤雨和宜人的温暖大大改变了大地的面貌。在这种变化以前，人好像一直躲在洞穴里，现在处处散布着，展示着各种耕作的技艺。鸟儿唱着更加欢快的歌儿，树上的叶子萌发了新芽。欢乐的、欢乐的大地啊！你在不久前还是凄凉、潮湿和有害于健康的，现在却成了神居住的地方。我的精神也被大自然迷人的景象所振奋鼓舞，往日已经从我的记忆里抹去，目前是一片宁静，而未来则在希望和对欢乐的期待的光辉里，被照耀得金光灿烂。”

第十三章　知识与痛苦

“我现在要赶快叙述我的故事中更为动人的部分。我将讲述种种深刻影响我的感情的事件，这些感情使我变得和从前大不相同，而成了现在的我。

“春天很快地过着，天气变得很好，晴空万里无云。从前荒凉阴郁的地方现在竟会开放着美丽的鲜花和长出青草绿叶，真让我惊奇。成千种令人愉悦的香气，成千种美丽的景色，使我的感官得到满足和振奋。

“就在这些日子里的一天，当小屋的主人们在劳作之余定期休息的时候——老人在弹着吉他，孩子们在听着——我留意到费利克斯的面容带着说不出的忧伤，他还不断地叹气。他父亲有一次停止了他的音乐，我从他的态度来猜测，是在询问他儿子悲伤的原因。费利克斯用快乐的声音来回答父亲，然后老人正要开始重新弹奏，突然有人在轻轻地敲门。

“那是一个骑着马的女子，还有一个充当向导的农民陪伴着她。那个女子全身穿着黑衣服，脸上还蒙着一条厚厚的黑纱巾。阿加莎问了她一个问题，陌生女子只用甜美的声音回答了费利克斯的名字。她的语音很动听，但和我的朋友们的口音都不相同。费利克斯一听到他的名字，急忙向这个女子走来。女子看见了他就撩起了面纱，于是我看见了具有天使般的美、带着天使般的表情的一张脸。她的头发乌黑发亮，编成了很奇怪的形状；她的眼睛也是黑色的，活泼有神，又很温柔；她的容貌匀称端正，皮肤极为白皙，两颊还微微泛起可爱的红晕。

“费利克斯见到那个女子的时候高兴得发狂，所有忧愁的迹象从他的脸上一扫而光，顿时充满了欢乐，那种欣喜的程度我认为简直难以置信。他的脸上快乐得发红，眼睛里闪耀着火花，这时候我觉得他就和那个陌生女子一样的美丽。女子好像怀着与他不同的心情，她擦去了美丽的眼睛里落下的几滴泪珠，把一只手伸给了费利克斯，费利克斯则狂喜地吻着她的手，还称她为——按照我能分辨出的声音——他可爱的阿拉伯人。她好像并不懂得他的话，只是微笑着。他扶她下了马，打发了向导，把她引进了小屋。他和父亲进行了一阵谈话。那个年轻的陌生女子在老人的脚下跪倒，正要吻他的手，但是老人扶起了她，并且亲切地拥抱了她。

“我很快就察觉到，尽管陌生女子说话声音很清楚，但似乎讲的是她自己的一种语言，她讲的话小屋主人们不懂，她也不懂他们讲的话。他们互相做了许多我不明白的手势，不过我看出来，她的到来使小屋里里外外都充满了欢乐，就像太阳驱散早晨的雾气一样驱散了他们的忧伤。费利克斯显得特别快乐，用愉快的笑容来迎接他的阿拉伯人。阿加莎，那永远温柔的阿加莎，则吻着那可爱的陌生女子的手，她还指着她的弟弟做着手势，在我看来，是说在女子到来之前他一直很悲伤。就这样他们度过了几个钟头，从面容看都显得很快乐，至于原因我却不明白。我不久就发现，那个陌生女子不停地跟着他们反复发出同样的声音，于是我知道那是她在努力学习他们的语言。我立即就有了一个念头，我应当利用这种教导来达到同样的目的。陌生女子在第一课里学会了大约二十个字，其中大多数都是我以前就懂得的，不过其他的字使我有所收益。

“夜晚到来了，阿加莎和那个阿拉伯人很早就回房间去了。当他们分手的时候，费利克斯吻着陌生女子的手说：‘晚安，可爱的沙菲。’他又再坐了很久，和父亲谈着话。从他不断地提到她的名字来看，我猜想他们谈话的内容就是他们那可爱的客人。我急切地渴望了解他们的谈话，为了这个目的而竭尽全力，可是我发现自己一点也不能理解。

“第二天早晨，费利克斯出门去干活。阿加莎的日常事务做完了以后，阿拉伯女子就坐在老人的脚下，拿起了他的吉他弹奏乐曲。乐曲是那样令人入迷的美妙，竟立即使我的眼中涌出了悲喜交集的泪水。她唱起了歌，她的歌声婉转流畅，抑扬顿挫，时而高昂，时而轻微，就像树林里夜莺的鸣啼。

“她唱完以后，就把吉他递给阿加莎，阿加莎起初推辞，后来她弹了一支简单的曲子，并用甜美的歌声来伴唱，不过她的歌曲和陌生女子的并不相像。老人似乎欣喜得着了迷，他说了一些话，阿加莎努力向沙菲解释老人的话，那些话似乎是老人表示她的音乐给了自己极大的快乐。

“现在，日子似乎在和过去一样平静地流逝着，唯一的改变是，我的朋友们脸上的悲伤已经被快乐所取代。沙菲总是欢乐和愉快的，她和我在语言知识方面都进步迅速，过了两个月，我的保护人所讲的大部分话，我都能够听懂了。

“在此期间，黑油油的土地被青草覆盖了，翠绿的河岸上散布着无数的花朵，芳香而悦目，在月光照耀下的树林里闪烁着点点微弱的亮光。阳光变得更温暖，夜色明净而温馨。我夜间的漫游是一种极大的乐趣，尽管太阳的晚落早起大大地缩短了它的时间，因为我从不冒险在白天走出去，害怕得到我在第一个村子里曾经遭遇过的那种待遇。

“我在白天的时间里都集中注意力，以便能够更快地掌握他们的语言，而且我可以夸口说我比阿拉伯女子的进步更快，她只能理解很少一点，说话也结结巴巴，而我对他们讲的每一个字几乎都能听懂，并且能够模仿。

“我一面提高自己讲话的能力，一面也随着陌生女子学习的课程学文字，这为我开辟了一个奇妙而充满乐趣的广阔天地。

“费利克斯教沙菲的那本书是沃尔涅的《帝国的衰亡》。(1)如果费利克斯不是一边念一边详细解释的话，我本来是理解不了这本书的含义的。他说他之所以选择了这本书，是因为它的雄辩风格乃是模仿东方作家才形成的。我通过这本书获得了历史方面的粗浅知识，对世界上现存的几个帝国也有了一个概略的了解，它使我较深地理解了地球上不同国家的生活方式、政府和宗教制度。我听说了什么懒散的亚洲人，希腊人的巨大的天才和精神活动，早期罗马人的战争和奇异的美德——他们后来的堕落——他们强大帝国的衰亡，还有骑士制度，基督教和国王等等。我也听说了美洲半球的发现，还和沙菲一道为当地土著居民的不幸命运而哭泣。

“这些神奇的故事激起了我许多奇特的感情。难道人类，一方面如此强大，如此高尚和健美，另一方面却又如此邪恶和卑鄙？他们一会儿似乎纯粹是罪恶原则产下的后裔，一会儿又是一切可以想象到的高贵的、神明般的品德的体现者。做一个伟大而具有美德的人，对于任何一个感觉敏锐的生命而言，似乎应该是最高的荣誉；做一个卑鄙邪恶的人，就像许多在历史上记载的人那样，则应是最低贱的堕落，那种状况比瞎眼的鼹鼠或无害的蠕虫还要卑鄙。有很长时间，我没法设想一个人怎么能去杀害他的同类，甚至不懂为什么要有法律和政府，可是当我听见了许多罪恶和流血的具体细节之后，我就不再惊奇了，而是怀着厌恶和鄙弃掉过头去。

“小屋里的人们每次谈话都给我展开了新的奇异景象。在我听费利克斯给阿拉伯女子讲课的时候，我懂得了人类社会那奇怪的制度。我听到了财产分配，巨大的财富和悲惨的贫穷；我听到了等级、家系和血统。

“这些话使我回过头来考虑自己。我懂得了，你的同类们最为珍视的占有物乃是与财富联系在一起的高贵而纯正的血统。一个人只要拥有了这两种有利条件中的一件，就会受到尊敬。可是，假如他一件也没有，除了极为罕见的例外情况之外，他就会被视为流浪汉或者奴隶，注定要为少数特别选出的人的利益而耗费他的精力。那么我又是什么呢？对于我被创造出来的情况和我的创造者，我一无所知，不过我知道自己没有金钱，没有朋友，也没有任何财产。此外，我还被赋予了一个丑陋畸形、令人憎恶的可怕形体，甚至我的属性也和人不一样。我比他们更灵活，能依靠粗劣的食物生存，我能承受极度的冷和热而不致损伤身体，我的体型也大大超过了他们。当我环顾周围的时候，我没见到、也没听到过有像我这样的生命。这么说来，难道我是一个谁都要逃避、谁都不接纳的怪物？是大地上的一个污点吗？

“我无法形容这些想法给我带来的那种剧烈痛苦，我竭力要驱散这些念头，可是随着知识的积累，苦恼也在增长。啊，但愿我永远留在我最初生活的树林里，除了饥、渴和炎热以外便一无所知、一无所感！

“知识具有多么奇怪的性质！它一旦控制了你的头脑，就紧紧地缠住了它，就像附着在石头上的苔藓一样。有时候，我真希望摆脱掉一切思想和感情，可是我明白，只有一个办法能克服痛苦的感觉，那就是死——那是我害怕然而又不能理解的一种状态。我赞赏我的主人们的那些美德和美好的感情，热爱他们温柔的举止与和蔼的性格。可是我不可能和他们直接接触，只有在他们看不见和不知道的情况下偷偷地和他们打交道，而这样并不能满足，而是更增强了我想成为他们之中一员的渴望。阿加莎那温柔的话语，迷人的阿拉伯姑娘那生气勃勃的笑容，都不是为了我。老人那温和的教诲，可爱的费利克斯那活泼生动的谈话，也不是为了我。悲惨的、不幸的可怜虫！

“费利克斯讲的其他课程给我的印象甚至更深。我听说了两性的区别，孩子的出生和成长，父亲怎样陶醉于婴儿的微笑和大孩子活泼的俏皮话，母亲的全部生活和关切又是怎样倾注在她的宝贝身上，青年的头脑怎样扩充和取得知识，以及兄弟、姐妹和其他种种关系怎样把一个人和另一个人联结在一起。

“可是，我的朋友和亲戚又在哪里？在我的婴儿时期没有父亲照看过我，也没有母亲用微笑和抚爱来祝福过我。即使他们这样做过，我过去的所有生活如今也变成了一团污迹，一片空白，我在里面什么也分辨不出来了。在我最早的印象里，我就已经具有和现在一样的重量和体型了。我从来没有看见过和我一样的生命，也没有任何人宣称他和我有过任何关系。我是什么呢？这个问题一再出现在我心中，我只有用呻吟来回答。

“我很快就会向你解释，这些感情将朝什么方向发展，不过现在请允许我回到小屋主人们身上来，他们的故事激起了我各种各样的感情，愤慨、快乐以及惊奇，而这一切又最终加深了我对我的保护者的爱和敬意（我怀着天真的、半带痛楚的自欺心理，喜欢这样称呼他们）。”

————————————————————

(1) 沃尔涅（Constantin Francois Volney，1757—1820），法国资产阶级革命时期的思想家，《帝国的衰亡》（Ruins of Empires）是他的代表作。

第十四章　小屋主人的故事

“过了一段时间，我才了解到我的朋友们的历史。它展开了一系列的情景，其中每一个对于完全缺乏体验的我来说都是有趣而奇妙的，不能不给我心中刻下了极深的印象。

“那个老人的名字叫作德·拉舍。他出身于法国的一个名门世家，在那里富足地生活了许多年，受到地位更高的人的尊重和相同地位的人的爱戴。他的儿子为国服役，阿加莎置身于最具声誉的贵夫人之列。在我来到这里之前几个月，他们还住在一个叫作巴黎的又大又奢华的城市里，被很多朋友簇拥着，享受着美德、文雅的智慧，或者说是高雅趣味，以及适度的财产所提供的所有快乐。

“沙菲的父亲就是导致他们生活崩溃的根源。他是个土耳其商人，在巴黎也住了很多年，由于我不懂得的某种原因，他后来成了法国政府讨厌的人。就在沙菲从君士坦丁堡到巴黎他这儿来的那一天，他被逮捕了，进了监狱。他受到审讯并被判处了死刑。对他的判决是极不公正的，整个巴黎都愤慨了，大家认为定罪的原因在于他的宗教信仰和财富，而不是他被指控的所谓罪行。

“费利克斯在审讯的时候碰巧在场，当他听到法庭的判决时感到不可遏制的惊骇和义愤。就在那个时刻，他庄严地立誓要救他出来，然后就找寻营救的办法。在他试图进入监狱的多次尝试毫无结果之后，在监狱没人防卫的一边，他发现有一扇牢固地上了铁条的窗户，光线就从那里照进了关着不幸的伊斯兰教徒的地牢。他被加上了重重镣铐，在绝望中等待着执行对他的野蛮的判决。费利克斯在夜间来到了铁窗前，告诉那个囚徒自己营救他的意图。那个土耳其人又惊又喜，竭力煽起营救者的热情，许诺以重酬和财富。费利克斯轻蔑地拒绝了他的条件，不过当他看见了被允许来探望父亲的沙菲，而且沙菲用手势表达了她强烈的感激时，年轻人不禁这样想：这个囚犯有一件珍宝，足以完全酬报自己的辛苦和危险的地方。

“土耳其人很快就察觉出他的女儿在费利克斯心中留下的印象，为了更牢靠地拴住费利克斯为自己效力，他答应一旦自己被送到了安全的地方，就让女儿和他成婚。费利克斯很体贴人，没有接受这个提议，不过他盼望着这桩事有可能会实现，从而达到幸福的顶点。

“在后来的几天里，正当为商人逃跑的准备工作处于进行之中的时候，费利克斯的热情因为收到了那个可爱的姑娘的几封信而更加炽烈了。姑娘通过父亲的一个懂得法语的老仆人，用她情人的语言表达了自己的意思。她以最热烈的措辞感激他为她父亲所做的事，与此同时，她又幽幽哀叹她自己的命运。

“我抄写下了这些信件，因为我住在那个小棚子里的时候，设法找到了写字的工具，而且费利克斯和阿加莎时常把这些信拿在手里念。在我离开之前，我会把它们交给你，它们会证明我的故事的真实性，不过现在太阳已经低低落下，我只来得及给你复述一下它们的基本内容。

“沙菲说到她的母亲是一个信奉基督教的阿拉伯人，被土耳其人掳掠而沦为奴隶，由于她的美丽，她赢得了沙菲父亲的心，他娶了她。这年轻姑娘用崇高而富于热情的言辞谈到她的母亲，说她生来是个自由人，鄙弃现在所受的束缚。她以基督教义来教育自己的女儿，教导她应该追求更高的智慧，坚持精神的独立，而那是伊斯兰教禁止女教徒获得的。后来母亲死了，不过她的教导不可磨灭地印在了沙菲的心上，她一想到要再被送回到亚洲，被禁闭在后宫的高墙内，只许做些幼稚愚昧的娱乐，就感到和她心灵的情趣格格不入，不禁十分厌恶，因为她的心灵已经习惯于崇高的思想和对美德的高尚追求了。嫁给一个基督徒，留在一个允许妇女在社会上占有一席之地的国家里，这种前景使她入了迷。

“处死土耳其人的日子已经确定了，可是，就在那一天的前夜，他逃离了监狱，在天亮以前就逃到了距巴黎数里之外的地方。费利克斯早已以他父亲、姐姐和本人的名义取得了几份护照。他事先就把他的计划通报给了父亲，他父亲助了一臂之力，伪装出门旅行而离开了家，和女儿一道藏匿在巴黎一个偏僻的地方。

“费利克斯引着逃亡者穿越法国来到里昂，又越过塞尼峰到了莱格亨。在那里，商人决定等到一个有利的时机，再转移到土耳其管辖的某个地方去。

“沙菲决定留在她父亲身边，直到他最后离开的时刻。在最后离开之前，土耳其人又重申他的保证，要让女儿和他的救命恩人结合。费利克斯也留下和他们在一起，期待着那桩喜事，与此同时，他也享受着与那个阿拉伯姑娘做伴的快乐，她对他表示出了最单纯、最温柔的情意。他们借助翻译互相交谈，有时候则通过眼神互通款曲，沙菲还给他唱自己祖国的美妙歌曲。

“土耳其人允许这种亲密的关系，并鼓励这对年轻的恋人对未来怀抱希望，然而他心里却另有打算。他一想到女儿会和一个基督徒结合就感到厌恶，可是他又害怕自己要是表现得三心二意，便会惹恼费利克斯，因为他明白自己仍然处于他的营救者的力量之下，费利克斯可以选择出卖他，向他们居留的意大利当局告发。他用尽千方百计，使自己能够继续欺骗费利克斯，直到完全没有必要的时候，他就会在自己离开的时候秘密地把女儿带走。

“法国政府对他们的牺牲者的脱逃大为光火，于是不遗余力地要找到和惩罚那个营救者。费利克斯的密谋很快就被发现了，德·拉舍和阿加莎被投进了监狱。这个消息传到了费利克斯的耳中，使他从欢乐的梦中惊醒了。他那失明的年迈的父亲，他那温柔的姐姐，现在躺在肮脏腐臭的地牢里，而他却呼吸着自由的空气，和自己心爱的人相伴相依。这个想法对他简直是一种折磨。他立即和土耳其人做了安排，如果在他回到意大利之前，他们能够找到有利机会逃出意大利的话，沙菲就寄居在莱格亨的一所修道院里，然后，他就离开了可爱的阿拉伯姑娘，赶到了巴黎，把自己交给法律听凭处治，希望这样可以解救德·拉舍和阿加莎。

“他并没有成功。他们一家被监禁了五个月，然后才开始审判。结果是剥夺他们的财产，并被判处终生流放国外。

“他们在德国的一个村舍里找到一个可怜的居所，我就是在那里见到他们的。费利克斯不久就打听到了那个背信弃义的土耳其人（为了这个人，他和他的家人才经受了这种闻所未闻的迫害），他一发现自己的救命恩人已经被弄得家贫如洗，就背弃了良心和荣誉，带着女儿离开了意大利，并侮辱性地给费利克斯寄来了一小笔钱，按照他的说法，是资助他们将来的生活。

“我初次见到费利克斯的时候，就是这些事变折磨着他的心，并使他成了全家最不幸的人。他可以承受贫穷，并且因为这场危难本是他的美德的应得报偿，他也为此感到光荣，可是，那个土耳其人的忘恩负义，失去他心爱的沙菲，则是更为痛苦和不可弥补的不幸。现在，这位阿拉伯姑娘的到来，给他的心灵注入了新的生气。

“当费利克斯被剥夺了财产和地位的消息传到莱格亨的时候，那个商人命令他的女儿不得再想念她的恋人，却要她做好准备返回她的祖国去。天性慷慨正直的沙菲被他的命令激怒了，她力图规劝她的父亲，可是他重申他那暴君式的训令，怒气冲冲地走了。

“过了几天，土耳其人走进了女儿的卧室，急匆匆地告诉她说，他有理由相信自己在莱格亨的住处已经暴露，他很快就会被引渡给法国政府，因此，他已租好了一条船载他去君士坦丁堡，几小时之后就要驶向那里。他打算把女儿交给一个可靠的仆人照料，将来带上迄今尚未抵达莱格亨的大部分财产，从容地回国。

“沙菲单独留下以后，她在心里确定了自己在这种紧急情况下应该采取的行动。在土耳其定居是她所厌恶的，她的宗教信仰和她的感情都与此对立。从偶然发现的她父亲的一些信件里，她了解到了她的恋人被流放的情况，并知道了他当时落脚的地方。她犹豫了一段时间，终于拿定了主意。她随身携带了一些属于自己的珠宝和一笔钱，和一个侍女一道离开意大利前往德国，那个侍女是莱格亨当地人，懂得土耳其日常用语。

“她安全地到了距德·拉舍的茅屋约二十里格的一个小镇，这时她的侍女得了急病。沙菲全心全意地照料她，但那可怜的姑娘还是死了，撇下阿拉伯姑娘孤身一人，她不懂这个国家的语言，也完全不了解当地的风俗。不过她遇见了好心人。她的侍女曾经提到过她们目的地的地名，在她死去以后，她们寄宿的那家女房东设法让沙菲平安地到达了她恋人的小屋。”

第十五章　野性的升华

“这就是我所爱的小屋主人的历史。它深深地打动了我。从它所展示的社会生活景象，我懂得了应该钦佩他们的美德，唾弃人类的罪恶。

“到那时为止，我还把犯罪看作一桩离自己很遥远的祸害，仁爱和慷慨始终在感召着我，激发起我的一种欲望，想要在倡导和展现着如此丰富的可敬品德的热烈场景中去做一个演员。不过，在叙述我心智方面的进步时，不应该忽略当年8月初发生的一件事情。

“一个夜晚，当我像平常那样到邻近的树林里，去采集食物和为我的保护者拾取柴火的时候，我在地上发现了一个皮箱，里面有一些衣物和几本书。我急忙抓起这个意外收获，带着它回到了窝棚。很幸运，这些书正是用我在小屋里学得了基本知识的那种语言写成的，它们包括《失乐园》、一卷普鲁塔克的《名人传》和《少年维特的烦恼》。(1)得到这批珍宝使我喜不自胜；现在，当我的朋友们忙着他们的日常事务的时候，我就持续不懈地读这些故事，锻炼自己的头脑。

“我难以向你形容这些书对我产生了怎样的影响。它们在我心中激起了无穷无尽的新的想象和感情，有时候使我欣喜若狂，但更多的时候是令我陷入深沉的沮丧之中。在《少年维特的烦恼》里，除了它质朴感人的故事很有趣以外，还详细探讨了那么多的见解，揭示了那么多至那时为止对我来说还是模糊不清的问题，所以我在其中找到了永不枯竭的思考和惊奇的源泉。它所描写的那种温柔而富于家庭气氛的言谈风度，以及追求自身之外更崇高的目标的高尚情怀，和我在我的保护者当中获得的体验相吻合，也和我自己心中一直存在的渴望相一致。不过我认为，维特本人比我所见过或想象过的任何人更为圣洁，他的性格里绝无半点虚伪矫饰，然而其痛苦又极为深沉。书中对于死亡和自杀的专门探讨使我充满惊异。我不敢擅自对这个问题的是非得失加以评论，但我倾向于赞同主人公的意见，他的死令我落泪，尽管我还不能准确地理解其意义。

“然而，在阅读的时候，我总是要联想起自己的感情和处境。我发现，和我在书中所读到的那些人物以及在书中所提到的谈话相比，我既是非常相似，又是奇怪地不同。我与他们感受相通，也部分地理解他们，可是我的心智构造并没有完成，我对谁也不依附，和谁也没有关系。‘死亡是必由之路’；然而在这个世界上无人会哀悼我的死亡。我形象可憎而体型巨大。这是什么意思？我是谁？我是什么？我从哪里来？我到哪里去？这些问题不停浮现在脑海里，可是我无法解答。

“我得到的那卷普鲁塔克的《名人传》，写的是古代共和国最早的创始人的历史。这本书对我的影响远远不同于《少年维特的烦恼》。我从维特的想象中了解到的是消沉和阴郁，而普鲁塔克却教给我崇高的思想。他使我超越了有关自己思绪的可怜的范围，而去崇敬爱戴往昔时代的英雄们。我所读到的许多事物都超过了我的想象力和经验。对于王国，辽阔的疆土，巨大的河流，无边的海洋，我只有一些混淆不清的知识。至于城市和大量密集的人口，我更是一无所知了。我的保护者的小屋一直就是我学习人类天性的唯一学校，可是这本书却展示出全新的、更为宏大有力的人类活动场景。我读到许多卷入公共事务的人物，他们管理或者屠杀自己的同类。我感到心中升腾起对美德的巨大热情和对邪恶的憎恶，就我对这两个词的理解，尽管它们的含义是相对的，我却把它们只当作欢乐和痛苦的意思来使用。受这些感情的引导，我当然就会敬仰努马、梭伦和卢克古斯这些和平的立法者，而不喜欢罗慕路斯和泰修乌斯了。(2)我的保护者一家的族长制式的生活方式也使这种见解在我心里扎了根，假如我接触人类的第一个人是个渴望荣誉和杀人的年轻士兵，或许我就会感染上不同的感情了。

“然而《失乐园》所激起的感情又不相同，而且更为深刻。我读它的时候，就和我读其他两本落入我手中的书一样，把它当作了真正的历史。全能的上帝和他的创造物之间激战的情景，最大限度地引起了我全部的惊奇和敬畏之情。我时常把某些场景用来和我的境况相比较，因为它们的相似性令我惊讶不已。我就像亚当，和世上的任何生命都毫无联系，不过就其他各个方面来看，他的情况和我又极不相同。他是经上帝之手诞生的完美的创造物，既快乐又幸运，受到他的创造者的特别呵护，允许他和更高级的生灵交谈，向他们取得知识，而我却是悲惨的，孤立无援，形只影单。有很多次，我觉得撒旦就是我的境况的恰当象征，因为我就像他一样，在见到我的保护者得到幸福的时候，心里常常产生怨恨的嫉妒。

“另一件事加强和坚定了我的这些感情。我住进窝棚后不久，在我离开你的实验室时拿走的衣服的口袋里，我发现了一些纸。开始时我并没有留意它们，现在既然我能够读懂那上面写的字了，我便开始努力研究起来。那是你在把我创造出来之前四个月里写的日记。你在这些纸上详细地描述了你的每一步工作进展，这段记载中还混杂着对于你的家事的叙述。你无疑想起了这些纸片吧，它们就在这里。一切关于我那可诅咒的起源的情况都记录在里面，创造我的一系列令人作呕的细节都展现在眼前，对我这引人憎恶的形象给予了最详尽的描写，所用的语言不仅刻画出了你的惧怕，也使我自己陷于不可磨灭的恐惧之中。我一面读一面感到厌恶。‘我获得生命的那个可憎的日子啊！’我痛苦地高叫道，‘该诅咒的创造者！你为什么要创造一个丑陋得连你自己也要厌恶的怪物啊？上帝出于慈悲而照着他的模样把人创造得美丽迷人，然而我的形象却是你的形象的龌龊的翻版，并且因为十分相似而更令人毛骨悚然。撒旦还有他的同伴，有他的魔鬼朋友来赞赏和鼓励他，可我却是茕茕孑立，遭人憎恶。’

“这些就是我在沮丧和孤独的时刻心里的想法。不过，当我思考着小屋主人们的美德和他们和蔼慈祥的性情时，我又劝说自己相信，只要他们知道我敬仰他们的美德，就会同情我而不再留意我的丑陋。不管我相貌如何怪异可怕，难道他们会把一个恳求他们的同情和友谊的人赶出门外吗？我决定，至少不能绝望，要为这一次决定命运的会见做好自己的一切准备。我把这次尝试推迟了几个月，因为它的成败关系重大，我唯恐会失败。此外，我发现随着自己每天经验的增进，我的理解力也大大提高了，所以我宁愿再等几个月，待智慧有所增长时才开始做这件事情。

“就在这段时间，小屋里发生了一些变化。沙菲的出现使家中充满了欢乐，我也发现他们的境况有了较大的改善。费利克斯和阿加莎把更多的时间花在了娱乐和谈话上，工作中也有仆人来协助他们。他们看来并不富有，但他们满足而幸福，他们的情感宁静而平和，而我的情感却一天天变得更加骚乱。知识的增长只是使我更清楚地看到自己是个何等可怜的弃儿。我曾怀抱着希望，的确如此，可是当我看见自己在水中的倒影或者在月光下的影子的时候，希望就幻灭了，就像那水中月下的脆弱影像和飘忽阴影一样。

“我竭力要消除这些恐惧，使自己坚强起来，去迎接几个月后决心接受的考验。有时候，我听凭思绪摆脱理智的约束，让它漫游在天堂的原野里，而且大胆地幻想有亲切可爱的生灵与我的感情共鸣，让我的阴郁化为欢乐，她们天使般的面容上流露着抚慰的微笑。可是这一切都是一场梦，并没有夏娃(3)来抚慰我的忧伤，或者分担我的思虑，我形只影单。我想起了亚当对他的创造者的祈求。然而我的创造者在哪里？他抛弃了我，在心灵的痛楚中，我诅咒他。

“秋天就这样消逝了。我怀着惊奇和忧愁，看着树叶凋零和飘落，大自然又和我第一次看见树林和月亮时那样，再度呈现出荒芜凄凉的面貌。不过我并不在意天气的凄冷，我的身体组织更适于抵御寒冷而不耐炎热。只不过我最大的赏心乐事是看到花儿、鸟儿以及夏天的欢乐景象，当它们离我而去以后，我便把更多的注意力转移到了小屋主人身上。他们的快乐并没有因为夏天的消逝而减少。他们相爱着，彼此情感相通，他们的欢乐依赖于相互间的关系，并不因周围环境发生事变而受到惊扰。我越是看着他们，就越是渴望得到他们的保护和关怀。我的心渴求着让这些可爱的人知道我和爱我，我最大的奢望便是看到他们用慈爱的目光瞧着我。我不敢设想他们会轻蔑而恐惧地逃避我。就是站在他们门前乞讨的穷人也绝没有被他们赶走过。是的，我所要求的东西是比一点食物和一夜寄宿更为巨大的珍宝，我要求得到的是关切和同情，但我并不相信我不配得到它。

“冬季在一天天过去。自我获得生命以来，一年四季已经完成了一个周期。到这时候，我的整个注意力都集中于考虑自己如何进入我的保护者的屋子。我订了许多方案，不过我最后确定的方案是，等到失明的老人单独在家的时候再进屋。我有足够的自知之明，知道原先见到我的那些人，主要是因为我这反常的可怕形象而大为惊骇。我的声音尽管刺耳，倒也没有什么可怕之处，因此我想，只要孩子们不在家，我便能博得德·拉舍老人的好感，争取以他为媒介，让那些年轻的保护者也能容忍我。

“一天，阳光照耀在洒满红叶的地上，烘染出欢快的气氛，虽然这并不足以使人感到温暖，沙菲、阿加莎和费利克斯出门去做一次乡间的远足，老人自愿单独待在家里。当孩子们离开后，他拿起了吉他，弹奏了几支哀伤而甜美的乐曲，胜过了过去我听他弹奏过的任何曲子。一开始他的面容因快乐而泛起了光彩，可是当他继续弹奏下去时，思虑和伤感便接踵而至，最后，他把乐器放到了一边，坐在那儿陷入了沉思。

“我的心疾速地跳动着，考验的时刻来到了，它将实现我的希望，或者证实我的担忧。仆人到邻近的一个集市上去了。小屋里里外外是一片寂静，这是极好的机会。可是当我接着要实行自己的计划时，我却四肢无力，倒在了地上。我重新站起来，我竭尽全力使自己坚定些，移开了放在窝棚前遮掩自己的木板。清新的空气使我振作起来，于是我怀着再度确立的决心，向小屋的门前走去。

“我敲了敲门。‘是谁啊？’老人问道，‘进来吧。’

“我进去了。‘请原谅我的打扰，’我说，‘我是个旅行者，需要休息一会儿。如果你允许我在炉火边待几分钟，我将十分感激。’

“‘来吧，’德·拉舍说，‘我乐意满足你的需要，不过很不巧，我的孩子们不在家，而我又双目失明，恐怕不能给你准备食物了。’

“‘不用麻烦了，我好心的主人，我有食物，我需要的只是温暖和休息。’

“我坐下来，接着是一阵沉默。我明白每一分钟对我来说都是宝贵的，然而我犹豫不决，不知道应该用什么方式开始这场谈话。这时候老人向我说道：

“‘听你的语言，陌生人，我猜想你是我的同胞；——你是法国人吧？’

“‘不，不过我是在一个法国家庭里受的教育，我只懂法语。我现在正要请求一些朋友的保护，我真诚地爱他们，我希望得到他们的恩惠。’

“‘他们是德国人吗？’

“‘不，他们是法国人。不过让我们换个话题吧。我是个不幸的、被抛弃的人，我举目四望，在世上既没有一个亲戚，也没有一个朋友。我要投奔的那些可爱的朋友从未见过我，也丝毫不了解我。我心里充满了忧虑，因为假如我失败了，我在世界上就永远是个被抛弃的人了。’

“‘不要绝望。没有朋友的确是不幸的，不过只要人们的心未因明显的私利而导致偏见，总是充满博爱和慈善的。所以，要坚信你的希望，如果那些朋友们是善良友好的，就不要绝望。’

“‘他们是善良的——他们是世界上最优秀的人，但是很不幸，他们正是对我抱有偏见。我具有善良的性格，我的一生至今为止无害于人，而且在某种程度上还是有益于人的，可是致命的偏见蒙住了他们的眼睛，他们本应看到我是一个富有同情心的、慈爱的朋友，却将我仅仅视为一个可憎的怪物。’

“‘这确实很不幸，不过假如你真的是无可责难的话，难道你就不能消除他们的偏见吗？’

“‘我正准备这样做，可是正因为这个缘故，我才感到如此恐惧不安。我深情地爱着这些朋友，好几个月以来，我一直在他们不知道的情况下经常为他们做些好事，可是他们却认为我是想伤害他们，我希望克服的正是这种偏见。’

“‘这些朋友住在哪里？’

“‘就在这附近。’

“老人沉默了一阵，然后继续说：‘如果你愿意毫无保留地把你的详细情况告诉我，也许我可以帮助你来消除他们的偏见。我双目失明，不能判断你的相貌如何，不过你的话使我相信你是真诚的。我很穷，而且是个流亡者，可是不管以什么方式，能为一个人做点好事，会让我得到真正的快乐。’

“‘你真是好人！我感谢你，我接受你慷慨的建议。是你的好心把我从困境里救了出来，我相信，有了你的帮助，我就不会被驱逐出社会，被排除在你的同胞们的同情心之外了。’

“‘上天不容如此！就算你真是一个罪犯，他们这样做只会使你绝望，而不会激励你向善。我自己也是不幸的，我和我的家人也被判了罪，尽管是无辜的，因此你可以判断，我是否会对你的不幸无动于衷。’

“‘我该怎么感谢你呢，我最好的、唯一的恩人？从你的口里，我才第一次听到对我表示好意的话语，我将永远怀着感激。你现在的仁慈使我确信，即将见面的朋友是会善待我的。’

“‘我可以知道你那些朋友的姓名和住址吗？’

“我沉默了。我想，决定性的时刻到了，或者永远剥夺我的快乐，或者永远使我幸福。我挣扎着，想保持足够的镇定来回答他的问题，但我办不到，这番努力反而摧毁了我剩余的力量，我倒在椅子上，大声啜泣起来。就在这个时候，我听见我的年轻保护者们的脚步声。我不能错过这千钧一发的时刻，我抓住老人的手，高声叫道：‘现在到时候了！——救救我，保护我！你和你的家人就是我要寻找的朋友。在这关键时刻不要抛弃我！’

“‘天啊！’老人叫道，‘你是谁？’

“门就在这一瞬刻打开了，费利克斯、沙菲和阿加莎走了进来。谁能描述他们在见到我的时候所表现出的恐惧和惊骇呢？阿加莎晕了过去，沙菲顾不得照看她的朋友，冲出了屋外。费利克斯向前扑过来，用超人的力量把我从他父亲身边拉开，那时我正紧抱着他父亲的双膝，他在一阵激怒中把我推倒在地，并用一根棍子狠狠地打我。我本来可以像狮子对付羚羊那样把他的肢体撕裂。可是我的心仿佛因剧烈痛楚而变得衰弱，便克制住了自己。我看到他还要继续打我，只好带着满身伤痛和满腔苦恼逃出小屋，在一片骚乱里偷偷潜回了我的窝棚。”

————————————————————

(1) 《失乐园》为17世纪英国诗人弥尔顿根据《圣经》写成的长诗；普鲁塔克（Plutarch，46—120）为罗马历史学家，《希腊罗马名人传》为其代表作；《少年维特的烦恼》为德国诗人歌德（Johann Wolfgang von Goethe，1749—1832）青年时代的小说。

(2) 以上均为《名人传》中的罗马历史人物。

(3) 据《圣经·创世记》，上帝创造出第一个人亚当后，亚当感觉孤单，于是上帝又创造了第一个女人夏娃，与亚当做伴。

第十六章　走上复仇之路

“可诅咒的，可诅咒的创造者！我为什么要活着？我为什么不在那一瞬刻把你如此随意赐予我的生命之火扑灭？我也不知道，绝望尚未完全控制我，当时主宰着我的情绪是暴怒和报复。我本来会逞一时快意毁灭那所屋子和它的住户，用他们的尖叫声和惨状来满足自己。

“夜晚来临时，我离开了窝棚，到树林里去漫游。现在，我不再担心被人发现而克制自己，我用可怕的嚎叫来发泄内心的痛苦。我就像一头冲出陷阱的野兽，毁坏着一切阻挡着我的东西，以牡鹿般的快捷在树林间乱跑。啊！我度过的是怎样一个不幸的夜晚啊！清冷的月光嘲弄似的照着我，光秃秃的树在我头顶上摇晃着枝丫，不时有一只鸟的甜美鸣叫声打破那无边的寂静。除了我，万物都在休憩或者独享其乐，而我，就像那个大魔王(1)一样，心里装着一座地狱，我得不到任何同情，真想把树木都连根拔起，在我周围制造一场大破坏和大灾难，然后坐下来欣赏那一片废墟。

“不过，这是一阵不能持久的狂暴感情，我因为身体过度劳累而精疲力竭，在绝望的衰弱中倒在了潮湿的草地上。在千万个人当中，竟没有一个来可怜我或者帮助我，难道我应该对我的仇敌们仁慈吗？不，从那一刻起，我宣布自己要永远与人类为敌，而且首先与那个人为敌，是他创造了我，把我打发到这种不堪忍受的苦难中来。

“太阳升起了，我听见人的声音，知道自己那个白天是不能回到住所去了。因此，我就躲到茂密的树林下层去，决定用接下来的时间好好考虑自己的处境。

“白天那令人愉快的阳光和清新的空气使我多少恢复了平静。当我考虑在小屋里发生的那幕情景时，我不能不相信自己的结论未免下得过早了些。我的行动显然过分鲁莽。很明显，我的谈话已经使那个父亲对我产生了好感，而我简直是个傻瓜，竟在他们面前暴露自己而引起他们的恐惧。我应该先让德·拉舍老人尽量熟悉我，然后再一步步地在他家的其余人跟前露面，那时他们对我就已经有了思想准备了。不过，我并不认为我的错误是无法弥补的，经过仔细考虑以后，我决定回到小屋去，找到那个老人，用我的陈述来争取他的同情。

“这些想法使我平静下来了，下午我昏沉沉地睡去，可是我的血液就像染了热病似的，让我不能进入安宁的梦境。前一天那可怕的景象一直在我眼前活生生地搬演着：女人们飞奔而逃，激怒的费利克斯把我从他父亲脚旁扯开。我精疲力竭地醒来，发现已经天黑了，便从藏身处爬出来，去寻找食物。

“当饥饿得到缓解以后，我就迈步向通往小屋的那条熟悉的小路走去。周围是一派寂静。我爬进窝棚，静静地等待着那一家人平常起床的时刻。那个时刻过去了，太阳也在天空高高升起了，可是屋里的人还没有出现。我剧烈地发起抖来，担心是不是发生了什么可怕的灾祸。小屋里黑沉沉的，听不到任何声响，我无法形容这种提心吊胆的痛苦。

“不久，有两个村民走过来了，他们在小屋附近停下，谈起话来，一边激烈地做着手势，但我听不懂他们说些什么，因为他们讲的是本国的语言，和我的保护者的语言不同。不过，费利克斯和另一个人很快也走过来了。我觉得奇怪，因为那天早晨我并没有见到他离开屋子，于是我急切地等待着，想从他的谈话中弄清这不寻常的情况到底意味着什么。

“‘你考虑过没有，’和他同来的人问道，‘你必须交三个月的房租，还要损失你菜园的收成？我不想占你的便宜，因此我请你对自己的决定再考虑几天。’

“‘完全没有必要，’费利克斯答道，‘我们不能再在你的屋子里住下去了。由于我给你讲过的那种可怕的情况，我父亲的生命已危在旦夕。我妻子和姐姐也无法从恐惧中恢复过来了。我请求你不要再劝说我了。收回你的房子，让我们逃离这个地方吧。’

“费利克斯在说这番话的时候，还在剧烈地颤抖着。他和他的同伴进了屋子，在里面待了几分钟，然后就离开了。从此，我就再也没有见过德·拉舍一家了。

“我待在窝棚里，在彻底的、麻木的绝望状态中度过了那天的剩余时间。我的保护者们已经离去了，从而断绝了我跟这个世界之间的唯一的联系。报复和憎恨的情绪第一次涌满了我胸膛，而且我并不试图抑制它，我听凭自己被这股情绪之流推动着，一心一意地要想进行伤害和杀戮。当我想到我的朋友们，想到德·拉舍那温和的声音，阿加莎那温柔的眼睛，阿拉伯女子那高雅的美丽，这些念头就消失了，喷涌的泪水使我稍获安慰。可是，当我回想起他们蔑视了我，抛弃了我，又感到愤怒，怒火又重新燃起，因为不能对任何人实施伤害，我便把怒火发泄到无生命的东西上。在夜色渐浓的时候，我在小屋周围堆上了各种易燃物，把菜园毁坏得面目全非，然后强压着耐性等待着月亮落下后开始行动。

“夜色愈浓，一阵猛烈的风从树林那边吹过来，很快驱散了飘荡在天上的云朵，疾风以排山倒海之势狂扫猛进，使我的精神产生了一种疯狂的劲头，突破了理智和思想的一切限制。我点燃了一棵树的干枝丫，围绕着那可爱的小屋狂怒地跳起舞来，我的眼睛仍然紧盯着西方的地平线，月亮差不多接触到了它的边缘。那个圆盘的一部分终于落下去了，我挥舞起手中的火把，月亮沉落了，我一声大叫，点燃了稻草，以及我收集来的石南枝和灌木条。风扇起了烈焰，小屋很快就被裹在了烈火中，火苗紧抓住它，用它那分叉的、毁灭一切的舌头舔着它。

“当我确信没有任何援助可以挽救屋子的任何部分时，便离开了火场，到树林里找栖身之地去了。

“现在，面对这个世界，我应当走向何处呢？我决定远离这个不幸的地方，可是对于被憎恨和被鄙视的我来说，任何国家都是一样的可怕。终于，我一下想到了你。我从你的那些纸片里了解到，你就是我的父亲，我的创造者，除了给予我生命的那个人以外，我向谁求援更合适呢？在费利克斯给沙菲讲授的课程中，地理并没有被省略。我从这些课程里了解了地球上不同国家的相对位置。你曾经提到过日内瓦是你的故乡；我决定到这个地方去。

“不过，我朝什么方向走呢？我明白必须往西南方走才能到达目的地，只有太阳作我的唯一向导。我不知道自己将经过的那些市镇叫什么名字，我也不能向任何人打听情况，但是我并不绝望。我只有在你那里才能得到拯救，尽管我对你并无任何感情，有的只是憎恨。无情的、残忍的创造者！你赋予我知觉和感情，然后就把我扔开，让我成为人类轻蔑和惧怕的对象。然而只有对你，我才有权利要求得到怜悯和补偿，对你，我决心要讨回公道，这是我从任何具有人形的生灵那里都无法得到的。

“我的旅程十分漫长，我所受的痛苦更是剧烈的。当我离开自己住了那么长时间的地方时，时令已是深秋。我只有在夜间赶路，唯恐见到一个人影。大自然在我周围日益凋败，太阳变得毫无热力，雨雪倾注在我身上，巨川大河也结了冰，地面变得坚硬、寒冷、荒芜，我找不到任何挡风避雨的处所。啊，大地！我多少次诅咒自己生命的起源！我天性中的温顺已经消失殆尽，心里只剩下恶意和狠毒。我越是接近你的家门，便越是深感复仇之火在心里燃烧。大雪纷飞，江河冰冻，可是我一刻也不停息。间或有一些偶然的事情给我指明前进的方向，而且我也有一张这个国家的地图，不过我还是经常大大偏离正确的道路。感情的剧痛催促我不敢稍微歇息，我在路上遇见的事，没有一件不是使我的愤怒和悲伤变得更强烈的。当我踏上瑞士的疆界，太阳又重新变暖，大地看上去又是绿油油的了，但就在这时发生了一件事，使我的感情变得特别怨愤和可怕。

“一般情况下，我是白天休息，只在夜晚人们确实看不见我的时候才赶路。可是在一天早晨，我发现我的道路将穿过一片幽深的树林，于是我就冒险在太阳升起以后继续行走。那是早春的一天，阳光的和煦，空气的清香，甚至使我也感到兴致勃勃。我觉得早已死亡了的温柔欢乐的感情又在心中复苏了。这种新奇的感觉让我有几分惊讶，我便听凭自己陶醉于这种情感，忘却了自己的孤独和丑陋，竟然高兴起来。柔情之泪沾湿了脸颊，我甚至抬起了湿润的眼睛来看神圣的太阳，感激它赐予我如此的欢乐。

“我继续沿着林间小径曲折地前行，一直到了树林的边缘，那里围绕着一条水深流急的河流，许多树木初春新发的嫩枝条弯弯地插在河水中。走到这儿我停住了，不知道该走哪条路，这时我突然听见了人的声音，就躲到一棵柏树的阴影里藏了起来。我刚藏好，就有一个姑娘朝我的藏身处跑过来，她还大声笑着，好像是在玩游戏躲着什么人。她沿着陡峭的河岸一直跑，突然脚下一滑，落进了湍急的流水中。我从藏身处冲出来，竭尽力气顶住激流救起了她，把她拖到了岸边。她失去了知觉，我用尽力所能及的办法想让她苏醒过来。就在这时，我的努力因为一个乡下人的突然逼近而中断了，他也许就是姑娘开玩笑要躲避的那个人。他一看见我就猛扑上来，从我手臂里夺走了姑娘，急忙向树林的深处跑去。我不知怎么的，很快地跟了上去，可是那个人看我走近了，就举起随身携带的一支枪朝我瞄准，开了火。我倒在地上，而伤害我的人却加快速度逃进了树林。

“这就是对我的仁慈的报偿！我从毁灭中救起了一个人，作为报答，现在我却因为皮开肉绽的枪伤而痛苦得在地上翻滚。几分钟之前我怀着仁慈而温柔的感情，现在已让位于恶魔似的狂怒和咬牙切齿地愤恨了。我被痛苦点燃了怒火，立誓要永远仇恨人类，报复人类。不过，伤口的剧痛压倒了我，我的脉搏停止了跳动，我晕过去了。

“好几个礼拜里，我在树林里过着悲惨的生活，尽力养好我受的枪伤。枪弹打进了我的肩膀，我也不知道它是留在了里面，还是穿过去了，不管怎样，我没有办法把它取出来。我强烈地感到人类的伤害是不公正的和忘恩负义的，这更增加了我的痛苦。我的报复之心日益强烈——要进行深重致命的报复，方足以补偿我所遭受的蹂躏和痛楚。

“几个月以后，我的枪伤痊愈了，于是我又继续我的旅程。我的劳累再也不会因明媚的阳光和温柔的春风而减轻了，一切欢乐只是对我的嘲弄，它对我的凄凉处境加以侮辱，使我更痛苦地感到我生来是不配享受欢乐的。

“不过我的艰难跋涉现在快到终点了。两个月后我抵达了日内瓦的近郊。

“到那里的时候是傍晚时分，我躲进郊外田野中的一个藏身处，考虑怎样向你提出要求。我受到疲惫和饥饿的逼迫，心情也极不痛快，远不能欣赏黄昏的和风，或者巍峨的尤拉山后日落的景观。

“这时我小睡了片刻，使我解脱那思虑之苦，却又被惊醒了，那是一个漂亮的小孩，他带着充满稚气的活泼劲儿朝我的藏身地跑来。在我注视着他的时候，突然有个念头攫住了我：这个小生命是没有偏见的，而且他出世不久，对丑陋也不至于恐惧。因此，如果我能抓住他，教育他作我的同伴和朋友，那么我在这个住满人类的地球上就不那么凄凉了。

“被这种冲动所激励，我在孩子走过的时候一把抓住了他，把他拖到身边来。他一见我的模样，就用手蒙住眼睛，发出了一声尖叫。我用力拉开他蒙在脸上的手，说道：‘孩子，你这是干什么？我无意伤害你，你听我说。’

“他猛烈地挣扎着。‘放开我，’他叫道，‘妖怪！丑八怪！你想吃掉我，把我撕碎——你是个吃人魔——放开我，不然我就要告诉爸爸。’

“‘孩子，你再也见不到你父亲了，你得跟我走。’

“‘丑妖怪！放开我。我爸爸是市政官——他是弗兰肯斯坦先生——他会惩罚你。你不敢不放我。’

“‘弗兰肯斯坦！那你是我的仇敌家的人了——我发誓要永远向他复仇，你正好是我的第一个牺牲品。’

“那孩子仍然在挣扎，同时用难听的名称大肆谩骂我，使我深感绝望。我掐住他的喉咙不让他再骂，瞬刻之间他就死在了我的脚下。

“我注视着我的牺牲者，心里充满了狂喜和恶魔般的扬扬得意。我拍着手，大声叫道：‘我，也能制造不幸，我的敌人也并非不可伤害的，这次死亡将给他带来绝望，还将有成千的苦难来折磨他和摧毁他。’

“当我紧盯着那个孩子时，看到有个东西在他胸前闪亮。我取下了它，那是一个极可爱的女子的肖像。不管我怎么狠毒，它仍然使我的心变得柔和并受到吸引。我欣喜地看了一会儿，凝视着她那黑黑的眼睛，眼睛周围浓密的睫毛，和那可爱的嘴唇。可是我的怒火随即又燃起了，我想起自己已被永远剥夺了如此美丽的生灵所能给予的欢乐，而且像上所画的女子假如看见了我，也会将她圣洁的温柔表情换为极度的厌恶和恐惧啊。

“这些想法竟会使我怒火万丈，难道你会觉得奇怪吗？我只是奇怪，在那个时刻我为什么没有冲到人类中去，毁灭他们，也毁掉自己，而只是以高声呼叫和痛苦挣扎来发泄我的感情。

“我被这些感情控制着，离开了杀人的现场。在寻找更隐蔽的藏身处时，我进了一个似乎是空着的谷仓。有个女子躺在草堆上睡觉，她很年轻，的确没有我手中肖像上的那个女人长得美，不过相貌也很逗人喜欢，而且青春焕发，健康可爱。我想，这里又有一个人，她那令人欢悦的微笑是给所有人的，唯独不给我。于是我俯在她的耳边悄声说：‘醒来吧，最美的姑娘，你的情人来啦——能让你深情地看上一眼，他宁愿献出生命，我亲爱的，醒来吧！’

“睡着的姑娘动了动，一阵恐惧袭遍了我的周身。如果她醒来，会不会看见我，咒骂我，斥责我是杀人凶手呢？一旦她闭着的眼睛睁开来看见我的话，肯定是会这样做的。这样一想就使我疯狂了，它唤起了我心中的魔鬼——受苦的不该是我，应该是她。我杀人是因为我被永远剥夺了她所能给予的快乐，这应由她来偿付代价。犯罪的根源在她身上，让她受到惩罚！多亏了费利克斯讲的课程和人类血淋淋的法律，我现在学会了阴谋陷害。我向她俯下身子，把那幅肖像稳稳当当地放在她衣服的一处褶皱里。她又动了动，于是我就逃走了。

“接连好几天，我都在发生这些事情的地方徘徊。有时候，我希望见到你，有时候我又下定决心永远离开这个世界和它的苦难。最后，我向这一片群山走来，在深谷巨洞里游荡，被一种燃烧的热望折磨着，而这种欲望只有你能够满足。你不答应我的要求，我们就绝不分手。我形只影单，十分可怜。人类不愿和我交往，可是，一个和我同样丑陋可憎的异性总不会拒绝我吧。我的伴侣应该是我的同类，应该有同样的缺陷。你必须创造出这个生命。”

————————————————————

(1) 指《失乐园》里的撒旦。

第十七章　最后的要求

那个有灵之物讲完了，紧盯着我，期待我的回答。而我却感到困惑和茫然，无法理清思绪来理解他的建议的全部含义。他又接着说——“你必须为我创造出一个女性，和我一起生活，彼此交流我必不可少的同情。这只有你才能做得到。我有权来要求你这样做，你不能拒绝。”

在他叙述他在小屋主人当中度过的那段平静生活的时候，我的愤怒已渐渐平息，可是他故事的后半部分又重新激起了我的怒气，当他说到这里时，我再也无法抑制在心里燃烧的怒火了。

“我就是要拒绝你，”我回答道，“无论受怎样的折磨，也不能迫使我答应你。你可以使我成为世上最不幸的人，可是你绝不能使我做自己也瞧不起自己的事情。难道我会再造出一个你这样的东西，让你们狼狈为奸搞垮这个世界吗？滚开！我已经回答了你，你可以折磨我，但是我绝不会答应。”

“你错了，”那个魔鬼回答说，“我不想威胁你，只要同你讲讲道理就满足了。我狠毒是因为我不幸。难道我不是被整个人类所回避和憎恨吗？你，我的创造者，也想把我撕得粉碎而后快啊。请你记住这一点，并且告诉我，为什么我应该可怜那些并不可怜我的人呢？假如你把我推进冰缝里，毁掉你亲手创造的这个躯体，你是不会把这个行为称作谋杀的。难道有人轻蔑我，我反倒要尊重他吗？如果他和我在相互关怀中一起生活，那我不仅不会伤害他，反而会对他的接纳感激涕零，为他做一切好事。不过这是不可能的，人类的观念是阻止我们结合的难以逾越的障碍。然而我的观念也并非甘愿忍受卑鄙的奴役。我要为自己所受的伤害复仇。如果我不能唤起爱，我就制造恐惧。首先是针对你，我的头号仇敌，因为你是我的创造者，我对你怀有不可消除的仇恨。你当心，我将慢慢地让你毁灭，不到你伤心欲绝我不会住手，我要让你诅咒你降生到这个世上来的那个时刻。”

他说到这里，魔鬼似的怒火使他兴奋若狂，他的脸皱缩歪扭得如此可怕，使人不敢看上一眼。不过他马上就镇静下来了，接着说下去：“我是打算讲道理的。这种激怒对我是不利的，因为你并没有想过，你本人正是我这种激怒的根源。只要有任何人对我怀有仁慈之情，我将千百倍地报答他，只因为这一个人的缘故，我就愿意和整个人类讲和！可是，我现在只不过是沉溺于不可能实现的美梦之中罢了。我向你提出的要求很合理，也并不过分。我要求有一个异性的伴侣，只不过要和我一样丑陋。这种满足真是微不足道，但它就是我能得到的全部东西，而且仅此就将使我满意。不错，我们将是与世隔绝的一对怪物，不过正因为这样，我们将更加相亲相爱。我们的生活不会很快活，但是于他人无害，也不会承受我现在所经受的痛苦。啊！我的创造者，给我幸福吧，让我因你做的这一件好事而感恩戴德吧！让我看到我自己能够激起某个生灵的感情共鸣吧，不要拒绝我的请求！”

我被感动了。但当我想到一旦应允可能会有怎样的结果时，却又不寒而栗，不过我觉得他的话也有几分道理。他的故事，他目前表现出来的感情，都证明他是一个具有细腻情感的生命，而我作为他的创造者，难道不应该把我所能给予的那份快乐给予他吗？他看出了我的感情变化，便接着说：“如果你同意了，无论是你还是其他人，都永远不会再见到我们了，我将到茫茫无边的南美洲荒原去。我的食物和人类的不同，我不会杀死羔羊或小山羊来满足食欲，橡实和浆果就可以给我提供足够的营养了。我的伴侣会具有与我相同的属性，同样的食物也可以满足她。我们将用干树叶来铺床，太阳将像照耀人类那样照耀着我们，并催熟我们的食物。我给你描绘的这幅图景是和平的、符合人性的，你一定会感到，如果拒绝我，那只是滥用权力和横施暴虐而已。尽管你一直对我毫无怜悯，可是现在我在你的眼里看到了同情，让我抓住这有利的瞬刻，说服你允诺赐给我如此热烈渴望的伴侣吧。”

“你提议，”我答道，“远离人类居住的地方，到只有野兽做伴的荒野去定居。可是你一直渴望人类的爱和同情，又怎么能够在这种放逐生活中坚持下去呢？你会回来的，再次寻求人类的关怀，并再遭到他们的厌恶，你那邪恶的怒火又将燃起，而且你那时将有个同伙帮助你施行破坏。这可不成，不要再争辩这个问题了，因为我不可能同意。”

“你的感情是多么的反复无常啊！在片刻之前，你还被我的请求所感动，怎么又硬起心肠对我的申诉无动于衷了呢？我以我居住的地球起誓，以创造了我自己的你起誓，我将和你赐予的伴侣一道，离开人类的周围，到任何一个最蛮荒的地方去生活。我的邪恶感情将会荡然无存，因为我将获得同情！我的生命将安安静静地流逝，而且即使在死亡的那一刻，我也不会诅咒我的创造者。”

他的话在我心上产生了一种奇怪的效果。我同情他，有时甚至感到有安慰他的愿望，可是当我看着他，当我看见那个污秽的躯体动来动去和说着话的时候，不禁感到恶心，而我的同情也就变为了恐惧和憎恶。我竭力去抑制这些感情，我想，既然自己不能同情他，也就没有权力去阻止他获得我尚有力量给予他的那一点快乐。

“你起誓，”我说，“不再为害，可是你难道不是已经显示出了某种狠毒，使我有理由不相信你吗？这难道不会是一种伪装，以便进行更大的报复，从而使更大的阴谋得逞吗？”

“这是怎么讲？我可不是好作弄的，我要求你答复我。假如我与人没有联系，没有感情，给我留下的就只有仇恨和邪恶了，另一个人的爱则可以摧毁我的罪恶的根源，同时我也可以销声匿迹，谁也不知道我的存在了。我的罪恶是一种强加给我的、连我自己也厌恶的孤独状态的产物，当我跟我的一个同类和谐生活的时候，美德就必然会从我的内心生成。我将感受到另一个敏感生命的爱，并成为连接到生存事变的锁链中的一个环节，而现在我是被排斥在外的。”

我沉默了一会儿，掂量着他所说的一切和他提出的各种论证。我想到，他在生命开始时也曾显示出富于美德的前景，后来因为他的保护者表示出了厌恶和轻蔑，这一切善良情感便受到了摧残。我在仔细考虑的时候也没有忽略他的力量和他的威胁：一个生物既然能够在雪原冰窟里生存，在高不可攀的悬崖峭壁上逃避追击，那一定具有无法对抗的能力。经过了长时间的思考，我得出了结论，无论是对于他或是我的同胞都要不失公正，我有责任答应他的要求。因此，我朝他转过身去，说道：“我同意你的要求，但你要庄严地起誓，一旦我交给你一个女性陪伴你去流放，你就要永远离开欧洲，以及其他接近人类的任何地方。”

“我凭着太阳，凭着蓝天，凭着燃烧着我的心的爱火起誓，”他高叫道，“如果你答应了我的请求，只要它们还存在，你就永远再见不到我了。回家去吧，开始你的工作，我会以无法言说的焦急心情关注着你的进展，在你完成之前，不要担心我会出现。”

他一边说着，一边就突然离开了我，或许是害怕我的想法会有什么改变。我望着他下山，真比老鹰飞翔的速度还快，即刻就消失在起伏不平的冰海里了。

他的故事讲了一整天，在他离去的时候，太阳已经落到地平线的边缘了。我知道自己必须尽快赶回下面的山谷中去，因为黑夜不久就会包围我，可是我的心情沉重，步伐很缓慢。白天发生的事所激起的情感充塞着我的心，我费力地在山间曲折小路上走着，极力一步步走稳，思绪纠缠不清。我走到半途歇脚的地方，在泉水边坐下的时候，夜色已深。星光时隐时现，因为浮云在它们前面飘过，黑黝黝的松林耸立在我面前，地上疏疏落落躺着断裂的树干，这是一幅奇妙而庄严的景象，它在我心中激起了许多奇怪的思绪。我苦涩地哭起来，我痛苦地紧握着双手，高声喊叫：“啊！星星，云彩，风啊，你们都来嘲笑我吗？要是你们真的可怜我，就把我的感觉和记忆毁掉吧，让我化为乌有吧，如果不，就走开，走开，让我留在黑暗里好了。”

这都是些狂乱而伤心的思绪，不过我没法向你形容星星那永恒的闪光怎么重压着我，我是怎样倾听着那疾风一阵阵呼号，仿佛是热带沉闷阴郁的怪风正要吹来吞没我似的。

我到天亮以后才回到萨姆尼村，我没有歇口气，马上就回了日内瓦。甚至在自己心里，我也说不清那复杂的感受——它们像大山一样沉重地压着我，过分巨大的重量压碎了我的痛苦。我就这样往家里走，进了家门，出现在家人面前。我那憔悴而狂乱的样子引起了大家的惊恐，可是我什么也不回答，几乎不说一句话。我觉得自己仿佛处于一种禁令之下——仿佛我没有权利要求大家的同情——仿佛我再不能和大家亲密相处。不过甚至在这种情况下我仍然深爱着他们，为了救他们，我决心把自己献给我最厌恨的工作。这种工作的前景摆在眼前，其他种种生活事项便都像梦幻一样地消逝了，对于我来说，只有考虑这个工作才是生活的现实。

第十八章　前往英国

我回到日内瓦以后，一天又一天，一周又一周，时间就这样过去了，可是我一直鼓不起勇气来开始我的工作。我担心失望的魔鬼会来报复，但我又不能克服对强加于我的这项工作的深恶痛绝。我发现，要制造一个女性，我非得再次耗费几个月做深入学习和刻苦研究不可。我听说一位英国科学家获得了某些发现，它们对我工作的成功极为重要，所以我有时候打算征得父亲的同意，为这一目的去英国访问。然而我又抓住每一个借口拖延行期，退缩着不肯跨出第一步，这便使得这项紧迫而必要的工作渐渐显得不那么要紧了。我自己的确也有了一些改变：我的健康本来一直在恶化，现在已经大大恢复了，当对那不愉快的诺言的记忆不再压抑我的时候，我的情绪也相应地高昂起来。父亲高兴地看到了这种变化，他集中心思要寻找最好的办法来根治我残余的忧郁情绪，这种情绪不时会一阵阵地发作，像吞食天空的乌云遮蔽住将要显露出的阳光。在这些时刻，我总是在绝对孤独中去寻找慰藉。我划着小船在湖上独自度过一整天，眺望浮云，倾听波浪的细语，默默无言，没精打采。不过，清新的空气和明媚的阳光也常常能使我在一定程度上恢复平静，当我回家的时候，面对家人的致意，我也能报以更欣然的笑容和比较愉快的心情了。

一次，在这样的漫游之后回到家里，父亲把我叫到旁边，对我这样说：“我很高兴地注意到，我亲爱的儿子，你已经重新获得了你从前的乐趣，而且看来正在恢复健康。可是你仍然郁郁不乐，而且在躲着我们。一段时间以来，我猜不透这是什么原因，但昨天我突然有了一个想法，如果这个想法确有根据，我请你坦率地承认。在这个问题上有所保留非但无用，而且会给我们大家带来三重的不幸。”

听到他这样的开场白，我浑身颤抖起来；父亲继续说下去：“我得承认，我的儿子，我一直盼望着你和我们亲爱的伊丽莎白结婚，这是我们家庭幸福的纽带，也是我风烛残年的依靠。你们在孩提时期就相依相伴，在一起学习，性格志趣彼此都完全投合。然而人的经验又是多么的盲目，我认为最有助于实现计划的做法却可能彻底破坏它。你，也许只把她看作妹妹，而并不希望她成为你的妻子。不仅如此，你也许遇见了另一个你可能爱上的女子，但你又考虑到自己对伊丽莎白负有道义上的责任，这种内心的斗争可能就使你感到了强烈的痛苦吧。”

“我亲爱的父亲，请你放心。我深情而真诚地爱着我的表妹。我从来没有遇见过任何女子，能像伊丽莎白那样激起我最强烈的爱慕和感情。我对未来的希望和憧憬，与对我们结合的期望是完全融为一体的。”

“我亲爱的维克多，在这个问题上你所表达的感情，使我感到了很长时间以来所未曾体验过的快乐。如果你是这样感受的，那么我们确实感到高兴，不管目前种种事变给我们投上怎样的阴影。不过正是这种阴影似乎已经牢牢控制了你的思想，而我希望能够驱散它。因此，请你告诉我，你是否同意马上举行婚礼。我们的生活很不幸，近来的一些事使我们失去了日常生活的宁静，而那又是年老体弱的我很需要的。你还年轻，可是我并不认为，像你这样大有前途的年轻人，早些结婚就会妨碍你实现未来追求光荣和事业的计划。不过，你不要认为我希望支配你的幸福，或者认为你推延婚期就会使我很不安。正确地理解我的话，并请你以信任和真诚之心来回答我。”

我默默地听着父亲的话，好长一段时间无法做出回答。我的心中千头万绪思潮翻滚，竭力想得出某种结论。唉！马上和伊丽莎白结婚，对我来说是一种令人恐惧和惊愕的想法。我还受着一项庄严诺言的约束，那项诺言我还没有履行，也不敢破坏，假如我破坏了它，有多少灾难将降临在我和我亲爱的家人头上啊！难道我能在脖子上戴着如此致命的、把我压得匍匐在地的枷锁，去举行婚礼的庆典吗？我必须先履行我的诺言，让怪物和他的伴侣离去，然后才能享受婚姻的快乐，从而得到我期望的和平生活。

我还想起自己必须做的事，或者到英国去一趟，或者和那个国家的科学家们长期通信，他们的知识和新发现对于我眼下的工作必不可少。通过后一种办法来获取我想要的资料，既费时，效果又不能令人满意。此外，在父亲的家里进行这桩讨厌的工作，一面还要和我所爱的家人每日亲密交往，这也使我感到不可克制的厌恶。我知道，有千百件可怕的意外事件可能发生，其中最轻微的也会使我的亲人们惊骇不已。我也明白，我常常会失去自我控制能力，无法掩饰我在进行这桩荒谬绝伦的工作期间所承受的剧烈痛苦。在进行这件事时，我必须远离自己所爱的一切人。工作一旦开始，就应该尽快完成，这样我就可以重新和家人过上和平快乐的日子了。我的诺言一旦兑现，怪物也就永远离去了。也许（我就这样想入非非），在此期间会发生什么意想不到的事情，把那怪物毁灭了，从而永远结束我受奴役的境况。

这些想法决定了我怎样回答父亲。我表示希望到英国去做一次访问，不过我隐瞒了真正的理由，以不致引起怀疑的借口掩饰了我的真实意愿，同时以诚挚的态度很容易地获得了父亲的首肯。在我这么长时期以来陷于忧郁，其深重程度几近于疯狂之后，父亲高兴地发现我竟能够对这样的旅行感兴趣，他希望环境的变化和多种多样的消遣能在我返回之前使我完全恢复健康。

离家多久由我自己决定。我考虑大概几个月，至多一年。父亲出于关怀，他还着手为我寻找一个旅伴。在事先没有告诉我的情况下，他和伊丽莎白商量妥当，安排克莱瓦尔在斯特拉斯堡和我会合。这件事干扰了我在进行自己的工作时所渴望的孤独。不过在我旅程的开始阶段，我的朋友绝不会对我有所妨碍，所以我感到由衷的高兴，因为这样可以免除我做许多小时的胡思乱想。此外，亨利可以把我和我的敌人隔离开来。假如我是单独一人，难道他那可憎的形象不会经常闯到我面前来，提醒我加紧工作，或者来观察我工作的进展吗？

就这样，我决定到英国去了，自然，一俟从英国返回就和伊丽莎白举行婚礼。我父亲因为年迈而极不乐意拖延。至于我自己，在我厌恶的辛苦工作中也有了一份可以期望的报偿——对于我无以复加的苦难也终于有所安慰了，那就是展望着那一天，摆脱了我悲惨的苦役，我将得到伊丽莎白，在我们的结合里忘却过去。

我开始为我的旅行做准备了，可是总有一种感觉纠缠着我，使我充满担忧和焦虑。当我撇下亲人离家外出的时候，他们丝毫不知道他们有个仇敌，对他的袭击也毫无防备，而我的离去又恰好可能激怒他。不过他答应过，我到哪里他就到哪里，他会不会跟着我到英国去呢？这个想法本身使我恐惧，但又让人宽慰，因为这意味着我的亲人们平安无事。可是一想到也可能发生相反的情况，便又使我极为痛苦。不过，在我沦为我的创造物的奴隶期间，我只好听任自己受当时的冲动去支配了，我眼下的感觉倒是使我坚信，那个魔鬼会跟着我，从而让我的家人免遭他的毒手。

在9月下旬的时候，我再度离开了祖国。这次出门是我自己的主意，因此伊丽莎白也赞成，可是她一想到我将离开她独自经受痛苦和忧伤的折磨，就不免感到忧虑不安。正是出于这种担心，他们才找了克莱瓦尔做我的旅伴——不过女性的周到细心所留意到的千百种细节，一个男人却往往视而不见。她盼望着我早早归来——错综复杂的千种思绪使她黯然无语，只是默默流着泪和我告别了。

我跌坐在那辆载我远行的马车里，几乎不知道自己在往哪里去，对周围发生些什么事情也无心加以理会。我只记得吩咐把我的化学仪器收拾好随身带走，而我一回想到这件事就感到剧烈的痛苦。我心里充满阴郁的想象，历经了许多美丽壮观的风光景物，然而我目光呆滞，一无所见。我唯一想的是我旅行的目的，以及旅行期间要进行的工作。

在消沉倦怠中度过了几天，赶了许多里程的路，我终于抵达了斯特拉斯堡，在那里待了两天等候克莱瓦尔。他来了。唉，我们之间构成了多么鲜明的对照啊！他对每一处新的景物都有活泼敏锐的反应，他看见夕照之美会充满喜悦，当他看到太阳升起，又开始新的一天时，则更加欢欣鼓舞。他指给我看色彩变幻的风景和天空的形态。“这就是生活的意义，”他高声说，“现在我正享受着生命！可是你，亲爱的弗兰肯斯坦，为什么郁郁不乐，愁容满面啊！”的确，我心中充满了阴郁的思想，既看不见黄昏星的沉落，也看不见反射在莱茵河上的金黄的朝阳。——你，我的朋友，你如果读到克莱瓦尔的日记将会更有兴致，他是以富于感情和欢悦的眼光来观赏自然景物的，这远胜于听我讲自己的回忆。我，一个倒霉的可怜虫，被一个诅咒纠缠住了，它关闭了我所有通往欢乐的道路。

我们一致同意乘船沿莱茵河顺流而下，从斯特拉斯堡到鹿特丹，从那里再坐船前往伦敦。在这段航程中，我们经过了许多绿柳飘拂的小岛，看到了好几个风光美丽的小镇。我们在曼海姆停留了一天，然后，在离开斯特拉斯堡后的第五天，抵达了美因茨。在美因茨以下的莱茵河更是风景如画。流水湍急，在山峦之间蜿蜒前进，那些山不很高，但很陡峭，而且形态极美。我们见到许多废弃的城堡矗立在峭壁悬崖的边缘上，被高耸入云、人迹罕至的黑黝黝的森林包围着。这一段莱茵河的确呈现出奇特而变化无穷的景象。在一处，你见到的是崎岖的山峦，城堡的废墟高耸在巨岩绝壁上，黝黑的莱茵河水在下面奔腾不息，而突然转过一处山岬，你又将看见整幅风景变为枝繁叶茂的葡萄园，翠绿的倾斜的河岸，蜿蜒曲折的流水，以及人烟稠密的市镇。

我们旅行的时间正值收获葡萄的季节，当我们顺流而下航行时，便听到采摘葡萄的工人们的歌声。即使是我，心情如此消沉，情绪老是被阴郁的思绪所折磨，也不禁感到愉悦。我躺在船舱底部，望着万里无云的碧蓝的天空，似乎沉浸于久已生疏了的宁静之中。如果说我的感觉是这样，那么谁又能描绘亨利的感觉呢？他觉得自己仿佛被带进了仙境，享受着很少能被人体验到的欢乐。“我见过我的祖国最美的风景，”他说，“我到过洛桑和尤利湖，在那里，皑皑雪山的山脚几乎垂直地矗立在水边，在水中投射下黑黝黝的、深不可测的倒影，要不是有苍翠欲滴的岛屿以明丽的风貌加以调剂，它们本会是一派阴郁哀伤的面貌。我见过湖上掀起了暴风雨，疾风将湖水激起漩涡，让人不禁想到大洋上龙卷风卷起的水柱，浪涛愤怒地冲击着山麓，那位牧师和他的情妇就是被山崩掩埋了的，据说在夜风呼啸的间歇还能听见他们垂死的哀号。我还见过拉·瓦莱和贝·德·旺的群山。可是这块国土，维克多，却比所有那些奇异景观更让我喜欢。瑞士的群山更为宏伟和奇特，但这绝妙的河流两岸却有着我从未领略过的无与伦比的魅力。看看那座耸立在绝壁上的古堡，还有那座小岛上的古堡，几乎被美丽的树荫所掩没。现在看看从葡萄园中走出来的那一群工人，还有那半隐在山坳里的小村庄。啊，真的，居住并守卫着这块地方的精灵，和我们国家里那些垒起冰川或者栖身于高不可攀的峰巅的精灵相比，一定具有与人类更为和谐的灵魂。”

克莱瓦尔！亲爱的朋友！即使是现在，我也愿欣然记下你的谈话，尽情给予你应得的赞美。他是在“大自然之诗”里饱受熏陶的人。他那奔放而热情的想象力又接受了他敏感心灵的净化。他的灵魂洋溢着热烈的情感，他的友谊是那样坚贞忠诚、异乎寻常，老于世故的人会告诉我们，这种友谊只有在想象中才能找到。不过人类的同情心还不足以满足他那热切的思想。对身外的大自然美景，别人只是赞叹而已，他却炽热地爱恋——

那喧哗的瀑布
像激情般萦绕心头：巨岩，
山峦，浓密而幽深的树林，
它们的色彩和形态，就像他的
欲念；是一种感情，一种爱，
它们不需要思想来提供
隔膜的魅力，也不依赖任何
并非来自眼睛的力量。(1)

可是如今他在哪里？难道这个温柔可爱的人就永远消逝了吗？这个头脑如此富于思想和奇幻宏伟的想象力，它本身就构成了一个世界，而它的存在又依赖于它的创造者的生命——难道这个头脑已经毁灭了吗？难道它现在只能存在于我的记忆之中了吗？不，不是这样，你那神授天造的、光彩照人的形体虽然腐朽了，但你的精神依然眷顾和安慰着你的不幸的朋友。

请原谅我这一阵哀伤的迸发，这些徒劳无益的言辞，只能表达我对亨利无与伦比的价值的些微敬意，不过它们对我因怀念他而充满痛苦的心有所安慰。我还是继续讲述我的故事吧。

我们的船顺流而下，经过了科隆，来到了荷兰平原。我们决定在剩下的路途中改乘驿车，因为吹着逆风，徐缓的水流提高不了船行的速度。

这段航程没有什么优美的风光来增添我们的兴致，不过几天之后我们就到了鹿特丹，再从那里渡海去英格兰。在12月下旬的一个晴朗的早晨，我第一次看见了英国那洁白的陡峭海岸。泰晤士河两岸呈现出一种全新的景象，沿岸土地平坦而肥沃，每一个市镇几乎都能让人回忆起某个历史故事。我们看到了蒂尔伯里要塞，想起了西班牙的无敌舰队，还看见了甚至在祖国就耳熟能详的格雷夫森德、伍尔威治和格林尼治这些地方。

终于，我们看见了伦敦那无数的尖塔，巍峨耸立在全城之上的圣保罗大教堂，以及英国历史上赫赫有名的伦敦塔。

————————————————————

(1) 引自英国诗人华兹华斯（William Wordsworth，1770—1850）的长诗《丁登寺旁》（Tintern Abbey）。

第十九章　在苏格兰北部荒村里

伦敦是我们目前休息的地方，我们决定在这个奇妙的著名城市住上几个月。克莱瓦尔渴望和富于才华的当代名流学者交往，不过这对于我来说只是次要的目的。我主要关注的是怎样获得履行我的诺言所必需的知识，尽快借助于随身带上的介绍信，求见那些最著名的自然科学家。

假如我是在求学和玩乐的时代做这次旅行的话，它本该给我带来无法言表的乐趣。可是我的生命已经饱受摧残，我去拜访那些人物的目的，只是因为他们在我的研究课题方面可以给予相关的知识，而这个课题对我来说具有可怕的利害关系。与人交往对我来说是讨厌的事，在独处的时候，我还可以用天空和大地的奇观美景来填补我的心灵，亨利的话语也抚慰着我，我还可以这样欺骗自己以求暂时的宁静。可是，见到忙碌的人群那一张张令人厌烦的欢乐笑脸，却使我的心情重新陷于绝望。我看到在我和我的同类之间有一个难以逾越的障碍，这个障碍被打上了威廉和于斯丁的鲜血的封记，回想起种种与这两个名字相联系的事变，我的心灵便不禁充满了剧痛。

不过，我在克莱瓦尔的身上看见了我往昔的影子，他喜欢探求知识，渴望获得经验和教益。他所观察到的种种不同的生活方式，正是他取得教益和乐趣的无尽的源泉。他也一直在追求他长期瞩目的一个目标。他的计划是去访问印度，他可以通过他所了解的那个社会的信仰和观念，他所懂得的印度的多种语言，大大促进欧洲的殖民和贸易事业。只有在英国，他才能进一步实施他的计划。他永远是忙忙碌碌的，唯一影响他的欢乐心情的是我的悲伤而沮丧的情绪。我力图尽可能地掩饰住自己的这种情绪，这样便不至于剥夺他的欢乐，那些欢乐对于一个正在进入新的生活场景、不受任何忧虑和苦涩回忆困扰的人来说，是天然应该享受的。我常常拒绝和他在一起，借口说已经另有约会，以便独自留下。我现在又开始收集创造新生命的必备材料了，这对于我的折磨，就像水滴不断落到头上那样绵绵不绝。一旦想到这件事，我就会极度痛楚，一旦说话隐约触及这件事，我的嘴唇就会颤抖，我的心就会悸动。

在伦敦度过几个月以后，我们收到了一位苏格兰人的来信，他以前曾经来日内瓦作过我们的客人。他提到他的祖国如何美丽，并且问我们，是否这还不足以诱使我们把旅程向北推移，直到他所居住的珀斯。克莱瓦尔热切渴望接受这一邀请。而我，虽然厌恶交际，也希望再看看高山激流，以及大自然用以装扮她的精选住所的一切奇观胜景。

我们是在10月初到达英格兰的，现在已经是2月了。于是我们决定在下月底动身北上。在这次旅程中，我们不打算沿着直通爱丁堡的大路走，而要去访问温莎、牛津、马特洛克和昆布兰湖区，这样将在7月底左右抵达旅程的终点。我收拾好了我的化学仪器以及收集到的材料，决定在苏格兰北部高原的某个偏僻角落里完成我的工作。

我们在3月27日离开伦敦，在温莎停留了几天，漫步于那里的美丽的森林。对于我们这样的山地居民来说，这里是一派崭新的景象，伟岸的橡树，供狩猎的大量猎物，一群群气派庄严的麋鹿，一切对我们都显得新奇。

从那里出发，我们又前往牛津。当我们进入这个城市的时候，脑海里便充满了对150多年前发生在这里的种种事件的回忆。就是在这里，查理一世集结起他的军队。在整个国家都背弃了他的事业，站到国会和自由的旗帜下时，唯有这个城市仍然效忠于他。回忆起这个命运坎坷的国王、他的那些侍从们、和蔼可亲的福克兰、骄横的葛林、他的王后和王子，便给这个城市的每一处都平添了一种特殊的情趣，因为据说他们曾经在这些地方居住过。往昔岁月的精灵把这里作为了它的居所，我们兴致勃勃地寻觅着它的足迹。假如这些思古幽情尚不能让想象力得到满足，那么城市本身的美丽风貌也足以令我们赞叹不已。那些学院古风盎然，风景如画，条条街道几乎都宏伟壮观，城边的爱西斯河穿过碧绿的草地，逐渐扩展成一片平静宽阔的水面，倒映着古树环抱之中的一群群庄严的塔楼、尖顶和圆拱。

我尽情享受着这片美景，然而，我的兴致却被对往昔的回忆和对未来的设想所败坏。我生性喜爱平静的欢乐。在少年时代我的心灵从未品尝过不满足。即使我偶感闷倦无聊，一看到大自然的美景，或者研读人类智慧的卓越崇高的产物，总是能唤起内心的兴趣，给我的精神注入狂喜。而现在我是一株枯残的树，雷电已经击穿了我的灵魂，我当时感到自己活着也不过在展示一副行尸走肉的凄惨形象，别人见了可怜，自己也不堪忍受——而且这副形象不久也将难以维持了。

我们在牛津度过了相当长的一段时间，在城郊漫游，极力要确认每一处可能与英国历史上最激动人心的时代有关的地点。我们小小的考古旅行常常因为不断出现新的目标而延长。我们参谒了著名的汉普顿的陵墓，还有这位爱国者阵亡的战场。有那么一刻，我的灵魂从低贱的、可怜的恐惧中升华，转而对这些景物所象征与体现的自由和自我牺牲的神圣观念沉思默想。有那么一瞬间，我敢于挣脱身上的锁链，以一种自由和高尚的精神来看待周围的一切。然而铁镣已经深深地嵌入了我的血肉，于是我战栗着，绝望着，重新堕入了可怜的自我。

我们不得不怀着遗憾离开了牛津，前往下一个歇脚处马特洛克。这个村子周围的田野与瑞士的景色比较相似，不过每件事物都要矮小一等，翠绿的山冈上方看不到更高的山峰，不像祖国有遥遥耸立的、银白色的阿尔卑斯山俯瞰着松林覆盖的群峰。我们探访了那个神奇的大洞穴，以及许多自然史的小陈列室，那里的稀世珍品摆放得与塞弗克斯和萨姆尼的收藏一模一样。当亨利说出后面这个地名时，我禁不住颤抖起来，我赶快离开了使我联想到萨姆尼那可怕情景的马特洛克。

我们从德比出发，继续北上，在昆布兰和威斯摩兰度过了两个月。我现在几乎觉得自己是在瑞士的群山之中了。在山脉的北边残留着的一块块雪地，那些湖泊，山间奔腾的激流，都是我所熟悉而颇感亲切的景象。在这里我们也结识了一些朋友，他们几乎竭尽全力来哄我快乐起来。克莱瓦尔的兴致相应比我高得多，在与才智之士做伴的时候，他的思想便开阔起来，他发现自己的天性中原来具有如此巨大的智慧与能力，那是他在和低于他的人们相处时所不曾想象到的。“我满可以在这里度过一生，”他对我说，“身在这里的群山之中，我几乎不会想念瑞士和莱茵河了。”

不过，他发现旅游者的生活在快乐之中竟也包含着许多痛苦。他的感情一直过于兴奋紧张。他刚刚开始沉静下来从容欣赏某件事物，却发现自己必须放弃它，去追求另一种引起他的注意的新鲜东西，而这种新乐趣随即又被另外的新奇事物所取代了。

我们刚刚探访过昆布兰和威斯摩兰各种各样的湖泊，对当地一些居民有了感情，这时候与苏格兰朋友约定的见面日期就逼近了，我们便离开了他们继续前行。对我来说，倒并不觉得遗憾。我已经有一段时间淡忘了自己的那个诺言，所以我担心那个魔鬼的失望会导致严重的后果。他可能还留在瑞士，可能向我的亲人们施加报复。这个念头缠绕着我，每时每刻都在折磨我，使我得不到本应享有的休息和平静。我怀着极为烦躁不安的心情等待他们的来信：一旦信来迟了，我就非常痛苦，被千百种忧虑所压倒；等到信件到了，我看见信封上伊丽莎白或者父亲的签名，竟几乎不敢拆阅，害怕厄运会得到证实。有时候，我又认为那个魔鬼在跟随着我，可能会为了催促我不再拖延而谋害我的同伴。当这些念头攫住我的时候，我片刻也不愿离开亨利，而是像影子一样地跟着他，保护他免遭想象中的杀人恶魔狂怒的报复。我觉得自己就像犯了什么大罪似的，简直无法摆脱这种犯罪意识。我其实并未犯罪，可是我的确给自己招来了一种可怕的灾祸，就像犯罪一样的致命。

我带着一双倦怠的眼睛和一颗消沉的心访问了爱丁堡，那座城市本来可以让最不幸的人也感兴趣的。克莱瓦尔并不像喜欢牛津那样喜欢它，因为牛津的古色古香使他更感愉快。不过，爱丁堡新城的美丽整齐，它那些富于浪漫情调的古堡，它那世界上最令人愉悦的郊区，亚瑟王的宝座，圣伯纳井，彭特兰山，这些又使亨利兴致勃勃，赞赏不已。可是，我却急不可耐地要想抵达旅程的终点。

一个礼拜后我们离开了爱丁堡，经过库帕、圣安德鲁斯教堂、泰伊河沿岸，最后到达了我们的朋友等候我们的珀斯。不过我没有兴致和陌生的人们笑谈，或者以一个客人应有的兴趣去分享他们的感情，参加他们的游览计划。因此我告诉克莱瓦尔自己希望在苏格兰单独旅行。“你尽情游玩吧，”我说，“让我们以后在这里会集。我可能离开一两个月，我请求你不要干预我的行动，让我过一段平静和孤独的日子。在我回来的时候，我希望自己会有更轻松的心情，更和你志趣相投。”

亨利想劝阻我，不过，他看到我坚持自己的计划，便不再劝告了。他请求我经常给他写信。“在你孤独漫游的时候，”他说，“我真愿意和你做伴，而不愿和我不认识的那些苏格兰人在一起。那么快些回来，我亲爱的朋友，这样我就可以重新感到像在家里一样，而你不在身边，我是不可能有这种感受的。”

和我的朋友分手以后，我决定到苏格兰最偏远的地方去，在与世隔绝中完成自己的工作。我不怀疑那个妖魔在跟着我，而且我一结束工作，他就会出现在我的面前，来领走他的伴侣。

按照这个决定，我穿越了北部高原，确定以奥克奈最偏僻的一个地方作为自己实施工作的地点。这是个适宜于做这种事的地方，因为这里几乎就只有一块巨岩，它那高耸的岩壁不断地被波涛拍打着。土地非常贫瘠，勉强可以喂养几头可怜的母牛，出产的燕麦也仅够五个居民糊口，他们骨瘦如柴的躯体显示出其生活的凄惨。当他们要享用蔬菜、面包这样的奢侈品，甚至需要淡水的时候，则须从大约五英里之遥的大陆上运过来。

整个小岛上只有三座极为简陋的茅屋，在我到那儿的时候，其中一座是空着的。我租下了它。它只有两个房间，都显示出最凄惨的贫穷所具有的一切污秽破烂。屋顶的稻草塌陷了，墙壁上没涂泥灰，门也脱了铰链。我让人把屋子修理了一下，买了几件家具，便住了下来。要不是村民们都已经被贫穷匮乏弄得感觉麻木了的话，我住在这儿无疑会引起某种震惊的。事实上，我完全没有受到注意和打扰，我赠送了村民们一点食物和衣服，也没有人来道谢，苦难竟能把人们最粗糙的感觉能力也弄得如此迟钝。

在这个隐居地，我上午全部用来工作，但在傍晚，在天气允许的时候，我就到多石的海滩上去散步，倾听海浪咆哮和拍击在脚下的声音。这是一派单调而又永远在变化着的景色。我想起了瑞士，它和这里荒凉而骇人的景象远远不同。它那些山冈都覆盖着葡萄树，村舍密密地散布在平原上。它那些美丽的湖水映照着蔚蓝而柔和的天空，当风打破湖面的宁静时，那浪花和这里大海的咆哮相比，只不过像活泼的儿童在戏水一样。

我刚到的时候，就这样安排我的工作和消遣，可是，随着工作的步步进展，它也一天天变得越来越可憎可厌。有时候，我接连几天也没法说服自己走进工作室，而在其他时候，我又夜以继日地拼命干以期尽快完成我的工作。我干的真是一件肮脏事。在前一次实验期间，我还被某种疯狂的热情遮住了眼睛，不知道这种工作的可怕，我的思想还完全专注于事业的成功，所以看不见整个工作过程是多么令人憎恶。而现在，每当我残忍地强使自己进入工作室的时候，不禁对手头的工作感到恶心不已。

我就在这样的处境中，干着最可憎的事情，在这样的孤独中，没有什么能让我的注意力有一瞬刻从实际工作的场景中转移开去，因此，我的精神状况失去了平衡，我变得焦躁不安，神经过敏。我每时每刻都在害怕见到我的那个迫害者。有时候，我眼睛盯着地面坐着，不敢抬头观看，唯恐会看见自己惧怕见到的那个东西。我也害怕走出当地村民的视野，唯恐他会趁我独自一人的时候来向我索要他的伴侣。

与此同时，我的工作也在继续，而且取得了相当大的进展。我怀着既疑惧又急切地希望的心理期待着它的完成，我不敢让自己去深究那个希望是什么，可是它交织着种种模糊的凶兆，使我的心异常沉重。

第二十章　决裂

一天傍晚，我正坐在工作室里。夕阳西下，月亮也刚刚从海面上升起，因为缺乏做工作的足够光线，我只好无所事事地待着，心里在考虑到底是把事儿留到夜晚来做呢，还是继续集中精力弄完它。就这样坐着的时候，我脑海中涌现出一连串的思绪，引得我去考虑目前所做的事可能产生什么后果。三年以前，我也曾像这样努力工作过，并创造出了一个魔鬼，他无比野蛮地摧残了我的心，使它永远充满了苦涩的悔恨。现在，我又要创造出另一个生命了，对她的性情我同样一无所知，她也许会比她的男伴恶毒一万倍，而且以杀人作恶本身为乐事。男魔鬼曾经立誓将远离人类，躲到荒无人烟的地方去，可是她并没有立过誓，而且她很可能是个能思想、会推理的动物，或许会拒绝服从在她诞生之前订下的契约。他们可能彼此产生憎恨，现在活着的那个家伙憎恶自己的畸形相貌，那么当他眼前出现了同样丑陋的一个异性时，难道他不会产生更强烈的憎恶吗？她也可能会厌恶他，转而爱上人类更加美好的形象，她可能离开他，而他便再次陷于孤独，便会因为受到新的刺激，即因被自己的同类所抛弃而变得万分恼怒。

即使他们会离开欧洲，到新世界的荒芜之地去定居，但那个魔鬼渴求的所谓同情的第一个后果便是生养孩子，这样魔鬼的种族将在地球上繁衍下去，从而使得人类的生存状况变得岌岌可危，充满恐惧。难道我为了一时的私利，有权给子孙万代种下这一个祸根吗？我以前被自己创造出来的那个家伙的诡辩所打动，被他那恶魔般的威胁弄得一时丧失了理智，可是现在，我第一次陡然发觉自己的许诺的邪恶性质。想到未来的人类将把我当作祸害来诅咒，因为我的私心，为了自己的安宁，竟然毫不犹豫地付出了整个人类生存的代价，我不寒而栗。

我浑身颤抖，心脏仿佛停止了跳动。就在这时候，我抬起了头，在月光中，竟看见那个魔鬼正在窗前。他凝视着我，见我正坐在那儿完成着他分派给我的任务，便裂着嘴唇露出了怪异的狞笑。对了，他一路上都在跟着我，他不是在森林里游荡，就是在洞穴里藏身，再不然就栖身于荒野的石楠丛中。现在他来查看我的进度，要求我履行我的诺言了。

在我望着他的时候，他的脸上露出了极其恶毒和狡诈的表情。我怀着发疯似的感觉想到，自己竟然会允诺给他再造一个和他一样的怪物，不禁愤怒得发抖，立即把我制作的东西撕得粉碎。怪物见我毁掉了他的幸福所依赖的未来的生命，便发出了一声恶魔般的绝望和仇恨的嚎叫，离我而去。

我走出房间，锁上了门，在心中庄严宣誓绝不继续干这项工作了，然后，我步履蹒跚地走回我的卧室。我孤零零的，身边没有一个人来排解心中的阴郁，将我从最恐怖的梦魇那令人作呕的压抑中解救出来。

几个小时过去了，我仍然在窗前凝视着大海，风已经平息了，大海几乎凝止不动，整个大自然都在宁静月亮的眼光下休憩了。只有几艘渔船点缀在海面上，微风不时飘送来渔夫们此呼彼应的话语声。我感受着这一片静谧，虽然我几乎察觉不到这种静谧无边的深沉，直到岸边的划桨声传入我耳中，有个人在我屋子的近旁上了岸。

过了几分钟，我听见屋门格格作响，似乎有人在尽量轻轻地打开它。我从头到脚都颤抖起来，我预感到是谁来了，想去叫醒离我的茅屋不远处一座村舍里的农民，可是我被无法动弹的感觉控制了，就像在噩梦中常常发生的那样，你费尽力气要想逃脱眼前的危险，可你就像在原地生了根似的。

接着我就听见了沿着过道传来的脚步声，门被打开了，我所恐惧的怪物出现了。他关上了门，走近我，用压抑住的声音说道：“你毁掉了已经开始的工作，你到底想做什么？你胆敢破坏你的许诺吗？我历经劳累和折磨；我跟你一道离开了瑞士；我沿着莱茵河的两岸潜行，走过长满柳树的小岛，翻越沿岸的山岭。我在英格兰的丛林中和苏格兰的荒野里度过了好几个月。我忍受了无法估计的疲惫、寒冷和饥饿，难道你胆敢毁灭我的希望吗？”

“滚开！我的确撕毁了我的诺言，我绝不会再创造一个像你那样的东西，跟你一样的丑陋，一样的邪恶。”

“贱奴，我以前还跟你讲道理，可是，你已经证明了自己不配我给你面子。你记住，我是有力量的，你认为自己很不幸，可是我要把你弄得更凄惨，直到你对阳光也感到憎恶为止。你是我的创造者，但我是你的主人，——听我吩咐！”

“我犹豫不决的时刻已经过去了，你施展威力的时候到来了。你的威胁不可能使我去做邪恶的事，它们只能坚定我绝不给你造一个罪恶伙伴的决心。难道我会残酷地给世界释放出一个以死亡和作恶为乐的魔鬼吗？滚开！我是坚定不移的，你的话只能更激起我的怒火。”

妖魔从我的脸上看出了我的决心，怀着无可奈何的愤怒一阵咬牙切齿。“难道每个男人都可以怀抱一个妻子，”他叫喊道，“每头野兽也都有它的配偶，而我就该孤孤单单？我也有爱悦之情，可是只能得到厌弃和轻蔑作为回报。人啊！你可以恨我，可是你得留神！你将在恐惧和悲伤中度过你的岁月，雷霆不久就会降临在你头上，并将永远夺走你的欢乐。难道我在悲惨境况中饱受凌辱之时，你竟会快乐吗？你可以摧残我的其他感情，但复仇之心绝不会消亡——复仇，从今以后将比阳光和食物更宝贵！我也许会死，但我先要让你，我的暴君和折磨者，诅咒那看着你受罪的太阳。当心，我毫无畏惧，因而无比强大。我将以毒蛇般的狡诈盯紧你，这样就可以用毒液来螫你。人啊，你将因伤害了我而懊悔的。”

“魔鬼，住嘴！别用你那些邪恶的声音来毒化空气。我已经向你宣布了我的决定，我绝不是在你的话语面前屈服的胆小鬼。去你的吧，我是不会改变的。”

“那好，我走。不过你记住，在你的新婚之夜我会来找你的。”

我向前扑去，高叫道：“恶棍！在你签发我的死亡证以前，当心你自己的狗命。”

本来我可以抓住他的，可是他躲开了我，猛然冲出了茅屋。很快就见他坐在小船里，像箭一般迅速掠过水面，不一会儿就消失在波涛间。

一切又恢复了平静，可是，他的话还在我的耳中回响着。我怒火万丈，恨不得去追赶那个破坏了我的平静的坏蛋，把他扔进大海里。我在房间里心情烦乱地急匆匆来回走动，同时，我的想象力又在脑海中描绘着千百种折磨和刺激我的情景。我为什么没有追上他，与他做一场生死搏斗啊？我竟然允许他离开，而且他是一直朝大陆方向逃去的。我一想到谁将是他那无法满足的复仇欲望的下一个牺牲者，就不寒而栗。接着我又想起了他的话——“在你的新婚之夜我会来找你的。”这么说来，那将是我命运结束的日子了。在那个时刻我将死去，同时也就满足并消除了他的怨恨。这种前景倒并不使我恐惧，然而，当我想到我亲爱的伊丽莎白——在发现自己的爱人被残酷地夺走时，她那痛苦的眼泪和无尽的哀伤——我的眼泪，许多个月以来的第一次，不禁夺眶而出。我决心在没有和我的仇敌苦斗一番之前，自己绝不能倒下。

黑夜过去了，太阳从海面上升起。我的心情变得比较平静了，如果狂暴的愤怒蜕化为深沉的绝望也可以称之为平静的话。我离开了茅屋，离开了昨夜发生激烈冲突的这可怕的地方，沿着海滩走去。我几乎已把大海视为隔绝我和我的同类的一座不可逾越的屏障了。不，这是我心里滋长起的一个愿望，唯愿其成为事实。我渴望自己能在这贫瘠的岩岛上度过余生，生活的确会是乏味的，但是不会受到任何突发不幸事件的袭击。如果我返回大陆，就会牺牲生命，或者亲眼看见我最爱的人死在我亲手创造的魔鬼手下。

我就像个烦躁不宁的鬼魂，在小岛上徘徊，和所爱的人分离，在这分离中备受痛苦。到中午时分，太阳高悬在天空，我在草地上躺下，不禁沉沉睡去。前一天夜里我通宵未曾入眠，精神焦虑，眼睛由于紧张守候和极度悲痛而发炎了。这一觉使我恢复了精神，当我醒来的时候，又感到自己仿佛回归到人类之中来了。于是我开始更冷静地考虑此前发生的事情，不过魔鬼的话语仍然像丧钟一样在我耳畔鸣响，它们仿佛是一场噩梦，可是又像现实那样清晰和难以忍受。

太阳已经西沉，我仍然坐在海岸上，用一块燕麦饼来填充辘辘饥肠，这时候，我看见有一条渔船在附近靠了岸，船上的一个人给我带来了一个邮包，邮包里有日内瓦的来信，还有克莱瓦尔给我的一封信，是请求我去和他会合的。他说，现在他在那里毫无收获地浪费着时间，而他在伦敦结识的朋友们来信要他到伦敦去，对他去印度的事做最后的商议。他不能再推迟离开当地的日子了。他到伦敦之后也许接着就要开始下一个漫长的旅程，出发的时间甚至会比现在预料的还早，所以他要我尽可能和他多聚些日子。因此，他恳求我离开孤岛到珀斯去和他碰头，然后一道南下。这封信在一定程度上把我唤回到现实生活中来了，我决定在两天后离开小岛。

可是，在离开之前我还有件事情要完成，一想起它我就不禁浑身颤抖。我必须收拾好我的化学仪器，为此我必须再走进那间我做过丑恶工作的房间，我必须处理那些我一看见就会作呕的器具。第二天早晨天一亮，我就鼓起勇气打开了工作室的门。我所毁掉的那个半完工的生命体狼藉不堪地散布在地上，我几乎觉得自己曾经胡乱肢解过一个人的鲜活的躯体。我站立了一会儿，借以镇定自己，然后走进了房间。我用颤抖的手把仪器搬到了房间外面，不过我又想起不能遗留下那东西的任何残骸，以免引起当地农民们的惊惧和怀疑。于是我又把残留物装进一个筐子里，再放进许多石块，决定暂时放在一边，等到当天夜间扔到海里去。在这段时间里，我坐在海滩上，清洗和整理我的那些化学仪器。

自从魔鬼出现的那个夜晚，我的感情发生了深刻的变化，世上再没有什么比这种变化更彻底的了。过去我总是怀着阴郁的绝望情绪来看待自己的诺言，认为不论结果如何，那都是我必须完成的一件事。而现在，我感到仿佛是蒙在眼睛上的一层荫翳被揭去了，我第一次把一切看得清清楚楚。我哪怕片刻也不会想到去重新开始那项工作了。我听到的那番威胁我的话，还沉重地压在我的心上，但我并未去想应该采取什么主动的行动去逃避。我在心里暗下决心，再造一个像我第一次制造的那样的魔鬼，将是最卑鄙、最残酷的自私行为，我从心里消除了可能导致不同结论的任何想法。

凌晨两三点钟，月亮升起来了，我把那个筐子放到一条小帆船里，驾船驶到离岸大约四英里的海上。万籁无声，有几条小船正从海上驶回岸边，我避开了它们。我觉得自己是去实施一桩可怕的罪行，战战兢兢地躲着不敢碰上别人。明净的月亮有一刻突然被一团乌云遮住了，我利用这黑暗的瞬刻，把筐子扔进了大海，我听着筐子沉下去的时候发出了汩汩的响声，随后便驾船离开了那里。天空渐渐乌云密布，不过空气很清新，尽管不断刮起的东北风带来了一阵寒意。它使我精神振奋，使我充满了惬意的感觉，所以我决定在海面上多待一阵，于是我把舵固定在直航的位置，伸展四肢躺在船底。乌云遮蔽了月亮，一切都朦朦胧胧，我只听见船身划破波涛的声响。那含混低沉的声音为我催眠，不一会儿我就沉沉入睡了。

我不知道自己在这种情况下待了多久，不过当我醒来的时候，我发现太阳已经升得相当高了。风力强劲，海浪不断地威胁着我的小船的安全。我发现刮的是东北风，它一定已经把我远远地吹离了我出发处的海岸。我极力改变航向，可是即刻就发现，如果我再试图这样做的话，小船立刻就会灌满海水。在这样的情况下，我唯一的办法是顺着风向航行。我得承认自己有点感到恐惧了。我没有带罗盘，而且对这一地区的地理情况知道得很少，所以太阳也不能给我帮多大的忙。我可能会被风刮进辽阔的大西洋，受尽饥饿的折磨，或者被周围咆哮冲击着的无边巨浪吞没。我在海上已经过了许多钟头了，此刻已感到口渴难耐，而这只不过是我其他种种苦难的开始。我抬头望天空，天上密布乌云，风刚吹开一团乌云，又吹来另一团代替它。我望着大海，它将是我的葬身之地。“魔鬼，”我高叫道，“你的任务算是完成了！”我想到了伊丽莎白，想到了父亲，想到了克莱瓦尔，他们还留在人世，魔鬼还可能用他们来满足残酷无情的嗜血欲望。这个念头把我抛进了如此绝望而恐怖的噩梦，即使是现在，在那个情景即将永远在我眼前消失的时候，我一想到它也不禁浑身发抖。

就这样过了几个钟头，在太阳向地平线坠落的时候，大风渐渐减弱为微风，海面上也不见了波浪。可是代之而起的是巨大的海潮，我感到头晕目眩，几乎不能掌稳舵，这时候我突然看见南边有一条高耸的陆地线。

我由于疲劳和几个钟头可怕的提心吊胆，几乎精疲力竭，这种突然得以确保生命的感觉真像一股暖流涌上了我的心头，我的眼泪也不禁夺眶而出。

我们的情感是多么的变幻莫测，而且，即使在极其悲惨的处境中，我们对生命执着的爱又是多么奇特！我用自己衣服的一块布做成另一片帆，急切地驾着船向那陆地驶去。它看上去像是一片荒野巨石，可是当我更接近一些的时候，我很容易就看出了耕种的迹象。我看到了岸边停泊着一些船，立即感到自己又被送回了文明人的社会。我小心地沿着弯弯曲曲的海岸行驶，终于看见一个教堂尖塔从一个矮小的海岬后面显露出来，我不禁欢呼起来。因为自己当时处于极度虚弱的状态，所以我决定直接向那座城镇驶去，那样可以很方便地获得食物。幸运的是我当时身边带有钱。船转过海峡，我看见了一个整洁的市镇和一个挺好的港口，我随即把船驶进去，因为意想不到的死里逃生而高兴得心里怦怦直跳。

就在我忙着停船和收拾风帆的时候，有几个人朝这边走来。他们似乎因为我的出现而感到惊异，可是他们并没有给我任何帮助，而是打着手势悄悄地议论着，换了别的场合，这种情况可能会多少引起我的警觉。事实上，我只是注意到了他们讲的是英语，因此我也用英语问他们。“好心的朋友，”我说，“你们可以告诉我这个市镇的名字，告诉我到了哪里吗？”

“你很快就会明白的，”一个人用嘶哑的声音答道，“也许你到了一个不怎么合你口味的地方。不过我可以保证，你该到哪里去，倒是由不得你了。”

听到一个陌生人如此粗鲁的回答，我不禁感到极为惊讶，同时我也觉察到他的同伴们那不满和愤怒的神情，更是感到不安。“你们的回答为什么这样不客气？”我答道，“如此不友好地接待朋友绝不是英国人的习惯。”

“我不懂英国人的习惯是什么，”那个人说，“不过爱尔兰人的习惯是憎恨坏蛋。”

就在这场奇怪的对话进行着的时候，我觉察到围观的人在迅速地增多。他们的脸上带着好奇与愤怒相交织的表情，这使我恼怒，也使我有些惊恐。我向他们打听去旅店的路，但没有一个人回答我。于是我就往前走，人群跟着我，围着我，并发出咕哝声。这时候有一个相貌恶狠狠的人走近我，拍着我的肩膀说：“来，先生，你得跟我去见克汶先生，谈谈你的情况。”

“谁是克汶先生？我为什么要谈我的情况？这里难道不是一个自由的国家？”

“当然，先生，对于诚实的人来说是够自由的。克汶先生是位行政官，而你要谈谈有关一位绅士死亡的情况，他昨晚在这里被谋杀了。”

这一回答使我大吃一惊，不过我立即就控制住了自己。我是清白的，这很容易得到证明。于是我便默默地跟随着我的指挥者，被带到了镇上最漂亮的一所房子里。我随时都可能因疲惫和饥饿而跌倒在地，可是自己被这一大群人围着，我想作为上策还是打起精神为好，以免别人把我体力的衰弱误认作恐惧或者自觉有罪。我那时一点也没料到几分钟后灾祸就会从天而降，一切对耻辱和死亡的忧虑都将在恐怖和绝望中消失殆尽。

讲到这儿我必须稍事休息了，因为我要根据记忆详细地讲述随后发生的事情，而回忆那些可怕的事需要我聚集起全部坚忍的意志。

第二十一章　克莱瓦尔之死

我很快就被带到了行政官的面前，那是一个慈祥的老人，态度平静而温和。可是他带着几分严厉的神情看着我，然后转身向着带我来的人，问谁将在这件事中做见证。

有五六个人走上前来；其中一个被行政官选定，他宣誓做证说，在发生谋杀的前一天夜里，他和儿子、妹夫丹尼尔·纽根特一起出海捕鱼，大约十点钟，他们发现刮起了一股强劲的北风，于是将船驶进了港湾。那是一个漆黑的夜晚，因为月亮还没有升起，他们没在港口上岸，而是按照习惯在港口下方两英里的一个小海湾那儿靠的岸。他拿着一部分捕鱼用具在前面走，他的同伴在后面不远的地方跟着他。就在他沿着沙滩往前走着的时候，脚下突然绊着了什么东西，跌倒在地上。同伴走上前来准备扶起他，借着提灯的光亮，他们发现他正扑倒在一个人的身上，那个人看来显然已经死了。他们起初猜测那是一个被淹死的人的尸体，是被海浪冲到岸上来的，可是，经过查看，他们发现死者的衣服并不是湿的，而且当时身体还没有变凉。他们立即把那个人抬到附近一个老妇人的茅屋里，并且尽力抢救，可是没能救活。死者是个相貌英俊的男子，大约二十五岁年纪。他显然是被掐死的，因为除了颈部有手指留下的乌黑印记以外，没有任何暴力的痕迹。

证词的前半部分没有引起我的半点兴趣，可是，当提到颈部的手指印的时候，我想起了弟弟被谋害的事，感到非常激动，我四肢发抖，眼前一片模糊，不得不靠在一把椅子上支撑自己。行政官敏锐的眼光注意到了我，从我的表现中无疑只能看出于我极为不利的征兆。

儿子证实了父亲的叙述，而丹尼尔·纽根特被叫上前来的时候，他发誓说在他的同伴摔倒以前，他看见在离海岸不远的地方有一条船，船上有一个人，他当时在微弱的星光下可以看清，那正是刚才靠岸的我的那一条船。

一个女人宣誓做证说，她住在那片海滩的附近，在听说发现了尸体前大约一小时，她站在自己的茅屋门前等候打鱼的人回来，这时候她见到了一条小船，船上有个男子，正在离开后来发现尸体的那段海岸。

另一个女人证实了把尸体抬到她屋子里来的那些渔夫们的叙述，尸体确实还没有变凉。大家把它放到床上，进行按摩，丹尼尔还到镇上去请药剂师，可是已经没法救活了。

关于我登岸的情况，还传讯了其他几个人，他们众口一词地说，因为那天夜里刮着强劲的北风，很可能我的船几个小时里被风吹来吹去，最后不得不回到我原来离岸的地点。此外，他们还说，看来我是从别的地方把尸体弄到这儿来的，这是很有可能的，因为我似乎并不十分熟悉这里海岸的情况，所以我会在这个港口停靠，一点也不知道镇子和我抛下尸体的地点之间相距有多远。

克汶先生听了这些证词，打算把我带到准备殡葬的尸体所停放的那个房间去，以便观察我看见尸体的时候会有怎样的反应。很可能是因为我在证人叙述谋杀案的情况时表现得过于激动，他才产生了这个念头。于是，我被行政官和其他几个人带到了旅店。在这个是非之夜竟然出现了这么多奇怪的巧合，我不能不感到极度的惊讶，不过我心里明白，在尸体被人发现的那个时候，我正在和自己居住的那个小岛上的几个人谈话，因此我对这件事的结果怎样是毫不担忧的。

我走进了停放尸体的房间，被带到了棺材前。我怎么能够描述自己见到那具遗体时的感觉呢？直到现在我还极为恐惧，我一想起那个可怕的时刻就不能不战栗和哀痛。当我看到亨利·克莱瓦尔那毫无生气的躯体直挺挺地躺在我眼前的时候，什么法律审查啊，行政官和见证人啊，都像梦幻一样在我脑海中消失了。我几乎喘不过气来，全身扑上了遗体，高声呼叫道：“亲爱的亨利，我那置人于死地的邪恶念头也夺去了你的生命吗？我已经毁灭了两个人了，更多的牺牲者还等待着他们的命运，可是你，克莱瓦尔，我的朋友，我的恩人——”

人的躯体再也无力承受我所受的剧烈痛苦，我猛烈地痉挛着被人抬出了房间。

接着我就患了一场热病。我躺了两个月，濒临死亡的边缘。后来别人告诉我，我的病中的疯狂呓语是令人骇然的，我称自己是杀害威廉、于斯丁和克莱瓦尔的凶手。有时候，我哀求我的看护帮助我去杀死那个折磨我的魔鬼；有时候，我觉得妖魔的手指已经掐住了我的脖子，于是痛苦而恐惧地尖叫起来。幸而在我用母语说话的时候，只有克汶先生能听懂，可是我的手势和痛苦的哭叫声却吓坏了其他的见证人。

我为什么不死啊？从来也没有人像我这样不幸，可是我为什么不归于遗忘和安息呢？死亡曾夺走了多少如鲜花盛开的儿童的生命，夺走了钟爱他们的父母们的唯一希望，有多少新娘和年轻的恋人们前一天还健康而充满希望，第二天便成了蛆虫的食粮和墓中的腐尸！而我是什么材料制成的，竟能抵抗住这么多突然打击，它们就像车轮转动一样周而复始地不断折磨我？

然而我命中注定要活下去。两个月以后，我发现自己仿佛从梦中苏醒，正躺在牢房里一张破烂的床上，周围是牢卒、看守，铁栓，以及监狱里应有尽有的恶劣器物。我记得，我恢复知觉的时候正是早晨，我已经记不得过去发生的事情的细节了，只是感到有一场大祸降临到了自己的头上。不过当我环顾四周，看到了装着铁条的窗户以及自己所在的污秽的房间时，所有的事都一下子闪过脑际，于是我痛苦地呻吟起来。

我的呻吟惊醒了坐在我旁边一把椅子上打瞌睡的老妇人。她是一个狱卒的老婆，被雇来看护我的。她的相貌表现出了那个阶层特有的各种低下的特征，她的面部线条生硬粗俗，正像那种惯于无动于衷地观看悲惨景象的人。她说话的语气也表明了她的漠不关心，她对我说英语，那声音让我觉得仿佛在发病的时候曾经听见过——

“现在好些了吗，先生？”她问道。

我也用英语回答她，声音非常微弱：“我想是好些了，不过要真是这样，而并不是我在做梦的话，那我非常遗憾自己还活着承受这种痛苦和恐惧。”

“说到这一点，”老妇人答道，“要是你指的是那位被你杀害的先生，我倒相信你不如死了的好，因为我想你活着会很难受的。不过这事儿和我没有关系，我是被派来看护你的，而且让你好起来了，我尽职尽责，问心无愧，要是人人都这样就好了。”

这个老妇人竟然对一个刚从死亡边缘上被救回来的人说这样无情的话，使我很反感，可是我觉得衰弱无力，无法思考发生过的一切事情。我生活中的一连串事变仿佛是一场噩梦，有时候我甚至怀疑它们到底是不是真的，因为它们对我的思想来说根本不具有真实作用。

随着在我眼前浮现的那些景象变得更为清晰，我的热病又发作起来。一片黑暗沉重地压着我，身边没有人用温柔的声音来给我抚慰，没有亲切的手来给我支持。医生来给我开了处方，老妇人给我准备了药，但前者显然漫不经心，后者的脸上则流露出强烈的残忍表情。除了可以得到一份佣金的刽子手而外，谁会对一个杀人犯的死活感兴趣呢？

这些是我开始时的想法；不过我很快就体会到克汶先生对我表现出了极大的仁慈。是他吩咐把监狱里最好的监房收拾出来给我住（尽管最好的监房也是很差的），也是他给我派来了医生和看护。的确，他本人很少来看我，因为他尽管热切地希望为每一个人减轻痛苦，但他并不愿意亲眼看着一个杀人犯受折磨，亲耳听见他那悲惨的呓语。因此，他只是有时候来看看我是否没被照管好，但他每次只待一会儿，间隔的时间也很长。

在我逐渐恢复的某一天，我坐在一把椅子上，半闭着眼睛，脸色青灰，就像死人一样。我完全被忧郁和悲伤压倒了，常常想到自己真不如死了好，何必活在这个充满了苦难的世上。我还曾经考虑过，自己并非像于斯丁那样完全清白无辜，是否干脆承认有罪，接受法律的惩处算了。就在我这样思忖着的时候，牢房的门被打开了，克汶先生走了进来，他的脸上流露出同情和怜悯的表情。他把一把椅子拉近我坐下，用法语对我说：“我想这地方对你来说很糟糕，我还能做些什么让你更舒适一点呢？”

“我感谢你，不过你提到的一切对我来说都是没用的，在这个世界上再没有什么舒适是我可以享受的了。”

“我明白，对于像你这样遭受了如此奇异的厄运的人来说，陌生人的同情是没有多大作用的。但是我希望你会很快脱离这个阴郁的住所，因为毫无疑问，我们很容易获得证据来解除对你的犯罪指控。”

“对此我并不在乎，由于一连串奇异的事变，我已经成为人间最不幸的人了。我现在受着、并且一直在这样受着迫害和折磨，死亡对于我来说难道还算什么灾难吗？”

“的确，最近发生的那些奇怪的巧合，真是最不幸、最痛苦的事了。由于某种惊人的偶然事件，你一到这个素以好客著称的海滨市镇，就被逮捕，并被指控犯了谋杀罪。你第一眼看到的是你朋友的尸体，他好像是被魔鬼以不可思议的方式杀害了，又被放置在你将经过的道路上。”

克汶先生说这番话的时候，尽管我因为回忆起自己的遭遇而感到激动，但又对他似乎非常了解我的情况感到相当惊奇。我猜想自己脸上一定流露出了惊讶的神情，因为克汶先生急忙说：“就在你病倒以后，你个人的所有文字材料都转给了我，我仔细地查阅了，希望能从中找出一些线索，以便把你的不幸遭遇和生病的情况通知你的亲人。我找到了几封信，其中一封从一开头就可以看出是你父亲写来的。我即刻向日内瓦发出了信函，从发信之日算起差不多过去两个月了。——不过你仍然病着，甚至现在你还在颤抖，你不宜再受任何性质的刺激了。”

“这样提心吊胆比听到最可怕的消息更让人难受。请告诉我，又发生了什么新的谋杀事件，现在我又要为谁的死亡而哀伤了？”

“你的家人平安无恙，”克汶先生温和地说，“有一个人，一个亲人，要来探望你。”

我不明白是怎么会有那个念头的，不过它一下子跳进了我的脑海：那个凶手要嘲弄我的不幸，利用克莱瓦尔的死来作弄我，制造新的刺激来迫使我就范。我用手捂住眼睛，痛苦地叫道：“啊！把他带走！我不能见他，看在上帝的分上，别让他进来！”

克汶先生带着困惑不安的表情看着我。他难免会从我的喊叫中推断出我是有罪的，因此他用相当严厉的口气说道：“年轻人，我本来以为你父亲的到来会受到欢迎，而不会激起如此强烈的反感的。”

“我的父亲！”我叫起来，我的痛苦化为了欢乐，我的面部表情和全身肌肉都即刻消除了紧张，“我父亲真的来了？多好啊，太好了！可是他在哪里，他为什么还不赶快来看我？”

我态度的变化使得行政官感到既惊讶又高兴，他也许认为我前面的喊叫是精神狂乱的暂时复发而已。他站起来，和看护一起走出了牢房，父亲接着就进来了。

在这个时刻，父亲的到来所给予我的欢乐，再没有别的什么能够比拟了。我向他伸出手，叫喊道：“你平安吗——还有伊丽莎白——还有欧内斯特都平安吗？”

父亲让我放心，说他们都平安无恙，并详细讲述了我最关心的种种话题，借以振作我沮丧的情绪，不过他很快就感到牢房并不是一个令人快活的居所。“你住的是怎样一个地方啊，我的儿子！”他说，一面悲伤地看着带铁条的窗户和室内的一派凄惨状况。“你的旅行目的在于寻求快乐，然而厄运似乎紧跟着你。还有可怜的克莱瓦尔——”

听到我那不幸的、被谋害的朋友的名字，真是一个太大的刺激，我衰弱的身体简直无法承受，我的眼泪夺眶而出。

“啊！是的，父亲，”我回答道，“某种最可怕的厄运笼罩在我的头上，而我不得不活着听它摆布，要不然我早该死在亨利的灵柩之上了。”

我们不可能继续谈下去，因为我那极不稳定的健康状况要求特别谨慎，必须确保情绪平静。克汶先生进来了，坚持说我不能因为过度劳累而导致体力衰竭。不过父亲的到来对我而言就像善良天使的降临，我的健康渐渐有了起色。

当我的病痊愈了，我又深深沉浸在阴暗忧郁的情绪中，任何事情也无法加以排遣。克莱瓦尔的形象，他那可怕的、被谋杀的模样，始终浮现在我的眼前。这种回忆使我极度的焦躁不安，我的朋友们不止一次地担忧我有旧病复发的危险。唉！他们为什么要保护一条可怜又可憎的生命呢？我的命运肯定已经走到了尽头，它正在逼近终点。快了，啊！很快了，死亡将遏制心脏的跳动，把我从那压垮我的痛苦的重负下解救出来，而且，在执行法律给我的判决的时候，我也同样会归于安息的。可是，尽管对死的渴望不断出现在脑海里，死亡的到来却仍是遥远渺茫的。我常常接连几个钟头一动不动、一言不发地坐着，盼望发生什么翻天覆地的巨变，把我和我的那个毁灭者一道埋葬在废墟里。

巡回法庭的开庭期快到了。我已经在监狱里被拘禁了三个月。尽管我的身体还很虚弱，并且一直处于病症复发的危险期，但我仍然要赶近百英里的路程到法庭所在的郡首府去。克汶先生竭尽全力为我收集证据和安排辩护事宜。我终于免于在大庭广众面前屈辱地作为罪犯出庭，因为本案并没有被呈交给操生死大权的法庭。鉴于有证据表明，我的朋友的尸体被发现的时刻我正在奥克奈群岛，大陪审团驳回了起诉状。就在我被移送到郡首府的两个礼拜后，我被释放出了监狱。

父亲看到我洗刷了强加于身的罪名，又可以呼吸新鲜的空气，并能回到自己的祖国，真是欣喜若狂。我却没法分享这样的感情，因为对于我来说，地牢的土墙和宫殿的墙壁都是同样的可憎。生命之杯已永远注满了毒汁，虽然太阳照耀着我，就像照耀那些心中充满幸福和欢乐的人们一样，可是我却只看见身边是一片浓密而可怕的黑暗，没有任何光线可以穿透它，只有两只目光闪烁的眼睛在黑暗中盯着我，有时候，那是在垂死痛苦中的亨利的如泣如诉的眼睛，乌黑的眼珠几乎被眼睑和周围的长长的黑睫毛遮掩了；有时候，那又是妖魔的湿漉漉的、像蒙着一层荫翳的眼睛，就像我在英戈尔施塔特的房间里第一次见到他时一样。

父亲极力要在我的心中唤起爱。他谈起我很快就要返回的日内瓦——谈起伊丽莎白和欧内斯特，可是他的这些话只能引发我更为沉痛的呻吟。有时候，我的确怀着对幸福的渴望，我也怀着略带几分忧郁的欢乐想念着我的表妹，我还怀着销蚀人心的思乡情，渴望再见到那些蔚蓝的湖泊和急湍的隆河，从少年时代起我就感到它们是那样的亲切。可是，我的心态总的说来却是麻木的，在这种麻木中，置身于一座监狱或是大自然最美妙的风景似乎毫无二致，而且这种麻木状态一直持续着，除非是阵发性的痛苦和绝望偶尔来打破它。在那样的时刻，我常常恨不得能结束我所厌弃的生命，这使得人们不得不一直留心和戒备着，防止我采取什么可怕的自残行为。

不过，我还留有一个未尽的责任，正是因为想着它我才最终战胜了自私的绝望情绪。那就是我必须毫不拖延地回日内瓦，去守护我深深热爱着的那些人的生命。我必须悄悄地等候着那个杀人凶手，要是我有机会找到他隐藏的地方，或者他胆敢再钻出来攻击我，我就可以准确无误地结果那个魔鬼的性命——在这个魔鬼怪异的形体里，我居然还赋予了冒充人类心灵的一个更为怪异的灵魂。父亲倒是希望再延迟一些日子动身，担心我受不了旅途的劳顿，因为我病得形销骨立——仿佛只是个徒具人形的影子了。我的精力消磨殆尽。我只剩下一副骨头架子，热病还昼夜不停地吞食着我羸弱的躯体。

然而我是如此急不可耐地催着要离开爱尔兰，父亲觉得最好还是答应我。我们搭上一艘驶往哈弗—德—格拉斯的船，趁着顺风从爱尔兰海岸出发了。时值午夜。我躺在甲板上，仰望着星星，倾听着海浪的拍击声。我欢呼那片黑暗将爱尔兰从我眼前遮没了，当我想到很快就要看见日内瓦的时候，强烈的欢乐使我的脉搏急剧跳动。过去的一切对我来说仿佛是一场噩梦，然而，我乘的这艘船，这一阵阵将我吹离可憎的爱尔兰的海风，这片包围着我的大海，它们都有力地证实了我并非被梦幻所欺骗，而且克莱瓦尔，我的朋友和最亲密的伙伴，也已经成了我的以及我所创造的魔鬼的牺牲品。我在记忆中回顾自己的一生：我在日内瓦和家人共度的宁静而快乐的岁月，母亲的去世，以及我离家去英戈尔施塔特。我浑身战栗地回想起，那种疯狂的热情如何促使我创造出了自己的可怕仇敌，我还记起了他第一次活起来的那个夜晚。我再也不能继续追溯我的思维线索了，万千思绪重压在我心头，我苦涩地哭了。

从我的热病痊愈以来，我就养成了一个习惯，每天夜里都要服用少量的鸦片酊，因为只有借助于这种麻醉药，我才能获得对维持生命至关重要的睡眠。这时，对种种不幸遭遇的回忆使我心情苦闷，于是我吞下了双倍于平时服用的剂量，很快就沉沉睡去了。可是，睡眠也没能使我摆脱思虑和痛苦而暂获安宁，梦中出现了千奇百怪的东西来惊吓我。快天亮的时候，我被某种梦魇攫住了，我觉得魔鬼掐住了我的脖子，我无法摆脱，我自己也听见呻吟声和叫喊声在耳边回响。父亲一直守护着我，发现我翻滚不宁，就叫醒了我。海浪拍击的声音仍在周围响着，头上是多云的天空，魔鬼并不在这里。我有了一种安全感，我感到，在眼前的时刻和那不可抗拒的、灾难性的未来之间暂时建立起了一种休战状态，它使我进入了某种平静的遗忘心态，这是人类精神借助于其构造特别容易获得的。

第二十二章　归家

海上的航程结束了。我们上了岸，接着向巴黎前进。我不久便发觉体力已经超出了负荷限度，必须休息以后才能继续我们的行程。父亲不知疲倦地关心和照顾我，可是他并不了解我痛苦的根源，找了一些谬误的方法来治疗我那无法医治的疾病。他希望我在社交场合去寻找消遣。我却厌恶看见人的面孔。啊，我并不厌恶他们！他们是我的兄弟，我的同类，我甚至会被他们当中最讨厌的人所吸引，正像我会被那些具有超凡天性和神奇才能的人所吸引一样。可是我觉得自己没有权利与他们交往。我解开了一个人类之敌的锁链，把他释放到了人间，他的快乐便是要洒尽他们的鲜血，在他们的呻吟声中取乐。假如他们知道了我的邪恶行为，明白了我就是那些罪孽的根源时，将怎样同仇敌忾地憎恨我，并把我驱逐出这个世界啊！

父亲终于对我避免参加社交的愿望让了步，又试图申说种种理由来消除我的绝望情绪。有时候，他以为我是因为被迫面对谋杀罪的指控而深感耻辱，所以极力要向我证明过分自尊是没有益处的。

“唉！父亲，”我说，“你太不了解我了。要是像我这样的可怜虫也有自尊的话，人类，人类的感情和热望，那确实是堕落了。于斯丁，可怜的不幸的于斯丁，和我是一样的清白无辜，她也受到了同样的指控，她因此而丧命了。而我就是罪魁祸首——是我杀了她。威廉，于斯丁，还有亨利——他们都是死在我手下的。”

父亲在我被监禁的时候常常听见我说这样的话，每当我这样谴责自己时，他有时似乎想得到解释，有时则似乎只把它看作谵妄病的后遗症，认为在我病中曾有这类念头出现在想象里，而在康复期还对它保留着记忆。我避免做解释，而且对我创造出来的那个可憎的东西坚持只字不提。我拿定主意，宁愿让别人以为我疯了，这种办法可以使我缄默不言。此外，我也不能让自己披露那个秘密，谁听到它也会感到惊愕，而且满怀超乎寻常的恐惧。因此，我克制着自己对别人同情的渴求，在可能会向他人暴露那个致命秘密的时候，我就保持沉默。然而像上面所讲的那些话，我有时也会控制不住脱口而出。我不能进行任何解释，不过讲几句这样的真话也可以部分地减轻我心头莫名痛苦的重负。

这一次父亲带着极为惊异的表情说道：“我亲爱的维克多，你怎么如此胡言乱语啊？亲爱的儿子，我求你再不要讲这种话了。”

“我没疯，”我奋力喊道，“看着我行动的太阳和苍天可以证明我的话是真实的。我就是杀害那些最清白无辜的牺牲者的凶手，他们是因为我的邪恶计划才死的。我宁愿一千次一滴一滴地流尽我的鲜血，只要能拯救他们的生命。我不能，我的父亲，我确实不能让整个人类都做牺牲。”

我这番话的结尾使父亲完全相信，我的思想一定是陷于狂乱了，他立刻改变了话题，努力把我的思路引到其他方向上去。他竭尽全力想把在爱尔兰经历的情景从我的记忆中抹掉，从此绝口不提它们，也不让我谈及自己所受的苦难。

随着时间的推移，我也变得比较平静了：痛苦已经深深地埋藏在心里，我也不再语无伦次地谈起自己的罪过了，意识到这一点也使我自己感到满意。我以最严酷的方式来遏制自己内心渴望向全世界惨痛呼号的声音。我的神情甚至比我从冰海回来后的任何时候还要显得平静和镇定。

在我们离开巴黎回瑞士的前几天，我接到了伊丽莎白的下面这封信——

我亲爱的朋友——收到了叔叔的巴黎来信，使我感到极大的快乐，你已没在遥不可及的远方，而且我有希望能在十来天后见到你了。我可怜的表哥，你一定经受了许多的磨难！我预料见到你的时候，你甚至会比离开日内瓦那会儿更憔悴。这个冬季的日子非常难过，因为我一直受到焦虑心情的折磨。不过我仍然盼望看到你面容安详，希望发现你的内心并没有完全失去安慰和宁静。

可是我还是担心，一年前使你那样痛苦的感情，现在依然还存在，甚至可能随时间流逝而加深了。现在如此众多的灾难还重压着你，我真不愿意打扰你，但是在叔叔离家之前我们曾谈过一次话，这使得在我们见面前做一些解释是必要的。

解释！你可能会说，伊丽莎白有什么要解释的呢？假如你真的这么说，我的问题便得到了答复，我的所有疑虑也就烟消云散了。可是你和我相距遥远，对我的解释，你可能会感到讨厌，也可能感到高兴，因为存在着这一可能性，所以我不敢再拖延地写了这封信，谈谈在你离家的日子里我常常希望向你表白，却又没有勇气开口讲的事情。

你清楚地知道，维克多，从我们的孩提时代起，我们的结合就一直是你父母的最大心愿。我们年轻的时候，他们就把这个愿望告诉了我们，并要我们把它当作理所当然的事情，期待着它的实现。我们在童年时期就是亲密的游伴，而且我相信，在长大成人之后，我们又是相互钟爱和彼此珍视的朋友。可是，兄妹之间往往怀有热烈感情而并不希望更亲密的结合，我们的情况可能也是这样吧？告诉我，亲爱的维克多，我恳求你，为了我们共同的幸福，真实地回答我——你是否爱着另一个人？

你长期出门旅行，你曾在英戈尔施塔特度过了许多年，而且我得坦率地向你承认，我的朋友，当我去年秋天见到你郁郁不乐、离群索居的时候，我就禁不住猜想你可能是在后悔我们的结合吧，同时你又感到尽管父母的意愿违背了你的心意，但你又有道义的责任来完成它。不过这只是毫无根据的推理。我要向你表白，我的朋友，我爱你，在我对未来的缥缈梦幻里，你始终是我忠贞不渝的朋友和伴侣。然而，正是因为我希望自己幸福，也同样希望你幸福，所以我要向你声明，我们的婚姻倘若不是出于你本人的自由选择，那它将使我永远痛苦。甚至现在，我也一边流泪一边想，像你这样已经被最残酷的厄运所压倒，唯有对爱情和幸福的希望才能使你复原，可是“道义”可能又会把这一切扑灭。我，对你怀着毫无私心的感情，却又可能成为你实现心愿的障碍，使你的痛苦加重十倍。啊！维克多，请你相信，你的表妹和游伴的爱是如此真诚，这种假设不能不使她感到难受。快乐起来吧，我的朋友，如果你应允我这唯一的请求，那么就完全不必顾虑，世界上没有任何力量能够扰乱我内心的宁静。

不要让这封信干扰你的心绪，假如答复我会给你带来痛苦，你用不着明天或者后天就回答，甚至回家以后也不必回答。叔叔会来信告诉我你的健康情况的，如果我们相见的时候，因为我的这一努力或其他的努力，我能在你唇上看见哪怕一丝笑意，我也就不再需要别的任何欢乐了。

伊丽莎白·拉文查

17××年5月18日，日内瓦

这封信在我的记忆里唤醒了一件早已遗忘了的事，那便是魔鬼的威吓——“在你的新婚之夜我会来找你的！”就是对我的判决，到那天晚上，魔鬼将采用所有的阴谋手段来毁灭我，把可能部分抚慰我的伤痛的一线幸福夺走。他已经决定，在那天晚上以我的死亡来圆满完成他的罪孽。好吧，但愿如此。到时候肯定将有一场生死搏斗，要是他胜利了，我就得到了安息，而他控制我的力量也就终结了。如果他被我击败，我就是个自由的人了。唉！那又是什么样的自由呢？正像一个农民，亲眼看见家人被杀戮，农舍被烧毁，土地变荒芜，自己漂泊异乡，无家可归，身无分文，孤苦伶仃，却又是自由的！我得到的将是这样的自由，只不过我还有伊丽莎白这一件珍宝，唉！悔恨和内疚所带来的恐惧感将抵消这一点幸福，并折磨我直到人生的终点。

可爱的、亲爱的伊丽莎白！我一读再读她的来信，某种温柔的感情偷偷潜入了我的心，悄悄唤起了对爱情和欢乐的幸福梦想，可是我已经吞下了罪恶之果，天使已经伸出手来夺去了我的一切希望。然而，为了她的幸福我宁愿去死。如果那个妖魔将他的威胁付诸实施的话，我的死一定是不可避免的，不过我又想，结婚会不会加速我的厄运呢。我的毁灭肯定会提前几个月到来的，但假如我因为他的威胁而推迟婚期，魔鬼也会有所怀疑，他一定会找出别的、也许更可怕的报复手段来。他曾发誓要在我的新婚之夜来找我，然而他并不认为那个威胁对他是一种约束，因此必须保证这段时间里我平安无事。而且他仿佛要让我明白他的嗜血欲望尚未满足，才在刚刚宣布了威吓之后便杀害了克莱瓦尔。因此，我毅然决定，只要我和表妹的结合能够有助于她的和我父亲的幸福，那么我的仇敌试图谋害我的任何阴谋，都不应该使我们的婚礼延迟哪怕一小时。

就在这样的情绪下，我给伊丽莎白写了回信。我信中的语气平静而充满了感情。“我担心，亲爱的姑娘，”我写道，“我们人生的欢乐留下的已经不多了，可是假如我有朝一日尚能享受到欢乐的话，那它就完全依赖于你了。驱散你那无谓的担忧吧，唯有对你，我愿献上我的生命和对幸福的追求。我只有一个秘密，伊丽莎白，一个可怕的秘密，假如告诉你，你将吓得周身冰凉，然后，你就绝不会对我的不幸感到吃惊了，而只会惊讶我居然能经受这一切活下来。在我们婚礼后的第二天，我会把这个悲惨而可怕的故事讲给你听的，因为，我可爱的表妹，这只能是我们之间知晓的秘密。不过我要请求你，在此之前你一定不要提起或暗示这件事情。我诚挚地恳求你做到这一点，而且我知道你是会这样做的。”

在伊丽莎白来信后大约一个礼拜，我们回到了日内瓦。那位可爱的姑娘热情地欢迎我，可是当她看到我消瘦的身躯和热病染红的双颊时，眼中不禁噙满了泪水。我也看出了她的变化。她更清瘦了，而且大大失去了过去使我着迷的那种天使般的活泼生气，不过，要做一个像我这样饱受摧残的不幸者的伴侣，她那种温柔的态度和充满同情的温和神情却显得更为适宜。

我在目前所享受到的宁静并没有持续多久。回忆又带来了精神的狂乱，我一想起经历过的一切，一种真正的疯狂又攫住了我。有时候我变得狂躁不安，大发雷霆；有时候我又情绪低落，郁郁寡欢。我不和任何人讲话，也不看任何人一眼，只是呆呆地坐着，因为巨大痛苦的压迫而神志茫然。

只有伊丽莎白才有力量使我从这些病态情绪中摆脱出来：我怒火燃烧的时候，她温柔的声音会来抚慰我；我陷于麻木的时候，她又用情感来激励我。她和我一起哭泣，也为我而哭泣。在我恢复理智的时候，她便规劝我，极力要我持顺从命运的态度。啊！对于不幸的人来说，顺从命运倒是合适的，可是对于有罪的人来说，根本就没有心灵的平静。沉湎于过度的悲痛有时候倒能使人得到某种感情的放纵，可是悔恨的剧烈痛楚却会毒化你的良心。

回家后不久，父亲就谈到了我和伊丽莎白马上结婚的事。我却一言不发。

“那么，你爱着别的什么人吗？”

“绝对没有。我爱伊丽莎白，并且快乐地盼望着我们的结合。那就定下日子来好了，到那一天我将把自己奉献给表妹的幸福，不论我是死是活。”

“我亲爱的维克多，不要这么说。深重的灾难已降临在我们头上，可是让我们更珍视留下的一切吧，把我们对已死者的爱转移到仍然活着的人身上来。我们的生活圈子会很小，但相互间被感情和共同不幸的纽带连接得很紧。当时光流逝缓和了你的绝望心情以后，值得你关切的新的、可珍爱的事物又会产生，替代你被如此残酷地剥夺了的一切。”

这就是父亲的教诲。可是对魔鬼威胁的记忆却回到了我的心头，魔鬼在施行血腥勾当的时候简直是无所不能，所以我几乎把他看作不可战胜的了，对这一点你不会感到奇怪的。当他说出“在你的新婚之夜我会来找你的”这句话的时候，我自然认为他用以恐吓我的厄运是难以逃避的。不过和失去伊丽莎白相比，死亡对于我来说就算不上是什么灾难了，因此，我带着满意的、甚至是兴高采烈的表情同意了父亲的意见，答应如果表妹愿意的话我们就在十天后举行婚礼。我想，这也就决定了我的命运。

上帝啊！哪怕我只有一瞬刻想到了那残忍的仇敌用心的险恶，我将宁肯把自己永远放逐异国，做一个无亲无友漂泊四方的流浪者，也不会应允这不幸的婚事了。然而，我却像被魔法迷住了一样，竟然没能看透魔鬼的真实意图，就在我以为是在准备自己的死亡的时候，我却在加速一个更亲爱的人的牺牲。

随着婚礼日期逐渐临近，不知是因为胆怯还是出于某种预感，我感到心情极为沮丧。不过我用强颜欢笑来掩饰自己的感情，这使得父亲的脸上也露出了笑意和欢乐，但它不能瞒过伊丽莎白那关注而精细的眼光。她怀着宁静的满足心情瞻望着我们的结合，但又混杂着以往的不幸所刻下的几许忧虑，她担心目前看来似乎确凿无疑、伸手可及的幸福不久就会烟消云散，除了绵绵不绝的深重悔恨以外，将留不下一点踪影。

为婚礼进行了种种准备，接待了前来祝贺的客人，一切都显得喜气扬扬。我竭尽全力隐藏起吞噬着内心的焦虑不安，佯装热切地履行父亲的所有安排，尽管这一切可能只在装点着我的悲剧。通过父亲的努力，奥地利政府归还了伊丽莎白应该继承的部分遗产。科莫湖畔的一小片房产现在属于她了。我们商量好了，婚礼之后立即动身去拉文查别墅，在别墅附近美丽的湖畔度过我们最初几天幸福的时光。

与此同时，我采取了一切措施来保护自己，以对付魔鬼的公开袭击。我身边随时携带着手枪和匕首，时刻防范着他耍出什么花招来，由于有了这些防备，我也镇静了许多。说句真话，随着那个日子的逼近，魔鬼的威吓显得更像一种幻觉，仿佛不值得我为此而影响自己的平静，因为预定举行结婚仪式的日子越来越近，我听到人们不断地谈论它，好像它是任何力量也不可阻止的事情，于是我所盼望的婚姻幸福也就愈加显得确定无疑了。

伊丽莎白显得也很快乐，我的平静态度大大有助于她的精神镇定。不过到了实现我的愿望和决定我的命运的那一天，她却陷入了忧郁，充满了不祥的预感，也许她想起了我许诺在第二天向她披露的那个可怕的秘密吧。我的父亲在这段时间里则过于欣喜，忙于准备婚事，只把侄女的忧郁当作是新娘的羞怯。

婚礼之后，在父亲家里又举行了一个盛大宴会，不过我和伊丽莎白商量好了，我们要乘船旅行，当晚住在伊维安，第二天又继续航行。那天天气晴朗，风向很好，万物都在为我们的蜜月旅行展颜欢笑。

这是我享受人生幸福感情的最后时刻了。我们的船飞速航行，阳光灼热，但是有船篷为我们遮阴，我们欣赏着美丽的景色，有时在湖的一侧，我们看见了萨勒维峰，蒙塔勒格那秀丽的两岸，远处是俯瞰一切的美丽的勃朗峰，以及徒然地和它一争高低的绵绵雪山；有时沿着湖的对岸航行，我们又看见巨大的尤拉山以它黑黝黝的峭壁阻止了人们离弃祖国的企图，同时又成为妄图奴役这个国家的侵略者所不可逾越的障碍。

我握住伊丽莎白的手说：“你显得很忧伤，我亲爱的。啊！要是你知道我受过怎样的折磨，还可能再经受什么苦难，你就会尽量让我品味一下至少今天还能享受到的宁静和自由了。”

“快乐起来吧，维克多，”伊丽莎白回答道，“我希望没有任何东西会带给你苦恼。请你放心，如果说在我的脸上看不到欢悦的话，我的心却是满足的。有一种声音在我耳边轻声说，不要太相信眼前展示的美好前景，不过我是不会理会这种不祥之言的。你看我们航行得多快呀，云朵一会儿掩蔽了勃朗峰的圆顶，一会儿又升腾上去，使得这一派美景更显得饶有趣味了。再看看那些在清澈的水中游泳的数也数不清的鱼儿吧，我们还能看清水底的每一颗卵石呢。多么神奇的日子！整个大自然显得多么欢乐和宁静啊！”

伊丽莎白就这样努力使她和我的思绪从令人忧郁的题目上转移开去。不过她的情绪一直是波动起伏的，欢乐在她的眼光里闪烁片刻以后，又总是被恍惚不定的神情所取代。

夕阳已低低沉落，我们经过了德朗斯河，看到它怎样蜿蜒穿越高山间的峡谷和小山间的沟壑。在这里阿尔卑斯山紧贴着湖水，我们已经接近了围绕它的东麓的半圆形群山。在环山的树林和重重叠叠的山岭中，伊维安教堂的尖顶在熠熠闪光。

沿途以惊人的速度吹送我们前进的那阵风，到日落时分减弱为一派和风，在我们接近湖岸的时候，它轻柔得只能吹皱湖水，拂动树丛微微地摇摆，并从岸边吹过来花朵和干草的惬意的馨香。到我们登岸时，夕阳坠落下了地平线。我一踏上湖岸，便立即感到忧虑和恐惧回到了心里，不久就会抓住我，永远缠住我。

第二十三章　最后的灾难

在八点钟的时候我们上了岸。我们先在湖畔散了一会儿步，欣赏转瞬即逝的夕照，然后回到了旅店，静观湖水、树林和山峦构成的可爱景色，它们虽然在黑暗中显得朦胧不清，但依然展示出黑黝黝的轮廓。

南边的风已经减弱了，现在它又从西边猛烈地吹了过来。月亮已升到了天顶，正在开始向下沉落，朵朵云团比兀鹰飞翔还要迅疾地掠过它的表面，使它的光辉变得黯淡了，湖面则倒映着天空纷乱的景象，刚刚开始涌起的不平静的波浪使这派纷乱景象愈加纷乱。突然之间，暴雨从天而降。

在白天我一直保持着镇静，可是当黑夜使一切化为漆黑一片的时候，千百种忧虑便涌上了心头。我变得十分焦虑和警惕，右手紧握着藏在怀中的一支手枪，每一个声响都让我感到惊慌，不过我下定决心绝不能毫无代价地丧失生命，绝不畏惧拼死搏斗，直至我自己的生命或者仇敌的生命毁灭为止。

伊丽莎白已经注意到了我的焦躁不安，但她畏怯而恐惧地保持着沉默，不过在我的眼神里有什么使她感到了恐慌，于是她颤抖着问我：“你为什么这么焦虑呢，我亲爱的维克多？你害怕什么啊？”

“啊！别担心，我亲爱的，”我回答道，“今天夜里一切都会平安无事，不过这个夜晚倒真是让人害怕，让人胆战心惊。”

我在这种精神状态下度过了一个钟头，猛然想到时刻可能发生的那场搏斗对我的妻子将是何等的恐怖，于是我恳求她回房间去休息，决定等到我对敌手的情况有了一定了解以后再到她那儿去。

她离开了，然后我就在房子的各个通道里来回走了一阵子，查看了每一个可供敌手隐藏的角落。不过我没有发现他的任何踪迹，于是开始猜测或许因为什么幸运的偶然机缘，阻止了他来实施他的恐吓。就在这时候，我突然听见一声尖利的可怕叫喊。它是从伊丽莎白进去休息的那间屋子里传出来的。我一听见这声叫喊，顿时明白了真相，我的双臂垂下了，每条肌肉每根纤维都无力动弹了，我能感觉到血液在血管里缓慢地流动，刺痛着我四肢的末梢。这种状态只不过持续了一瞬刻，又传来一声尖叫，于是我冲进了那个房间。

上帝啊！我为什么不在那一刻死去呢！为什么我还在这儿讲述自己最美好的希望和世界上最纯洁的生命的毁灭呢？伊丽莎白就在那儿，毫无生气地一动不动，她躺在床上，头垂了下来，头发半掩着她那苍白而扭曲的脸。直到现在，我无论朝哪儿看，都只看见同一个景象——伊丽莎白那毫无血色的手臂和衰颓无力的躯体，被凶手扔在她新婚的灵床上。难道我目睹这一切还能再活下去吗？唉！在最厌弃生命的时候，生命却顽固地紧紧缠着不放手。就在一瞬刻间，我失去了记忆力，我毫无知觉地倒在了地上。

当我苏醒的时候，我发现旅店的人围绕着我，他们的神情都表现出极度的恐惧，可是局外人的恐惧和压迫着我内心的感情相比真是轻若鸿毛。我逃离了他们，回到了伊丽莎白躺着的房间。我的爱，我的妻子，刚才还那么富于生气，那么可爱，那么珍贵。她已经被人挪动了，改变了我最初见到的姿势，现在她头枕着一只手臂躺在那儿，一张手帕覆盖着她的脸和脖子，我几乎认为她是睡着了。我向她冲过去，热烈地拥抱她，然而她死一般无力的躯体和冰凉的四肢告诉我，我怀中拥抱着的已不再是我深深钟爱的伊丽莎白了。魔鬼那致死的手指印还留在她的脖子上，她的唇间已没有了呼吸。

当我怀着绝望的痛苦站在她身前的时候，我偶然地抬起头来望了一眼。房间的百叶窗原先是掩蔽好了的，现在我却看见淡黄的月光照亮了房间，不禁感到一阵惊慌。百叶窗已经被打开了，而且，我带着难以形容的恐惧感看见，在打开的窗户前站着那个最可怕和最可憎的怪物。怪物的脸上露出了狞笑，他用那恶魔的手指指着我妻子的尸体，仿佛是在嘲笑我。我冲向窗前，并从怀中抽出了手枪，开了一枪，可是他闪开了，从他站的地方跳开去，以闪电般的速度跑向湖边，一跃身扎进了水里。

枪声引得一大群人来到我的房间里。我向他们指出了怪物逃匿的方向，随后我们就乘了几条小船去跟踪追击，我们还撒了网，但一无所获。过了几个钟头，我们失望地返回了，大多数人认为这事是出自我的幻觉。登岸以后，他们还继续在乡间搜索了一阵，在树林和葡萄园里分头查找。

我本来试图和他们一道去，而且从旅店出来走了一小段路，可是我感到天旋地转，步伐踉跄犹如一个醉汉，最后精疲力竭地倒下了。我的眼前一片模糊，周身发着高热，皮肤滚烫。我就这样被人们抬了回去，放到床上，自己几乎不知道发生了什么事。我的眼睛漫无目标地在房间里四面张望，就好像在寻找什么遗失了的东西。

稍微歇了一会儿我就爬起来，仿佛凭着本能似的，我缓慢地走到了我心爱的人躺着的那个房间。有些女人正围着她哭泣——我站到遗体前，和她们一起抛洒着悲伤的眼泪。在这整段时间里，我的脑子里没有任何明晰的观念，思想只在各种各样的事件上绕来绕去，纷乱无序地思考着我的不幸以及原因所在。我在一团惊愕和恐惧的迷雾中茫然若失。威廉的死，于斯丁的被处决，克莱瓦尔的被谋杀，最后是我妻子遭到杀害，甚至在这一刻，我还不知道其余的亲人们是否躲过了魔鬼的毒手，我的父亲现在也许正在他的魔掌下挣扎着，欧内斯特也许已经死在了他的脚下。这个念头使我不寒而栗，提醒我必须采取行动。我一跃而起，决定尽快地赶回日内瓦。

这时弄不到马车，我不得不乘船从湖上走，可是遇到了逆风，而且暴雨如注。不过天还刚刚破晓，我还有希望在晚上赶到家里。我雇了一个人来划船，自己也操起了一把桨，我过去常常体会到身体的活动可以减轻精神上的痛苦。可是我现在满怀悲痛，心中过分焦虑，使不出半点力气。我扔下了船桨，用双手抱着头，只好向涌上心头的阴郁感情屈服了。只要我抬起头来，便看见我在欢乐的时刻所熟悉的那些景物，只不过在昨天，我还和她在一起观赏着这一切，而如今她已只是一个影子、一段回忆了。泪水不禁从我的眼中涌流而出。雨刚才已经停了，我看见鱼儿就像几个小时以前那样在水里嬉戏着，那时候伊丽莎白也在观看着它们啊！对人类心灵来说，再也没有比如此巨大而突然的变故更令人伤痛的了。阳光还会灿烂，云彩还会低飞，然而一切在我眼里再也不会像昨天那样了。魔鬼已经从我这里夺走了一切对于未来幸福的希望。从没有任何人像我这样的不幸，在人类的历史上也再没有像这样可怕的事件了。

我还有什么必要再细细讲述在这次最重大的事件之后的种种情况了呢？我的故事一直充满了恐怖，而现在它已经到达了顶点，后面不得不讲的事只能让你感到乏味了。要知道，我的亲友们一个接一个地被夺走了，我的处境已是无限凄凉。我的力量已经衰竭，因此我只得简略地讲述这骇人听闻的故事的剩余部分。

我到了日内瓦。父亲和欧内斯特还活着，不过父亲听到我带来的消息就完全垮了。我现在还仿佛看见他在我眼前，一个不寻常的、可敬的老人！他的眼光茫然失神，因为已经丧失了过去使之陶醉和欢欣的力量——他的伊丽莎白，那胜似女儿的姑娘，他曾以男人最大的慈祥钟爱着她，而在他垂暮之年所余感情不多的时候，又特别执着于这些仅剩的情感。那该诅咒的魔鬼，竟给白发老人带来不幸，让他不得不凄惨地耗竭生命！他在身边屡屡发生恐怖惨案的情况下再也活不下去了，生命的源泉突然干涸了，他再也起不了床，几天后便在我怀中去世。

我后来怎样了呢？我不知道。我丧失了知觉，只感到镣铐和黑暗在压迫着我。有时候，我也确实梦见过和我青年时代的伙伴们在繁花盛开的草地上或风光宜人的山谷里漫游，但醒来的时候，却发现自己在一间牢房中。此后我又陷入了忧郁，不过我还是渐渐地对自己的不幸处境有了清晰的概念，人们这才从牢房中把我释放出来。因为大家都说我疯了，据我所知，有好几个月我是被囚禁在一间单人牢房里。

要不是我恢复了理智，同时也恢复了报仇的决心，自由对我而言本会是一份毫无意义的赠礼。由于对过去不幸遭遇的回忆沉重地压着我，我便开始思考它们的根源——我亲手创造的那个魔鬼，我释放到世间来毁灭我自己的那个卑鄙的恶魔。我一想到他就充满了疯狂的愤怒，我渴望并热切地祈求能把他牢牢抓在手中，砸碎他那该诅咒的脑袋来雪我深仇大恨。

我的仇恨并没有长期局限于空洞无用的愿望，我开始思考抓住他的最好的办法。为了这一目的，我在获释后大约一个月，便去拜访了城里一位刑事法官，告诉他说我要提出一项指控，我知道杀害我一家的凶手是谁，我请求他运用他的全部职权拘捕那个杀人犯。

法官专注而和蔼地听我说完了这番话。“请放心，先生，”他说，“我将不遗余力地搜捕那个歹徒。”

“我谢谢你，”我回答道，“那么，请你听取我下面提出的证词。这确实是一个非常离奇的故事，要不是因为有某种尽管不可思议却又确凿无疑的真实性的话，你或许是不会相信的。这个故事紧密连贯，不至于被当作梦魇，而且我并没有任何动机需要撒谎。”在我向他讲这番话的时候，态度十分感人，但又非常镇静，我在心里已经狠下决心，一定要追踪那个凶手并置之死地。怀着这个目标，我的痛苦也就有所减轻了，并且暂时又有了活下去的意愿。于是我用简洁的但又是坚定和准确的语言讲述了我的故事，精确地标明各种事件的日期，而且绝不偏移到咒骂和感叹的方向上去。

法官开始时似乎完全不相信我的话，不过当我继续往下讲的时候，他便表现出越来越强烈的关注和兴趣了。我看到他一会儿恐惧得发起抖来，一会儿脸上又流露出强烈的惊讶表情，其中没有掺杂着丝毫的怀疑。

我在结束叙述的时候说道：“我要指控的就是他，我吁请你行使你的全部权力将他拘捕和严惩。这是你作为行政官的责任，而且我相信并希望你出于人的情感，在这一案件中不会拒绝履行你的职责。”

这番话在我的听讲者的面容上激起了显著的变化。他在听我的叙述时，原本带着听鬼怪故事和奇闻逸事时的那种半信半疑的态度，现在，当我要求他据以采取官方行动的时候，他心中的怀疑倾向又抬头了。不过他还是很温和地回答我说：“我非常愿意为你的追捕提供一切帮助，可是你所说的那个家伙似乎有本领来对抗我的任何努力。谁能够追踪一个可以横穿冰海、居住在任何人也不敢侵入的岩穴山洞里的怪物呢？此外，在他实施罪行之后已经过去了几个月，谁也猜不到他跑到哪里去了，现在又居住在什么地方。”

“我毫不怀疑，他就在我的住所附近出没，即使他真的逃进了阿尔卑斯山，我们也可以像捕捉羚羊一样把他抓到，并像杀死野兽一样把他消灭。不过我领会到了你的想法，你并不相信我的叙述，也不打算抓捕我的仇敌，给他以应得的惩罚。”

我说这番话的时候，怒火就在我的眼中燃烧，法官被吓着了。“你弄错了，”他说，“我会尽力的，要是我有力量抓住那个魔鬼的话，请你放心，他一定会受到与他的罪行相当的惩罚。不过我担心，根据你所形容的那个怪物的特性来看，这种想法是不切合实际的，因此，我们要采取一切适当的措施，但你也要做好思想准备去面对失望。”

“绝不会如此，可是我不管怎么说也是徒费口舌而已。我的复仇对于你来说是无足轻重的，不过，尽管我承认复仇是件坏事，但我要坦言，它已经成了吞噬我的灵魂的唯一强烈情感。当我想到自己释放到人类社会里来的那个杀人恶魔还活着，我心中的愤怒简直是无法形容的。你拒绝了我的正当要求，我现在只有一个办法了。我将为他的毁灭而付出我自己，不管是死是活。”

我一边这样说，一边激动得浑身颤抖。我不怀疑，在我的神情中有几分狂乱，还有几分据说是古代殉道者所特有的那种狂傲的凶悍。不过对于一个日内瓦的行政官来说，他的头脑里装的东西远非这种献身精神和英雄气概，我的崇高思想在他看来太像某种疯狂的表现了。他像保姆哄孩子那样极力安慰我，把我的故事当作谵妄狂想的产物。

“嗨，”我喊道，“你自诩聪明却多么无知啊！住嘴吧，你自己也不知道在说些什么。”

我气愤而烦躁地冲出了那所房子，回去细细思考怎么采取其他的行动。

第二十四章　追踪仇敌

在我目前的处境中，一切主观意志所能控制的思想都被吞没了、消失了。我被狂怒驱赶着，只有复仇的意愿给了我力量和自我控制力，它规范着我的情感，在我本该陷于狂乱或死亡的时候，是复仇的欲望使我得以深谋远虑和保持冷静。

我的第一个决定是永远离开日内瓦。当我幸福而且为人所爱的时候，祖国对于我来说是可亲的，而现在我苦难深重，祖国也变得可憎了。我带上了一笔钱，再加上原来属于母亲的一些珠宝，离开了祖国。

我的流浪生活由此开始了，只有我的生命结束时它才会终止。我穿越了世界上广袤的地区，忍受了旅行者们在沙漠和野蛮国度里惯常遭遇到的一切艰险困苦。我几乎不知道自己是怎么活下来的，有多少次，我四肢无力地长躺在沙地上，但求一死。然而复仇的欲望使我活着，我不敢就此死去，而让我的仇敌继续活着。

离开日内瓦的时候，我做的第一件事便是想找到一些线索，借以追寻我那恶魔般的敌人的踪迹。不过我并无明确的计划，只是在城郊绕了许多钟头的圈子，弄不清到底该走哪条路。当夜晚来临时，我发现自己正站在威廉、伊丽莎白和父亲安息的那片公墓的入口处。我走了进去，来到了标志着他们的坟墓的墓碑前。一切都归于寂静，只有树叶被风吹动而沙沙作响，夜色近乎漆黑，这一派景象即使对于一个漠然的旁观者来说，也是肃穆庄严而令人感动的。亡者的精灵仿佛在周遭徘徊，并在哀悼者的头上投下了一道可以感觉到而看不见的阴影。

这种情景最初在我心里激起的深切哀痛很快就让位于愤慨和绝望了。他们死去了，而我却活着，杀害他们的凶手也活着，为了消灭他，我不得不苟延我毫无意趣的生命。我在草地上跪下，吻着脚下的泥土，哆嗦着嘴唇高声说：“凭着我膝下的神圣大地，凭着在我身边游荡的幽灵，凭着我心中深切而无尽的哀痛，我发誓，而且凭着你，啊，黑夜，以及统治着你的精灵，我发誓要追寻那个酿成这一场灾难的魔鬼，直至他或者我在殊死搏斗中灭亡为止。为了这个目的，我将保存自己的生命，只是为了这代价高昂的复仇，我才愿意再见到太阳，再踏上大地的绿草，否则我唯愿它们从我眼前永远消失。我呼唤你们，亡者的精灵，我也呼唤你们，漫游的复仇之神，望你们助我一臂之力，指引我去行动。让那个该诅咒的地狱里的妖魔受尽痛苦，让他也感受到现在折磨着我的绝望吧。”

开始起誓的时候，我怀着庄严肃穆而凛然敬畏的感情，自己几乎相信那些被害亲友的幽灵一定听到了并赞许我的祈愿，然而在我结束的时候，狂怒又攫住了我，愤慨噎得我说不出话来了。

在黑夜的寂静中，忽然有一声响亮的恐怖笑声来回答我的誓言。它久久地、深沉地在我耳边震响，群山反射着它的回声，我觉得仿佛周围就是地狱，到处是嘲弄和嬉笑。要不是我已经发出了誓言并且决心要复仇的话，在那一瞬刻我完全可能陷于疯狂，毁灭了自己这可悲的生命。笑声渐渐消失，这时有一个很熟悉的可憎的声音，似乎贴近我的耳际清晰可辨地悄声说道：“我很满意，倒霉的可怜虫！你决定要活下去，我很满意。”

我猛扑向这声音发出的地方，可是魔鬼闪开了。突然间一轮满月升了起来，清晰地照亮了他那可怕的畸形身躯，这时他正以惊人的速度飞逃而去。

我跟踪追寻他，有好几个月我就做着这件事。根据一点渺茫的线索，我沿着曲折的隆河搜寻，可是一无所获。蔚蓝的地中海出现在我的眼前，凭着一个偶然的机会，我看见他在夜里爬上了一艘驶往黑海的船，藏在船上。我也登上了这艘船，可是他又逃走了，我不知道他是怎么逃掉的。

在鞑靼和俄罗斯的荒野中，尽管他仍然躲避着我，我却一直紧跟着他的行踪。有时候，被这个可怕的鬼怪吓到的农民们把他的路线告诉我，他担心我找不到他的踪迹会绝望而死，所以故意留下一些印记来指引我。我的头上大雪纷飞，在银白色的原野上，我看到他那硕大的脚印。对你这样初涉人世、不知忧虑痛苦为何物的人来说，怎么能理解我感受过并仍在感受着的这一切呢？寒冷、匮乏和疲惫只是我命定要经受的种种痛楚中最轻微的。我受到魔鬼的诅咒，背着永恒的地狱，然而仍有善良的精灵在跟随着我，为我指引着方向。当我怨天尤人时，他会突然将我从似乎不可克服的困苦中解救出来。有时，当饥饿弄得我精力枯竭时，荒漠中会准备好了一餐饭食，振作起我的力量和精神。那食物的确是很粗糙的，就和当地农民们吃的东西一样，但我绝不怀疑那是我所祈求的精灵放在那儿的。而且常常有这样的情况，当大地干旱，天上不见一丝云，我渴得口舌冒火的时候，会有一片乌云遮住天空，洒下几滴雨水令我复苏，随后又消失得无影无踪了。

我总是尽可能地沿着河道走，而魔鬼却老是避开河道，因为这些地方是人口密集的区域，在其他地方则很少看见人的踪影。我一般是靠捕捉偶然碰见的野兽维持生命。我也带着钱，把钱分给村民们可以获得他们的帮助。我也带着我捕杀的猎物，自己吃一小部分，把其余的送给那些提供烹煮炉灶和用具的人家。

像这样艰难度日确实让我感到厌恶，只有在睡梦中我才能体味到欢乐。啊，幸福的睡梦！在最痛苦的时候，我常常躺下来睡觉，我的梦境给我抚慰，甚至让我欢悦。守护着我的精灵们给了我这些快乐的瞬间，或者一段快乐的时光，使我能够保持力量来完成自己的漫长旅程。没有这些短暂的休歇，我可能早已被艰难困苦压倒了。白天，我以对夜晚的渴盼来支撑自己，激励自己，因为在睡梦中我会见到我的亲友，我的妻子和我可爱的祖国，我能见到父亲那慈爱的面容，听到伊丽莎白那银铃般的声音，看到青春焕发的克莱瓦尔。在我被艰难跋涉弄得精疲力竭的时候，我总是极力要让自己相信当时是在梦中，而到了夜晚，在我亲爱的人的怀抱里才是在享受现实的欢乐。我对他们怀着怎样的痛苦的爱恋啊！甚至在白天他们也总在我身边，我是怎样眷恋着他们可爱的形象，并要自己相信他们仍然活着！在这样的时刻，我心中燃烧的复仇之火便消失了，而我之所以继续前进去消灭那个魔鬼，也更是把它当作上天赋予的使命，更是出于某种我不了解的机械性的冲动，而并非是自己心灵的热切欲望了。

我所追踪的那个魔鬼的心情怎样，我不可能了解。有时候，他确实在树皮上写些字或在石头上刻些字，给我指路，同时也激起我的怒火。“我的统治尚未结束”（在一处刻痕中可以看清这句话）；“你活着，我便拥有充分的权力。跟着我，我要去北方千年不化的冰国，你将在那里经受严寒冰霜的折磨，而我却毫不在意。假如你跟我不算太慢，那你将在附近找到一只死野兔，吃了它恢复体力。来吧，我的仇敌，我们还要进行一场生死搏斗呢，不过在那个时刻到来以前，你必须忍受许多悲惨的时日。”

你这幸灾乐祸的魔鬼！我再次发誓要复仇，我要让你受尽折磨而死，卑鄙的妖魔。我绝不会放弃我的追踪，直到他或我灭亡为止。到那时，我将何等欣喜地和伊丽莎白以及死去的亲友们相聚啊，即便是现在，他们已经在准备着报偿我这漫长的苦役和可怕的旅程了！

当我继续向北方前进时，冰雪更深更厚，天气愈加寒冷，几乎到了无法忍受的程度。农民们都龟缩在小屋里，只有最能吃苦耐劳的少数人才敢于冒险出门，去捕捉被饥饿逼迫跑出藏身地来觅食的动物。河面结满了冰，根本捉不到鱼，这样我就失去了维持生命的主要食物。

随着我的旅程越来越困苦，我的仇敌也愈加得意扬扬。他留下的话中有一句是这样的：“准备好！你的苦活儿才刚刚开始。裹紧皮衣，带好粮食。因为在我们即将踏上的旅途里你将受尽苦难，使我永不消泯的仇恨获得满足。”

这些嘲弄的话语激发了我的勇气和毅力，我下定决心一定要达到目的，我祈求上天保佑我，继续怀着毫不衰退的热情穿越无垠的沙漠，直到大海出现在远方尽头的地平线上。啊！这片海洋和南方蔚蓝的海洋是多么不同！它的表面被冰封住，只能根据那无比的荒凉和崎岖不平的表层来判断它并非陆地。当年的希腊人在亚洲的山峦上望见地中海时曾喜极而泣，欣喜若狂地欢呼艰难历程的终结。我却没有哭泣，我只是跪下来，激动万分地感激引路的精灵把我平安地带到了这里，不管我的仇敌怎么嘲笑我，现在我终于可以和他面对面地决一死战了。

此前的几个礼拜，我弄到了一辆雪橇和几只狗，因此我便用难以想象的速度穿越那一片雪原。我不知道魔鬼是否也获得了这个便利条件，不过，如果说过去我跟踪他每天都要落到后面的话，现在我发现自己能赶上他了。这样看来，在我刚看见大海的时候，他不过快我一天的路程，现在我有希望在他到达海滩之前截住他。因此我怀着新增的勇气继续追赶，两天后来到了海滨的一个破烂的小村子。我向居民们询问有关那个魔鬼的情况，得到了确切的信息。他们说，前一天夜里有个身躯庞大的怪物来过，还带着一支长枪和好几支手枪，那副可怕的模样把一个孤立的茅舍里的住户吓得逃跑了。他搬走了他们储存的过冬的食物，放在一辆雪橇里，为了拉雪橇还牵走了一群受过训练的狗，把它们套上，当晚，吓坏了的村民高兴地发现他又继续赶路了，穿过冰海向不通往任何陆地的方向走去。他们猜想，他一定会很快送命的，不死于冰层的断裂，也会被永恒不变的严寒冻死。

听到了这个消息，我不免一时感到绝望。他逃脱了我的追踪，而我必须开始一次毁灭性的、几乎没有尽头的旅程，不得不跨过海上的冰山——那种严寒即使是当地居民也很少有人能够长期忍受的，而像我这样在温暖而晴朗的气候里生长的人简直没有希望幸存。然而，我一想到那个魔鬼还活着并且扬扬得意，愤怒和复仇的情绪便又高涨起来，就像汹涌巨浪压倒了任何其他感情。在我稍事休息的时候，死者的精灵仿佛在我周围徘徊着，激励我不畏艰苦去复仇，休息之后我就为继续赶路做好准备。

我用自己的陆地雪橇换了一辆为崎岖不平的冰海特制的雪橇，并购置了充裕的粮食，接着就驶离了陆地。

我估算不出从那时候起又经过了多少日子，只记得自己经受了无穷的苦难，只有我心中永远燃烧着的正义的复仇之火才支撑着我承受住了这一切。巨大而崎岖难行的冰山常常阻拦了我的道路，我还时常听见海啸的轰鸣似乎在威胁着要毁灭我的生命。不过严寒又再度降临了，海上的通路又变得安全了。

从我消耗了的食物数量来判断，我猜想自己已经在这段路程上走了三个礼拜了。我心里再次想到希望总是不能实现，沮丧和悲痛之泪便常常从眼中滚滚跌落。的确，绝望几乎控制了我，在这种痛苦中我一定会很快倒下的。有一次，那些可怜的狗经过难以置信的艰苦努力把我拉到了冰山斜坡的顶上，一只狗疲惫地倒下死去了。我极度痛苦地眺望着前面的广袤冰海，就在这时我突然看到在昏暗的冰原上有一个黑点。我聚集目光去看清那是什么东西，终于辨认出一辆雪橇和雪橇上坐着的那个熟悉的畸形躯体，不禁狂喜地大叫。啊！希望在心头是怎样熊熊燃烧起来了啊！热泪充盈了我的双眼，我急忙擦掉泪水，以免影响了我紧盯着魔鬼的视线，可是滚热的泪水仍然模糊了我的视野，到最后我只得屈服于压在心头的感情，放声大哭起来。

不过这可不是容许延误的时候，我从狗群里解下了死狗，让它们饱餐了一顿。我休息了一个钟头，这是绝对必要的，可我对此仍然极不乐意，随后我就继续上路了。那辆雪橇还看得见，我也绝不让它在眼前消失，除非有时某座冰山突出的岩石暂时挡住了我的视线。我确实感觉到自己在与它接近，又过了两天的行程，我看到仇敌距我只不过有一英里远了，我的心便怦怦跳起来。

可是，就在我几乎要抓住我的敌人的时候，希望却突然破灭了，有关他的一切踪迹都消失了，比过去任何时候都要消失得更彻底。我听见了一阵海啸，深海潜流正在行进，仿佛浪涛就在我脚下翻滚汹涌，它的轰鸣声时时刻刻发出不祥的预兆和恐吓。我奋力前行，但徒劳无益。风吹得愈加猛烈，海在高声咆哮，冰海就像受到地震的强烈撼动一样迸裂开来，发出惊天动地的巨响。一切很快就完结了，几分钟以后，一片汹涌翻滚的大海横亘在我和我的仇敌之间，我留在一块碎冰上漂浮着，冰块在不断地缩小，为我准备下了一条可怕的死亡之路。

我就这样度过了惊心动魄的几个钟头，几只狗死去了，我自己也差不多要在越来越沉重的哀痛打击下死亡，就在这时，我看见了你们这艘抛锚的船，它给了我获救和生存的希望。我根本想不到会有船只航行到这么遥远的北极来，看到它使我极为震惊。我急忙拆掉雪橇的一部分做成了船桨，借助这种办法，我用尽疲惫之力划着自己的冰筏向你们的船靠近。我做出了决定，假如你们要向南航行的话，我就宁可把自己交给大海处置，也绝不放弃自己的目标。我只希望能说动你们给我一只小船，让我驾着它去追赶我的敌人。不过你们的航行方向是朝北的。你们救我上船时，我已经精疲力竭，本来会很快在重重苦难的折磨下死去的，而我仍然不愿死——因为我的任务还没有完成。

啊！我的守护精灵什么时候才会把我带领到魔鬼的面前，并让我得到我如此渴望的内心安宁呢？难道我非得死去而他仍然活着吗？假如我真要死去，你要向我起誓，沃尔顿，不能让魔鬼逃掉，你一定要找到他，以他的死来满足我的复仇欲望。难道我真的敢于要求你接替我的任务，去经受我经历过的那些苦难吗？不，我还不至于如此自私。不过，在我死了之后，假如他竟敢出现，假如复仇之神把他引到了你的面前，你要发誓不让他活下去——绝不能让他在我无尽的苦难面前趾高气扬，并活着变本加厉地施行他那黑暗的罪恶。他能言善辩，很会蛊惑人心，他的话也曾打动过我的心，可是你不要相信他。他的灵魂和他的形象是一样的丑恶凶狠，满肚子的阴谋诡计和狠毒伎俩。不要听信他的话，你要呼喊着威廉、于斯丁、克莱瓦尔、伊丽莎白、我父亲和悲惨的维克多的名字，用你的利剑刺穿他的心脏。我的精灵将在你身边徘徊，指引你的剑锋正中目标。

续前信　致萨维尔夫人

你已经读完了这个奇异而可怕的故事，玛格丽特，你是否像我甚至现在还害怕得浑身冰凉一样，感到自己恐惧得连血液也凝固了？有时候，他被突发的痛楚攫住了，无法继续讲他的故事；有时候，他又以嘶哑然而尖锐的声音艰难地说着那些充满痛苦的话语。他那双明澈可爱的眼睛一时因愤慨而闪闪发亮，一时又堕入颓丧苦恼，在无尽的哀痛中黯然失色。有时候他会控制住表情语调，以平静的声音叙述最可怕的事件，不显示任何激动的征兆，接下来他又像火山喷发，面容突然改变为狂怒的表情，并对他的迫害者发出尖声咒骂。

他的故事情节连贯，他叙述的时候就像在讲朴素的事实，不过我得承认，不管他讲得多么诚恳而有条理，他给我看的费利克斯和沙菲之间的通信，以及我们从船上看到的那个怪物的身影，比他自己所声称的更令我确信那是事实。这样看来，真的有这么一个怪物了！我无法怀疑这一点，不过我还是惊讶和感叹得难以自持。有时候我极力想从弗兰肯斯坦那儿打听有关创造生命的细节，可是在这一点上他的态度是绝不动摇的。

“难道你疯了不成，我的朋友？”他说，“你无知的好奇心把你引到哪里去了？你也要为你自己和整个世界造出一个恶魔般的敌人吗？冷静下来，冷静下来！从我的苦难中吸取教训吧，不要给自己增添不幸。”

弗兰肯斯坦发现我记录下了他的故事，他要求看看我的笔记，然后在不少地方亲自做了修改和补充，不过主要是使自己和仇敌之间的谈话更加生动传神。“既然你保存了我叙述的故事，”他说，“我不愿流传于后代的是个残缺不全的东西。”

一个礼拜就这样过去了，在此期间我听到了人类想象力所能产生出的最奇异的故事。我的思想，我心灵中的每一种感情，都完全被我的客人吸引住了，这是因为他的故事和他本人高贵优雅的风度而导致的。我唯愿自己能安慰他，可是，对于这样一个无限痛苦、毫无可资慰藉的希望的人来说，难道我的劝说能使他活下去吗？啊，不可能！他现在所知道的唯一欢乐是，使自己那被摧垮的精神恢复平静，走向宁静和死亡。不过他还能享受到一种安慰，那是他在孤独和狂想中的产物，他相信在梦中能够和亲人们会聚，从中得到慰藉以抚慰他的痛苦和复仇的激情，他认为梦中的亲人们并非幻想的产物，而是他们亲自从一个遥远而缥缈的世界来探望他来了。这种信念使他的狂想带上了一种庄严的色彩，令我也感到像真有其事一样的确凿和有趣。

我们的交谈并不总是局限于他的故事和不幸遭遇。在一般学识的每一个问题上，他都表现出渊博的知识和敏捷而深刻的领悟力。他的口才既有极强的说服力，又有很深的感染力。当他讲到某个凄惨的事件，或者想要激起怜悯和爱心的时候，我总是禁不住边听边掉眼泪。在濒临毁灭之际他尚且如此高贵脱俗，那么他在风华正茂的时候又应该是怎样一个富于丰采的人物啊！他似乎也感觉到了自己的价值和自己毁灭的不同凡响。

“在我年轻的时候，”他说，“我相信自己命中注定要从事某种伟大的事业。我有丰富的情感，然而我又具有足以使自己取得杰出成就的那种冷静的判断力。正是这种对自己天性富于价值的意识在支撑着我，要是其他人早就被压垮了。因为我认为，如果把有益于我的同类的这些才能虚掷在无用的忧伤上面，那是一种犯罪。当我想到自己完成的那个创造物，绝不逊色于一个有知觉有理性的生物的时候，我就不能将自己归属在平庸的研究者之列。不过，这种想法虽然在我事业开始的时候曾经支持过我，现在却只能使我惭愧得无地自容了。我的一切思考和希望都分文不值。我就像那个渴求万能的大天使，被囚禁在永恒的地狱里。我的想象力非常活跃，而我的分析力和实际操作能力也极强。由于我综合了这些品质，便产生了创造人的念头并付诸实施。甚至现在，我回忆起工作尚未完成时自己所怀抱的幻想，还不能不充满激情。我的思想仿佛进入了天堂，时而因我的才能欣喜若狂，时而因我的异常效力热情高涨。我从童年时期就充满了崇高的希望和远大的抱负，可是如今我是多么的沮丧啊！啊！我的朋友，假如你认识过去的我，你会认不出现在萎靡蜕化了的我来。过去我的心情很少颓丧失望，似乎有一种崇高的命运在推动着我，直到我倒下为止，并且永远、永远也站不起来了。”

难道我一定得失去这个可崇敬的人吗？我一直渴望得到一个朋友，我一直在寻找一个可以同情和爱我的人。看，在这片荒凉的大海上，我终于发现了这样一个人，然而我担心自己得到了他，却只是为了在了解他的价值之后又失去他。我劝告他应该活下去，但他拒绝接受这种看法。

“谢谢你，沃尔顿，”他说，“谢谢你对如此不幸的可怜人给予的好意，可是你谈到人间新的纽带和新的感情的时候，你想过没有，它们难道能代替失去的东西吗？对于我来说，有哪个男子比得上克莱瓦尔，有哪个女子比得上伊丽莎白？就算我们的感情不是被超凡的卓越品德所激励，那童年时代的相依相伴也对我们的心灵发挥着作用，而后来结交的朋友是不可能如此的。他们了解我们幼年的癖性，这些癖性不管后来受到怎样的影响，却是永远不可磨灭的，他们对于我们整个的动机有确切的了解，也更能准确判断我们的行为。姐妹和兄弟绝不会怀疑彼此在作伪欺诈，除非在早期就确实表现出这一类征兆，而别的朋友，无论彼此间是多么亲近，也有可能不由自主地心生猜疑。而我有过不仅就习惯和关系而言，而且从其自身美德而言都堪称珍贵的朋友，无论我在哪里，伊丽莎白抚慰的话语和克莱瓦尔的言谈都始终萦绕在我耳边。他们都死了，现在只有唯一的一种感情能在孤寂中支持我去延续自己的生命：假如我从事的是某种崇高的事业或计划，能给人类带来巨大的效用，那么我还能活下去并完成它。可是我的命运并不是这样，我不得不去追寻和毁灭自己创造出的那个生物，然后我在世间的使命才算完成，我才可以辞别人世。”

17××年8月26日

我亲爱的姐姐——我现在是在危险包围之中给你写信，而且我不知道自己是否能再见到亲爱的英格兰和在祖国的亲爱的朋友们。我们被重重冰山围困着，它们让我们无法逃匿，而且每分每秒都可能把我们的船压得粉碎。经我说服而成为我的伙伴的那些勇敢的船员们，都盼望着我能帮助他们，可是我一筹莫展。我们的处境足以令人魂飞魄散，然而勇气和希望仍然没有抛弃我。不过，一想到因为我而使这许多人的生命遭遇危险，的确是很可怕的。假如我们罹难了，那么我的疯狂计划便是这一切的根源。

玛格丽特，你又将是怎样的心情呢？你不会听到我们毁灭的消息，你会焦急地等待着我的归来。一年又一年过去了，很多时候你会感到绝望，然而又受到希望的折磨。啊！我亲爱的姐姐，你热切的盼望将变为伤心失望，我想到这一点，就感到比我自己的死亡还更加可怕。不过你有丈夫和可爱的孩子，你会幸福的，上帝保佑你并将赐给你幸福！

我那不幸的客人以最亲切的同情来对待我。他极力要让我心中充满希望，他谈起话来就仿佛对生命是非常珍惜似的。他提醒我说，其他试图在这一海域探险的航海家也曾遇到过类似的情况，他使我心中不由自主地充满吉祥的预兆。甚至水手们也感受到了他那雄辩的威力，只要他一讲话，大家就不再绝望了，他激发起了他们的力量，而且当他们听见他的声音时，便觉得那些巨大的冰山都只不过是些鼹鼠丘，在人的决心面前全都会化为乌有的。不过这些感觉只是短暂的，希望的实现每一天延误都使他们更加害怕，我几乎开始担忧这种绝望情绪可能会导致水手们的哗变。

9月2日

刚才发生了不同寻常的一幕，尽管这些记录很可能永远到不了你的手中，但我仍然禁不住要把它记下来。

我们仍被重重冰山包围着，仍处在随时可能被冰山的冲撞压碎的极度危险中。严寒让人不堪忍受，我的许多不幸的伙伴已经在这一派荒凉的境地里找到了他们的归宿。弗兰肯斯坦的健康日益恶化，他的眼中虽然还闪耀着狂热的火光，但他的元气已经枯竭了，即使有时突然振作一下，随后也仍旧陷入死气沉沉的状态。

我在上一封信中曾提到我担忧会发生水手哗变。就在今天早晨，当我坐在那儿望着我的朋友那苍白的面容时——他半闭着眼睛，四肢无力地下垂——五六个水手惊扰了我，他们要求进入我的船舱。他们进来后，由带头的人向我讲话。他告诉我，他和同伴们是被其他水手们推选出来的，代表大家来见我，向我提出一个就公正原则而言我不可拒绝的要求。我们现在被冰层困住了，也许根本无法逃脱，不过他们担心的是，冰海也可能会融化，船又可以自由通航，那么我会鲁莽地继续我的航程，使他们在本可以幸运地摆脱危险的情况下再陷入新的危险。因此，他们坚持要我许下庄严的诺言，船一旦可以航行，就必须立即掉头向南。

这一番话使我深感苦恼。我并没有绝望，我也从没有产生过解冻以后返航的念头。然而就公正性而言，甚至就可能性而言，我能够拒绝这个要求吗？我在做出答复之前踌躇不定，这时，起初一直保持沉默，而且似乎根本无力留意我们谈话的弗兰肯斯坦却惊醒了，他的眼睛闪烁着火花，双颊因一时激起的活力而泛着红晕。他转向水手们说：“你们这是什么意思？你们要求队长做什么？难道你们就这样轻易放弃自己的计划吗？难道你们没把这称为光荣的探险吗？它的光荣何在呢？并不在于这里的航道如南方的海洋那样顺畅平静，而在于它充满了危险和恐惧；在于每一个新的意外事件都要求你们坚韧不拔，显示自己的勇气；在于处处关系生死存亡，需要你们勇往直前，克服困难。正因为如此才叫作光荣，正因为如此才叫作荣誉的事业。你们日后将作为人类的恩人而接受欢呼，你们的名字将会像拼死争取荣誉和人类利益的勇敢者那样备受崇敬。而现在呢，看看吧，才刚刚想象到有危险，或者你们愿意这样说的话，才刚刚遭遇到对你们勇气的巨大而可怕的考验，你们就畏缩了，甘愿被后人视为无力承受寒冷和危险的人，要是这样的话，可怜的人们，就打着寒战缩回到温暖的火炉边去吧。何必当初要做这种准备呢？你们真不必跑这么远，拖着你们的队长来蒙受失败的耻辱，仅仅是为了证明你们自己是些胆小鬼。啊！不要胆怯，还要更加勇敢，要坚韧不拔地追求你们的目标，要像磐石般的坚定。冰山和你们的心并不是用同一种材料做成的，冰山是会移动的，只要你们说它不能阻挡你们，它就阻挡不了你们。不要在额头上带着耻辱的烙印回去见你们的家人，要像奋战和胜利了的英雄，像面对敌人绝不逃避的勇士那样载誉凯旋。”

在他说这番话的时候，语调随着言辞所表达的不同感情而抑扬顿挫，眼光里洋溢着崇高的思想和英雄精神，因而使得那些人深受感动，难道你会觉得这奇怪吗？他们面面相觑，无言以对。我说话了，我让他们回去想一想刚才听见的这番话，假如他们仍然坚持相反的意见，我将不会带他们再往北航行，但我希望他们经过考虑之后会恢复勇气。

他们退下了，我转身去看我的朋友，可是他已经精疲力竭，几乎耗尽了生命力。

我不知道这一切将怎样终结，但我宁可死去也不愿可耻地返航——我的目的还没有达到。不过我担心自己的命运已注定如此了，那些水手并无荣誉或自尊观念来支持自己，绝对做不到心甘情愿地继续忍受目前的苦难。

9月5日

情势已无可改变了，我业已同意，假如我们不死就返航。就这样，我的希望被怯懦和犹疑断送了，我一无所获、饱受挫折地回去了。要忍耐命运的如此不公，我真必须具有更多的乐天知命的哲人精神才行。

9月7日

一切都过去了，我正返航回英格兰。我想有益于人类和赢得光荣的希望破灭了，我也失去了我的朋友。可是我将尽力把那些惨痛情景详细地告诉你，我亲爱的姐姐，而且我正在漂向英格兰和你，我不应该感到沮丧。

9月9日，冰块开始移动了，当冰岛向四面八方分崩离析的时候，远远地就能听见雷鸣般的轰隆声。我们处于迫在眉睫的危险境况中。不过，既然我们对此完全无能为力，我的主要注意力便集中在我那不幸的朋友身上，当时他的病情已经恶化到躺在床上不能动弹的地步。冰层在我们背后断裂了，并被猛力推向北方。西边刮起了一股微风，到了11日，往南的航道完全畅通了。当水手们看见这种情况，感到他们返回祖国显然已确保无虞的时候，不禁高声地、长时间地发出了欣喜若狂的欢呼。正在昏睡的弗兰肯斯坦被惊醒了，询问这阵喧哗的原因。“他们在欢呼，”我说，“因为他们很快就将返回英格兰了。”

“那么你真的要返航啦？”

“唉！是啊，我无法对抗他们的要求。我不能强求他们跟我去冒险，我不得不返航。”

“如果你愿意，就回去好了，可是我不回去。你可以放弃你的目标，可是我的目标是上天分派给我的，我不敢放弃。我很衰弱，但助我复仇的精灵们肯定会给我足够的力量。”他一边这样说，一边竭力想从床上爬起来，可是力不从心，又倒回床上昏了过去。

过了很长时间他才苏醒过来，其间我常常以为他的生命已经完结了。他终于睁开了眼睛，艰难地呼吸着，说不出话来。医生给他服了镇静剂，吩咐我们不要惊扰他。他同时也告诉我说，我的朋友肯定活不了几个钟头了。

他必死无疑了，我只能满怀悲痛地耐心等待着他生命的终结。我坐在他的床头守候着。他紧闭着眼睛，我想他是睡着了。可是他很快又用微弱的声音叫我，要我靠近他，然后说：“唉！我赖以生存的力量已经耗尽了，我觉得自己快死了，而他，我的仇敌和迫害者，或许还活着。沃尔顿，你别以为我在生命的最后时刻还像过去那样，燃烧着仇恨之火，怀着强烈的复仇欲望，可是我仍然认为有理由要我的敌人死。在这最后的时日里，我一直在反省过去的所作所为，我并没有发现有什么可责备的。我在一种疯狂的热情中创造了一个有理性的生物，我当然有义务尽自己的力量保证他快乐和幸福。这是我的责任，可是我还有一个更为重大的责任。我更应该关注我对自己的同类所应负的义务，因为这涉及更多的人的幸福或痛苦。在这种看法的推动下，我才拒绝为第一个创造物造一个伴侣，我的拒绝是正确的。他行为邪恶，表现出了无与伦比的狠毒与自私，他杀害了我的亲人，他专门毁灭具有优美感情、享有幸福和智慧卓越的人，我简直不知道他的复仇欲望到哪里才是尽头。他自己是不幸的，但他必须死去才不会再酿成其他人的不幸。消灭他的任务应该由我来完成，可是我失败了。我曾出于自私和错误的动机要求你担当起我未完成的工作，现在我仅仅是出于理智和善的目的再次向你提出请求。

“不过，我不能要求你为完成这个任务而抛弃你的祖国和亲友。既然你现在就要回英格兰去，也就很少有机会遇见他了。至于你如何考虑这些问题，如何权衡你自己的责任，我留待你自己去决定好了。我的判断力和思考力已被正在逼近的死亡扰乱了。我不敢要求你去做我自以为正确的事，因为我仍可能被狂热误引上了歧途。

“令我心里不安的是，他还会活着继续作恶。要不是考虑到这一点，此刻，当我随时都在期望解脱的时候，应该是我好几年来唯一享受到幸福的时刻。亲爱的死者的形影正在我眼前游动，我要赶快投入他们的怀抱。永别了，沃尔顿，要追求宁静中的幸福，而不要野心勃勃，即使看来是出于纯洁的动机，只不过是想在科学发现上出人头地。可是我为什么要这样说呢？我本人的这些愿望应当受到指责，但换一个人也许就会成功。”

他越说声音越微弱，终于，他的力气枯竭了，陷入了沉默。大约半个钟头后，他又再次想说话，但已经办不到了。他无力地握了握我的手，永远地闭上了眼睛，一丝柔和微笑的光辉从他的唇边消逝了。

玛格丽特，对于这个光辉的心灵过早的泯灭，我能说什么呢？我又能说什么才能使你了解我的悲痛是何等深重呢？无论我说什么，都将是不贴切的、软弱无力的。我的泪水在涌流，我的心灵被失望的乌云所笼罩。不过，我正在返回英格兰，我或许能在那里找到安慰。

我的沉思突然被打断了。这些声响预示着什么？现在正是午夜，微风在轻轻吹拂，甲板上的守卫也没有任何动静。又响了一声，似乎是人的说话声，只不过更嘶哑，是从停放弗兰肯斯坦遗体的那间船舱里传出来的。我必须起身去查看。晚安，我的姐姐。

上帝啊！刚刚发生了怎样的情景！我一想起那一幕还不免头晕目眩。我不知道自己还有没有能力做详细的记叙，可是不写下这最后的、不可思议的悲惨结局，我记叙的故事就会是不完整的。

我走进了停放我那命运坎坷、令人崇敬的朋友弗兰肯斯坦的舱房。在他的遗体旁边立着一个我无法以语言来形容的形体：躯体庞大，但又模样粗野、身材畸形。他伫立在棺材前，脸面被蓬乱的长发遮住了，一只大手伸了出去，手的颜色和表面肌肤就像木乃伊一样。当他听见了我的脚步声，便停止了哀伤和恐惧的喊叫，向窗子那边跳了过去。我从来没有见过如此可怕的脸，竟如此的可憎和丑陋。我不由自主地闭上了眼睛，努力提醒自己面对这个杀人凶手应该尽到什么责任。我叫他站住。

他停住了，很诧异地望着我，接着，又转身朝他的创造者那毫无生气的身体走去。他似乎忘记了有我在场，整个表情和姿态好像都被无法抑制的狂怒所控制。

“这也是死在我手下的一个牺牲者！”他喊叫着，“杀了他，我的罪行就算圆满完成了。我生命的一连串不幸也就算结束了！啊，弗兰肯斯坦！胸怀宽广和自我献身的人啊！现在我求你宽恕又有什么用呢？我，毁灭了你所爱的一切，从而也无可挽回地毁灭了你。唉！他浑身冰凉，无法回答我了。”

他的声音哽咽了，我最初的冲动提醒我要遵照朋友的临终嘱托，杀死他的仇敌，现在却因为混杂在一起的好奇心和同情心而暂时缓和下来了。我向这个庞然大物逼近，但我不敢抬起眼来看一看，因为他那丑陋的形象是如此吓人和怪异。我企图讲话，可是话到嘴边就消失得无影无踪。怪物继续倾诉着狂野而语无伦次的自我谴责。在他暴风雨般的狂热稍微停息的时候，我终于下定决心对他讲话。“你的悔悟现在无济于事了，”我说，“假如在你恶魔般的报复心还没有发展到极度以前，你能倾听良心的声音，感受到内疚的刺痛，弗兰肯斯坦也许现在还活着。”

“你在做梦吗？”魔鬼说，“你以为我对痛苦和悔恨毫无所感吗——他，”他指着尸体继续说，“他在生命终结的时候并没有受苦——啊！就算他痛苦，但和我苦苦挨过的漫长痛楚相比还不到万分之一。一种可怕的自私心驱策着我，但我的心同时又在受到悔恨的吞噬。难道你认为克莱瓦尔的呻吟在我听来竟会是美妙的音乐？我的心生来就对爱和同情很敏感，而苦难却把它扭曲为邪恶和仇恨，在这种剧烈变化的过程中它受尽了折磨，那是你不可能想象到的。

“在杀死了克莱瓦尔以后，我悲痛欲绝地返回了瑞士。我可怜弗兰肯斯坦，我的怜悯渐渐发展成为憎恶，我憎恶我自己。可是，我发现他，我生命的创造者，同时又是我无法形容的痛苦的制造者，竟想获得幸福。他一面在不断给我制造不幸和绝望，自己却企图享受我永远被禁止获取的种种美好感情。这时候，无可奈何的嫉妒和狠毒的愤怒便充溢了我的心，唤起了我难以满足的复仇欲望。我想起了对他的恐吓，决心将它付诸实行。我明白，这也是在给自己准备致命的折磨。可是我已成了这种冲动的奴隶而不是主人，我尽管厌恶它，却又无力反抗它。然而，当她死的时候！——不，我当时并不感到痛苦。我已经割舍了一切感情，抑制了一切痛苦，在极度绝望当中肆意放纵了。在我眼里，恶从此以后变成了善。我被驱赶着走了这么远，我已经别无选择，只有使自己的本性去适应那种并非我自愿选择的原则了。完成我那恶魔似的计划，这已成为我无法餍足的欲望。现在终于结束了，这就是我手下最后一个牺牲者！”

我一开始被他对自己苦难的描述所打动，不过，我想起了弗兰肯斯坦说过他富于雄辩和说服的力量，而且我的目光又再次投向我的朋友那丧失生命的躯体，禁不住心里燃起了怒火。“卑鄙的家伙！”我说道，“你跑到这儿来对着你制造的惨状哭哭啼啼，倒是挺不错啊。你在一片房屋里放上一把火，等它们烧光了，就坐在废墟上对火灾表示悲痛。伪善的魔鬼！假如你所哀悼的人还活着的话，仍然会成为你该死的复仇欲的目标，受到你的摧残。你的感情并不是怜悯，你伤心的只是你残杀的牺牲者已经不由你控制了。”

“啊，并不是这样——不是这样，”他打断了我的话，“不过你从表面来看我的行为动机，也难免会有这样的印象。可是我并不寻求人对我的苦难的同情。我永远也找不到这种同情。当我刚开初寻求它时，是因为我的内心充满着对美德的爱、对幸福的向往和对感情的需求，我希望能有人和我分享。而现在对我来说，美德只是一个幻影，幸福和感情也变成了痛楚和厌弃一切的绝望，我能在哪里去找同情呢？只要我的苦难还存在，我宁愿独自去承受，在我死去的时候，如果我的记忆里装满了憎恶和轻蔑，我将心满意足。一度，我的幻想曾在关于美德、名誉和欢乐的梦想中获得安慰。一度，我曾抱着虚幻的希望，相信会遇见那样的人，他们将不在意我的外表，而会因我所能展示的优秀品德而爱我。我曾怀抱着关于荣誉和献身的崇高思想。可是现在，罪恶已经使我堕落到连最卑贱的动物也不如的地步了。找不到任何罪过，任何危害，任何邪恶，任何苦难，能和我的所作所为相比拟。当我历历回顾自己犯下的所有罪孽的时候，我不敢相信我竟是过去那同一个我，心中曾经充满了对于美与善的崇高而超凡的憧憬。然而事实就是如此，堕落的天使变成了狠毒的魔鬼。即使是上帝和人类的那个敌人(1)，在他凄惨的处境中也还有朋友和伙伴，我却是孤零零的。

“你，既然称弗兰肯斯坦为朋友，看来也知道我的罪行和他的不幸了。可是他告诉你的无论多么详尽，也无法概括我所经受的日复一日、月复一月的痛苦，时光就在无可奈何的愤怒中耗尽了。因为我即使毁灭了他的希望，却并没有满足自己的欲望。我的欲望永远是那么热烈和迫切，我仍然渴望着爱和友谊，然而我仍然遭人唾弃。这里面难道没有不公平的地方吗？全人类对我犯了罪，难道唯有我应该被看作罪犯吗？为什么你不憎恨那个把自己的朋友无礼地赶出家门的费利克斯？为什么你不憎恶那个想杀死他孩子的救命恩人的乡下人？是呀，这些人都是道德高尚、毫无瑕疵的人！我，这悲惨的和被遗弃的生命，是个畸形儿，活该受唾弃、受欺辱、受践踏。甚至是现在，我一想起这种不公平，血液就会沸腾起来。

“可是说老实话，我确实是个卑鄙的家伙。我杀害过可爱的、孤弱无援的人，我掐死过熟睡中的无辜者，扼死过从未伤害过我或其他任何生灵的人。我一心要给我的创造者制造苦难，而他却是一切人当中最值得爱的佼佼者，我甚至执意要逼迫得他走向无可挽回的毁灭。他就躺在那儿，惨白地冰凉地死了。你恨我，可是你对我的憎恶比不上我对自己的憎恶。我看着干下这种行为的双手，我想到孕育了这些恶念的心，我真渴望那个时刻，我的双手将蒙住我的眼睛，恶念也不再纠缠我的思想。

“不要害怕我将来还会为非作歹。我的事情差不多做完了。我的生命已经终结，必须做的也都已完成，并不需要你或其他任何人再去死，现在需要的只是我自己的死亡。别以为我会慢悠悠地实施我的生命的献祭。我将离开你们的船，登上带我来的那个冰筏，找到地球的最北端，我将聚起自己葬身的火堆，把这可怜的躯体烧成灰烬，不让残骸给任何好奇而邪恶的坏蛋提供线索，再造出一个像我这样的怪物。我将死去。我将不再感受到现今折磨着我的痛苦，也不再忍受那些无可满足、却又无法泯灭的感情的吞噬。给我生命的人已经死去，当我也不复存在的时候，对我们两个的记忆也将很快地消泯。我将再也见不到太阳和星星，也感受不到风吹拂我的脸颊了。光明、感情和知觉都将消失，在这种状态下我一定能找到自己的欢乐。若干年前，当这个世界的景象第一次展现在我眼前的时候，当我感受到夏日令人欢欣的温暖，听见树叶沙沙作响和鸟儿的婉转鸣唱的时候，它们就是我的一切，那时假如死去我是会哭泣的，现在死亡却是我唯一的安慰了。我被罪孽所玷污，被痛楚的悔恨所撕裂，除了死亡以外我还能在哪里求得安宁呢？

“永别了！我将离开你，你将是我这双眼睛所见到的人类中的最后的一个。永别了，弗兰肯斯坦！假如你还活着，还怀着向我复仇的欲望的话，我活着要比死去更能满足你。可是事实上不是这样，你一直要想毁灭我，以免导致更大的不幸。然而，假如你以某种我不知道的方式还仍然保持着思考和感觉的话，你将宁愿让我处在目前的状况中，因为再没有比这更厉害的报复方法了。尽管你遭到了摧残，可我的痛苦远远胜过了你，因为悔恨之痛的尖刺将永远拨弄着我的伤口，直至死亡使它永远愈合为止。

“不过快了，”他满怀惨伤而庄严的热情高喊道，“我就要死了，我现在所感受的一切都将不再感受到了。痛苦的火焰快熄灭了。我将意气昂扬地登上火葬的柴堆，在烈焰烧灼的痛楚中狂喜欢悦。火焰的光辉会渐渐黯淡，我的灰烬将被风刮进大海。我的灵魂将永远安息，假如它还会思想的话，它肯定不会像现在这样想了。永别了。”

他一面说着，一面从船舱的窗口跳了出去，落到了紧靠船边的冰筏上。他很快就被波涛带走了，消失在黑暗的远方。

9月12日

————————————————————

(1) 指撒旦。

译序

国人崇拜海明威（哪能不崇拜呢？），因为他影响了我们的生活态度，影响了我们的文风。他是个叫人热血沸腾的钢铁汉子，敢于为正义的事业赴汤蹈火。1937年至1938年，他以战地记者的身份奔波于西班牙内战前线。在第二次世界大战期间，他作为记者随军行动，并参加了解放巴黎的战斗。1941年底太平洋战争爆发后，海明威立即将自己的游艇改装成巡艇，侦察德国潜艇的行动，为消灭敌人提供情报。1942年，德国潜艇击沉了多艘美国运货船。美国海军还未从珍珠港大战的巨大损失中恢复过来，所以不得不让一些民间志愿者开着他们自己的私人游艇去巡逻海岸。这些志愿者被称为“烂污海军”。他们只是进行简单的巡逻，然后通过无线电将海下的情况报告给岸上的军方。海明威以船长自称，开始在古巴海岸巡逻，一心希望看到一艘德国潜艇，然后用汤普森机枪和手榴弹将其击沉。他召集了一群“杂牌军”，其中包括巴斯克回力球球员和百万富翁等。诺曼底登陆海明威也参加了，但军方认为他这个大人物不能受一丝一毫的损失，所以只允许他待在船上。他们很快就明白海明威可不是一个愿意接受照顾或是听从命令的人。在跟随第二十二军团行进过程中，海明威得到军方批准，可在朗布依埃小镇开展情报搜集工作。很快，他便成了一支游击队的头头，他的部下有一个特工、几个法国士兵和几个普通平民，这些人对他唯命是从，恭敬地称呼他为“爸爸”、“上尉”，甚至是“伟大的上尉”。在人们眼中，这支非正规军就是一帮狂热崇拜海明威的匪徒，他们甚至模仿海明威的言谈举止和行事风格。随着越来越多平民与法国士兵的加入，海明威的这支非正规军逐渐扩大至几百人。海明威甚至穿着陆军上校的制服，带领他们多次加入战斗。战争结束两年之际，他被授予一枚铜质奖章。

海明威喜欢这种正义的“血性”，也喜欢“原始性”，他对非洲有着剪不断理还乱的情结。他曾经随狩猎队去非洲，经历了许多惊心动魄的“原始”场面，并进行了生动的描述，本书里的《弗朗西斯·麦康伯短暂、幸福的人生经历》、《乞力马扎罗的雪》和《一段非洲的往事》记载了他当时的见闻和见解。在《一段非洲的往事》里，从一个小男孩戴维的角度出发，海明威表现出对于人类与自然关系的强烈关注，揭示了人类残忍的本性，表达了创造人类与自然和谐关系的美好愿望。小说中的大公象是坚强不屈的人的象征体。这样的形象和海明威在名著《老人与海》中塑造的那个与鲨鱼搏斗的老人，在许多地方是相通的。

海明威虽然作品并不多，但他的小说思想性强，令人回味无穷，赢得了成千上万的读者。美国著名史学家威勒德·索普曾在《二十世纪美国文学》中写道：“尽管海明威的小说要隔很长时间才出版一本，但是在一本新小说出版之前几个月就已经引起了人们的争论，并且这种争论在小说出版后几个月还在继续进行。”海明威的作品大受欢迎，还有一个原因，就是其中充溢着美国人所喜欢的“阳刚之气”。正如我国学者于冬云在评论文章中所言：“所谓海明威的文体风格，即赫·欧·贝茨所称道的简洁、干净、含蓄、凝练。这是一种‘绝不矫饰’、‘平易粗放、街头硬汉般的文风’，他尤其擅长用‘那种公牛般的、出于本能的、缺少思想的语言’来陈述他故事中的那些猎人、渔夫、斗牛士、士兵、拳击者的思想和行为。福柯认为，影响和控制语言运动的最根本因素是权力。现代社会语言学也发现男性语体是一种有力的语体，女性语体则是一种无力的语体。以此标准来重新审视贝茨一再称颂的海明威的文体风格，便不难发现在这种简洁粗硬的文风下掩盖的男性权力的特征。从早期创作开始，海明威就有意识地选择了这样一种叙事文体，并坚持使用了一生。因此，我们完全有理由说海明威的叙事文体是一种典型的男性话语方式。”

这样的一种文体对欧美大陆当时流行的冗长、繁杂的文风简直就是叛逆和颠覆，在一些大牌评论家的吹捧之下立时犹如一阵狂风席卷大地，引起了一场“文学革命”，在许多欧美作家的身上留下了深深的痕印。海明威所尊奉的是美国建筑师罗德维希的名言“越少，就越多”，使作品趋于精练，缩短了作品与读者之间的距离，提出了“冰山原则”，只表现事物的八分之一，使作品充实、含蓄、耐人寻味。海明威写作态度极为严肃，十分重视作品的修改。据说他每天开始写作时，先把前一天写的文稿读一遍，写到哪里就改到哪里。全书写完后又从头到尾改一遍，草稿请人誊清后又改一遍，最后清样出来再改一遍。他认为这样三次大修改是写好一本书的必要条件。他主张“去掉废话”，在修改时把一切华而不实的词句删去，每一句、每一段落都达到“精益求精”。还有人说，由于在第一次世界大战中膝盖被子弹打碎，海明威必须站着写作，久而久之形成了“永远站着”的“强硬”风格，字句也异常简练。自杀前他留下遗言，要人在他的墓碑上刻下“恕我再也不能站起来了”。不管原因如何，反正他惜墨如金，字字句句都是详细推敲的结晶。虽然没有开创一个新的文学流派，他却是开了一代文风的语言艺术大师。

海明威的作品可谓字字珠玑，读者从中吮吸营养，大快朵颐。其中最广为人知的有《第五纵队》、《丧钟为谁而鸣》、《老人与海》、《太阳照常升起》、《永别了，武器》、《乞力马扎罗的雪》等。1954年，海明威荣获诺贝尔文学奖。获奖后的海明威患有多种疾病，给他的身心造成了极大的痛苦，没能再创作出很有影响力的作品，这使他精神抑郁，形成了消极悲观的情绪。1961年7月2日，蜚声世界文坛的海明威用自己的猎枪结束了他的生命。整个世界都为之震惊，人们纷纷叹息这位巨人的悲剧。美国人民更是悲悼这颗美国文坛巨星的陨落。在这个总统死了都不会哀痛的国家，海明威何以能令举国上下“沉浸在哀痛之中”？就凭他独特的作品，就凭他那硬汉精神！海明威本人及其笔下的人物影响了整整一代甚至几代美国人，人们纷纷仿效他和他作品中的人物。他就是美国精神的化身。人们在为这种精神哭泣。

海明威的作品难以翻译，因为他的语言过于“含蓄”和“简练”——阅读原文尚可以“咀嚼”出其中所包含的“精神”，但翻译成其他语言，难免会“缺斤少两”。如此，便不能一味地“直译”，需用艺术的“再创造”方法辅以“意译”——其目的是为了不“失真”，让读者通过译文了解“海明威精神”，了解那动人魂魄的故事情节。有人说海明威作品中的词句过于“刚硬”，而“刚硬”则易折，即破碎成许许多多的“节”。翻译时应该掌握好“火候”，既要还原其“硬汉风格”，还要让读者看到一个完整的海明威。译者已“绞尽脑汁”，但愿不“亵渎”海明威，不辜负读者热切的希望！

方华文

于苏州大学外国语学院

2015年11月3日

弗朗西斯·麦康伯短暂、幸福的人生经历

午饭时间，大家来到帐篷餐厅，坐在双层的绿色篷顶下，好像什么事情也没有发生过似的。

“你们喝酸橙汁还是柠檬汽水？”麦康伯问。

“给我来一杯伏特加杜松子鸡尾酒吧。”罗伯特·威尔逊回话说。

“我也要一杯伏特加杜松子鸡尾酒。我需要喝一杯酒。”麦康伯的妻子说。

“我想是该喝杯酒的。”麦康伯同意妻子的说法，“那就叫他调三杯吧。”

说话间，杂役从帆布冷藏袋里取出几瓶酒，已经在调制了。帐篷遮蔽在林间，一阵风穿过树林吹来，使酒瓶上凝结出一层水珠。

“应该给他们多少钱？”麦康伯问。

“一英镑就不少了，”威尔逊说，“可别把他们给惯坏了。”

“他们的头头会把钱分下去吧？”

“当然会的。”

半个小时前，弗朗西斯·麦康伯得意扬扬地被厨子、贴身杂役、剥皮工(1)以及脚夫用胳膊抬、用肩扛，从营地的边缘送到了他的帐篷。这次游行，扛枪的杂役没有参加。那些土著人把他送到帐篷前，将他放下，接着他跟大伙儿一一握手，接受他们的祝贺。之后，他进入帐篷坐在床上，直至他的妻子走了进来。妻子进来，却没有和他说话。他起身离开了帐篷，在外边的便携式盥洗盆里洗了把脸和手，随即便去了餐厅帐篷，在一把舒适的帆布椅子上落座，于林荫之中吹着习习的微风。

“你算是猎到了狮子，”罗伯特·威尔逊对他说道，“而且是一头非常棒的狮子哩。”

麦康伯夫人飞快地瞥了威尔逊一眼。她有着沉鱼落雁的容貌，而且保养得很好。五年前，凭着姿色和社会地位，她拿几张照片为一款自己从未用过的美容产品做广告，获得了五千块钱的酬金。她嫁给弗朗西斯·麦康伯已经有十一个年头了。

“那头狮子很不错，是不是？”麦康伯说。此时，他的妻子正看着他。麦康伯夫人打量着眼前的这两个男人，那样子好像是以前从来没见过他们似的。

这个威尔逊，是位白人猎手，她觉得自己以前从未仔细看过他。他看上去中等身材，沙色头发，胡子拉碴，一张通红的脸，蓝眼睛冰冷冷的，眼角罩着细细的白色皱纹，一笑那皱纹便成了一道道深沟。此时，他正冲着她笑哩。她将目光从他的脸上移开，看他那穿着宽松束腰外衣的溜肩膀——外衣上原该有个左胸兜的，却被几个环套所取代，环套里有四个大弹药夹。接着，她便看他那棕褐色的大手、旧旧的宽松长裤以及脏兮兮的靴子，最后又将目光收回来看他的红脸。她注意到那张被阳光烤红的脸上有一圈白线，那是戴斯泰森毡帽留下的印迹（此时，那顶毡帽挂在帐篷支柱的钉子上）。

“好，咱们为那头狮子干杯。”罗伯特·威尔逊说，他又冲着她笑了笑。而对方没有笑，却在看她的丈夫，眼神有些古怪。

弗朗西斯·麦康伯个子特别高，如果不计较骨骼的长短，身材算是非常匀称的了，黑黑的肤色，寸头，头发剪得很短，像个桨手，两片嘴唇薄薄的，可以说是一表人才。他和威尔逊一样，穿的都是狩猎队的服装，只不过他的衣服簇新。他今年三十五岁，身体相当强健，擅长球类运动，钓过许多大鱼，而刚才却当着众人的面暴露出自己是个胆小鬼。

“为那头狮子干杯。”他说道，“对于你的付出，我感激不尽。”

他的妻子玛格丽特把目光从他的身上移开，又转向了威尔逊。

“那头狮子咱们就不谈了。”她说道。

威尔逊看了看她，这次没笑，而她却冲他笑了笑。

“这是一个非常奇怪的日子，”她说道，“中午即便在帐篷里，是不是也该把帽子戴上？这可是你告诉我的。”

“戴倒是可以戴的。”威尔逊说。

“要知道，你有一张非常红的脸，威尔逊先生。”她说完，又嫣然一笑。

“喝酒喝的。”威尔逊说。

“恐怕不是的。”她说，“弗朗西斯也经常手不离杯，但他的脸从来就没有红过。”

“今天红了呀。”麦康伯想开个玩笑，于是这样说道。

“不对，”玛格丽特说，“今天红脸的是我。要说威尔逊先生，他的脸历来都是红的。”

“这八成是人种的关系吧。”威尔逊说，“喂，你不会再想拿我英俊的外表做话题吧？”

“我这只是开了个头。”

“这个咱们就不谈了。”威尔逊说。

“大家谈谈话怎么就这么难。”玛格丽特说。

“别说傻话，玛戈(2)。”她丈夫说。

“没什么难的，”威尔逊说，“打到了一头非常棒的狮子呀。”

玛格丽特扫了他们俩一眼，两人看得出她都快要哭了。威尔逊老早就注意到了，这让他感到担心。麦康伯倒是坦然，已经并不为之感到担心了。

“真希望这件事就没有发生过。唉，真希望这件事就没有发生过。”她边说边到自己的帐篷去了。她没有哭出声，但他们看到她那裹在玫瑰色防晒衬衣中的肩膀在抖动。

“女人动不动就伤感。”威尔逊对那位高个子丈夫说，“不会出什么事的。只是精神紧张，接触到的事情多了些罢了。”

“没什么，”麦康伯说，“我想我的后半生都得忍耐了。”

“胡说什么呀。来，为精彩的猎杀干杯。”威尔逊说，“该忘的就忘掉它，没什么可遗憾的。”

“试试吧。”麦康伯说，“不过，对于你的帮助，我是不会忘的。”

“没什么，”威尔逊说，“都是不着边的话。”

两人坐在树荫里说着话。他们的营地设在几棵浓荫似盖的洋槐树下，背后是巨石高耸的悬崖，前面有一片草地一直延伸向一条小溪边，溪水里净是石头，过了小溪就是森林。杂役摆饭桌的时候，他们喝着刚冰镇好的酸橙汁，尽量不去看对方的眼睛。威尔逊看得出，杂役们全都知道实情了。麦康伯的贴身杂役一边把饭菜摆上饭桌，一边用异样的目光打量着自己的主人。威尔逊见状，用斯瓦希里语呵斥了一声。那杂役一脸的茫然，转身走了。

“你对他说了什么？”麦康伯问。

“没什么。只是让他识相些，不然就没他好果子吃，给他狠狠来上十五下。”

“十五下什么？鞭打吗？”

“鞭打完全是非法的。”威尔逊说，“仅仅允许扣他们的工钱。”

“你是不是还用鞭打惩罚他们？”

“哦，是的。假如他们选择去告状，很可能会祸起萧墙。可是，他们不会告我的，情愿挨鞭子，也不愿被扣工钱。”

“真是咄咄怪事！”麦康伯说。

“其实没什么奇怪的。”威尔逊说，“你会怎么做？是愿意被桦条狠狠抽打一顿，还是拿不到工钱？”

话刚一出口，他就感到挺难为情的，于是没等麦康伯回话，又急忙说：“要知道，每一天每一日人人都在挨鞭子，不是这种鞭子，就是那种鞭子。”

这话也没让情况好到哪儿去。他心想：“上帝呀，我都成了个玩外交辞令的人了！”

“不错，是都在挨鞭子。”麦康伯说，眼睛仍然没有朝着他看，“对于猎狮子这件事，我感到十分遗憾。这件事到此为止，不应该再张扬了吧？我的意思是不让他们任何人知道此事，好吗？”

“你是说我会在马赛卡俱乐部谈起此事？”威尔逊冷冷地望着他。真没想到对方会如此猜忌人。他心中暗想，麦康伯不仅是个可恶的懦夫，还是个该死的下流种。在这之前，他竟然还十分喜欢麦康伯哩。美国人真是叫人捉摸不透呀！

“不会的。”威尔逊说，“我是个职业猎手。对于主顾，我们是闭口不谈的。你尽管放心好啦。不过，听到别人提出要求，叫我们闭嘴，挺不是滋味的。”

他决定就此来个了断，那样处境会容易得多。他照样吃饭（独自一人吃饭），可以边吃饭边看书。让那两口子吃他们自己的。他会公事公办，照样陪他们把打猎进行到底。法国人把这叫什么来着？体面的尊重！那样一来，比这样陷于情感旋涡里利落得多。他将羞辱羞辱对方，给他来个一刀两断。那时，他可以吃吃东西、看看书，而对方的威士忌他照喝不误。打猎时出现不愉快的情况，一般都说这种话。遇见一位白人猎手，你问他：“情况怎么样呀？”如果他说“他们的威士忌我照喝不误”，那你就知道情况糟透了。

“对不起。”麦康伯说，一边抬起他那张美国脸望着他——那张脸就是到了中年也会青春焕发。威尔逊注意到他留着桨手那样的寸头，一双眼睛漂漂亮亮（只是目光有些躲闪），端正的鼻子，薄嘴唇，下巴很好看。“对不起，我没料到会出现这种情况。有许多规矩我都是不知道的。”

威尔逊心里真不知怎么才好了。他已经决定跟对方彻底翻脸了，可是这个不要脸的家伙刚刚侮辱了他，现在又向他表示歉意了。他只好再做做尝试，把关系缓一缓。“别担心我会张扬此事，”他说道，“我得有碗饭吃呀。要知道，在非洲，就是女人也能猎杀狮子，没有一个白人会见了狮子就跑。”

“我是跑了，像只兔子撒腿就跑。”麦康伯说。

威尔逊心里没了谱，遇到这么一个会说软话的家伙，真不知该怎么应付了。

威尔逊用他的那双机枪手的坚毅的蓝眼睛看了看麦康伯，而对方冲他莞尔一笑。假如你注意不到他自尊心受损时所表现出来的眼神，可以说他的微笑令人心情愉悦。

“也许打野牛时，我可以做一弥补。”他说，“接下来就要去打野牛了，对不对？”

“如果你愿意，咱们明天早晨去。”威尔逊说道。也许，他刚才的想法是错的。这样想的确是个应付局面的方法。对于美国人，你是捉摸不透的，不知道会出现什么现象。此刻，他的天平又倒向了麦康伯。今天早晨的事能忘就忘了吧。可是，那样的事是想忘也忘不了的。今天早晨简直倒了血霉。

“哦，太太来了！”他说道。只见玛格丽特袅袅婷婷从她的帐篷走了过来，显得精神焕发、情绪高涨，可爱极了。她有一张无可挑剔的鹅蛋脸，简直完美极了，叫你甚至会以为她是个头脑愚蠢的花瓶。不过，威尔逊觉得她不蠢，一点也不蠢。

“怎么样，英俊的大红脸威尔逊先生？我的宝贝弗朗西斯，感觉好些了吧？”

“哦，感觉好多了。”麦康伯说。

“这件事我全都想透了。”她边说边在桌旁坐了下来，“弗朗西斯是不是擅长于猎狮，那又有多大关系呢？他又不是吃这碗饭的。那是威尔逊先生的行当。在打猎方面，威尔逊先生的确是得心应手。你是什么样的动物都猎杀，对不对？”

“哦，是什么样的猎物都行。”威尔逊说，“什么样的动物都猎杀。”他心里在想，这种女人是天下最强硬、最无情、最具掠夺性，也是最富于魅力的女人；随着她们强硬起来，她们的丈夫就会变成脓包，或者被折磨得发疯。难道她们在选择丈夫时，专拣软柿子捏？可是，结婚时年轻，不会这么有心计呀！值得庆幸的是，他已经完成了关于美国女人方面的教育，意识到眼前的这个是极具吸引力的女人。

“我们明天早晨去打野牛。”他对她说道。

“我也去。”她说。

“不行，你不能去。”

“行的，我能去。弗朗西斯，你说呢？”

“留在营地里不好吗？”

“那是绝对不行的。”她说，“像今天的这种场面，我是绝对不愿错过的。”

威尔逊心想，她刚才走开，躲到一边去哭的时候，看上去女人味十足，像是懂事、体贴，为丈夫以及自己感到痛心，是个通情达理的人，二十分钟后返回就变了样，又涂抹上了一层美国女人的那种狠心肠的彩釉。这种女人真是可怕，简直太可怕了。

“明天我们为你再来一场表演。”弗朗西斯·麦康伯说。

“你还是不要去了。”威尔逊说。

“你这样阻拦是不对的。”她说道，“我还想再看你表演一次呢。你今天早晨的表演很精彩哟。如果说把野兽的脑袋打得稀巴烂也可以算是精彩的话。”

“该吃饭了。”威尔逊说，“你挺高兴的，是不是？”

“为什么不呢？我来这儿又不是找烦恼的。”

“哦，没什么可烦恼的。”威尔逊说。放眼望去，他可以看得到河水里的大石头以及树影婆娑的高高的河岸。看着看着，他又想起了今天早晨的事情。

“是啊，没什么可烦恼的。”她说，“一切都很好。明天也是个好日子。对于明天，你都不知道我是怎样期盼呢。”

“这道菜是大羚羊肉。”威尔逊说。

“大羚羊的个头像牛一样，跑起来像野兔，对不对？”

“我觉得你描绘得很生动。”威尔逊说。

“大羚羊的肉是很好吃的。”麦康伯说。

“羚羊是你打到的吧，弗朗西斯？”她问。

“是的。”

“这种动物不危险吧？”

“只要别让它们扑到你身上就行。”威尔逊说。

“真叫人高兴。”

“能不能收敛一些，别轻飘飘的，玛戈。”麦康伯说，一边从大羚羊肉排上切下一片来，用叉子朝下将肉叉住，往上涂抹土豆泥、肉汁以及胡萝卜丁。

“既然你把话说得这么漂亮，我想我是可以做得到的。”她说。

“今晚喝上一杯，为那头狮子干杯。”威尔逊说，“中午的天气有点太热。”

“啊，那头狮子，”玛格丽特说，“你不提我都忘了！”

罗伯特·威尔逊觉得她话里夹枪带棒。或者说她这是在演戏给人看。当一个女人发现自己的丈夫是个可恶的懦夫时，你说她会怎么样呢？这娘们真够狠心的。不过，女人不是都狠心么？当然，为了掌握控制权，有时候就得狠心。话虽这么说，狠毒心肠还是叫人受不了的。

“再吃点羚羊肉！”他客客气气地对她说。

当天下午晚一些的时候，威尔逊和麦康伯乘车出去了。同行的有土著汽车司机以及两个扛枪的人。麦康伯夫人留在了营地里，因为天气太热，她出不了门。她说明天一大早随他们出行。汽车启动时，威尔逊看见她站在那棵大树下，身穿她的那件淡淡的玫瑰色卡其布衫，虽然不是天姿国色，却也妩媚动人，一头乌丝从脑门朝后梳，绾成一个髻，低垂在脖后，脸蛋水灵灵的，就像身处英国一样。她频频招手送别。汽车开过长满高高荒草的洼地，穿过一片树林拐了个弯，驶入遍布果子灌木丛的山丘间。

他们发现果子灌木丛里有一群黑斑羚，于是便下了车，悄悄向一只年老的公羚摸了过去——那只公羚有一对长角，向两边分得开开的。麦康伯开了一枪，射杀了它。中间隔着足足有两百码的距离，这一枪真是值得称赞。羚羊群吓得仓皇奔逃，一蹿一跃的，将长长的腿收起，你从我的背上跳过去，我从你的背上跃过去，像是飘在空中一样，似梦里的场景，令人难以相信。

“这一枪打得漂亮。”威尔逊说，“黑斑羚目标小，难打中的。”

“黑斑羚的脑袋值得一要吗？(3)”麦康伯问。

“它的脑袋棒极啦。”威尔逊说，“你这样打枪，就不会有什么问题了。”

“你觉得明天能找到野牛吗？”

“概率是很大的。它们一大清早出来吃草，运气好就能在野外看到它们。”

“我想借此机会将猎狮的那件事一笔抹掉。”麦康伯说，“出了这样的事情，让妻子看见了总是不太好的。”

威尔逊心想，更不好的是你自己做了这样的事情，别管妻子计较不计较，而且还把此事挂在嘴边提来提去。他是这么想的，但口中却说：“要是我，就不多想此事了。头一次猎狮，换上谁都会心慌的。过去的就让它过去吧。”

可是晚上吃过饭之后，上床前喝了杯威士忌加苏打水，弗朗西斯·麦康伯躺在罩着蚊帐的小床上，细听着夜色里的响动，这件事仍没有过去。它既没有过去，也不是刚开始，而是已经发生，历历在目，有些细节不可磨灭，尤为清晰，让他痛苦和害臊。比害臊更可怕的是，他内心感到寒冷而空洞的恐惧。恐惧感仍折磨着他，像一个冷冰冰、黏糊糊的黑窟窿，在他空荡荡的内心里占据了原来属于自信心的位置，这叫他感到难过。这件事让他难以忘怀。

此事是在昨天夜里开始的。当时他被惊醒，听见河的上游传来狮子吼声，声音低沉，吼完一声，还呼噜呼噜咳嗽几下，听上去就好像在帐篷外似的。弗朗西斯·麦康伯半夜醒来听到的就是这声音，这叫他感到害怕。他可以听见妻子已熟睡，发出均匀的呼吸声。没有人听他诉说心里的恐惧，也没有人跟他一起害怕。他孤孤单单一个人躺在那里。他并不知道索马里有条谚语，说勇敢的人总会被狮子吓上三次：一是发现狮子足印的时候，二是听见狮吼，三是跟狮子照面的时候。黎明时分，太阳升起之前，他们借着马灯的光亮在餐厅帐篷里吃早饭，又听见了那只狮子的吼叫声。弗朗西斯觉得它就在营地的边上。

“听声音像是只老狮子。”正在吃熏鱼、喝咖啡的罗伯特·威尔逊抬起头说，“听它的咳嗽就知道了。”

“它是不是离得很近？”

“在河上游，大概有一英里吧。”

“需要去看看吗？”

“会去看的。”

“它的叫声能传这么远吗？听上去就好像在营地里似的。”

“传得远得很呢。”罗伯特·威尔逊说，“传得这么远，的确挺奇怪的。但愿是只可以猎杀的大猫。杂役们说这一带的确有一只个头非常大的家伙。”

“假如开枪，应该打它的哪个地方才能把它撂倒？”麦康伯问。

“打两个膀子的中间。”威尔逊说，“假如办得到，就打它的脖子。瞄准骨头打，一枪放翻。”

“但愿能打得准。”麦康伯说。

“你的枪法是很好的。”威尔逊说，“沉住气，瞄准再开枪。头一枪就打中是至关紧要的。”

“开枪的距离呢？”

“很难说。这得看狮子的情况而定了。应该近一些，能够一枪射中，否则别开枪。”

“在一百码以内可以吧？”麦康伯问。

威尔逊飞快地瞥了他一眼。

“一百码是差不多的。也许要在一百码之内开枪射击。千万别远在一百码之外就莽撞射击。一百码是个很好的距离，想打哪个位置就打哪个位置。瞧，太太来啦。”

“早晨好！”玛格丽特说道，“今天咱们去找那头狮子吗？”

“你把早饭吃完就出发。”威尔逊说，“感觉怎么样？”

“非常好。”她说，“我激动得不得了。”

“我去看看，把准备工作做好。”威尔逊说完起身要走。就在这时，那只狮子又吼了一声。

“这个大叫大嚷的讨厌家伙，”威尔逊说，“会让它叫不出声的。”

“你怎么啦，弗朗西斯？”妻子问。

“没什么。”麦康伯说。

“是有原因的。”她说，“什么事情叫你如坐针毡似的？”

“什么事也没有。”他说。

“告诉我实情，”她盯住他说，“你感觉不舒服？”

“是被可恶的狮子吼吵着了。”他说，“要知道，它吼了整整一夜。”

“你为什么不把我叫醒。”她说，“我倒是喜欢听狮子吼叫。”

“我得杀了那讨厌的家伙。”麦康伯阴沉着脸说。

“哦，你到这儿来，不就是为了猎杀狮子吗？”

“是的。不过，有点紧张。一听见那畜生吼叫，我就神经紧张。”

“那好，那就按威尔逊说的，去杀掉它，让它再也叫不出声来。”

“好的，亲爱的。”弗朗西斯·麦康伯说，“听上去怪容易的，是不是？”

“你不害怕吧？”

“当然不害怕。不过，听它吼了一夜，精神倒是有些紧张。”

“你会很漂亮地将它干掉的。”她说，“我知道你一定能。我真是渴望看到那场面哩。”

“把你的饭吃完，咱们这就出发。”

“天还没亮呢。”她说，“这个时刻不尴不尬的。”

就在这时，那头狮子从胸腔的深处发出一声呻吟，那声音突然变为喉音，继而调门升高，成为颤音，似乎连空气都随之颤抖。最后，那声音化为一声叹息和一种发自胸腔深处的呼噜声。

“听那声音，好像近在咫尺。”麦康伯的妻子说。

“天呀，”麦康伯说，“我讨厌那可恶的声音。”

“让人听了印象非常深刻。”

“还说印象深刻。简直是可怕！”

这时，罗伯特·威尔逊走了过来，手里拎着他那支又短又难看、口径大得惊人的.505吉布斯猎枪，嘴角挂着微笑。

“走吧。”他说道，“你的扛枪手把你的斯普林菲尔德步枪以及那支大枪都带上了。东西都装上车了。你有实心弹吗？”

“有。”

“我准备好了。”麦康伯夫人说。

“这次务必让它叫不出声来。”威尔逊说，“你坐前排，太太和我可以坐在后排。”

大家伙都上了汽车，在灰蒙蒙的第一缕曙光中驱车穿过树林，向河的上游驶去。麦康伯打开步枪的后膛，看见里面装了金属壳的子弹，便合上膛门，推上了保险栓。他看到自己的手在哆嗦。他把手伸进衣袋去摸了摸子弹夹，然后又用手摸上衣胸前环套里的弹夹。接着，他回头朝这辆没有门的厢式汽车的后座望了望——威尔逊和他的妻子就坐在那儿。那俩人兴高采烈，都咧着嘴笑呢。威尔逊把身子朝前探了探低声说：

“瞧那些落在地上的鸟儿。这就是说，那只老狮子抛下被它咬死的猎物走了。”

麦康伯可以看见，在远处河岸上，一群秃鹫在树林的上空盘旋，然后垂直下落。

“那只狮子很可能会来这一带喝水，”威尔逊悄声说，“在它去睡觉之前。得把眼睛睁大些。”

汽车慢慢悠悠行驶在高高隆起的河岸上。在这一段，河水把满是石块的河床冲出了个深坑。他们在参天大树间迤逦而行。麦康伯仔细观察着对岸的动静，突然感到威尔逊用手抓住了他的胳膊。汽车停下了。

“它就在那里。”他听见威尔逊压低声音说，“在前方靠右的地方。你下车干掉它。那是一只非常棒的狮子。”

此时，麦康伯看到了那只狮子。它几乎完全是侧身站着，将巨大的脑袋抬起，转向他们。清晨微风拂面，把狮身上的深色鬃毛微微吹起。狮子看上去是个庞然大物，其轮廓于灰蒙蒙的晨曦中巍然挺立在隆起的河岸上，肩膀厚重，肚子像水桶般光滑、滚圆。

“它离这儿有多远？”麦康伯抓起枪问。

“大概有七十五码吧。你下车，干掉它。”

“为什么不叫我从车上开枪？”

“不能从车上开枪。”麦康伯听见威尔逊伏在他耳边说，“下车去，把它干掉。它不会老待在那儿等你的。”

麦康伯钻出前座旁的圆弧形开口，踩在踏板上，然后把脚落在了地面上。狮子仍站在那里张望，威武而冷静，望着这个在它的眼里仅显现出轮廓的物体，样子像只超级大犀牛。人的气味没有传到它的鼻孔，于是它只是张望着，望着这个物体，巨大的脑袋微微左右晃动着。这个时候，它并不感到害怕。不过，面对着这样一个东西，它在走下河岸喝水之前，觉得有些犹豫。它看见一个人影从这个物体上脱离出来，便把它那沉重的脑袋调转开，晃晃悠悠向着树丛隐蔽地走去。此时只听啪的一声，它感到一颗.30-06射出的220格令(4)重的实心子弹击中了它的侧腹，胃里突然有一种火辣辣的烧灼感，令它直想呕吐。它抬起巨大的爪子小跑起来，脚步沉重，由于腹部受伤，身子一晃一晃的。就在它穿过树丛向高高的荒草那儿奔逃寻找隐身之处时，啪地又传来一声枪响，子弹擦身而过，把空气都撕裂了。接着又是一声响，它感到下肋被击中了，子弹射穿了它的躯体，一股滚烫的泛着泡沫的鲜血从嘴里奔涌而出。它快步飞跑向高高的荒草那儿，要找个地方卧下来，让人看不见，等拿着那个啪啪响东西的人走近时，就扑上去咬住他。

麦康伯走下汽车时，并没有想到狮子会有什么感觉。他只知道自己的两只手在发抖。离开汽车的当儿，连腿都快挪动不了了。他的大腿发硬，不过他却可以感到大腿上的肌肉在颤抖。他举起步枪，瞄准狮子的脑袋和肩膀相连接的地方，扣动了扳机。扣扳机他用了很大劲，觉得手指都快要断了，可是一点动静也没有。这时他才意识到，原来是保险栓没有打开。于是他将枪身放低，打开保险栓，同时又向前僵硬地迈了一步。狮子看见他的轮廓与汽车的轮廓分离开，便转身迈着碎步小跑走了。麦康伯开枪时，听见嗵的一声，说明子弹击中了目标，可是狮子仍在跑。他又开了一枪。大家看见子弹与跑动着的狮子擦身而过，在前方激起一股尘土。他又补了一枪，这次没忘将枪口朝下低一些。人人都听见了子弹击中目标的声音。狮子开始飞奔，没等他推上枪栓，一溜烟钻进了高高的荒草丛里。

麦康伯站在原地，胃里感到一阵难受，手哆嗦不止，手里的斯普林菲尔德步枪仍处于瞄准状态。他的妻子和罗伯特·威尔逊走过来站在他身旁。那两个扛枪人也在跟前，用瓦坎巴土话叽里哇啦交谈着。

“我打中了，”麦康伯说，“击中了两次。”

“你击中了它的胃，还击中了它前身的某个地方。”威尔逊缺乏热情地说。那两个扛枪人停止了交谈，都阴沉着脸。

“原来是可以一枪毙命的。”威尔逊又说了一句，“这下子得等一会儿，再去看结果怎么样了。”

“你这是什么意思？”

“那就是等它不行了，咱们再找过去。”

“明白了。”麦康伯说。

“这头狮子相当棒，”威尔逊带着几分高涨的情绪说，“只可惜它跑进了一个糟糕的地方。”

“为什么说是糟糕的地方呢？”

“那是因为你看不见它，除非迎面碰上。”

“明白了。”麦康伯说。

“走吧。”威尔逊说，“太太可以留在车里。咱们过去看看它留下的血迹。”

“你留在这里吧，玛戈。”麦康伯对妻子说。他嘴干得嗓子眼冒烟，说话感到困难。

“为什么？”她问。

“威尔逊这么说的。”

“我们过去看看。”威尔逊说，“你留下，从这儿看更清楚。”

“好吧。”

接着，威尔逊操起斯瓦希里语对司机交代了一通。后者点点头说：“遵命，先生。”

随后，他们走下陡峭的河岸，蹚过河水，绕过一块块大石头，用手抓住突出来的树根，登上了对岸。沿岸走去，他们找到了麦康伯开第一枪后，狮子跑过的地方。扛枪人用草茎指出矮草上深红色的血迹，那血迹向前延伸，一直延伸到岸边的树丛后。

“接下来怎么办？”麦康伯问。

“没多少选择的余地。”威尔逊说，“汽车开不过来。河岸太陡。只好等它僵硬下来一些，咱们再过去查看一下。”

“就不能放把火烧草吗？”麦康伯问。

“草太青了。”

“那么，就不能派人用棍子击打草丛，赶它出来吗？”

威尔逊心里掂量了一下，用眼睛望着他。“此计当然可行，”他说，“只是有点太玩命了。咱们都知道，这头狮子是受了伤的。没受伤的狮子是可以赶的——它听见响动会躲开的。而受伤的狮子会直接扑过来。你现在看不见它，除非跟它打个照面。它会平卧在一个你觉得连兔子也藏不住的地方，完全隐蔽起来。这种情况，是不便于派人过去的，那是送死。”

“叫扛枪人去看看怎么样？”

“哦，他们要守在咱们身边。这是他们的职责。对于这一点，他们是签了合同的。你瞧，他们有点不太高兴，是不是？”

“反正我是不愿过去的。”麦康伯说。他连想也没想，话便脱口而出了。

“我也不愿去呀。”威尔逊乐呵呵地说，“不过，的确是别无选择了。”随后，他略作沉思，向麦康伯瞟了一眼，结果看见他抖如筛糠，脸上一副可怜巴巴的神情。

“当然喽，不一定非得要你去。要知道，雇我来就是干这种事情的。我的身价高也正因为如此。”

“你的意思是自己独身前往？为什么不让它待在那儿，非得去查看呢？”

罗伯特·威尔逊的职业就是跟狮子打交道，以及处理由狮子引出的问题，之前倒是没多想麦康伯，只是觉得他有点怯懦罢了，而现在突然觉得自己开错了一扇旅馆的房门，瞧见了叫人害臊的现象。

“此话怎讲？”

“为什么不让它待在那儿，非得去查看呢？”

“你是说咱们假装什么事也没有，权当没有射中它？”

“不是的。仅仅丢下它别管就是了。”

“那是绝对不行的。”

“为什么不行？”

“一是因为它疼得死去活来，二是因为让其他人碰上会遭遇不测。”

“明白了。”

“不过，你不一定非得再管这件事了。”

“我还是愿意管的。”麦康伯说，“我只不过心里有些害怕罢了，这你是知道的。”

“咱们一起过去，我打头阵，”威尔逊说，“让康格尼断后。你随在我身后，稍微靠边一点。也许路上能听见它的吼声。看见它，咱们俩都开枪。什么顾虑都不要有。我会做你的后盾的。说实在的，你也许还是别去的好。那样会好得多的。你何不过河去跟太太在一起，让我把此事了结掉算了！”

“不，我还是想去看看。”

“那好吧。”威尔逊说，“不过，你如果心里不愿去，就别去了。现在这是我分内的事情了，这你知道的。”

“我心里是想去的。”麦康伯说。

他们在一棵树下席地而坐，吞云吐雾，抽起烟来。

“趁着在这里等待的工夫，想回去对太太说一声吗？”威尔逊问。

“不了。”

“那我就回去一下，叫她别着急。”

“好吧。”麦康伯说。他坐在那儿，胳肢窝里直冒汗，嘴发干，胃里觉得空空的。他恨不得能鼓起勇气来，对威尔逊说一声，让他独自去结果掉那头狮子。他不知道威尔逊心里窝着火，因为之前没发现对方有发怒的征兆，于是就由着对方去见他的妻子了。威尔逊返回时，他仍坐在原地。“我把你的大枪取来了。”威尔逊说，“你把它拿上。等的时间大概也够了。咱们走吧。”

麦康伯将大枪接过来，只听威尔逊说：

“跟在我后边，靠右首大概五码就行了。我让你做什么，你就严格地按我的话去做。”随后，他又用斯瓦希里语向两个扛枪人交代了一通，而听话的人表情凝重。

“咱们出发。”他末了说道。

“能先喝口水吗？”麦康伯问。那个年纪大一些的扛枪人皮带上挂着一个水壶，威尔逊对他说了一声，他便将水壶取下来，拧开盖子，然后把水壶递给了麦康伯。麦康伯接过来，觉得水壶沉甸甸的，毛毡水壶套摸上去毛刺刺的，一摸就知道是劣质品。他拿起水壶喝水，顺便望了一眼前方的高草以及高草后面的平顶树丛。一股微风吹来，荒草在微风中轻轻摆动，形成了一道道细浪。他瞧瞧身旁的扛枪人，可以看出对方也在经受着恐惧的折磨。

在荒草丛中三十五码的地方，那头大狮子平卧在地上，两只耳朵朝后，一动不动，只是微微地把它那长长的穗状的黑尾巴上下拍打几下。一来到这块藏身之地，困难的境况就出现了。圆滚滚的肚子被子弹射穿，使它痛苦万分，而肺部中的那一枪叫它虚弱了下来，每呼吸一次，就有稀稀的血沫从嘴里涌出。它的腰部湿湿的，滚烫滚烫，实心弹在它那褐色的毛皮上留下的小枪眼上爬满了苍蝇。它那黄色的大眼睛充满了仇恨，眯成了一条缝，直端端望着前方，只有在呼吸时感到疼痛才眨巴一下。它的爪子插入松软的干土里。所有的疼痛、难受和仇恨都凝聚在了一起，与残存的力量融合在一处，形成一股聚合力，时刻准备扑向来犯之敌。它可以听见人们的说话声，于是便耐心等待着，调动起每一根神经，准备那些人一进草丛就冲上前去。听着人类的说话声，它的尾巴变硬了，上下抽打着。当那几个人走到草地边时，它嗓子眼发出呼噜的一声咳嗽，忽地冲了过去。

那个叫康格尼的年纪大些的扛枪人正走在前头查看血迹，而威尔逊望着草丛观察动静，拿着枪随时准备射击。另外一个扛枪人眼睛注视着前方，竖耳倾听着。麦康伯贴近威尔逊走着，手里端着步枪。刚一进草丛，麦康伯便听见狮子的嗓子眼被血呛住而发出的呼噜咳嗽声，见荒草里有东西唰地扑了上来。他吓得掉头便跑，一路狂奔，没了魂似的跑到空旷的野地，接着向河边逃命。

此时，他听见轰隆一声！那是威尔逊的大枪射击的声音。接着又是轰隆一声，震耳欲聋。转过身来，他看见了那头狮子，样子很惨，好像半个脑袋都不见了，还拼命地朝高草地边的威尔逊跟前爬。而那个红脸汉子端着那支难看的、短短的步枪，推上枪栓，仔细瞄准，开了一枪，枪口又发出轰隆一声响。正在爬动的、沉重的、黄黄的狮子躯体逐渐变得僵硬了，而它的那个巨大的、残缺不全的头颅向前耷拉了下来。麦康伯独自一人站在他逃跑穿过的那块空地上，手里拿着上好了子弹的步枪，而那两个黑人和一个白人回过头来轻蔑地看着他。他知道狮子已经死了。他抬腿向威尔逊走去，就连他高高的个子对他似乎也是赤裸裸的谴责。威尔逊看了他一眼说：

“想照相吗？”

“不了。”他说。

返回汽车的路上，谁都没有再说一句话。到了汽车跟前，才听见威尔逊说道：

“这头狮子真够棒的。让伙计们剥皮，咱俩可以到阴凉地歇歇去。”

麦康伯的妻子对丈夫看也不看，他也没有看她。两口子坐在后排，威尔逊坐在前排。当丈夫的曾经一度伸出手，拉住了妻子的手，眼睛却没有看她，而后者把手抽了回去。目光越过小河投向那两个扛枪人剥狮子皮的地方，他可以看出妻子将全过程都瞧在了眼里。两口子呆坐时，妻子朝前探探身子，把手搭在了威尔逊的肩膀上。威尔逊转过头来，而她欠起身子，趴在低矮的座位靠背上，在他的嘴上亲了一口。

“啊，哎呀。”威尔逊叫了一声，原本就红的脸变得更红了。

“这是给你的，罗伯特·威尔逊先生，”她说道，“英俊潇洒、红脸膛的罗伯特·威尔逊先生。”

说完，她又在麦康伯身旁坐了下来，眼睛却望着河对岸狮子横尸的地方，只见狮子的两条前腿朝天，皮正在被那两个黑人剥掉，露出白白的肌肉、腱子肉以及鼓胀胀、雪白的肚皮。最后，扛枪人干完活，把一张又湿又沉的狮子皮扛了回来，先是卷在一起，然后带着它爬上了汽车的尾部。汽车启动了。在返回营地的路上，没有一个人说话。

这就是猎狮的经过。那头狮子在开始发动攻击之前，以及在攻击的过程中被一颗初速度达两百英里的.505子弹以难以置信的冲击力射中嘴，究竟感觉怎么样，麦康伯一无所知。他也不知道在轰隆第二声枪响打烂了它的后半身，而它依然向那个轰隆作响、断送了它的东西爬去时，心里究竟有什么感受。对于这些，威尔逊是知道一些的，仅仅用这么一句话来表达：“简直是一头非常棒的狮子。”可是，至于威尔逊心里有什么感受，麦康伯是不知道的，他也不知道妻子的感受，只知道她心里已经和他决裂了。

妻子以前也跟他决裂过，但时间都不很长。他很有钱，以后会更有钱，所以他知道，即便现在她也不会离开他的。他真正知道的事情并不多，而这是其中之一。除此之外，他还知道摩托车（那是早年的事情了）和汽车方面的情况，知道怎样打野鸭、钓鱼（有鳟鱼、鲑鱼以及海鱼），知道书里的性爱故事（这方面的书很多，简直不计其数），熟知球类运动，知道怎样养狗（对于养马不太了解），知道怎样捂紧自己的钱口袋，对于他这个圈子遇到的情况大多都知道，还知道妻子绝不会离开他。妻子一直都是个大美女，在非洲仍是个大美女，但在国内却没有美丽到能离开他去享受更阔绰的人生，对此他俩都心中有数。她已经错失良机，无法再离开他了，这一点他是知道的。假如他善于猎艳，那她也许会多几分忧虑，害怕他另寻新欢，娶一房漂亮妻子，可是她对他太了解了，知道不必为此操心。再说，他一直都很宽宏大度，倘若这不是他最大的弱点，那就是最大的优点了。

总而言之，在别人眼里，他们是一对比较幸福的夫妻。这类夫妻，尽管街坊经常有谣传说要散伙，也绝对不会各奔东西的。至于他们到所谓的“黑暗非洲”狩猎，一位社交生活专栏记者说是“为他们备受羡慕、固若金汤的浪漫生活添上几分颇为冒险的色彩”。黑暗非洲是由马丁·约翰逊夫妇(5)照亮的，他们在非洲猎取狮子、野牛和大象，为自然史博物馆收集标本，并将这些场面拍成了多部电影。要说麦康伯两口子的关系，还是那位专栏记者报道说他们曾三次濒于离婚，实情也的确如此。不过，他们每一次都会重归于好，因为他们有着坚实的婚姻基础。玛戈太漂亮了，让麦康伯欲离难舍，而麦康伯的钱太多了，叫玛戈根本离不开他。

此刻大约是凌晨三点钟。弗朗西斯·麦康伯自打不再想那头狮子之后，稍微睡了一会儿，接着便睡睡醒醒的。他做了个梦，梦见那头狮子站在他面前，脑袋上血淋淋的，吓得他醒了过来。他侧耳听听动静，心里扑扑乱跳。他看看帐篷里另一张小床，发现妻子不在上面。他躺在那儿左思右想，有两个小时的时间。

两个小时之后，他的妻子回到了帐篷里，撩起蚊帐，舒舒服服爬到了床上。

“你去哪儿啦？”麦康伯在黑影里问。

“哦，”她回了一声，“醒着呢？”

“到哪里去了？”

“出去吸了口新鲜空气。”

“胡说八道。”

“你想让我说什么呢，亲爱的？”

“你到底去哪儿了？”

“去呼吸新鲜空气了呀。”

“这倒是个新借口。你这个骚货。”

“你呢？你是个胆小鬼。”

“胆小鬼就胆小鬼，”他说，“那又怎么样？”

“至于我，我不会怎么样的。算啦，不要再说了，亲爱的，我都快困死啦。”

“你以为我什么气都能咽得下去。”

“我知道你能咽得下去的，小心肝。”

“哼，我咽不下这口气。”

“求求你，亲爱的，别说了，我都快困死啦。”

“这种事是不应该发生的。你是答应过我的。”

“哎，现在事情已经如此了。”她语气甜蜜地说。

“你说过如果这次来旅行，你就不会再干这种事情了。这你是许诺过的。”

“不错，亲爱的。我的确是这么想的。可是，昨天把一切全给毁了。此事就不说了，好不好？”

“一有个机会，你就急不可耐，对不对？”

“请别说了，我困极了，亲爱的。”

“我就是要说。”

“那你就说你的吧，我反正是要睡了。”话刚说完，她就睡着了。

次日天未亮，三人坐在桌旁吃早餐。弗朗西斯·麦康伯觉得，在所有的仇人中，罗伯特·威尔逊是他不共戴天的头号仇敌。

“睡得还好吧？”威尔逊一边用他那喉音问了一声，一边往烟袋里装着烟丝。

“你呢？”

“好极啦。”白人猎手说。

“你这个王八蛋，嚣张的王八蛋！”麦康伯在心里骂道。

“看来，她进帐篷时把他给吵醒了。”威尔逊心想，一边用缺乏表情、冷冰冰的眼睛打量着那两口子，“哼，他为什么就不能管住自己的妻子，让她待在应该待的地方呢？他把我当成了什么——一尊麻木的石膏圣徒像吗？要怪都怪他管不住自己的妻子。毛病出在他自己身上。”

“你觉得咱们能找到野牛吗？”玛戈把一盘杏子推开，启口问道。

“机会是有的。”威尔逊冲她笑了笑说，“你为什么不留在营地里呢？”

“那是绝对不行的。”她说。

“你为什么不下一道命令，叫她留在营地里？”威尔逊对麦康伯说。

“这道命令还是由你下吧。”麦康伯冷冰冰地说。

“就不要下什么命令不命令的了。”玛戈又转过身对着麦康伯语气欢快地说：“你呢，就不要冒傻气了。”

“准备好出发了吗？”麦康伯问。

“随时都可以走。”威尔逊说，“你愿意让太太也跟着去吗？”

“我愿意不愿意又管什么用呢？”

罗伯特·威尔逊心想：“真是活见鬼！简直糟得一塌糊涂。早知道会闹成这样。哎，事已至此，只能这样了。”

“是的，是不管用。”他说。

“你敢肯定你不想陪她留在营地，让我自己去打野牛吗？”麦康伯问。

“这行不通。”威尔逊说，“我要是你，就不会说这么难听的话。”

“这不是说什么难听的话，而是我觉得恶心。”

“恶心就是一个难听的字眼。”

“弗朗西斯，你能不能说些通情达理的话！”麦康伯的妻子说道。

“我的话他妈的太通情达理了。”麦康伯说，“你吃过这么脏的东西吗？”

“难道这食物有问题吗？”威尔逊不动声色地问。

“不比别的事情问题更大。”

“我这就让你放下心来，先生。”威尔逊小声说，“这里有个负责饭菜的杂役，他懂得一点英语。”

“让他见鬼去吧。”

威尔逊立起身，抽着烟走开了，对一个正站在那儿等他的扛枪人用斯瓦希里语说了几句话。麦康伯和妻子仍坐在桌旁。他把眼睛盯在咖啡杯上。

“如果你胡闹，我就离开你，亲爱的。”玛戈平静地说。

“不，你不会的。”

“你可以试试看。”

“你绝不会离开我的。”

“那好，”她说，“我不离开你，你可要放规矩些。”

“让我放规矩？说的是屁话。要放规矩的是你自己。”

“是你。是你应该规矩些。”

“你为什么就不能做出努力，注意注意自己的行为呢？”

“我努力了，努力了很长时间，很长很长的时间。”

“我讨厌那个红脸猪猡。”麦康伯说，“一看见他，我就恨得牙根痒痒。”

“他是个挺不错的人。”

“哼，你还是闭上嘴吧。”麦康伯几乎吼了起来。就在这时，汽车开了过来，停在了餐厅帐篷前，司机和那两个扛枪人下了车。威尔逊走了过来，看了看仍坐在餐桌旁的这对夫妻。

“去打猎吗？”

“去。”麦康伯说着站起了身，“去的。”

“最好带件毛衣。车上有些凉。”威尔逊说。

“我去把我的皮夹克拿上。”玛戈说。

“杂役已经拿来了。”威尔逊对她说。他说完爬上车，坐到了前排，跟司机在一起，而弗朗西斯·麦康伯和妻子谁都没说话，坐到了后排。

“但愿这个愚蠢的家伙别一冲动，开枪把我的后脑勺打掉。”威尔逊暗自思忖，“打猎时带着女人真不方便。”

在灰蒙蒙的晨曦中，汽车嘎吱嘎吱开下河岸，从一处鹅卵石浅滩过了河，然后走“之”字形路，爬上对面陡峭的河岸。昨天威尔逊叫人开出了一条路来，这样汽车就能开到远处去了——那儿林木茂盛，连绵起伏，跟猎苑一样。

“真是个美好的早晨。”威尔逊心想。露水很重。汽车轮子碾过青草和低矮的灌木丛，可以闻到被碾碎了的蕨叶散发出的清香。这气味和马鞭草的味道很相像。汽车行驶在这一片人迹罕至的猎苑似的地带，而他欢喜地嗅着清晨露水的气味，嗅着被碾碎的蕨类植物散发的芳香，欣赏着在晨雾里隐隐发暗的一根根树干。此刻，他把后排的那两口子忘到了九霄云外，心里盘算着打野牛的事情。他要猎杀的野牛白天待在沼泽泥地里，根本无法到跟前猎杀。可是在夜间，野牛会来到这一片空地上吃草。如果把汽车开过去，阻断它们回沼泽地的路径，麦康伯的机会就来了，可以在这开阔地开枪射击。他并不想和麦康伯来这块林木茂盛的地方打野牛。不管是打野牛还是别的什么猎物，他压根就不愿意跟麦康伯在一起。不过，他毕竟是个职业猎手，曾经陪许多稀奇古怪的人一起打过猎。假如今天能猎杀到野牛，接下来该猎杀的就只剩下犀牛了。那时，这个可怜的家伙就可以结束这种危险的游戏了，情况也许能好转。那时，他就斩断跟这个女人的情缘，而麦康伯也会恢复过来的。看上去，这种事情麦康伯一定经历过不少。真是个可怜蛋！他一定有自己的方法恢复过来的。哎，这个可怜虫，要怪也要怪他自己。

他，罗伯特·威尔逊，每次打猎都带着一张双人床，准备迎接任何飞来的艳遇。他陪各种国籍的客户打猎，有些客户放荡不羁、玩世不恭。有些女客户如果不和这位白人猎手分享分享他的双人床，就觉得自己的钱花得不值。在交往中，有些女人他还是挺喜欢的，可是一旦分手，便从心里瞧不起她们。不过，话又说回来，他是靠这些人谋生的。只要受雇于他们，他们的标准就是他的标准。

只有在打猎时，他们要服从于他的标准。对于打猎，他是有自己的标准的，客户要是不服从，那就请他们另寻高手去。他很清楚，客户们为此对他心怀敬意。不过，这个麦康伯却是个怪家伙，简直古怪极了。他的那个妻子……他的那个妻子嘛……哎，他的那个妻子嘛……想到此处，他就不再往下想了，而是回头看了看那两口子——麦康伯阴沉着脸，怒容满面；玛戈则冲他嫣然一笑。她看上去比平时年轻、天真，也比平时水灵，这种美并非矫揉造作的美。天知道她心里在想什么。昨天夜里，她的废话不多。就冲这一点，他还是蛮愿意见她的。

汽车爬上一个小土坡，穿过树林，来到了一片开阔的草地上，望上去像大草原一样。他们在树的遮蔽下贴着草地边走，司机把车开得很慢，威尔逊仔细观察着草原的动静，然后把目光投向远处。他让汽车停下，用望远镜瞭望了一番。随后，他叫司机继续把车朝前开。汽车慢慢行驶，一路绕过疣猪挖的洞穴以及蚂蚁筑起的土围子。威尔逊扫视着开阔地，然后突然转过身说：

“上帝呀，它们原来在那儿！”

汽车颠簸着冲上前去，威尔逊用斯瓦希里语急促地对司机说着什么。麦康伯顺着他指的方向望去，看见了三个庞然大物般的黑色野兽，身躯长大，几乎呈圆柱形，看上去像黑颜色的大油罐车，此时在开阔的草地上顺着远处的边缘飞奔。它们快如风，脖子僵硬，身子也硬挺挺的，脑袋前抵，一动不动，一对宽宽的黑犄角向上翘起。

“那是三只老公牛。”威尔逊说，“咱们去把它们的路截断，别让它们跑进沼泽地。”

汽车以一小时四十五英里的速度在草地上狂奔。麦康伯观望着，看见野牛变得越来越大，最后看清了其中一只大个子公牛的样子——灰色，无毛，满身疥癣，脖子和肩膀连在一起，一对犄角黑得发亮。它跟着同伴们，在稍微靠后一点的地方。三只公牛排成一列，迈着稳稳的步子向前冲去。汽车颠了颠，摇晃了几下，好像跳过一条路似的。车开到跟前时，可以看到奔逃的公牛是多么庞大，稀稀拉拉长着几根毛的牛皮上满是尘土，可以看到它那宽宽的犄角管以及那张得大大的、宽宽的鼻孔。他一边看着一边拿起了步枪。此刻只听威尔逊大叫一声：“笨蛋，别从车上开枪！”此时他毫无畏怯之心，只有对威尔逊的仇恨。司机踩了一脚刹车，汽车猛地停住，车身向旁边一斜。没等车停稳，威尔逊从一侧跳下车，而他从另一侧跳下车，双脚踏上好像仍在快速移动的土地，不由打了个趔趄。他朝着逃窜的公牛开了一枪，听见子弹噗的一声射进了牛身子，接着一枪又一枪，把子弹全打光了，而公牛仍在迈着稳稳的步子奔逃。这时他才记起应该朝前瞄一些把子弹射入牛的肩膀。正当他摸索着重新上子弹时，看见那只公牛倒下去了，跪在地上，巨大的头颅朝上扬了扬。他见另外两只牛仍在飞奔，于是便向前边的那只射击，一枪命中。他又开了一枪，这次打偏了，却听见轰隆一声巨响，原来是威尔逊开了枪。只见前边的那只牛向前一窜，一个倒栽葱倒了下去。

“打另外的一只！”威尔逊说，“现在才是你亮枪法的时候。”

另外的那只公牛仍在疾奔，步子还是那么稳。他开了一枪，没打中，扬起一股尘土，威尔逊开枪也打偏了，子弹着地处升起一片尘云。只听威尔逊大叫一声：“咱们追去。隔得太远了！”随即一把拽住了他的胳膊。两人回到车上，一边一个站在踏板上，汽车左右摇晃着在坑洼不平的地面上飞驰，逼近那只梗着脖子、迈着稳稳步子向前冲的公牛。

汽车追到了公牛的身后。麦康伯给枪里装子弹，几颗子弹掉在了地上，而枪膛里卡了壳，等他排除了障碍，汽车眼看就追上公牛了。此时却听见威尔逊喊了一声“停车”，汽车一个急刹车，差点没向旁边侧翻。麦康伯身子朝前一倾，然后站稳了脚跟。他咔地推上枪栓，尽可能向前瞄准，对着那只狂奔不止的公牛，向它那圆滚滚的黑色脊背开了一枪，接着又一枪一枪地持续射击，枪枪命中，但可以看到没有一枪是致命的。这时，威尔逊开枪了，声音大得能把耳朵震聋，只见公牛脚步一踉跄。麦康伯仔细瞄准，又开了一枪，公牛倒下去了，跪在了地上。

“很好，”威尔逊说，“干得漂亮，三只全报销了。”

麦康伯高兴得飘飘欲仙。

“你开了几枪？”他问道。

“只开了三枪。”威尔逊说，“头一只是你打死的。那只最大。另外两只是我帮了你一把，把它们撂倒了，怕的是它们会躲起来。反正它们都是你干掉的，我只是帮衬了一把罢了。你的枪法棒极了。”

“走，回车上去，”麦康伯说，“我想喝上一杯。”

“先把这只牛结果了再走。”威尔逊说。那只牛跪在地上，见他们走上前去，便狂怒地摆动着脑袋，牛眼圆睁，怒气冲天地大吼大叫。

“小心点，别让它站起来。”威尔逊叮咛道，“站得稍微偏一些，对准它的耳朵根，在它的脖子上来一枪。”

麦康伯仔细瞄准公牛那粗壮的、愤怒地摆来摆去的脖子，冲着脖子的正中心开了一枪。枪声一响，公牛的脑袋耷拉了下来。

“这下好了。”威尔逊说，“打到脊椎上了。这几只牛看上去很棒，是不是？”

“走，喝酒去吧。”麦康伯说。他感觉好极了，一生中从来都没有过这样好的感觉。

他的妻子正坐在车上，脸色惨白惨白。“你真是棒极啦，亲爱的。”她对丈夫说，“车开得快极了。”

“颠簸得厉害吗？”威尔逊问。

“吓死人啦。我这一生从来都没有这样害怕过。”

“大家伙都来喝酒吧。”麦康伯说。

“乐于从命。”威尔逊说，“先让太太喝一口吧。”

玛戈接过酒瓶喝了一口精纯的威士忌，把酒咽下肚时身子哆嗦了一下。接着，她把酒瓶递给了麦康伯，而后者随手将其给了威尔逊。

“刺激，惊悚，”她说，“看得我脑袋疼得厉害。允许你们从车上开枪，这我是不知道的。”

“没有人从车上开枪呀。”威尔逊用冷冷的语气说。

“我是说驱车追赶它们。”

“一般情况下是不会这样做的。不过，驱车追赶，我觉得很好玩。开车穿过坑坑洼洼的平原，险情不断，这比徒步狩猎更具冒险性。每次开枪，野牛一发性子，都有可能会向我们冲来。它有的是机会。此事不便向任何人提起，说起来这可是违法的。”

“乘坐汽车追赶那些可怜无助的大牲口，”玛戈说，“在我看来十分不公平。”

“是吗？”威尔逊说。

“假如内罗毕得知这种情况，会怎么样呢？”

“首先，会吊销我的执照。除此之外，还会有其他不愉快的事情。”威尔逊拿起酒瓶喝了一口说，“那时，我就没饭碗了。”

“真的？”

“是真的。”

“好呀，”麦康伯说，一天里头一次露出了笑容，“这下子她可抓住你的短处了。”

“瞧你把话说得难听的，弗朗西斯。”玛戈·麦康伯说。

威尔逊看了看这两口子，心想：“半斤的男人娶了个八两的妻子，谁知道他们的孩子会是几斤几两呢。”心里这么想，他嘴上说的却是另一码事：“一个扛枪人不见了。你们注意到了吗？”

“我的上帝，没注意到。”麦康伯说。

“哦，他过来了，”威尔逊说，“没事的。他肯定是打完第一只公牛开车走的时候摔下车去了。”

那个中年扛枪人一瘸一拐地在渐渐走近。他头戴编织帽，上身穿卡其布衫，下穿短裤，足蹬橡胶凉鞋，阴沉着脸，一副闷闷不乐的表情。走到跟前时，叽里呱啦用斯瓦希里语冲威尔逊大声说了些什么，大家都看到这位白人猎手脸色大变。

“他说什么来着？”玛戈问。

“他说头一只公牛站起来，藏进灌木丛里去了。”威尔逊说道，声音里一点波动都没有。

“哦？”麦康伯茫然地说。

“这次又要跟打狮子的那次一模一样了。”玛戈充满期待地说。

“跟打狮子的那次没有一点相似之处。”威尔逊说，“还要来口酒吗，麦康伯？”

“谢谢，再来一口吧。”麦康伯说。他以为猎狮子时的那种感觉又会回到心头，但这样的情况没有出现。他平生第一次真正地有了一种毫无畏惧的感觉。代替畏惧感的是显而易见的喜悦情绪。

“走，去看看第二只公牛。”威尔逊说，“我叫司机把车停在阴凉地。”

“去干什么来着？”玛格丽特·麦康伯问。

“去看看公牛。”威尔逊说。

“我也去。”

“那就走吧。”

三个人走过去到开阔的野地，只见第二只公牛躺在那儿，又黑又大，脑袋向前耷拉在草地上，两只犄角朝两边分开，中间隔得很宽。

“这只公牛的头真是漂亮，”威尔逊说，“两只犄角之间的距离差不多有五十英寸。”

麦康伯兴致勃勃地望着那只牛。

“样子狰狞可怕。”玛戈说，“能不能到阴凉地里去？”

“当然可以。”威尔逊说。随后他又用手指着对麦康伯说：“看见那片灌木丛了吗？”

“看见了。”

“第一只公牛就躲在了那里。那个扛枪人说，他摔下车时，那只牛正躺在地上。他光顾着看咱们拼命地追赶另外两只逃窜的牛了，后来瞧了瞧跟前，见躺在地上的牛站了起来，正盯着他望呢。他吓得撒丫子就跑，而那只牛慢慢悠悠地走开，躲进了那片灌木丛里。”

“是不是需要进去把它找出来？”麦康伯急切地问。

威尔逊把他打量了几眼，心想：“真是邪了门了。昨天他还吓得屁滚尿流，今天就天不怕地不怕的。”

“暂时别去，让它再活一会儿。”

“还是到阴凉地里去吧。”玛戈说。她脸色苍白，像病了一样。

三人寻路回到汽车跟前（汽车停放在一棵枝叶宽展如盖的孤树底下），全都爬上了车。

“也许它已经死在了那里。”威尔逊说，“过一会儿咱们去看看。”

麦康伯莫名其妙地感到一阵狂喜，那是一种以前从未体验过的狂喜心情。

“上帝呀，去追杀它！”他说道，“这种激动的心情我以前从未有过。真是扣人心弦，你说是不是，玛戈？”

“我讨厌。”

“为什么？”

“反正我就是讨厌。”她痛苦地说，“我感到的是厌恶。”

“要知道，我觉得自己以后什么都不会再害怕了。”麦康伯对威尔逊说，“自打一眼看见公牛，并开始追杀时，我的内心就发生了变化，就像有一道堤坝决了口一样。这是一种彻彻底底的激动心情。”

“就像是五脏六腑被水清洗过了一样吧？”威尔逊说，“一些奇怪的现象的确会发生在人们的身上。”

麦康伯满面生辉。“要知道，我的身上的确发生了变化。”他说道，“我感觉像变了一个人一样。”

他的妻子什么也没说，以异样的目光看了看他。她身子靠后坐在座位上，而麦康伯身子前倾跟威尔逊滔滔不绝地说话，后者则扭过身隔着前排的椅背回话。

“要知道，我很想再去猎杀一头狮子。”麦康伯说，“现在，我对狮子真的不感到害怕了。说到底，它们能把你怎么样呢？”

“是这么回事。”威尔逊说，“大不了就是命一条嘛。那是怎么说的来着？莎士比亚说的真是他妈的好。让我想想，看能不能想起来。啊，说的真是太精彩了。以前有段时间，我倒是经常引用他的这段话的。大概是这么说的：‘说实在的，我对死亡并不在乎。人生在世谁无死？人人都欠上帝一条命，该怎么还就怎么还吧，今年死了，明年就不用死了。’(6)你说精彩不精彩？”

一口气说出了自己的生活信条，他觉得很不好意思。不过，男人突然长大成熟，这他是见过的，每一次见了心里都大受感动。这种感动可不是看见人们过二十一岁成年生日的那种感动。

由于一次奇异的机会参加狩猎，没有事先精心筹划，而是仓促行动起来，结果这种变化发生在了麦康伯身上。不管它是怎么发生的，铁的事实是它已经发生了。威尔逊心想，现在再看看这个家伙吧！有些人在很长时间里都是小孩子，有些甚至终身都是小孩子，都五十岁了还一身孩子气。美国男人就是孩子气十足，真是一些奇怪的人。不过，他现在喜欢上了麦康伯。这个家伙怪怪的。也许，这意味着他和玛戈暧昧的关系结束了。啊，那将是大好事情！一件非常好的事情！这个窝囊废大概一直都唯唯诺诺的，不知是什么原因造成的，而现在这种现象结束了。他刚才没有时间对公牛产生害怕的心情，再加上肚子里窝了一团火，还有汽车也发生了作用——汽车消除了一些生疏感。反正他现在成了一个英勇无畏的人。战争中也见过这种转变，转变之大胜过失去童贞。恐惧感消失了，像做手术割除了似的。取而代之的是另一样东西，一样男人所应该具有的重要的东西——正是这样东西使男人成为男子汉。对于这样东西，女人是很清楚的。总之，麦康伯已经丝毫没有恐惧之心了。

玛格丽特·麦康伯从座位的角落里打量着这两个男人。威尔逊没有变化，还是昨天的那个男人——当时她第一次发现他是个很有本事的人。而在弗朗西斯·麦康伯身上她看出了变化。

“对于即将发生的事情，你有没有一种兴奋的感觉？”麦康伯仍沉浸在一片全新的天地里，于是这样问道。

“这种心情是不应该讲出来的。”威尔逊看着对方的脸说，“还不如说自己感到害怕，这样倒时尚得多。注意，你还会害怕的，还会害怕许多次呢。”

“但对这一次即将采取的行动，你有没有一种兴奋的感觉？”

“有。”威尔逊说，“有倒是有的，只是不要多说就是了。话说多了，就没有意思了。话说三遍淡如水嘛。”

“你们俩闲扯个啥劲！”玛戈说，“就因为开着汽车追杀可怜无助的动物，你们说起话就像英雄人物一样！”

“对不起，”威尔逊说，“我空话说得太多了。”他心里觉得她在为此担惊受怕。

“如果你不知道我们在谈什么，为什么就不能不干涉呢？”麦康伯问妻子。

“你一下子变得异常勇敢了，怪突然的。”他妻子以轻蔑的语气说，但这种语气缺乏底气，像是有很大的顾忌。

麦康伯哈哈大笑了起来，开怀大笑了起来。“我是变了，”他说，“的确变了。”

“这变化是不是来得太晚了些？”玛戈苦涩地说。这许多年来，她已经竭尽全力了。一个巴掌拍不响，目前的状况并不是她一个人造成的。

“对我而言并不晚。”麦康伯说。

玛戈没吱声，又坐回到了角落里。

“你看咱们给它的时间够长的了吧？”麦康伯高高兴兴地问威尔逊。

“可以去看看了。”威尔逊说，“实心弹还有吗？”

“扛枪人那里还有一些。”

威尔逊用斯瓦希里语喊了一声，那个年纪大些的扛枪人正在剥公牛头皮，听见后直起身来，从衣袋里掏出一盒实心弹，走过来递给了麦康伯。麦康伯给弹仓里装满子弹，将剩余的放入了自己的衣袋。

“你可以用斯普林菲尔德步枪打，”威尔逊说，“这是你用惯了的。把这支曼利彻尔步枪留在车上让太太看管。你的扛枪人替你拿上大枪，我自己拿着这‘大炮’。接下来我给你介绍一下情况。”他把这一项放到最后，是不想让麦康伯生出顾虑来，“公牛冲过来时，会把头扬得高高的，端直朝前冲。犄角管护着它的大脑，子弹打不穿。要打只能直接打它的鼻子，还有一处可打的地方是它的胸脯。如果你是在侧面，就打它的脖子或肩膀。一枪没有毙命，要最后结果它可就费事了。你可不要耍什么新花样。找最致命的地方打。他们把牛的头皮剥完了。咱们出发吧？”

他冲着那两个扛枪人喊了一声，两人擦着手走了过来，那个年纪大些的坐到了汽车的尾部。

“我只带康格尼，”威尔逊说，“另一个留下来轰鸟。”

汽车慢慢悠悠穿过开阔的野地，向那片岛屿一样的灌木林开去。那片灌木林看上去形状像舌头，枝叶纵横交错，沿着一条经过洼地的干涸的河道延伸。麦康伯觉得自己的心怦怦乱跳，又一次感到嘴发干，不过不是由于恐惧，而是激动所致。

“它就是从这儿钻进去的。”威尔逊说。接着，他用斯瓦希里语对那个扛枪人说：“顺着血迹朝前找。”

汽车开到与灌木林平行的地方，麦康伯、威尔逊和那个扛枪人一起下了车。麦康伯回头望了望，看见妻子在盯着他瞧，身旁放着那支步枪。他冲她挥了挥手，而对方没有挥手作答。

灌木长得非常稠密，地面干干的。那个中年扛枪人汗流不止。威尔逊朝下压了压帽子，把帽檐遮在眼上方，红红的脖子正好挡在麦康伯的前边。突然，那个扛枪人用斯瓦希里语对威尔逊说了句什么，随后向前跑去。

“牛已经死了，”威尔逊说，“干得漂亮。”说完，他一把抓起了麦康伯的手，两人一边握手一边冲对方咧着嘴微笑。就在这时，耳旁传来了扛枪人的狂呼乱叫声，接着就见他斜刺里从灌木林冲了出来，快得像一阵风，而那只公牛紧随其后，牛鼻子前伸，嘴巴紧闭，鲜血淋漓，巨大的脑袋直直地朝前戳着，猛地冲了过来，眼睛小得似猪眼，布满了血丝，死死盯着他们。走在前边的威尔逊跪下射击，麦康伯也开了一枪，由于威尔逊的枪响声太大，他没有听见自己的枪声，只看到公牛巨大的犄角管碎片纷飞，像是瓦片被击碎了一样。牛头猛地摆了摆，他朝着宽宽的牛鼻孔又开了一枪，却见牛犄角又震动了一下，随之碎片纷飞。此刻，他看不见威尔逊了，只见野牛那庞大的身躯山一样压了过来，便仔细瞄准，又开了一枪。他的枪管几乎快碰到那急速冲过来的牛头和前伸的牛鼻子。他可以看到那双邪恶的小眼睛，接着看见牛头开始下垂。他感到自己的脑袋里猛地白光一闪，火一样热，让人睁不开眼睛——这就是他所有的感觉了。

刚才，威尔逊闪身躲到一旁，朝着公牛的肩膀开了一枪。麦康伯则站在原地，朝牛鼻子开枪，每一次都偏高一些，击中的是沉重的牛犄角，像击中了房瓦一样，打得牛犄角碎片纷飞。麦康伯夫人见牛犄角马上就要戳到丈夫，急忙用那支6.5口径的曼利彻尔步枪向野牛开枪，结果却射中了丈夫，打在了他脑袋底部朝上约两英寸，向旁边稍微偏一些的地方。

此时，弗朗西斯·麦康伯倒了下去，脸朝下，而公牛躺在旁边不到两码的地方。他的妻子跪在他跟前，威尔逊守在她身边。

“我觉得还是不要把他的身子翻过来了。”威尔逊说。

玛戈歇斯底里地痛哭流涕。

“我回车上去。”威尔逊说，“那支步枪在哪里？”

她摇了摇头，面部已经变了形。那个扛枪人把步枪捡了起来。

“把它留在原来的地方！”威尔逊说，“你去把阿卜杜拉找来，让他对事故现场做个见证。”

随后，他跪下来，从衣袋里取出块手帕，盖在弗朗西斯·麦康伯那头发短得像划船手发型一样的脑袋上。鲜血浸入了松软的干土里。

威尔逊立起身子，看了看侧躺着的野牛，见它腿伸得直挺挺的，肚皮上的毛稀稀拉拉，爬满了虱子。“好一只公牛！角距足足有五十英寸，或者更多一些。肯定更多一些！”他的大脑机械地将这只牛记了下来。他把司机叫了来，让司机把一块毯子盖在尸体上，然后守在跟前。接下来，他走到汽车那儿，而那个女人正坐在汽车的角落里哭泣。

“这样也好，”他用一种平淡的声音说，“反正他会离开你的。”

“别说了！”女人说。

“这完全是一次意外的事故。”他仍在说，“这我是知道的。”

“别说了！”女人说。

“别担心。”他又说道，“接下来还会有一连串令人不愉快的事情发生，但我会叫他们拍些照片，验尸的时候会非常有用的。扛枪人和司机也可以提供证词，你肯定不会有事的。”

“别说了！”女人说。

“事情千头万绪，还有许多工作要做呢。”他仍在说，“我得派一辆卡车去湖边发封电报，联系一架飞机接咱们三个去内罗毕。你为什么不用毒药毒死他呢？在英国她们都是这么做的。”

“别说啦！别说啦！别说啦！”女人失声叫了起来。

威尔逊用他那双缺乏感情的蓝眼睛打量着她。

“我的职责算是尽到了。”他说，“我刚才有点生气。我本来开始喜欢上你丈夫了。”

“天呀，求求你别说啦！”女人说，“求求你别说啦！”

“这样才像回事。”威尔逊说，“求人才像回事。现在我就不说了。”

————————————————————

(1) 打猎时，专门负责剥兽皮的人。

(2) 玛格丽特的爱称。

(3) 羚羊头以及羚羊角主要用来做标本或装饰品。

(4) 1格令=0.0648克。

(5) 同为美国著名电影摄影师。

(6) 引自莎士比亚戏剧《亨利四世（下）》第三幕第二场。

世界之都

在马德里，到处都有叫帕克的男孩，这是“弗朗西斯科”一名的爱称。马德里流传着一则笑话，据说一位父亲来马德里，在《自由报》私人广告栏登了一条启事说：“帕克，星期二来蒙塔纳饭店见我。往事一概不究。——父。”看了启事跑来的年轻人竟有八百人之多，最后叫来一个中队的骑警才把他们驱散。卢阿卡寄宿公寓的餐厅里有个侍者也叫帕克，但他既没有父亲原谅他，也没有过错需要父亲的原谅。他有两个姐姐在卢阿卡当房间服务员，谋得此职得益于同村的一个女子，那女子曾在卢阿卡做服务员，由于干活勤快和待人诚恳为自己的村子以及同村人赢得了好口碑。这两个姐姐给弟弟钱，让他乘汽车来到马德里，为他弄了份侍者学徒的工作。他来自于埃克斯塔马杜拉大区的一个村庄，那儿的生活条件原始得让人无法相信，食物匮乏，使人舒适的享受就更谈不上了。自打记事，他只知道拼命干活。

他体格健美，乌黑乌黑的头发有点卷曲，牙齿雪白，皮肤细腻，叫他的姐姐羡慕不已；平时，他的脸上老挂着明朗的笑容。他做事麻利，把活儿干得有声有色。他爱自己的两个面容美丽、懂得人情世故的姐姐，爱好得仍叫他难以置信的马德里，爱自己的工作——干活时身穿晚礼服，灯火辉煌，餐桌的桌布一尘不染，厨房里食物丰盛，似乎有着浪漫的瑰丽色彩。

在卢阿卡，另外还有八九个或十来个人，他们都来餐厅里吃饭。餐厅里有三个侍者，帕克是最年轻的一个。但在他看来，真正存在的只有那些斗牛士。

这家公寓里住的是些二流斗牛士，因为公寓地处圣哲罗尼莫，位置好，吃的棒，而且食宿费便宜。斗牛士是需要顾面子的，即便不能飞黄腾达，起码也得体面一些，因为体面和尊严比勇气还重要，在西班牙是最有价值的。斗牛士怎么都要住在卢阿卡，直至口袋里的比塞塔(1)全花光。据说，没有一个斗牛士搬出卢阿卡，住进档次更高、更豪华的饭店——二流斗牛士就是二流，永远也不会成为一流的。不过，一旦离开了卢阿卡，他们的境况就会日落西山。凡是能在此处住宿的人都是可以挣些钱的，不自己提出，老板娘绝不会将账单交给客人，除非老板娘知道这位客人已到了山穷水尽的地步。

眼下，卢阿卡住着三个正式的斗牛士，另外还有两位出类拔萃的骑马长枪手和一个优秀的徒步短枪手(2)。这几个长枪手和短枪手家住塞维利亚，春季赛来马德里求宿，住卢阿卡对他们而言算是奢侈的了。不过，他们薪酬高，有固定的职位，雇用他们的斗牛士对于即将到来的赛季全都签订了重金合同。按说，这三个副手不管哪一个都比此处三个斗牛士中的任何一个挣的钱要多得多。三个斗牛士中的一个在生病，却装出一副没病的样子；另一个曾走红过，但那只是昙花一现；第三个则是个懦夫。

这个懦夫曾经天不怕地不怕，技艺高超，可是在作为正式斗牛士参加的第一个赛季，一出场就叫公牛用犄角在小肚子上戳了一下，伤情很重，以后就变得胆小了。他风光的时候气度豪爽，其中许多意气风发的素质保留至今。他谈笑风生，乐呵呵的，不管有没有原因，都时常会哈哈大笑。当年功成名就时，他喜欢搞恶作剧，现在却已放弃了这项娱乐。很可能是没有这份心情了吧。这个斗牛士看上去不乏智慧，有一张坦率的面孔，言谈举止颇有风度。

生病的那位斗牛士处处留意，不让病态显现出来，小心翼翼的，摆上桌的饭菜每一样怎么都要吃上几口。他有许多手帕，而这些手帕他都是在房间里自己洗。最近，他在出售他的斗牛服，圣诞节前低价卖出了一套，四月份的头一个星期又售出了一套。这些衣服原本是很贵重的，一直保存得很好，现在却只剩下一套了。患病之前，他曾经一度前途似锦，是个轰动一时的斗牛士。他目不识丁，却收集了一些剪报，剪报上说他在马德里的初场表演比贝尔蒙特(3)还高一筹。现在，他孤零零一个人守在一张小餐桌旁就餐，很少抬起头来。

那个曾走红过，但名气只是昙花一现的斗牛士，个子矮小，有着黝黑的皮肤，显出一副很尊贵的样子。他也是独自一人在一张单独的餐桌旁吃饭，很少露出笑容，更不用说哈哈大笑了。他的家乡在巴利亚多利德，那里的人都不苟言笑。他是个有本事的斗牛士，然而没等他靠勇敢无畏、镇定自若的优秀素质成功赢得公众的青睐，他的风格就已经过时了。他的名字登在海报上，是绝不会吸引人去观赛的。他的独特之处在于他是个“三寸丁”，矮到连公牛的肩隆都看不到，但身材矮的斗牛士又不止他一个。于是他没有能够持久地吸引住公众的眼球。

长枪手里有个瘦子，长得像老鹰，灰白头发，并不强壮，胳膊腿却硬得似铁棍。他裤管下总穿着一双牧牛人的靴子，每天晚上都灌大量的黄汤，见公寓里出现个女人，便色眯眯盯着看。另一位长枪手是个大块头，肤色黝黑，古铜色脸膛，相貌堂堂，头发黑得像印第安人，一双手似簸箕一样大。两人都是很棒的长枪手。只不过，据说头一个因为酒色过度而能力大减，第二个则刚愎自用，喜欢吵架，跟任何一个斗牛士共事都不会超过一个赛季。

那位短枪手是个中年人，头发霜染，可是尽管有了一把岁数，却敏捷得像只猫。在餐桌旁坐着，他看上去倒有点像个商人，生意经营得不错。这个赛季，他的手脚依然好使。每当用到这副手脚时，他都会运用智慧和经验确保自己受到雇用，而且能长期受到雇用。问题在于：他脚下的速度早晚会变慢的，那是一定会叫他担心的。不过目前，他还是挺有信心的，挺淡定的，无论场内场外均如此。

这天晚上，大家吃完饭都走了，餐厅里只剩下了那个鹰脸长枪手，他喝酒喝多了。另外还有一个脸上印着胎记的生意人和两个加利西亚省来的牧师。这位生意人一旦国内有个节日，都会到集市上拍卖手表，此时也把酒喝过了头。两个牧师坐在墙角的一张餐桌旁，即便喝酒喝得不算过多，肯定也不少了。当时，在卢阿卡，酒钱是含在食宿费里边的。侍者又拎来几瓶瓦尔德帕那葡萄酒，先送到那个拍卖商的桌上，再依次送给长枪手以及那两个牧师。三位侍者均守候在餐厅的一端。

卢阿卡有个规矩：所有的侍者都应该坚守岗位，不等自己负责的客人全部离开餐桌，不得随便走掉。可这一次，负责两个牧师那张餐桌的侍者有个约会，要去参加一个无政府工团主义者会议，帕克答应过为他伺候那张餐桌。

楼上，那个生病的斗牛士脸朝下独自趴在床上。那位风光不再的斗牛士则坐在窗前向外边张望，想出去到咖啡馆散散心。而那个懦夫斗牛士此时把帕克的姐姐扣在自己房间里调情，千方百计想让她如自己的愿，而帕克的姐姐呵呵笑着加以拒绝。斗牛士说：“来吧，小野人。”

“不。”帕克的姐姐说，“我图个什么？”

“行个方便嘛。”

“你酒足饭饱，现在可拿我当餐后点心哟。”

“就这么一次嘛。有什么害处呢？”

“别碰我！我告诉你别碰我！”

“这只不过是小事一桩嘛。”

“我告诉你别碰我！”

在楼下的餐厅里，那个个子最高的侍者此时已误了开会的时间。只听他说道：“瞧那两个黑猪喝酒的样子。”

“不能这样说话，”另一位侍者说，“他们可是体面的顾客，酒又喝得不算太多。”

“我觉得这样说他们没什么不妥当的。”高个子说，“西班牙有两大公害，一是公牛，二是牧师。”

“这当然指的不是具体的某一条公牛和某一个牧师。”另一个侍者说。

“不对。”高个子侍者说，“只有拿个体开刀，才能向整个阶级发动进攻。应该把每一条公牛和每一个牧师斩尽杀绝，一个不剩，那时就再也没有这样的公害了。”

“这种话还是留在开会时说吧。”另一个侍者说。

“瞧瞧马德里的这种不人道的现象吧，”高个子侍者说，“都十一点半了，这些家伙还在大吃大喝。”

“他们是十点钟才开始吃的呀。”另一个侍者说，“你也知道，菜上得挺多，酒又便宜。酒是付过钱的，度数也不高。”

“有你这样的傻瓜，工人阶级怎么能团结在一起呢？”高个子侍者问。

“听着，”这另一个侍者已到了知天命的年纪，此时只听他回话说，“我干了一辈子活，后半生还要继续干活。对此，我没有什么牢骚话。干活是天经地义的事情。”

“不错，可你不干活是活不下去的。”

“所以我一直在干。”这位年纪稍大些的侍者说，“你去开你的会吧，没必要守在这里了。”

“你是个好同志，”高个子侍者说，“但就是缺乏思想。”

“Mejor si me falta eso que el otro(4)，”年纪稍大些的侍者说（意思是缺思想总比缺活干好），“去开你的会吧。”

帕克一句话也没说过。他不懂政治，但听到高个子侍者提到要把牧师和警察斩尽杀绝，不由热血沸腾。在他看来，高个子侍者代表的是革命，而革命具有浪漫的色彩。他本人很想成为一名虔诚的天主教徒，成为一名革命者；他既想有一份这样的稳定工作，又想当一个斗牛士。

“去开会吧，伊格纳西奥。”他说，“你的活我替你负责干。”

“我们两个替你干。”年纪稍大些的侍者说。

“一个人就足够了。”帕克说，“开会去吧。”

“好吧，那我就走了。(5)”高个子侍者说，“谢谢喽。”

就在这个时候，帕克的姐姐在楼上从那个斗牛士的怀里挣脱开，动作巧妙得就跟摔跤运动员摆脱了对手的纠缠一样，怒容满面地说：“都是些饿狼似的人。你当斗牛士是个窝囊废，胆小如鼠。你有本事，就到斗牛场上露一手呀。”

“你个婊子，怎么这么说话！”

“婊子也是人。再说，我也不是个婊子。”

“你会成为婊子的。”

“再怎么也不跟你干那种事。”

“你走吧。”斗牛士说。由于遭到拒绝和驳斥，他顿感懦夫的本性又回到了他身上。

“让我走？你还有什么本事呢？”帕克的姐姐说，“你难道不想让我为你把床铺好吗？我拿薪酬是干这种活儿的。”

“你走吧。”斗牛士又说了一声。他那张宽宽的英俊的脸都变了形，皱成了一团，像是要哭了。“走吧，你个婊子，你个臭婊子。”

“好吧，斗牛士，”帕克的姐姐走时，一边随手将门关上一边说道，“好吧，我的斗牛士。”

在房间里，这位斗牛士坐在床上，面部仍扭曲着。斗牛时，他往往会在这张脸上堆起笑容，叫坐在头排的观众看了担忧，因为他们看得出那笑容里包含着怎样的酸楚。“竟然到了这样的地步。”他想着想着说出了声，“竟然到了这样的地步。竟然到了这样的地步。”

他曾经风光一时，对此他仍记忆犹新。那只不过是三年前的事情。他记得那是在一个五月份的炎热的下午出的事。当时他穿着沉甸甸的金色锦缎斗牛服，在斗牛场上说话的声音跟他在咖啡馆时一样充满了自信，记得刺杀牛时，自己的目光顺着剑锋望去，瞄准了公牛两肩中间突起的地方，那儿蒙着灰尘，是一团黑色的长着短毛的隆起的肌肉，而下首便是低垂的牛角——那牛角宽宽的，尖端已经裂开，冲锋时能把树木撞倒。他记得他把剑刺进了牛的身体，容易得就像刺进了一块硬硬的奶酪里，手掌用力推剑柄，左胳膊弯得低低的，左肩膀前倾，全身的重量压在左腿上，后来重心突然偏移，转移到了小肚子上——公牛抬起了头，将犄角刺进了他的小肚子里。他被犄角顶起甩了两下，才被人们救了下来。现在，他刺杀公牛时，这种机会已经不多，十有八九都会不由自主地先胆怯地望望牛的犄角。投入战斗之前便有了畏怯之心，这种窘态一个婊子是怎么知道的呢？这些人竟然耻笑他，心里不知怎么想的呢！婊子毕竟是婊子，懂得怎样利用这一点做做文章。

此时在楼下的餐厅里，那个长枪手在盯着两位牧师瞧。如果餐厅里有女人，他就看女人，没有女人，便看看外国人，看看一个英国人(6)取乐子。可是此时跟前既没有女人又没有外国人，他就乐滋滋、厚颜无礼地盯着那两个牧师瞧了。就在他乱张望之际，那个脸上有胎记的拍卖商立起了身，将餐巾一折，走了出去。他要的最后一瓶酒还有一半没有喝完。假如在卢阿卡需要付酒账，那他一定会喝得一滴不剩的。

话说那两个牧师，他们却没有向长枪手这边张望。只听他们当中的一个在说：“我等着见到他，已经有十天之久了。我在接待室一待就是一整天，可他始终不肯见我。”

“该怎么办好呢？”

“没办法。有什么办法呢？当权的就是当权的，你拿他们一点办法都没有。”

“我来这儿两个星期了，也是一点办法都没有。我等来等去，他们硬是不肯见。”

“谁叫咱们来自荒郊僻壤呢。钱花光了，咱们还是回去吧。”

“又要回那个荒僻的地方了。加利西亚是死是活，马德里才不管呢！咱们那儿可是个穷省。”

“巴西利奥兄弟采取的行动是可以理解的。”

“不过，我对巴西利奥·阿尔瓦雷斯的人格还是缺乏真正的信心。”

“到了马德里就学聪明了。这地方会扼杀西班牙的。”

“他们应该见见咱们呀，哪怕拒绝也行。”

“没门呀。他们得叫你等得身心疲惫、精神崩溃。”

“好呀，那就瞧着吧。别人等得了，我也等得了。”

就在这时，那个灰白头发、长得像老鹰的长枪手站起身子走了过来，立在两个牧师的餐桌跟前，眼睛看着他们微微一笑。

“是个斗牛士。”一位牧师对同伴说。

“是一个优秀的斗牛士哩。”长枪手说了一声，走出了餐厅。只见他上穿灰色夹克衫，下穿紧身马裤，足蹬高跟的牧牛人皮靴，腰身紧凑，弓形腿，一边微笑一边迈开稳健的大步朝外走，皮靴踩在地板上咯吱咯吱响。他生活在一个狭小、封闭的职业圈子里，讲究的是个人能力。在这个圈子里，他志得意满、目中无人，夜夜酗酒寻乐子。来到过厅里，他点起一支雪茄烟，将帽子向一边歪了歪，然后出门去咖啡馆了。

长枪手一走，两个牧师很快也离开了。他们意识到餐厅里只剩下他们两个客人，才慌慌张张走掉了。人去屋空，这下子餐厅里只有帕克以及那个中年侍者两人了。两人收拾好餐桌，把酒送进了厨房。

负责洗碗碟的小伙子正在厨房里忙活。他比帕克大三岁，愤世嫉俗，为人很刻薄。

“来喝一杯。”中年侍者说完，斟了一杯瓦尔德帕那葡萄酒递给了他。

“有酒为什么不喝！”小伙子把酒杯接了过去说。

“你(7)，帕克？”中年侍者问。

“我也来一杯吧。谢谢。”帕克说。

三个人把杯里的酒一饮而尽。

“我要走了。”中年侍者说。

“晚安。”他的同伴们说。

中年侍者走了，只剩下帕克他们俩了。帕克拿起一条牧师用过的餐巾，站直身子，脚后跟立定，然后将餐巾放低，头也顺势放低，摆动胳膊，来了一个斗牛士抖动披风的动作，样子从容舒缓。接着，他一个转身，右脚向前轻移，又抖了一下餐巾，面对假想中的公牛占据了一个比较有利的位置，随后又抖了抖餐巾，动作舒缓、优雅，时间掌握得恰到好处。最后，他收起餐巾，将其放至腰部，一闪身，算是躲过了冲过来的公牛。

洗碗工名叫恩里克，在一旁用挑剔和嘲笑的目光观看他表演。

“你的那条公牛怎么样？”他末了问道。

“非常勇敢。”帕克说，“你看这里。”

他说完站直细细的腰身，又完美地连着做了四个抖披风的动作，如行云流水，潇洒、优雅。

“公牛怎么样呢？”恩里克靠洗碗槽站着，手里端着酒杯，腰上系着围裙。

“底气仍然很足呢。”帕克说。

“你叫我恶心。”恩里克说。

“为什么？”

“你瞧我的。”

恩里克说完解下围裙，用它引着假想中的公牛冲过来，做了四个完美的抖披风的动作，像吉卜赛人表演那样自如。最后，他一甩围裙，躲开公牛，让围裙形成一个硬硬的弧度掠过公牛的鼻子。

“你瞧瞧这套动作吧。”他说，“谁想得到我却是个洗碗工。”

“为何不去斗牛呢？”

“害怕呗。”恩里克说，“是因为害怕(8)。走上斗牛场，面对一条真的公牛，你也会同样感到害怕的。”

“不会的，”帕克说，“我不会害怕的。”

“去你的！(9)”恩里克说，“谁遇上都会害怕的。只不过斗牛士能够控制内心的恐惧感罢了，那样才能斗得好牛嘛。我参加过一场业余斗牛赛，当时吓得不得了，不由自主掉头便跑。人人都觉得这挺滑稽的。换上你，也会害怕的。要不是因为害怕，在西班牙就连擦鞋匠也可以当斗牛士。你，一个乡下人，一定会比我更害怕的。”

“没有的事。”帕克说。

在想象中，他已经有过许多次斗牛的经历了。他看见牛的犄角、湿湿的牛鼻子和扑闪的牛耳朵不知有多少次了；他看见公牛低头冲过来，牛蹄子把地面踏得嗵嗵响，而他一抖披风，让发了疯的公牛从身边冲过；接着，他一次又一次抖披风，引得公牛一次又一次冲锋；最后，他潇洒地来了个大回转，引得公牛围着他团团转。当他大模大样走开时，他那夹克衫的金色饰品上由于擦着了牛身子而粘了几根牛毛，公牛傻呆呆站在那儿，像中了催眠术，观众欢声雷动。不，他绝不会害怕的。别人会害怕，但他是绝对不会的。对此他胸中有数。退一万步来说，即便害怕，他也可以应付的。对此，他信心百倍。于是他说：“我是绝对不会害怕的！”

恩里克又说了一声：“去你的！(10)”

接下来，他建议道：“是不是需要试一试？”

“怎么试？”

“你看，”恩里克说，“你心里光想到了公牛，却没有想到牛角。公牛力大无穷，它的犄角锋利似刀剑，戳人像刺刀，又像铁棒一样可以一击毙命。你瞧瞧这个。”他说着将桌子的一个抽屉拉开，取出两把切肉刀来，“我把刀绑在椅子腿上，再将椅子举在头前边给你扮演公牛。假如你还能像刚才那样来那么几手，那才是好样的呢。”

“你把围裙借给我，”帕克说，“咱们到餐厅表演去。”

“算啦，”恩里克突然变得不那么刻薄了，这样说道，“别表演了，帕克。”

“要表演的，”帕克说，“我才不害怕呢。”

“看见刀子刺过来，你就怕了。”

“等着瞧。”帕克说，“你把围裙给我。”

恩里克动手拿两条用过的餐巾将切肉刀的刀身绑在椅子腿上，固定牢，绑死，然后打了结。切肉刀沉甸甸的，跟剃刀一般锋利。与此同时，帕克的那两个房间服务员姐姐正走在去电影院的路上，要去看葛丽泰·嘉宝主演的《安娜·克丽丝蒂》。至于那两个牧师，一个身穿内衣在念祈祷书，另一个则穿着睡衣在诵读玫瑰经。除了那个生病的斗牛士，其他的斗牛士晚间均去了福尔诺斯咖啡馆。在咖啡馆里，那个深色头发的大块头长枪手在打弹子，而那位表情严肃的矮个子斗牛士坐在拥挤的桌旁，前边放着一杯牛奶咖啡，身边坐的是那位中年短枪手，另外还有几个不苟言笑的工人。

那个喜欢喝酒的灰白头发长枪手也坐在一张桌子旁，面前放着一杯卡扎拉斯白兰地，兴致勃勃地望着另一张桌子——那个丧失了勇气的斗牛士和另外的一个弃剑而重新改用短枪的斗牛士坐在那儿，身边坐着两个面容憔悴的烟花女子。

至于拍卖商，则站在街角跟朋友谈天说地。那位高个子侍者已到了无政府工团主义者的会场，在等待机会发言。此时，那个中年侍者正坐在阿尔瓦雷斯咖啡馆的平台上端着一小杯啤酒细品慢咽。卢阿卡寄宿公寓的老板娘已入梦乡，仰面躺着，把长枕夹在两腿之间。她人高马大，性格诚实，心地纯净，为人随和，笃信宗教，没有一天不思念已过世二十年的丈夫，没有一天不为亡夫祈祷。那个生病的斗牛士独自一人待在房间里，脸朝下平趴在床上，嘴巴下垫着一块手帕。

此刻，卢阿卡的餐厅已人去屋空。恩里克用餐巾将厨刀绑在椅子腿上，把最后的一个结打好，然后举起了椅子。他把绑着厨刀的椅子腿向前一戳，将椅子举过头顶，两把刀一左一右，直挺挺指向前方。

“挺沉的。”他开口说道，“听我一言，帕克。这太危险了，还是别表演了吧。”他说着话，脸上淌下了汗珠。

帕克面对着他站着，将围裙展开，拇指朝上，食指向下，用两手把围裙捏紧，然后抖了抖以吸引“公牛”的目光。

“冲过来吧，”他说，“像公牛一样该转身就转身。你想冲多少次都可以。”

“你怎么知道何时抖披风何时停呢？”恩里克问，“最好先试三个回合，然后中间休息片刻。”

“那好吧。”恩里克说，“冲过来吧。冲呀，小公牛(11)！来呀，小公牛！”

恩里克把头一低朝他冲了过来。帕克眼见刀锋到了跟前，便将围裙一抖，让刀子从他的肚皮前划了过去。对于他，那刀子就是真实的牛角，黑颜色，白白的尖，光滑光滑，而与他擦身而过，转身又冲过来的恩里克则是公牛，身躯庞大、滚烫，腰上鲜血淋漓——那“公牛”嗵嗵嗵地冲过去，然后猫一样敏捷地转过身子，见他慢慢一抖“披风”，就又冲了过来。接着，“公牛”又冲了一次。这一次，他望着那刺过来的刀尖，急忙向前迈出左脚，结果多迈出了两英寸，刀子没有躲过去，而是扎进了他的身体，轻轻易易就扎了进去，就像扎进了酒囊一样容易。坚硬的钢刀扎了进去，滚烫的鲜血顺着刀身的上面以及周围泉涌而出。恩里克大叫一声：“哎呀！哎呀！快让我拔出来！快让我拔出来！”帕克向前一栽，栽在了椅子上，手里仍抓着那条围裙披风。恩里克拽着椅子，于是那刀子在帕克的体内转了一下，又转了一下。

刀子拔了出来，而帕克一屁股坐在了地板上，身下的血流成了河，温温的，越来越多。

“快用餐巾捂住伤口。快捂住！”恩里克说，“你可要捂紧。我去喊医生来。千万要捂紧，别让血流出来。”

“跟前有个皮碗就好了。”帕克说。他曾在斗牛场上见过那种东西。

“都怪我冲得太猛了。”恩里克带着哭腔说，“我只是想让你看看这种表演有多危险。”

“别担心，”帕克用一种听上去很微弱的声音说道，“你去把医生叫来就是了。”

在斗牛场上遇到这样的情况，他们会把你抬起来快快离去，送你到手术室去。如果没到手术室你股动脉里的血就流光了，他们便直接请牧师来。

“再请一个牧师过来！”帕克一边把餐巾紧紧捂在受伤的小肚子上，一边说道。他简直无法相信这样的事情竟然发生在了自己身上。

可是恩里克没听见他的话，而早已顺着圣杰罗尼莫赛马场跑了，朝着通宵服务的急救站狂奔。屋里只剩下了帕克一人，他先还是直坐着，后来蜷缩起来，最终瘫倒在了地上，直至一切结束。他感到生命在离他而去，就像拔掉了浴缸里的塞子，缸里的水在渐渐流尽。他害怕了，感到一阵眩晕，鼓起劲想说几句忏悔词。他记得忏悔的开场白是这样的：“上帝啊，我对自己的过错深表痛心。我爱你，全心全意地爱你，下定决心……”他的语速很快，但没等他把忏悔词说完，就感到头晕目眩，一头栽倒在地板上，很快没有了生命。股动脉一旦割断，里面的血就会流光，简直快得惊人。

当急救站的医生和一个警察（那警察紧紧抓住恩里克的胳膊）相伴赶到时，帕克的两个姐姐仍在格兰维亚大街的电影院里看电影。嘉宝主演的这部电影让两人大失所望，因为在这个大明星主演的片子中，周围的环境一般都豪华奢侈、金碧辉煌，可是这部电影里的环境却寒酸、凄凉。由于对电影强烈不满，观众们又是吹口哨又是跺脚以示抗议。至于卢阿卡寄宿公寓的其他人，在事故发生时，都在干着之前一直在干的事情。只有那两个牧师做完了祈祷，正准备睡觉。灰白头发的长枪手端着酒杯走过去，和那两个面容憔悴的烟花女子坐在了一起。过了一会儿，他带着其中的一个走出了咖啡馆。而这位烟花女子刚才喝的酒，一直都是那个失去了勇气的斗牛士为她埋的单。

这些人究竟在干些什么，第二天以及以后的日子会干些什么，帕克永远都不会知道了。他不会知道这些人的一生究竟过得怎么样，他们的生命是怎样完结的。他甚至都没有意识到，他们的生命已经完结了。正如一句西班牙的谚语所说的，他是抱着幻想死去的。生前，他没来得及经历幻想破灭的过程，生命结束时甚至都没有来得及把一套忏悔词念完。嘉宝主演的这部电影让马德里整整失望了一个星期，而他生前甚至都没来得及表达自己的失望之情。

————————————————————

(1) 西班牙银币，现已被欧元取代。

(2) 骑马长枪手和徒步短枪手均为斗牛士的助手。

(3) 贝尔蒙特1892年生于塞维利亚一个穷苦人家，1913年投身斗牛，1935年退役，他与1920年惨死于斗牛场上的何塞利托缔造了西班牙斗牛的“黄金时代”。

(4) 西班牙语。

(5) 原文为西班牙语。

(6) 原文为西班牙语。

(7) 原文为西班牙语。

(8) 原文为西班牙语。

(9) 原文为西班牙语。

(10) 原文为西班牙语。

(11) 原文为西班牙语。

乞力马扎罗的雪

乞力马扎罗(1)是一座雪山，高达19710英尺，据说是非洲最高的山。乞力马扎罗的西峰被马赛人(2)叫作“恩嘉琪-恩嘉怡”，意思即“上帝的殿堂”。在靠近西峰的地方有一具已经风干冻僵的豹子尸体。至于豹子为什么要来这么高的地方，无人做过解释。

“奇妙之处就在于没有疼痛感。”他说，“发作的时候就是这么一种状况。”

“真的吗？”

“当然是真的。不过，气味太难闻，真是抱歉得很。一定叫你感到不舒服了。”

“别这么说！求你别这么说！”

“你瞧它们！”他说，“到底是看见了我，还是这气味把它们招来了？”

说话的男子躲在一棵含羞草乔木如盖的浓荫里，躺在一张小床上，目光穿过阴凉地，投向亮晃晃的平原上，那儿有三只大鸟虎视眈眈守候着，另外还有十来只盘旋在空中，掠过时在地上投下一道道影子。

“自从卡车抛锚的那天起，它们就一直盘旋不去。”他说，“今天这是第一次有几只落在了地面上。它们在天上飞，我起初用心观察过它们飞翔的姿势，想着以后说不定写东西能用得上，现在说来怪可笑的。”

“但愿别写它们。”她说。

“只不过随便说说罢了。”他说，“说说话，感觉能轻松许多。不过，我可不想让你心烦哟。”

“不会让我心烦，这你是知道的。”她说，“不心烦，只是内心却极其不安，因为我一点忙都帮不上。想来想去，还是把日子尽量过得轻松些，等着飞机来吧。”

“或者说就这么等下去，飞机压根就不来了。”

“请你吩咐，看我能做些什么。总有我力所能及的事的。”

“你可以把我的腿截掉，让我少受洋罪，虽然我对此持怀疑态度。或者开枪把我一枪崩掉。你现在打枪可是个好手了。起初还是我教你打枪的哩，对不对？”

“请别说这么晦气的话。难道我就不能给你读读书解闷吗？”

“读什么书？”

“书包里的书，只要没看过，哪本都可以呀。”

“我怕是听不进去。”他说，“耍耍嘴皮子倒是最轻松。咱们打打口水仗吧，那样来消磨时间。”

“我才不和你拌嘴呢。吵架我是绝对不愿意的。从今往后咱们就不要打什么口水仗了。不管心里有多么烦躁，都不应该吵架。也许，他们今天又会另弄一辆卡车来的。说不定飞机也会来的。”

“我可不想转移了。”男子说，“现在转移已经没有任何意义了，除非能让你感觉好受些。”

“那可是懦夫说的话。”

“一个人快死了，你就不能别骂他了，让他死得舒心一些吗？你这么抹黑我，又有什么意思呢？”

“你不会死的。”

“别犯傻了。我正在死去。不然你去问问那些杂种。”他说着向大鸟那边瞅了一眼，只见那三只肮脏的大鸟把光秃秃的脑袋缩起来，缩进耸立的羽毛里。另有一只从天而降，落地后紧跑几步，然后慢慢悠悠朝着同伴们的跟前走去。

“每个营地都有这种鸟，只是你从来不注意罢了。只要不放弃希望，你就不会死。”

“这样的论断，你是从哪本书上看到的？你可真是傻得不透气。”

“你应该也为别人考虑考虑。”

“看在基督的分上，”他说，“我历来都是把别人装在心里的。”

他躺在床上，沉默了一会儿，让目光越过平原上一闪一闪的滚滚热浪，飘向灌木林的边缘。黄色的平原上有几只野羊，白白的，小小的，远处的灌木林那边有一群斑马，在绿叶的映衬下显得白乎乎一片。他们的营地扎在参天大树之下，背依山丘，水源充足，是个很舒适的营地，不远处有一个快干涸了的水坑，早晨总有沙鸡在那儿飞来飞去的。

“想让我为你读上几页书吗？”她问。她正坐在他床边的一把帆布椅子上。“起风了。”

“不用了，谢谢。”

“也许会有卡车来的。”

“我才不在乎什么卡车不卡车呢。”

“我在乎。”

“你在乎的东西多如牛毛，而我都不在乎。”

“并不是很多的，哈里。”

“喝上一杯怎么样？”

“喝酒对健康不好。布莱克(3)的书里说得好，要远离一切酒精。所以，你不应该喝酒。”

“莫洛！”他喊了一声。

“在，先生！”

“拿威士忌加苏打水来。”

“遵命，先生。”

“劝你不要喝了。”她说，“这就是我所谓的‘放弃希望’。书上都说了对健康不好。我很清楚，喝酒对你是有害的。”

“言之差矣，”他说，“喝酒对我是有好处的。”

他心想，好啦，这下结束了。要不然，他们会喋喋不休争论个没完。为喝杯酒拌嘴，最后来个了断。自从右腿生了坏疽，他就没有了疼痛感，随着疼痛感消失的还有恐惧感，现在只剩下沉重的疲倦感和愤怒感——他没想到会落得这么个下场。对于这样的结局，以及结局就这样到来，他并不感到奇怪。多年来，它一直纠缠着他的心，可现在它出现了，他反倒不在乎了。事情就这么怪：疲倦过了头，便什么都不在乎了。

他原来收集了些素材，打算等掌握了足够的资料，确保能写好的时候再动笔，现在却永远也写不成了。是啊，他可不愿写上几段，就尝到失败的滋味。也许，他压根就写不了，所以才一拖再拖，迟迟没有动笔。其中的原因，只有鬼才知道。

“真后悔跑到了这鬼地方。”女人说。她瞥了一眼他那端着酒杯的手，芳唇紧咬。“在巴黎，绝不会出这样的事。你老是说你喜欢巴黎。咱们完全可以留在巴黎或者到哪个别的地方去。就是天涯海角，我也愿意随你去的。我曾说过，你去哪儿，我就去哪儿。如果你想打猎，那咱们就去匈牙利打猎好啦，那儿会很舒适的。”

“你不就是有些臭钱嘛。”他说。

“这话说得可不公平。”她说，“我的钱，也就是你的钱。我舍弃了一切，跟随你到你想去的地方，做你想做的事情。但话又说回来，我还是后悔跑到了这鬼地方。”

“你说过你喜欢这儿。”

“你没出事之前，我的确这么说过。可现在我讨厌这里。真不明白为什么这样的事偏偏发生在你的腿上。咱们究竟做错了什么，竟然有这样飞来的横祸？”

“恐怕都怪我自己，怪我忘了给伤口涂碘酒，就用手抓那儿搔痒。对此我没有经心，因为我从未有过伤口感染的情况。后来，这伤情就恶化了。其他杀菌剂都用完了，可能因为随便涂了些药性差的石炭酸溶液，结果令微血管出了问题，引发了坏疽。”他说着看了看她，“除此之外，还会有什么呢？”

“我指的不是这个。”

“当初要是雇个懂行的把式，而不是个半吊子基库尤人(4)司机，他就会检查检查机油，绝不会让卡车的轴承烧坏。”

“我指的不是这个。”

“假如你没有离开你那社交圈子，没有离开老韦斯特伯里、萨拉托加以及棕榈滩(5)的那些狐朋狗友，而把我收在了囊中……”

“说什么呀，我是爱你的。这样对我是不公平的。我过去爱你，现在爱你，以后还会永远地爱你。难道你不爱我吗？”

“不爱，”男子说，“恐怕是这样的。我从来就没有爱过你。”

“哈里，你在说什么呀？你简直是昏了头了。”

“不，我已经没有头可昏的了。”

“别喝酒了。”她说，“亲爱的，求你别喝酒了。咱们应该做出一切努力，共渡难关。”

“要努力你自己努力吧，”他说，“我已经精疲力竭了。”

在脑海里，他看见了卡拉伽奇的一个火车站，看见他背着行囊站在那里，辛普伦东方快车的车灯划破了黑暗——大撤退之后，他正要离开色雷斯。这是一段情景，他准备以后写作时用。另外还有一段情景是这样的：吃早饭时，他凭窗远眺，只见保加利亚群山上白雪皑皑；南森(6)的女秘书问老人那是不是雪，老人看了看说不是的，说那不是雪，还不到下雪的时候呢。女秘书把这话给其他几个女孩子讲了，那些人都承认自己看走了眼，说那的确不是雪。其实，那是雪，一点都不假。等到交换难民，他送她们进山，走到了雪地上。那年冬天，她们踩着积雪走啊走，直至最后倒地死去。

话说同一年过圣诞节的那一周，高尔泰山也在下雪，纷纷扬扬一个劲在下。他们住在伐木工的小屋里，这儿的空间被一个硕大的四四方方的瓷砖炉子占了一半。大家睡的褥垫里装的是山毛榉树叶。这时，那个逃兵跑了来，脚上淌着血，在雪地里留下了痕迹。他说宪兵就在身后追捕他。大家让他换了双毛袜子，宪兵来了就拉着他们胡扯，直至大雪盖住了逃兵的足印。

在舒茨，过圣诞节的那天，白雪亮晃晃的，刺得人眼疼。从旅馆向外看，可以看见人们做完祈祷，从教堂纷纷返回自己的家中。在这个地方，他们肩扛沉重的滑雪板，沿着河岸旁的那条尿黄色的平展的滑雪道攀上松林覆盖的陡峭山坡，然后从耸立在马德莱纳旅馆旁的那座雪山上踩着滑雪板一阵风似的冲下来，雪地平展得像一块涂了糖霜的蛋糕，雪花轻盈得似粉末。他们一路滑行，风驰电掣，无声无息，如鸟儿从天而降。对于这些，他仍记忆犹新。

当时他们住在马德莱纳旅馆，由于暴风雪的缘故受困于此达一个星期之久，整天都借着提灯的灯光在烟雾缭绕的屋子里打扑克解闷。兰特先生输得越惨，赌注下得越高。最后，他输了个精光，输掉了滑雪学校的钱，输掉了本季度的盈利，连资金也输掉了。他仍可以看到当时的情景——大鼻子兰特先生捡起几张牌，然后摊开说：“我不跟。”他们整天地赌，不下雪时赌，雪下得太多还赌。他想了想，觉得自己一生中花在赌博上的时间真是太多了。

不过，对于这些，他在写作时只字未提，也没有提那个寒冷、晴朗的圣诞日。那一天，目光穿越平原，可以看见对面的群山。巴克驾机飞越防线去轰炸运送休假的奥地利军官的列车，见那些军官抱头鼠窜，便用机枪扫射他们。记得巴克走进食堂吃饭时，提起了这事，食堂里顿时鸦雀无声。后来不知谁说了一句：“你这个杀人不眨眼的家伙。”

巴克杀死的也许就是前不久跟他在一起滑雪的奥地利人。不，不是的。那年，跟他一起滑雪的奥地利人叫汉斯，属于皇家狩猎队的成员。他们一起到锯木厂跟前的那个山谷猎杀野兔，途中聊起了帕苏比奥战役以及波提卡拉和阿萨洛纳的那场进攻战。这些他在写作时都只字未提。至于在蒙特·克罗纳、赛特·科穆尼和阿西埃罗的那些经历，他也只字未提。

他在沃拉堡和阿尔堡究竟度过了几个冬天呢？总共四个！他记起了和那个卖狐狸的人在一起的情形，记得他们一起到布卢登茨去。他是去买礼品的。他记得樱桃酒醇香可口，记得怎样在冰天雪地里飞驰，激起团团雪粉，嘴里高唱：“嗨哟！罗利是这么说！”记得穿过最后一片开阔地，冲下陡坡，然后直直朝前滑。进果园转三个弯，出果园后越过水沟，就到了客栈后边的那条冰雪覆盖的路。然后，解开滑雪板上的绳子，把滑雪板从脚上踢下来，将它们靠在客栈的木板墙上。灯光从窗口泻出；屋里烟雾缭绕，新酿的酒芳香扑鼻，给人以阵阵暖意；手风琴声袅袅绕梁。

“去巴黎住哪个地方？”他问坐在身旁一把帆布椅子上的女人。此时，他们这是在非洲。

“住科里伦酒店。那地方你是知道的。”

“我怎么会知道？”

“咱们每次都住那儿呀。”

“不对。不是每次都住那里。”

“反正在那里住过吧，还住过圣日耳曼区的亨利四世大厦。你曾说你爱那个地方。”

“爱只不过是一堆粪，而我是站在粪堆上打鸣的公鸡。”

“假如你不得不离开人世，”她说，“是不是需要在走之前把所有的一切都毁掉？我是说一点东西也不留？你是不是必须宰马杀妻，将马鞍和盔甲付之一炬？”

“是的。”他说，“你的臭钱就是我的盔甲，是我的斯威夫特和阿穆尔(7)。”

“求你别这样了！”

“好吧，我就不多说了。我并不想伤你的心。”

“现在怕是有点晚了。”

“那好，那我就继续伤你的心好啦。这样倒更有趣味。这是我真心想做的一件事，现在却做不成了。”

“不，这不是事实。你想做的事情多得很呢，而每一件都是我想做的。”

“噢，看在基督的分上，别再吹牛了好吗？”

他看了她一眼，见她在暗自落泪。

“你听我说，”他说道，“你以为这样说话能给人以乐趣吗？真不知道我为什么要这样。大概是鬼迷心窍，觉得刺伤别人才能使自己活下去吧。刚开始的时候，我还是好好的。惹你伤感并非我的本意。这下子，我成了地地道道的傻瓜，竟然狠下心这样对待你。我的话你权当放屁，别往心里去哟，亲爱的。其实，我是爱你的。我爱你，这你心里是清楚的。我从来没有像爱你这样爱过任何别的人。”

他不知不觉又故技重演，信口雌黄地编造起谎话来。

“你对我挺贴心的。”

“你这个坏婆娘，一个有钱的坏婆娘。”他说，“我这是在作诗。我现在满肚子都是诗句。发腐的诗，发臭的诗！”

“别这样。你为什么非得把自己变成一个魔鬼呢，哈里？”

“因为在死之前，我要毁掉一切，”男子说，“身后什么东西都不愿意留下。”

已经到了傍晚时分。他睡了一大觉。太阳躲到了山后，平原上影影绰绰，一片朦胧。一些小动物在靠近营地的地方觅食。他观望着它们，见它们已远离灌木林，脑袋很快地一起一伏，将尾巴摆来摆去。那些大鸟已不在地面上等候了，而是一只只全都重重地压在了一棵树上。它们的数量还不止这些呢。他的贴身杂役坐在床的旁边。

“太太打猎去了。”杂役说，“先生需要什么吗？”

“什么都不需要。”

她到别处打猎去了。她知道他喜欢看狩猎的场面，所以才跑得远远的，为的是不惊扰他跟前的这一小块清静之地。她可真是处处为他着想。无论是知道些什么，在书上看到些什么，或者听到了什么消息，她心里总是为他着想。

当初他找她时，已经到了无可救药的地步，说什么也不能怪她。你口是心非、谎话连篇，叫一个女人怎么辨得清呢？他谎言脱口而出，完全是出于习惯，只图个方便！自从他言不由衷之日起，他在情场上如鱼得水，比说实话时还要风光。

与其说他愿意撒谎，倒不如说他没有实话可讲。他原来也堂堂正正地做人，现在却成了潦倒之人，生活成了苟延残喘，今天攀这个高枝，明天攀那个高枝，四处游乐，满世界地跑。

你不让自己想这些烦心事，而这是你的了不起之处。只要有一副笃定的心肠，就不会像大多数同样处境的人那样一朝崩溃。你大势已去，昨日的风光已不复存在，文采尽失，而你摆出一副全然不在乎的架势。可是在内心，你却声称一定要写写周围的人，写写那些有钱的人，声称自己没有与他们同流合污，而只是潜伏在他们国家的一个间谍，早晚都会离开他们，把东西写出来，那时的你就是一个了解内幕的人，会是不俗的手笔。可惜这一心愿他永远也无法实现了，因为他每一日都懒于动笔，只贪图眼前的安乐，过着一种自己所鄙视的醉生梦死的生活，渐渐笔锋呆滞，意志消退，最终无所事事，什么都不写了。他不写作了，跟狐朋狗友胡混，倒落了个自自在在。非洲是块福地，他在此处度过了人生中最快活的一段时光——他来这儿是要把日子重新过起。这次狩猎，安逸的程度是极低的。虽然并不艰苦，但也没有奢华可言。他觉得这样也算是重返训练场上，可以将心里的脂肪去掉，就像一个拳击手要去掉身体上的脂肪，得到山里苦练一样。

她喜欢这次狩猎，说她喜欢得不得了。凡是有刺激性的事她都喜欢——换换环境，结交结交新的朋友，看看赏心悦目的景色。他甚至产生了错觉，认为自己又意气风发，有了写作的意愿。可结果并非如此，他心里很清楚。事已至此，他也不必破罐子破摔，像一条断了脊梁的蛇一样自残。错不在这个女人的身上。这个女人没错，那就是别的女人的错。如果说他靠撒谎苟延残喘，那就让他因为撒谎而死去吧。想到这里，他听见山后传来了一声枪响。

她的枪法很好。这个富婆，既呵护着他的天赋，又毁掉了他的天赋。鬼话！毁掉他天赋的罪魁正是他自己！为什么要嫁祸于人，怪罪这个把他照料得无微不至的女人呢？他毁掉了自己的天赋，因为他弃而不用，让天赋生了锈，因为他背叛了自己的灵魂和信仰，因为他酗酒过度使观察力不再敏锐，因为他懒惰成性，因为他势利、傲慢、充满偏见，还因为他蝇营狗苟、投机钻营。这算干什么？难道是在写一本书的目录不成？他有天赋固然不错，但他没有加以利用，而是拿来做交易了。他根本不在意自己写了些什么，而在意能换取些什么。他做出了选择，选择放弃笔耕，而靠别的本事谋生。他爱上的女人一个比一个有钱，你说怪不怪？可是，后来他没有了爱情，只有满口的谎言，就像对这个女人一般——这个女人比他所有的情人都有钱，钱简直多得不得了。她曾有过丈夫和孩子，有过情人，只是对情人们不满意，偏偏钟情于他，觉得他是个作家，一个男子汉，一个伙伴，一个令人感到自豪的宝贝。奇怪的是，他根本不爱她，而且对她撒谎，可这产生的效果更好，更能够回报她为他付出的钱财。

他觉得人的命天注定，是怎样一块料都是有定数的。不管靠什么谋生，其中都包含着天赋的因素。他终生出卖自己的能力，形式各异，当感情投入不太多的时候，在换取金钱方面产生的价值会大得多。这是他的一大发现，但他绝不会写出来。不，他绝不会将其付诸笔端，尽管这值得一书。

就在这时，她出现在了视野里，穿过空地向营地走来。她穿着马裤，背着她的那杆步枪。两个杂役扛着一只野羊，紧随其后。他觉得她仍然有几分风韵，肉体能给人以欢愉。对于床笫之间的风流，她具有出众的才华和欣赏力。她并不漂亮，但他喜欢她的脸蛋。她博览群书，喜欢骑射，当然喝酒喝得极其多。当她还是个比较年轻的少妇时，丈夫便离开了人世。一时间，她把所有的心思都放在了两个刚刚成年的孩子身上，放在了骑马、读书和喝酒上。其实，她的两个孩子并不需要她，有她在跟前反而不自在。她喜欢在傍晚时分读书，在晚餐之前读，边读书边喝苏格兰威士忌及苏打水。该吃饭的时候，她已醉眼蒙眬了，饭桌旁再来一瓶红酒，通常便醉得糊里糊涂，趁此入睡。

那是有情人之前的状况。有了情人之后，她的酒便喝得不那么多了，因为她不必非得喝醉酒才能入睡了。不过，那些情人叫她感到乏味无聊。她嫁的那个丈夫从未让她感到乏味过，而那些情人叫她觉得乏味得要死。

后来，她的一个孩子在一次飞机失事中丧了命。这次事件过后，她就再也不想要情人了，不再把酒当麻醉剂了，觉得必须开始新的人生。突然之间，她对孤独产生了强烈的恐惧感。不过，她想要的是一个能让自己敬重的伴侣。

事情发生了，经过极其简单。她喜欢他写的东西，一直都很羡慕他的生活方式。她觉得他是在按照自己的心愿生活。至于她是采用什么手段将他弄到了手，又是怎样最终迷恋上了他，反正都是些常规步骤。在这一过程之中，她给自己建立了一种新的生活，而他把自己残留下来的一部分旧的生活方式拿来做了交易的筹码。

他拿这个筹码换取的是高枕无忧的日子以及安逸的生活，这是毋庸置疑的。除此之外，还换取到了什么呢？他简直说不清楚。反正他想要什么，她就给他买什么。这一点，他心里是有数的。说起来，她是个挺不错的女人。对待她，就像对待别的女人一样，他非常乐意立刻和她上床，而且更愿意跟她逞床笫之欢，因为她更有钱，因为她让人心情愉悦，懂得欣赏人，还因为她从不惹是生非。现在，她苦心经营的小日子就要寿终正寝了。事情的起因是，两个星期前，一根刺扎破了他的膝盖，而他没有涂碘酒消毒。当时，他们看见一群非洲大羚羊，于是悄悄摸上去要拍照。那些羚羊昂起脑袋，支棱起耳朵听动静，一有响动就会逃进灌木林里去。就这样，羚羊跑了，照片没拍成，他的膝盖却被扎伤了。

此时，她走了过来。

他在小床上转过脸来，冲她打了声招呼。

“我打到了一只野羊，”她说道，“能给你炖上一锅美味汤。我叫他们捣些土豆泥，撒点奶粉进去。你现在感觉怎么样啦？”

“好多了。”

“简直太棒了！要知道，我有个预感，知道你可能会病情好转的。我走时，你正睡觉。”

“我睡得很死。你刚才走得很远吗？”

“不远，就在山后转了转。我一枪就把这只羊撂倒了。”

“你是个神枪手，枪法很棒。”

“我喜欢打枪，喜欢非洲。这是真的。如果你平平安安的，对我而言这可是最有意思的一次旅行了。和你一起打猎，你都不知道是多么有趣。我爱这个国家。”

“我也爱。”

“亲爱的，看见你病情好转，你都不知道多么叫人欣慰。见你受洋罪，我心里简直受不了。以后你不要再那样跟我讲话了，好不好？能答应我吗？”

“能。”他说，“我记不得自己都说了些什么了。”

“你可不能把我毁掉，好吗？我只不过是个深爱着你的中年女子，愿意听命于你，服从你的意愿。我已经被毁掉两三次了。你无意再让我经受一次毁灭，对不对？”

“我倒想在床上把你毁掉几次。”他说道。

“好呀，那可是令人舒畅的毁灭。要毁灭，就应该有那样的毁灭。明天飞机就要来了。”

“你怎么知道？”

“我敢肯定一定会来的。杂役把木头准备好了，还准备了青草熏浓烟。今天我又去检查了一遍，降机坪地方很宽，两边准备各生一堆浓烟。”

“是什么原因叫你断定飞机明天一定会来？”

“我有把握它一定会来。到了城里，他们就会把你的腿治好，那时咱们痛痛快快来一次‘毁灭’。这指的不是那些难听的话说的那种毁灭。”

“来杯酒怎么样？太阳都落山了。”

“你觉得自己能喝吗？”

“我是要喝上一杯的。”

“那咱们就一起喝吧。莫洛，拿威士忌加苏打水来！”她喊了一声。

“你最好穿上防蚊靴。”他建议道。

“洗完澡再穿吧……”

两人喝着酒，天色渐渐黑了下来。就在天色尚未黑透，但已没有了亮光，开枪无法瞄准目标时，一条鬣狗穿过空地向山后跑去。

“那个杂种每天晚上都从这里跑过，”男子说，“两个星期了，天天如此。”

“夜里叫的就是它。我倒无所谓。说来，这种动物挺招人嫌的。”

两人一道喝着酒，他感觉不到疼痛，只是由于老是一种姿势待在床上觉得有些不舒服。杂役们生起一堆篝火，投在帐篷上的光影跳跃着，他感到往日的那种对令人愉快的放纵生活所采取的听之任之的态度又回到了自己身上。她对他真是太好了。今天下午都怪他心肠太狠，有失公道。她是个好女人，实在是好极了。就在这时，他突然想到自己快要死了。

这一念头的出现突如其来，不是像一股水冲过来，或者像一阵风刮过来，而是像一种虚无缥缈的臭气突然飘了过来。奇怪的是，那条鬣狗循着这气味悄悄摸了过来。

“怎么啦，哈里？”她问道。

“没什么。”他说，“你最好坐到那边去，坐到迎着风的那个地方。”

“莫洛给你换过药了没有？”

“换过了。刚刚敷上硼酸膏。”

“感觉如何？”

“有点不稳定。”

“我去洗个澡，”她说，“这就去。回头咱们一起吃饭，然后把小床移进帐篷。”

他在心里对自己说，结束无谓的争吵是明智之举。跟这个女人，他吵架吵得不太多，可是跟那些自己所爱的女人却争吵不息。结果，吵架就像腐蚀剂，腐蚀掉了他和那些女人的感情。那时他爱得太深，索要的回报太多，把双方的感情都耗干了。

他回想起自己独身一人在君士坦丁堡漂泊的情形。那是在巴黎跟情人吵架之后，愤而出走的。那段时间，他日日风流，夜夜嫖娼。之后，却仍然未能消除孤独感，反而使孤独感愈加强烈。他给第一个情人，即那个离他而去的情人写了封信，说他难以忘怀昔日的感情……说有一次在摄政宫外以为看见了她，于是心里翻江倒海、思绪万千；他曾经在林荫大道尾随一个女人，因为那个女人长得跟她有点像，心中有几分担忧，一怕到头来发现那女人不是她，二怕失去跟踪过程中产生的温馨感情；他每每跟别的女人睡觉，只能加深他对她的思念之情；他无法摆脱对她的爱恋，对她以前的所作所为绝不会耿耿于怀。这封信是在俱乐部里写的，当时他没有喝酒，头脑冷静。信寄往纽约，求她回信寄到他在巴黎的事务所，那样似乎较为保险。那天晚上，他只有对她的思念，除此之外，心里空落落的。他在街上游荡，走过马克西姆饭店，路上泡了一个女郎，带着她一起去吃消夜。吃完消夜，两人一道去跳舞。女郎的舞步太糟糕，于是他撇下她，跟一个风骚的亚美尼亚浪荡女跳了起来——浪荡女跳舞时把肚皮在他的身上蹭来蹭去，蹭得他身上发烫。他和一个英国的炮兵中尉争风吃醋，硬要把亚美尼亚浪荡女带走。中尉让他出去较量。于是，两人走到黑灯瞎火的鹅卵石街面上拳脚相向，打了起来。他冲着中尉的下巴颏狠狠打了两拳，可对方没有被击倒，于是他心想这下有好戏看了。中尉挥拳打在他身上，再一拳打在他的眼眶上。而他来了个左勾拳，中尉扑过来抓住他的衣服，把袖子都扯掉了。他朝着中尉的后耳根猛击两拳，就在对方将他推开之际，急忙挥动右拳把对方放翻。中尉一个狗吃屎倒了下去。听见宪兵的脚步声，他带着浪荡女跑掉了。他们钻进一辆出租车，沿着博斯普鲁斯海峡向瑞米力西萨驶去，在寒夜里兜了一圈，然后去一家旅馆睡觉。她跟自己的相貌一样，在床上也是过于成熟了。不过，她肤如锦缎，体似玫瑰花瓣、蜂糖浆，肚皮平平展展，大胸脯，行事时臀下不用垫枕头。次日，在第一缕曙光之中，她一副邋遢相。在她没睡醒之前，他就离开了，带着一只青肿的眼，拎着他那件被扯掉一只袖子的上衣回到了佩拉宫酒店。

就在那天晚上，他起身前往安纳托利亚。记得在那趟旅途中，他们整天穿行在罂粟田间（罂粟是用来提炼鸦片的），时间久了，会让你产生奇怪的感觉，觉得不管往哪儿走，方向都是错的。最后，他来到了一处战场——部队曾和从君士坦丁堡刚赶到的军官一道发动进攻，而那些军官狗屁不通，让炮弹落在了自家的队伍里，气得英国观察员像个小孩子一样哇哇哇地哭。

也是在那一天，他第一次看见了死人——那些死人身穿白色芭蕾舞裙，脚上的鞋缀着绒球，向上翘起。当时，土耳其人不断朝前涌来，一波一波的。只见穿裙子的士兵们落荒而逃，军官开枪阻止也不管用，后来军官也狼狈鼠窜。他和英国观察员亦跑了起来，跑得他心口痛，嘴里满是尘土味。他们躲到岩石后边，看见土耳其人仍然一个劲朝前涌。接下来出现了一些他想都不敢想的事情，再往后他所看到的情景更是可怕。回到巴黎，对那段往事他不愿提起，就是别人说起来他也受不了。路过咖啡馆时，见那位美国诗人坐在里面，面前放着一摞碟子，土豆一样的脸上挂着愚蠢的表情，正在跟一个罗马尼亚人谈达达主义(8)运动。那个罗马尼亚人自称特里斯唐·查拉(9)，总戴着一个单片眼镜，老是闹头疼。他回到公寓和妻子过起了小日子，他又恢复了对于妻子的爱情，不再争吵，不再发狂——回家让他喜悦盈怀。事务所把收到的他的信件给他送了来。事情就是这样，他写的那封信有了回信，一天上午被人用一个托盘送了来。他一看那笔迹就浑身发冷，急慌慌想把那封信藏到另一封的底下。可妻子却问道：“那是谁来的信呀，亲爱的？”于是，刚刚开始的好日子就此被断送了。

对于和那些女人一起度过的悠悠岁月以及一场场的争吵，他仍记忆犹新。那些女人总是挑最不恰当的场合跟他拌嘴。她们真是没眼色，为什么总是在他心情最好的时候对他发难呢？关于情场上的这些遭遇，他从来没写过，一是因为他不想伤害她们，二是因为他的素材很广，似乎没必要写这些风流案。不过，他还是心存一念，觉得最终还是要写的。要写的东西真是多之又多。他目睹了大千世界的千变万化，而不仅仅是这些事件。他见多识广，对世人进行观察，不仅纵览，而且入微，至今仍能记得起人们在不同的时刻不同的表现。他置身于变化的潮流之中，观察了变化的过程，有责任把它写出来。可是，现在他却再也写不成了。

“你感觉怎么样了？”她问道。她在帐篷里洗完了澡，此时走了出来。

“还好。”

“能吃饭了吧？”

他看见莫洛立在她的身后，提着折叠桌，另一个杂役端着一些碟子。

“我想写点东西。”他说。

“你应该先喝些肉汤长长精神。”

“我今天夜里就要死了，”他说，“不需要长精神。”

“不要夸张嘛，哈里。求求你了。”她说。

“你为什么不用鼻子闻一闻！我半条腿都烂了，烂到大腿根了。都这样了，还喝什么肉汤呀。莫洛，给我拿威士忌加苏打水来！”

“求你还是喝肉汤吧。”她温情款语地说。

“那好吧。”

肉汤太烫，他只好端着盛肉汤的杯子放凉，不烫嘴之后一饮而尽，中间没有出现恶心的感觉。

“你是个好女人，”他说，“不要再为我操心了。”

她痴痴望着他。她的这张脸出现于《潮流》和《城市与乡村》杂志，家喻户晓，人人喜欢，只是由于酗酒减了几分颜色，还因为贪恋床笫之欢又减了几分颜色，但《城市与乡村》却显现不出她那诱人的酥胸、销魂的大腿以及那双轻抚你的腰背让你陶醉的纤手。他也望了望她，看到她那招牌式的微笑时，觉得死神又来到了跟前。这次，死神不是猛地冲过来，而是像一阵轻风徐徐刮来——这样的风吹得烛光摇曳，吹得火焰腾旺。

“过一会儿叫他们把我的蚊帐拿出来挂在树上，然后生一堆篝火。今晚我不进帐篷里睡了。不值得搬来搬去的。今天夜里是晴天，不会下雨的。”

死神就是这么来到的。它在低语，可惜你却听不到。绝不会再跟任何人吵架了——这一点他可以保证。这是一次前所未有过的人生经历，他可不愿坏了兴致。不过，他也许会败兴的，因为他老是成事不足败事有余。但这一次他或许不会坏事。

“你会不会听写？”

“从没学过。”她说。

“好吧。”

已经没有时间了。不过，往事浓缩了，只要处理得当，可以用一小段文字加以展现。

湖边有座山，山上有座原木筑成的木屋，原木之间的缝隙抹了白灰泥。门边的柱子上挂着一只铃铛，是叫人进屋吃饭用的。木屋后有片田野，再往远处则是树林。一排伦巴第白杨从木屋一直延伸向码头。还有一排白杨树排列在岬角旁。树林边有条羊肠小道通向山上。他曾经沿着这条小道采摘黑莓。后来木屋遭大火焚毁，而火塘旁鹿脚形枪架上的那些枪支也随之化为灰烬。大火过后，枪管和枪托烧坏了，枪膛里的子弹熔化了，残余物胡乱放在一堆灰上——那些灰是制肥皂的大铁锅用来熬碱液的。你问祖父能不能把那些东西拿来玩。祖父说不能。那些枪是他的宝贝，从那以后他再也没买过其他的枪，再也没打过猎。如今，在老地方又建起了一座木屋，漆成了白色。从门廊可以看见白杨树以及远处的湖泊，但木屋里再也没见到过枪支。那些曾经架在原木小屋墙壁鹿脚形枪架上的枪支，如今只剩下了枪管，胡乱放在灰堆之上，再也没有人动过。

战争结束后，我们在黑森林(10)租赁了一条小溪，可以在里面钓鳟鱼。有两条路可以抵达那儿。一条路是从特里贝格出发，直下山谷，沿一条白白的山谷小路前行，两旁是郁郁葱葱的林木，然后取一条偏道翻山越岭，沿途可见鳞次栉比的小农场和一幢幢高大的“黑森林”式房屋。这条偏道穿过小溪，而我们就是在偏道和小溪交叉的地方钓鱼的。

另一条路是爬陡坡抵达森林跟前，穿过松树林，翻过山头，出林子之后走到一片草场边，接着越过草场抵达那座小桥跟前。在那儿，小溪旁长着一排排桦树，水面不宽，而是很窄，溪水清澈、湍急，冲击着桦树的树根，冲出了一个个小水潭。在特里贝格的那家旅馆，正值好季节，老板的生意很是兴旺。当时的气氛令人愉悦，我们成了好朋友。可第二年遇上通货膨胀，他前一年挣的钱不够买开旅馆所用的必需品，于是他上吊寻了短见。

这些情况倒是可以口授，可是你在护墙广场(11)的所见所闻就难以口授了。在大街上，卖花的小贩给花上染料，弄得路面上染料水横流；这儿是公共汽车的发车点；老头老太太喜欢来此处喝葡萄酒和劣质的渣酿白兰地酒；孩子们在寒风中清鼻涕直流；“业余爱好者”咖啡馆里散发着难闻的汗臭和贫穷的气味，顾客们喝得酩酊大醉，而妓女们在风笛舞厅卖弄风情（她们就住在舞厅的楼上）。那个看门的女人在她的小房间里款待共和国卫队的队员，队员那插着马鬃的头盔放在一把椅子上。门厅对面住着个女子，丈夫是个自行车赛手。这天早晨喝牛奶时，她打开《车讯报》，看见丈夫在环巴黎车赛中名列第三（这是他首次参加大赛），不由满面生辉，大笑出声，然后手里拿着那份黄颜色的体育报，大喊大叫冲下楼去。经营风笛舞厅的是个女人，丈夫是开出租的。一次，他（即哈里）早晨赶飞机，女人的丈夫敲门叫醒他，两人到酒吧间的吧台喝了杯白酒，然后才出发。他跟那块区域的邻居混得很熟——那些邻居都是些穷人。

广场附近住着两类人——酒鬼和运动员。酒鬼借酒浇愁，以忘掉贫困，运动员则是坚持锻炼以驱除贫穷。他们是巴黎公社社员的后代，不用费力就熟知巴黎的政治。他们知道是谁枪杀了他们的父兄及亲友……当年，凡尔赛的军队开进巴黎，继巴黎公社之后占领了这座城市，见手上有老茧的、戴工人帽的，或者有任何其他的标志说明是工人的，一律格杀勿论。他住在这个贫民区里，街对面有个马肉铺和一个酿酒合作社。也就是在这里，他开始了自己的写作生涯。在巴黎，再也没有一块比这儿更叫他喜爱的社区了。他喜欢那婆娑的树影，喜欢那墙壁粉白但墙根涂成棕色的老房子，喜欢圆形广场上那些长长的绿色公共汽车，喜欢那在路面上流淌的染花用的紫色染料水，喜欢那从山上急转直下一直延伸向河边的莱蒙主教街以及另一条街——狭窄、热闹的穆费塔得街。穆费塔得街通向万神殿。还有一条他常在上面骑自行车的街道他也喜欢——那是该地区唯一一条沥青路，在车轮下平平展展的，两旁有又窄又高的房屋和一座高高耸立的廉价旅馆（保罗·魏尔伦(12)就是在这家旅馆离开人世的）。他们住的公寓里只有两个房间。他租了廉价旅馆顶层的一个房间，月房租是六十法郎，专门在此处写作，从窗口可以看到各家各户的屋顶和烟囱，也可以将巴黎的山峦尽收眼底。

从公寓的窗口，却只能看到那家经营木材和煤炭的店铺。他还卖酒，卖劣质酒。马肉铺外边挂着金黄色的马头，而橱窗里挂的是金黄色和红色的马肉。他们一般都到涂着绿漆的酿酒合作社里买酒，那儿的酒物美价廉。其余的景物还有泥灰墙以及邻居家的窗户。夜间酒鬼醉卧街头，哼哼唧唧地呻吟，呈现出典型的法国式醉态（根据宣传，这种醉态压根就不存在），此时邻居们会打开窗户，嗡嗡嗡地交流看法。

“警察跑到哪里去了？不需要他的时候，他偏偏在跟前晃悠，现在却跟哪个女人睡觉去了。还是找个顶事的人来吧。”一桶冷水从哪家的窗口兜头泼了下来，酒鬼这才不乱哼唧了。“这是什么？是水！天呀，这是个好主意！”各家的窗户纷纷关上了。他的女佣玛丽针对八个小时的工作日提出了抗议，说道：“丈夫如果上班上到六点，回家的路上只能喝一点点酒，挥霍的钱不算太多，但如果五点就下班，那他就会夜夜酗酒，把兜里的钱挥霍一空。缩短工时，让工人之妻深受其害。”

“想再喝些肉汤吗？”女人问他

“不喝了。非常感谢，肉汤好喝极了。”

“再喝几口吧。”

“我倒想喝几口威士忌加苏打水。”

“喝酒对你不好。”

“是的，是不好。为此，科尔·波特(13)还专门写过一首歌，并谱了曲呢。恐怕正因为了解这些，你才生我的气。”

“你心里清楚我是愿意让你喝酒的。”

“哦，是吗？愿意让我喝，却又说酒对我不好！”

他心想，等她离开，他想喝多少就喝多少。哦，不，不是想喝多少就喝多少，而是有多少就喝多少。唉，他累了，简直太累了，必须睡一会儿才行。他静静地躺着，发现死神不在跟前，觉得死神一定是到别的地方遛大街去了，可能是结着伴儿，骑着自行车，或者一声不吭地走在人行道上。

不，他从未写过巴黎，未写过让他魂牵梦绕的巴黎。还有些内容他也从未写过。那么，它们究竟是什么呢？

那牧场，那银灰色的鼠尾草灌木丛，灌溉渠里那清澈、湍急的水流，那深绿色的苜蓿！羊肠小道在山间蜿蜒，夏季的牛儿像鹿一样腼腆。牛群哞哞地叫着，喧闹的声音不绝于耳，你秋季赶它们下山时，它们慢慢移动着步子，身后扬起一片尘土。翻过山梁，夕阳中那突兀的山峰清晰可见。月亮升起，在月光下骑马沿羊肠小道下山，山谷里一片皎洁的月色。记得穿过树林时，眼前漆黑，伸手不见五指，只好抓住马的尾巴前行。往事如烟，他曾经有意付诸笔端。

还有那个脑子缺根弦的干杂活的伙计……当时把他留下来看护牧场，叮咛他不准任何人动用牧场上的干草。那个老杂种从河岔口过来，想弄些饲料。小伙计曾为老杂种干过活，挨过他的打，此时一口拒绝了对方，老杂种威胁说还要揍他一顿。小伙计从厨房拿来一杆步枪，就在老杂种试图闯进饲料房时，开枪把他打死了。大家回到牧场时，老杂种已死去一个星期了，尸体在牲口栏里冻得硬邦邦，一部分尸体已被野狗吃掉。你把剩下的尸体卷在毯子里，用绳子捆在雪橇上，让小伙计帮你拖走。你们俩拖着雪橇上路，走了六十英里进城，然后你举报了他。小伙计怎么也想不到自己会被逮捕，满以为自己是在履行职责，以为你是他的朋友，以为自己会得到奖赏呢。老杂种的尸体是他帮着拖来的，谁都知道老杂种是个坏家伙，企图抢走并不属于他的饲料！警长给他戴手铐时，他简直不能相信这是真的，禁不住痛哭流涕……这一素材他原本是打算写成故事的。这样的素材何止二十个，可是他一个都没有用于写作。为什么？

“你说说这是为什么。”他出声地说道。

“什么为什么，亲爱的？”

“哦，没什么。”

自从有了他，她就不再那么嗜酒如命了。但尽管如此，他也绝对不会写她的，对此他是很清楚的。这类人一个都不写！富人乏味得很，喝酒喝得太多，整天就知道玩双陆棋(14)，一个个无聊得厉害，全无鲜明个性。他想起了可怜的朱利安以及朱利安对富人带有浪漫色彩的敬畏感，记得后者写过一篇小说，头一句话便是：“富佬们跟你我截然不同。”八成是有人风趣地对朱利安说富人的钱多得花不完，可是朱利安并不觉得风趣，而是将富人看作一个特殊的富于魅力的种群。当朱利安发现并非如此时，他的心都碎了，就像他的其他幻觉破灭时心碎一样。

至于他，对于那些因幻觉破灭而心碎的人，压根就瞧不起。他心明如镜，当然瞧不起那些人了。他觉得自己打不垮压不倒，因为他什么都不在乎，任什么都伤害不了他。

没什么了不起的。现在就连死亡他也不在乎。一直以来，他唯一害怕的东西是疼痛。他固然能和别人一样忍得住痛，直到疼痛持续的时间太长，折磨得他筋疲力尽。可这一次，正当他疼得死去活来，眼看就要崩溃时，疼痛感却突然停止了。

记得很久以前，一天夜里，投弹军官威廉逊钻铁丝网时，被德军巡逻队扔来的一颗手榴弹炸伤了。他疼得乱叫，央求战友开枪打死他。他是个胖子，虽然喜欢出风头，但作战极其勇敢，称得上一名优秀军官。那天夜里，他被缠在铁丝网上，探照灯光把他照得一览无余，只见他的肠子都被炸了出来，挂在铁丝上。战友们把他救回来时，只好将肠子割断。“开枪打死我，哈里！看在基督的分上，开枪打死我！”他惨叫着。记得关于疼痛，大家有过一场讨论，有人说天主绝不会让你经历无法忍受的疼痛，还有人说疼痛会在某个时刻自行消失的。但他一直对威廉逊的遭遇难以忘怀，记得那天夜里威廉逊的疼痛始终没有消失。他把自己留下来准备自服的吗啡片给了威廉逊，也没有止住对方的疼痛。

眼下，他倒是感到挺轻松的。只要疼痛感不加剧，就没有什么可担心的。他所渴望得到的是一个较好的伴侣。

关于自己想要什么样的伴侣，他略微想了想。

他觉得自己做事优柔寡断，总是迟一步。你总不能让人家老等着你吧。一旦分离，便各奔东西。昔日的聚会已经结束，现在只剩下了你和女主人在一起。他觉得要死还一时死不了，就像所有别的冗长的事情一样让他都感到厌烦了。

“烦死了。”他想着想着说出了声。

“你说什么来着，亲爱的？”

“我是说任何事情都拖得太久。”

说话时，他隔着篝火望着她的脸。她靠在椅背上，火光照亮了她的那张线条优美的脸，看得出她已经有了困意。此刻，他听见篝火的光圈外边传来了鬣狗的一声嚎叫。

“我在写东西，”他说，“感觉很是疲倦。”

“你看你能睡得着吗？”

“这没问题。你为什么不去睡觉呢？”

“我喜欢陪你坐着。”

“难道你感觉有哪个地方不对劲吗？”

“不是的。只是感到有点困。”

“我觉得有点不对劲。”他说。

他感觉到死神又在跟前徘徊了。

“要知道，我唯一没有失去的就是好奇心了。”他对她说道。

“你任何东西都没有失去。你是我所认识的最完美的男子汉。”

“天呀，”他说，“女人家知道的事情真是太少了。你凭什么这么说？难道凭的是直觉？”

此时此刻，他看见死神走上前，将头枕在床脚上，他甚至闻得到死神呼出的气味。

“要是有人说死神像镰刀和骷髅，你可千万别信，”他对她说，“死神完全可以是两个骑自行车的警察，或者说是一只鸟。也许，死神像鬣狗一样有一个宽宽的鼻子。”

此时，死神向他走了过来，但没有任何形体，只是占了一些空间罢了。

“让它走开！”

它没有走开，而是继续朝跟前凑。

“你呼出的气好臭呀，”他冲它说道，“你这臭烘烘的东西。”

它又靠近了些，而他已说不出话来了。它见他说不出话，就又朝前凑了凑。他口不能言，试图将其赶走，可是它爬到了他身上，重重压在他的胸口上，稳稳当当坐在那里，使得他动不能动、说不能说，却听得见那女人说道：“先生睡着了。你们把床抬起来，手脚放轻，抬进帐篷里去。”

他说不出话，无法让女人将死神赶走。死神坐在那里，越来越重，压得他透不过气。当杂役把床抬起来时，感觉却突然好了，压在胸口上的重量消失了。

此时到了早晨，天已经亮了一些时间了。他听见了飞机的声音。飞机显得很小，在空中兜了一个大圈。杂役们跑出去用煤油点火，将青草堆在火上，于是空地两端就有了两大堆火，冒着滚滚浓烟。晨风习习，把烟吹到了帐篷这儿来。飞机又兜了两圈，此时飞得很低，然后向下滑翔和拉平，最终平稳地落在了地上。接着就见康普顿老伙计走了过来，下穿宽松长裤，上穿粗花呢夹克，头戴一顶棕色毡帽。

“怎么啦，老伙计？”康普顿问了一声。

“腿受伤了。”他说道，“需要吃些早点吗？”

“不用了，谢谢。喝杯茶就行了。我的这架飞机是‘舟蛾’型的，只能坐一个乘客，这次就带不了太太了。你们的卡车已在路上了。”

海伦把康普顿拉到了一边，和他说了些什么。康普顿回来时，显得异常高兴。

“这就抬你上飞机，”他说，“送完你，我再回来接太太。恐怕中途得在阿鲁沙停一下加油。现在最好马上出发。”

“茶还喝不喝了？”

“随便说说，我并不是真的想喝茶。”

杂役抬起小床，绕过一个个绿色的帐篷，下了石台，走到空地上。空地两端的火堆烧得正旺，冒烟的青草已熊熊燃烧，风助火势，火势越大。杂役从火堆旁经过，把床抬到了小飞机跟前。抬他进机舱时，着实费了一番力气。而一进机舱，他便瘫倒在皮椅上，伤腿直直伸到飞行员的座位旁。康普顿把飞机发动后，钻进了驾驶舱。他向海伦及杂役们挥手告别。飞机发出咔嗒咔嗒的声音，随后那咔嗒声变成了他所熟悉的吼叫。康普顿让飞机掉过头，躲开疣猪打的洞，轰隆轰隆颠簸着开过两堆火之间的空地，最后又颠了一下便腾空而起。他看见底下的人们在挥手，山丘旁的营地成了平面图，平原一望无际，一片片的树丛和灌木丛成了扁平状，通向干涸水坑的狩猎小道显得很平展。他还看见了一处自己以前所不知道的水源地。斑马显得很小，只能看得见它们那圆滚滚的脊背。牛羚成了蠕动的黑点，昂着巨大的脑袋，像长长的手指一样穿过平原。当飞机投下的影子向它们冲来时，吓得它们四散逃窜。它们小极了，虽疾奔却像是爬行。极目远眺，看得见平原一片灰黄色，而眼前看到的则是康普顿的粗花呢夹克和棕色毡帽。飞机下开始有大山出现了，牛羚群正在往山上爬。从群山上空飞过时，看得见山谷陡峭，那儿的森林郁郁葱葱，坡地上竹林成片。再往前飞，仍是浓密的森林，覆盖了山巅，覆盖了峡谷。飞过森林，山势逐渐平缓，山后又出现了平原。天气炎热，平原上一片紫棕色。飞机在热浪中颠簸着。康普顿回头看了看，看他情况如何。飞着飞着，前边又出现了群山，黑压压的。

后来，他们转了方向，没有继续朝着阿鲁沙飞，而是拐向了左边。他猜想一定是飞机加好了油。往下看，只见一片粉红色的云彩掠过大地，那云彩像筛子眼里筛出来的一样，从空中看，又像是凭空而降的暴风雪袭来时打头阵的飞雪。他知道那是从南方飞来的蝗虫。接下来，飞机开始往高爬，像是朝东方飞，飞着飞着天色黑了下来，原来是遇到了暴风雨，雨点密密麻麻，弄得飞机像是在穿过一道瀑布。暴风雨过后，康普顿回过头咧嘴笑了笑，然后指了指前方，只见那儿矗立着乞力马扎罗山的山巅，方方正正，开阔得不得了，高耸入云，在阳光下白得令人无法相信。他意识到那儿是他的目的地。

就在这时，在一片夜色里，鬣狗不再呜咽，开始发出一种奇怪的声音，跟人的哭声差不多。女人听了，不安地翻了个身，但没有醒来。梦中的她待在长岛的家里，那是女儿步入社交界的头一个夜晚。不知怎么，她的父亲也在场，显得很粗暴。鬣狗的叫声太大，把她从梦中吵醒了。一时间，她不知自己身在何处，不由感到非常害怕。她拿起手电筒，照了照另外的一张床——那张床是哈里睡着后大家抬进帐篷里来的。透过蚊帐，她可以看到哈里的身躯，但不知怎么哈里的一条腿伸了出来，耷拉在小床的一边，绷带都脱落了，让她不忍看下去。

“莫洛！”她喊了起来，“莫洛！莫洛！”

随后，她叫道：“哈里！哈里！”见对方没答应，她提高了嗓门，“哈里！请你醒醒！天呀，哈里！”

她听不到回答，也听不到哈里的呼吸声。

帐篷外，鬣狗又在叫了——正是那奇怪的叫声惊醒了她。但此刻，她却听不见那叫声了，因为她的心怦怦乱跳，心跳声盖过了那叫声。

————————————————————

(1) 乞力马扎罗（Kilimanjaro）位于坦桑尼亚东北部及东非大裂谷以南约160公里，是坦桑尼亚和肯尼亚的分水岭，非洲最高的山脉，同时也是火山和雪山。

(2) 马赛人（Masai）属于尼罗河流域半游牧民族的一个分支，生活在肯尼亚以及坦桑尼亚北部，2009年统计肯尼亚共有84万马赛人。因其独一无二、与众不同的生活习俗、服装和居住地，马赛人成为非洲大陆最为世界所知的一个民族。马赛人有自己的语言，是尼罗河及撒哈拉地区语言大家族中的一员，与苏丹南部丁卡人（Dinka）和努尔人（Nuer，苏丹境内和埃塞俄比亚边界上的游牧民族）的语言有血缘关系。

(3) 詹姆斯·布莱克（1823—1893），美国戒酒运动领袖。

(4) 肯尼亚的一个部族。

(5) 以上三处均在美国。

(6) 南森（1861—1930），挪威北极探险家、博物学家及外交家，曾获1922年诺贝尔和平奖。

(7) 斯威夫特和阿穆尔是美国的两大巨富，代表的是豪门。Armour（阿穆尔）和armour（盔甲）同词同音。

(8) 达达主义是1916年至1923年出现的一种艺术流派。达达主义是一种无政府主义的艺术运动，它试图通过废除传统的文化和美学形式发现真正的现实。

(9) 特里斯唐·查拉（1896—1963），罗马尼亚人，达达主义运动创始人之一。

(10) 黑森林，又称条顿森林，位于德国西南的巴符州。由于森林树木茂密，远看一片黑压压的，因此得名。

(11) 巴黎最著名的广场之一，此处咖啡馆较多，名人题词随处可见。

(12) 保罗·魏尔伦（1844—1896），法国诗人，象征主义文学的代表人物之一。

(13) 科尔·波特（1891—1964），美国著名音乐家。

(14) 一种棋盘游戏，双方各有15枚棋子，靠掷骰子决定走棋步数，棋子先到达终点的胜。

桥头旁边的老人

一个戴金丝边眼镜的老人坐在路边，衣服上落满了灰尘。河上架着个浮桥，桥上人来车往，有骡车有汽车，有男人有女人，也有小孩。下了桥就是陡坡，骡车爬坡时十分吃力，几个士兵用手抓住车轮的轮辐帮着朝上推。一辆辆卡车轰隆轰隆开上坡，随后向远方驶去。一些农民在脚踝深的尘土里艰难跋涉。而老人坐在那里，连挪动一下也没有。他太累了，一步也走不动了。

当时我的任务是过桥去侦察桥头堡，看敌军推进到了哪个地方。完成任务后，我又经桥上返回。此时车辆已不多了，行人也稀稀拉拉的。可老人仍坐在原来的地方。

“你是哪儿来的？”我问他。

“从圣·卡洛斯来。”他说完笑了笑。

圣·卡洛斯是他的故乡，提到那儿让他高兴，于是脸上出现了笑容。

“我当时正在照看几只动物。”他解释说。

“是吗？”我说道。对于他的话，我不太明白。

“是的。”他说，“我留在圣·卡洛斯镇照看动物，是最后一个离开的。”

看他那样子，既不像羊倌也不像牛倌。我望了望他那落满了灰尘的黑衣服以及满是尘土的脏脏的脸，又望望他的金丝边眼镜，然后问道：“什么动物呀？”

“有各种各样的动物。”他说着，无奈地摇了摇头，“没办法，只好把它们丢下了。”

搭着话，我眼睛观察着桥面，观察着那非洲味十足的埃布罗河(1)三角洲地区，心里在打小鼓，不知敌军还有多长时间就会出现。我侧耳倾听动静——一有动静便预示着那带有几分神秘色彩的遭遇战就会打响。这段时间，老人始终坐在那儿。

“都有什么动物？”我问。

“总共有三种，”他回答说，“两只山羊、一只猫以及四对鸽子。”

“你是被迫把它们丢在了身后？”我问。

“是的。因为那儿在打炮。上尉怕我伤着，劝我赶快走。”

“你家里没亲人吗？”我问着话，一边观察着远处的桥头，那儿最后的几辆骡车正在驶下河岸的斜坡。

“没有。”他说，“只有我刚才提到的几只动物。那只猫当然不成问题，它会照料自己的。我所担心的是另外几只动物，真不知它们会怎么样。”

“你有政治信仰吗？”我问。

“我不过问政治。”他说，“我已是七十六岁的人了，今天走了有十二公里的路，恐怕再也走不动了。”

“这地方不适合于歇脚。”我说，“如果你还能走得动，岔路口那边有卡车，那儿通向托尔托萨。”

“我要等一会儿，”他说，“等一会儿再走。卡车是到哪儿去的？”

“到巴塞罗那。”我说。

“那边我没有认识的人。”他说，“不过，还是要感谢你的。非常感谢。”

他望着我，目光茫然、疲倦。随后，他好像是为了有个人为他分担一些心里的忧虑，又说道：“那只猫能熬得过去，这一点是肯定的，没必要为它操心。但另外的几只动物就不行了。你看它们会不会出事呢？”

“哦，它们可能会挺得过来的。”

“你是这么想的吗？”

“那是没有问题的。”我说着话，眼睛盯着远处的河岸，那边已看不到骡车了。

“他们叫我走，是因为要打炮了。可是，一旦开炮，那些动物该怎么办呢？”

“鸽子笼的门没有关吧？”我问。

“没有。”

“那它们会飞走的。”

“是呀，它们肯定会飞走的。可别的那几个是不会飞的。算啦，不为它们担心了。”他说。

“歇够了吧？我该走了。”我催促道，“你站起来，看能不能走。”

“谢谢你了。”他说完站了起来，可是摇晃了几下，又一屁股坐到了尘土里。

“我原来是在照料动物的。”他木然地说道，这次的话不是讲给我听的，而是喃喃自语，“我只是照料照料动物，又没有妨碍谁。”

对于他，我爱莫能助。那天是复活节的星期天，法西斯正在逼近埃布罗河。当时，天色昏暗，阴云压顶，法西斯的飞机没能起飞。这一点，再加上猫能够自己照料自己，对老人而言就是不幸中的万幸了。

————————————————————

(1) 埃布罗河位于西班牙北部。

在密歇根州北部

吉姆·吉尔摩从加拿大来到霍顿斯湾，从霍顿老头手中把铁匠铺买了下来。吉姆矮矮的个子，皮肤黝黑，大胡子，大手。他是个钉马掌的行家，可即便系上皮裙，他也不太像个铁匠。他歇宿于铁匠铺的楼上，就餐于迪·吉·史密斯家中。

莉兹·科茨为史密斯家干杂活。史密斯夫人是个大块头女人，酷爱干净。说莉兹·科茨是她所见过的最整洁的姑娘。莉兹有两条漂亮的腿，腰间总系着干干净净的条纹棉布围裙。吉姆注意到她头后的发辫总是一丝不乱。他喜欢她的脸，因为那张脸上荡漾着欢乐，可是对她这个人心里却没有多想。

莉兹对吉姆喜欢得不得了。她喜欢他从铁匠铺走过来的样子，于是常跑到厨房门口，等着看他沿大路走过来。她喜欢看他的大胡子，喜欢他微笑时露出的一口白牙。就连他看上去不像个铁匠以及史密斯夫妇对他有好感，也让她喜欢。一天，吉姆在屋外的洗脸盆里擦身子，她看到他胳膊上的毛是黑的，而没有被太阳晒黑的上半部分十分白，她发现这竟然也让她感到喜欢。这种莫名的喜欢叫她觉得挺可笑的。

霍顿斯湾是个小镇，镇上的一条大路，一头通达博伊恩市，另一头通向沙勒沃伊，这条大路上只有五户人家。镇上有座房屋，既是杂货铺又是邮局，有个高高的假门脸，或许门前还会停放一辆大车。那五户人家是史密斯家、斯特劳德家、迪尔沃思家、霍顿家以及范·胡森家。这些住家坐落于一大片榆树林中。那条大路是条沙土路，路两边是农田和树林。顺着大路朝前走是卫理公会教堂，而相反的方向则是所镇办学校。铁匠铺用油漆漆成了红色，和学校面对面。

一条陡峭的沙土路顺山而下，穿过树林，直达港湾。从史密斯家的后门眺望，目光越过延伸向山脚下湖边的林木，可以看到港湾对面的景色。春夏两季，这儿风光旖旎，港湾湛蓝湛蓝，阳光明媚，从沙勒沃伊和密歇根湖那边吹来的微风会在岬角后的湖面上掀起朵朵白浪。从史密斯家的后门口观景，莉兹看得到运矿石的驳船行驶在湖面上，朝着博伊恩市开去。眼睛望着那些驳船，它们好像一动不动。可是，如果进厨房擦干净几个碟子再走出来看，驳船就不见了踪影，消失在了岬角之后。

莉兹心里无时无刻不在想着吉姆·吉尔摩，可是对方似乎对她并不十分上心。他老是跟迪·吉·史密斯谈铁匠铺的事，谈共和党，谈詹姆斯·吉·布莱恩(1)。晚上，他则凑在前厅的灯下读《托莱多(2)刀锋报》和《大急流城报》，要不然就提着灯和迪·吉·史密斯一道去港湾里叉鱼。秋天，他则随史密斯、查利·怀曼，赶着大车，带上帐篷、干粮、斧子、步枪以及两条狗，前往范德比尔特那边的松树平原猎鹿。在他们出发之前，莉兹和史密斯夫人为他们准备吃的，要忙活四天。莉兹原本想特地为吉姆做些东西带去路上吃，却最终没有如愿，因为她不敢问史密斯夫人要鸡蛋和面粉，假如自己去买了食材来，做的时候又怕被史密斯夫人看见。其实，史密斯夫人是不会计较的，可莉兹就是不敢。

吉姆去猎鹿期间，莉兹老想他。他这一走，时间可真是难熬呀。由于思念他，她睡觉也睡得不香了。不过，她发现正是因为想他，生活也有了乐趣。听之任之，日子倒是挺好的。他们回来的头一天晚上，她彻夜未眠，意思是说她认为自己彻夜未眠——她魂游梦乡，分不清自己究竟睡着了没有。看见大车沿着大路驶来，她心里翻江倒海，忐忑不安，有一种急不可耐的心情。直到看见吉姆，她的心才安宁了下来。看来，吉姆一回来，万般忧虑都烟消云散了。大车停在了外边的那棵大榆树下，史密斯夫人和莉兹迎了出去。男人们满脸胡须，大车的后面装着三只鹿，细细的鹿腿从车厢边硬邦邦地戳了出来。史密斯夫人吻了吻迪·吉，后者则给了她一个拥抱。吉姆说了声“你好，莉兹”，然后咧嘴一笑。事先，莉兹并不知道吉姆回来后会出现什么情况，但她觉得一定会发生什么事件。可是，什么事件也没有发生。男人们回家了，仅此而已。吉姆把蒙在鹿身上的粗麻袋片取掉，莉兹朝车上瞅了一眼。有一只鹿是大个头公鹿，已经僵硬了，从车上卸下来时费了些气力。

“这只是你打的吗，吉姆？”莉兹问。

“是的。漂亮不漂亮？”吉姆说着，把公鹿扛到背上，扛到熏制室里去了。

晚上，查利·怀曼留在史密斯家吃饭，由于天色已晚，回不成沙勒沃伊了。男人们擦洗完，来到前厅等着吃饭。

“酒罐里还剩下一些酒吧，吉米(3)？”迪·吉·史密斯问。吉姆听了，便到停放在谷仓里的大车那儿，去取狩猎路上带的那个威士忌酒罐。酒罐能装四加仑，罐底还有不少酒液在晃荡。回屋的路上，吉姆美美地喝了一大口。酒罐太大，把它举起来喝酒决非易事。一不小心，一些威士忌酒液流到了他的衬衫前襟上。那两个男人见他抱着酒罐进来，不由得会心一笑。迪·吉·史密斯让取酒杯来，莉兹应命去取了来。迪·吉斟满了三大杯。

“来，为你干杯，迪·吉！”查利·怀曼说。

“为那只大公鹿干杯，吉米！”迪·吉说。

“为所有没有被打中的猎物干杯！”吉姆说完，把杯里的酒一饮而尽。

“男子汉就应该喝这样的酒。”

“真是一杯解千愁呀。”

“再来一杯怎么样，伙计们？”

“祝你万事如意，迪·吉！”

“祝大家万事如意，伙计们！”

“为明年干杯！”

吉姆开始有了腾云驾雾的感觉。他喜欢威士忌的味道，喜欢畅饮威士忌的那种感觉。回家真好——这儿有舒服的床、热腾腾的食物，有那个铁匠铺。他干完了一杯之后，又来了一杯。男人进餐厅吃饭时，一个个兴高采烈，但不失风度。莉兹把饭菜端上来，也坐在桌旁跟大家一起进餐。饭菜的味道喷香，男人们吃圆了肚子。饭后，他们又回到了前厅，而莉兹和史密斯夫人清理桌面。忙活完，史密斯夫人上楼休息去了。不一会儿，史密斯走出前厅，也上楼去了。吉姆和查利仍在前厅闲坐。莉兹坐在厨房里炉子旁边，假装在看书，心里却净在想吉姆。她不甘心就这么去睡觉，觉得吉姆早晚都会从前厅出来的，想着趁他出来最后看他一眼，之后带着他的眼神上床睡觉。

就在她苦苦把吉姆千思万想时，吉姆从前厅出来了。他双眼闪着亮光，头发有点凌乱。莉兹没抬眼睛，把目光盯在书上。吉姆步上前，站在了她的椅后。她可以感觉到他的呼吸。后来，他把她抱在了怀里。在他的抚摸下，她感到胸脯发胀，乳头挺立了起来。她吓得魂魄都没有了，因为还没有男人摸过她呢。同时，她也有一丝庆幸，心想：“他终于来找我了。这是千真万确的。”

由于害怕，她身体变得发硬，真不知如何是好。吉姆搂紧她，使她紧贴椅背，吻了她一口。随之而至的是一种剧烈的疼痛感，一种受伤害的感觉，她觉得自己都快受不了了。透过椅背，她感觉得到吉姆，一时间都快崩溃了。而就在这时，她的内心咔嗒响了一下，随之便有了温暖的感觉，便有了缱绻的柔情。吉姆搂紧她，让她紧贴椅背，而此刻的她渴望得到吉姆的拥抱。吉姆悄声说：“走，咱们出去走走。”

莉兹从厨房的衣钩上取下外套，两人厮跟着出了门。吉姆用一只胳膊搂住她的腰。他们走几步路就要停下来，搂一搂抱一抱。吉姆不断地吻她。天上没有月亮，他们走在路上，沙土有脚踝深，穿过树林，一直走到港湾旁的码头和库房那儿。湾里的水轻轻拍打着码头的木桩，港湾对面的岬角黑黢黢地矗立在那儿。天气寒冷，但是和吉姆在一起，莉兹感到浑身热乎乎的。两人走到仓库的遮檐下坐了下来。吉姆把她拉到怀里。她害怕了。吉姆把一只手伸进她的怀里摸她的胸脯，另一只手搭在她的膝上。她惊魂难定，不知接下来会出现什么情况，可是身子却偎紧了他。她觉得搭在她膝上的那只手大极了。后来，那只手移到了她的腿上，接着便顺着腿朝上摸。

“别这样，吉姆！”她说道。吉姆没理会，那只手继续朝上摸。

“你不能这样，吉姆。你不能这样。”

可是，无论是吉姆还是吉姆的那只大手，对她的央求都没有加以理会。地板很硬。吉姆已经掀起了她的衣服，对她有所图谋。她心里又害怕又渴望。她必须实现心愿，同时又感到心惊肉跳。

“你不能这样，吉姆。你不能这样。”

“我必须这样。我要做的。你也知道不做是不行的。”

“不，不能这样，吉姆。不该这样。这样做是不对的。哎哟，那东西太大，把我弄疼了。不能这样。哎哟，吉姆。吉姆，哎哟。”

码头的铁杉木板已经破损，又冰又硬。吉姆重重压在她身上，对她的伤害已经造成。她觉得难受，浑身痉挛，推了一把吉姆。吉姆竟然呼呼大睡起来，一动不动。她挣扎了几下，总算从吉姆的身下挣脱了，然后拉了拉裙子和衣服，用手指梳理了一下头发。吉姆仍在大睡，嘴巴微张。她俯下身子，吻了吻他的脸颊。他没醒，仍在梦乡中。她把他的头朝上抬了抬，摇了摇。他脑袋一歪，转了过去，咽了一口口水。她不由潸然泪下，举步走到码头边，望了望脚下的水。轻雾从港湾那儿冉冉升起。她身上发冷，心里一阵悲哀，觉得一切都完了。她回到吉姆躺着的地方，又摇了摇他，想把他摇醒。

她流着泪说道：“吉姆，吉姆，求求你了，快醒醒。”

吉姆仅仅动了动，身子蜷缩成了一团。她脱下外套，俯身给他盖上，然后为他掖好，动作麻利、细心。接着，她穿过码头，走上陡峭的沙土路回家睡觉去了。轻雾带着寒意从港湾升起，弥漫在树林里。

————————————————————

(1) 美国共和党议员。

(2) 美国一港市。

(3) 吉姆的昵称。

印第安人营地

又有一条小船被拽上了湖岸。两个印第安人站立在一旁。

尼克和父亲坐进了小船的尾部。印第安人用力一推，把小船推下水，其中的一个跳进去准备划桨。乔治大叔乘的是营地的小船，坐在小船的尾部。那个年纪轻的印第安人推营地的船下水，为他执桨。

在一片黑暗中，两条船出发了。浓雾茫茫，尼克听见前边老远的地方另外一条船的桨架发出咯吱咯吱的声响。印第安人划动着船桨，又快又猛。尼克躺了下来，父亲用一条胳膊搂着他。水面上寒气逼人。为他们父子划船的那个印第安人倒是挺卖力的，可是另一条船在浓雾里始终领先于他们，越来越远了。

“这是去哪儿，爸爸？”尼克问。

“去印第安人营地。有个印第安妇女病得很厉害。”

“明白了。”尼克说。

到了港湾的对面，他们发现另一条船已被拉上了岸。乔治大叔在黑影里抽雪茄。那个年轻的印第安人把小船在沙滩上拖了好一段路。乔治大叔给了两个印第安人每人一根雪茄烟。

大家离开沙滩，穿过一片露水浸湿的草地。年轻的印第安人提着一盏灯在前边引路。后来进了树林，沿着一条羊肠小道前行，而小道通向运木材的大路，大路则通向山间。大路上要亮堂得多，因为两边的树都被砍光了。年轻的印第安人停住脚步，吹灭了灯。大家继续前行。

他们转过一道弯，见一条狗狂吠着跑了过来。前边几间简陋的小屋里亮着灯，那儿住着一些靠剥树皮为生的印第安人(1)。又有几条狗冲了过来。两个印第安人喝退了它们。离道路最近的小屋窗口闪射出一线灯光。一个老妪提着一盏灯等候在门口。

屋里的木床上躺着一个年轻的印第安女子。她在生孩子，已经两天了也没把孩子生下来。营地里的老年妇女纷纷前来照料她，男人们则顺着大路走得远远的，直到听不见她的惨叫声，坐在黑影里抽烟。尼克以及那两个印第安人随父亲和乔治大叔走进小屋时，正赶上产妇在惨叫。她躺在双层床的下铺，盖着被子，肚子鼓得很大，脑袋偏向一旁。上铺躺着她的丈夫。几天前他干活时，斧头掉在脚上，把脚伤得很厉害。此刻，他在抽烟，把屋里弄得烟味很重。

尼克的父亲吩咐把水放到炉子上烧热。在此期间，他跟尼克说了几句话。

“这个妇人要生孩子了，尼克。”他说道。

“我知道。”尼克说。

“你并不了解。”父亲说，“我讲给你听。产妇正在经历的阶段叫‘分娩’。孩子想从肚子里出来，她也想把孩子生下来，于是肌肉紧绷，用全身力气生孩子。她尖声叫喊，就是因为这种情况的出现。”

“明白了。”尼克说。

他话音未落，产妇又尖叫了一声。

“天呀，爸爸，你就不能给她服点药，让她不要再叫了？”尼克问。

“不行，我没有带麻药。”父亲说，“她叫不叫都没有关系。因为没有关系，我都不去听她的。”

躺在上铺的那个丈夫翻了个身，把脸转向墙壁。

在厨房里忙活的那个女人冲医生（尼克的父亲）做了个手势，表示水已经热了。后者走进厨房，把大壶里的水倒进脸盆，倒了大概有一半的样子。接着，他将包在一块手帕里的几样药物放入大壶剩下的水里。

“这个是需要烧开的。”他叮咛道。然后，他就用盆里的热水以及营地里带来的一块肥皂开始洗手，边洗边搓。尼克在一旁观看，看父亲用肥皂把两只手搓来搓去的。父亲洗手洗得很仔细，很彻底，嘴里还说着话。

“要知道，尼克，生小孩应该是头先出来，但例外的情况时有发生。遇到这例外的情况，可就麻烦了。这个产妇出现这种情况，恐怕得做手术。等一会儿就知道了。”

待他觉得把手洗干净了，便到产妇那儿准备接生。

“请你把被子掀开好吗，乔治？”他说，“我的手是不能动那被子的。”

随后，接生开始了。乔治大叔和三个印第安男子用力将产妇按住。产妇在乔治大叔的胳膊上咬了一口，气得乔治大叔骂了一声：“该死的臭婆娘！”惹得划船送他过来的那个年轻印第安人大笑了几声。这期间，尼克为父亲端着脸盆。接生接了很长时间。孩子生下来后，父亲将他拎起，拍了拍，让他能够呼吸，最后把他交给了那个老妪。

“你也看到了，尼克，是个男孩。”他说，“让你当这个实习医生，还喜欢吧？”

“还好吧。”尼克说，眼睛却望着别处，因为他不愿看父亲手里正在做的事情。

“好啦，这就可以了。”父亲说着，不知把什么东西放进了脸盆里。尼克连看也没有看。

“接下来，”父亲说道，“需要缝上几针。你看不看都可以，尼克，随你怎么样吧。我要把割开的口子缝上。”

尼克没有观看那一幕。他的好奇心早已不见了踪影。

父亲将伤口缝合后，直起了身子。乔治大叔和那三个印第安男子也直起了身子。尼克把脸盆端到了厨房里。

乔治大叔低头看了看自己的胳膊。那个年轻的印第安人想起刚才的情景，微微一笑。

“我会给你涂点双氧水的，乔治。”医生说。他说完，俯下身子查看印第安产妇的情况。产妇现在安静了下来，双目紧闭，面如死灰。她不知道孩子的状况，对于别的情况也一无所知。

“明天早晨我再过来看看。”医生直起了身子说，“中午，会有护士从圣·伊格纳斯赶来，把需要的东西都带过来。”

他心情很好，话也多了起来，就像足球运动员赛后回到更衣室里一样，说起话来滔滔不绝的。

“这台手术简直可以上医学杂志了，乔治。”他说，“用一把大折刀做剖腹产手术，缝伤口用的是锥形羊肠线！”

乔治大叔靠着墙根，眼睛望着自己那被咬伤了的胳膊。

“是呀，你的确十分了不起。”他说。

“应该看看那个自豪的爸爸。遇到这类事情，他们初为人父，通常忍受的痛苦最大。”医生说，“我得说，这位爸爸实在能沉得住气。”

说着，他将蒙在那个印第安人头上的毯子一把扯开。这一扯，他觉得手上湿乎乎的。他一手提起灯，踩到下铺的床沿上，查看了一下上铺，只见那个印第安人面朝墙躺着，喉咙已经彻底被割断，血流成河，聚积在他身子在床上压出来的深窝里。印第安人把头枕在自己的左胳膊上。一把剃刀打开着，刀锋朝上放在毯子上。

“快把尼克带出去，乔治！”医生说。

这已是多此一举了。父亲一手提灯，一手把印第安人的头向后推去时，尼克正站在厨房门口，一览无余地看见了上铺的情况。

父子俩沿着运木材的大路回到湖边时，天已开始放亮。

“都怪我，真不该带你来，尼克。”父亲说道。他做完手术后那种得意的劲儿彻底消失了。“这件事搞得一团糟，都让你看见了。”

“女人生孩子是不是都这么难呢？”尼克问。

“不，这是个例外，一个罕见的例外。”

“他为什么要自杀呢，爸爸？”

“我也不知道，尼克。我想他可能是受不了了。”

“自杀的男人是不是很多呢，爸爸？”

“不太多，尼克。”

“自杀的女人多不多？”

“很罕见。”

“到底有没有呢？”

“哦，有的。她们有时候也会自杀的。”

“爸爸！”

“怎么？”

“乔治大叔去哪儿了？”

“他会过来的。”

“死亡是件很难的事吗？”

“不难。我想是很容易的，尼克。这要看怎么说了。”

父子两人上了船。尼克坐在船尾，父亲划桨。太阳从山后冉冉升起。一条鲈鱼跃出水面，落下来在水中激起一圈涟漪。尼克把手伸进水里划动着。早晨的空气冰冷冷的，而水是温的。

清晨，坐在船尾行驶在湖面上，有父亲划桨，尼克心情笃定，觉得自己永远也不会死去。

————————————————————

(1) 当时，铁杉树的树皮价值很高，一些印第安人靠剥树皮为生。

三日狂风

尼克拐上了一条贯穿果园的小路。就在这时，雨停了。果子已经摘了，秋风呼呼地在光秃秃的树木间吹着。路边有只瓦格纳苹果躺在草丛里，由于被雨水洗过而闪着亮光。尼克停住脚步，把它捡起来，放入他那件厚呢短大衣的口袋里。

小路出了果园，蜿蜒抵达山头。山头上有座农舍，门廊里空无一人，烟囱里冒着烟。屋后有车库、鸡舍，还有一片二茬树，二茬树像一道藩篱，将后边的林子隔开。放眼望去，只见远处的大树在风中摇晃。这是秋季的第一场风暴。

尼克出了果园，穿过一片空地，农舍的房门打开了，比尔走了出来。比尔站在门廊那儿，向这边望着。

“你好，维米奇！”他说。

“你好，比尔！”尼克说，一边抬腿走上了台阶。

两人站在了一起，一道向远处眺望，目光越过田野，从果园上方飘过，再经过小路、山脚下的野地以及岬角处的树林，一直望向湖水。狂风卷过湖面，看得到十里岬那儿浪花翻涌。

“在刮大风呢。”尼克说。

“这场风要连着刮三天呢。”比尔说。

“你爸爸在家吗？”尼克问。

“不在。他拿着枪出门了。来，进来吧。”

尼克走进了农舍。壁炉里炉火熊熊。狂风吹来，吹得火呼呼地响。比尔急忙关上了门。

“喝一杯吧？”他说。

他转身去了厨房，拿来了两个杯子和一罐水。尼克伸手到壁炉架上取放在那儿的一瓶威士忌。

“可以吗？”他问。

“好的。”比尔说。

两人在炉火前坐下，开始喝掺水的爱尔兰威士忌。

“这酒挺好喝的，有一股烟草味。”尼克说，一边透过杯中的酒望着炉火。

“是泥炭味。”比尔说。

“怎么能往酒里加泥炭呢？”尼克说。

“加点泥炭是没什么大不了的。”比尔说。

“你见过泥炭吗？”尼克问。

“没见过。”比尔说。

“我也没见过。”尼克说。

他把脚放在炉边，鞋被火烤得冒着蒸汽。

“最好把你的鞋脱掉。”比尔说。

“我没有穿袜子。”

“你把鞋脱下来烤干，我去找双袜子来。”比尔说。他说完就上楼到小阁楼里去了。尼克听到了他在头顶走动的声音。阁楼没有天花板，直接处于屋顶之下。比尔父子以及尼克偶尔在里面睡睡觉。阁楼的后部有间更衣室。他们把小床移到雨水淋不着的地方，用橡胶罩子罩严。

比尔拿着一双厚厚的毛袜子走了下来。

“天晚了，不穿袜子走动起来不方便。”他说。

“真不愿穿袜子哟。”尼克说。他把袜子套到脚上，又一屁股坐回到椅子上，将两只脚架在炉火前的防护栏上。

“可别把防护栏弄坏了。”比尔说。尼克听了，急忙将脚移开，放到了壁炉旁。

“有什么书看看吗？”他问。

“只有报纸。”

“卡斯队(1)的战况如何？”

“两场都输给了巨人队(2)。”

“原本该赢的呀。”

“拱手把胜利送给了人家。”比尔说，“联合会里有好的球员，麦格劳(3)都会花钱买走，别的队根本没戏可唱。”

“他总不能都买走呀。”尼克说。

“反正他看上谁就买谁。”比尔说，“行不通，他就让球员产生不满情绪，乖乖地归顺于他。”

“海尼·齐姆就是一例。”尼克赞同地说。

“那个笨蛋会给他带来许多好处的。”

比尔说着站起了身。

“他可以为他得分。”尼克说。炉火的热气把他的腿烤得暖暖的。

“他还是个出色的外野手呢。”比尔说，“不过，他也有输球的时候。”

“麦格劳要他，恐怕正是因为这些。”尼克分析说。

“也许吧。”比尔同意了他的观点。

“里面肯定还会有更多不可告人的勾当。”尼克说。

“当然喽。不过，咱们远离他们，反而听到的内幕消息更真实。”

“这就跟买赛马票一样，眼睛看不到马，选择时反而更明智。”

“就是这个道理。”

比尔伸手取过酒瓶，一只大手把酒瓶整个儿握住，把威士忌倒入尼克递过来的酒杯里。

“掺多少水？”

“跟往常一样吧。”

斟完酒，比尔席地而坐，坐在了尼克座椅旁的地板上。

“秋天起风暴还怪好的，是不是？”尼克说。

“是挺不错的。”

“这可是一年中最好的时候了。”尼克说。

“待在城里可能会很惨吧？”比尔说。

“我很想看世界职业棒球大赛。”尼克说。

“哦，如今这样的赛事老是在纽约或费城举办。”比尔说，“这对咱们没一点好处。”

“不知道卡斯队能不能赢上那么一场。”

“这辈子怕是看不到了。”比尔说。

“可惜，他们会疯掉的。”尼克说。

“还记得火车出事之前他们的那种热血沸腾的样子吗？”

“当然记得！”尼克回忆起往事说道。

比尔伸手去拿扣在窗前桌子上的那本书，那是他去开门时放在那儿的。他一手端酒杯，一手拿书，把背靠在尼克的椅子上。

“你在看什么书？”

“《理查德·费福利尔》(4)。”

“这本书我是看不下去的。”

“还好吧。”比尔说，“反正这不是本糟糕的书，维米奇。”

“你这儿有没有别的我没有看过的书？”尼克问。

“《森林情侣》(5)你看过没有？”

“看过。书中的主人公每天夜里睡觉，两个人之间都要放一把出鞘的剑。”

“这是本好书，维米奇。”

“是本不错的书。有一点我始终不明白，他们中间放一把剑有什么用处呢？要放你得让剑锋始终朝上才行，因为平着放，你把身子滚过去也不会伤着你的。”

“那是一种象征。”比尔说。

“当然喽。”尼克说，“但那样做没有实际用处。”

“你看过《坚忍不拔》(6)吗？”

“那是本好书，”尼克说，“一本真正的好书。主人公家的老爷子把他看管得够紧的，眼睛就没有离开过。沃波尔的书，你还有什么？”

“《阴暗的森林》，”比尔说，“写的是俄罗斯发生的事情。”

“俄罗斯那边的情况他怎么了解呢？”尼克问。

“我也不知道。那些人神通广大，让人搞不清。也许他小的时候在那儿待过吧。反正俄罗斯的内幕他掌握的可真是不少。”

“我倒是想见上他一面。”尼克说。

“我想见的作家是切斯特顿(7)。”比尔说。

“真希望他此时就在跟前。”尼克说，“咱们明天可以带他一道去沃伊克斯钓鱼。”

“谁知道他喜欢不喜欢钓鱼呢。”比尔说。

“当然喜欢。”尼克说，“他一定还是个出类拔萃的钓鱼好手呢。你还记得他写的《飞行客栈》那本书吗？”

天使走出天堂，

赐给你一杯琼浆。

你谢过他的好心肠，

却把琼浆倒入水塘。

“是这样的。”尼克说，“我想他是个好人，人品比沃波尔强。”

“哦，他的确是个挺不错的人，”比尔说，“但沃波尔的作品却胜他一筹。”

“谁知道呢。”尼克说，“反正切斯特顿的东西挺经典。”

“沃波尔的东西也经典。”比尔寸步不让地说。

“希望他俩都能来这儿，”尼克说，“明天带他俩一起去沃伊克斯钓鱼。”

“来，喝酒，一醉方休。”比尔说。

“一醉方休。”尼克随声附和地说。

“我老爹是不会介意的。”比尔说。

“你敢肯定他不介意？”尼克说。

“我心里有数。”比尔说。

“我都有点醉了。”尼克说。

“你没有醉。”比尔说。

他从地板上站起身，去取那瓶威士忌。尼克把酒杯伸过去。比尔为他斟酒时，他的眼睛盯着杯口。

比尔斟酒只斟了半杯。

“你自己掺点水吧。”他说，“剩下的酒只够一杯了。”

“再没有了吗？”尼克问。

“有倒是还有许多，但爸爸只让喝已开了瓶的酒。”

“当然喽。”尼克说。

“他说自己开瓶喝酒，会变成酒鬼的。”比尔解释了一句。

“说的有道理。”尼克说。这让他很有感触。以前他可从未想到过这些。他老觉得一个人喝闷酒才会变成酒鬼。

“你老爹怎么样？”他充满敬意地问。

“还可以吧，”比尔说，“只是偶尔发发脾气。”

“他是个好人呀。”尼克说。他从水罐里往杯子里倒了些水，让水和威士忌酒液慢慢融合在一起。融合后，杯里的酒比水要多一些。

“一点不错，他是个好人。”比尔说。

“我家老爷子也挺好的。”尼克说。

“千真万确，他是个好人。”比尔说。

“他声称自己这一辈子滴酒不沾唇。”尼克说，口气就像是在宣布一项科学发现一样。

“哦，他是个医生嘛，而我老爹是个画家。区别就在于此。”

“他落下的遗憾可真不小。”尼克忧伤地说。

“仁者见仁，智者见智。”比尔说，“各有利弊吧。”

“他自己说落下了很大遗憾。”尼克推心置腹地说。

“哎，当爸爸的都不容易呀。”比尔说。

“各有各难念的经。”尼克说。

他们坐在那儿，眼睛望着火，心里想着这条深奥的道理。

“我去后门廊取点木柴来。”尼克说。他在往火里望时，注意到火快熄灭了。同时，他想显示自己酒量大，没有喝糊涂。虽说他父亲滴酒不沾唇，可他并不是想灌醉就能灌醉的。

“那就把山毛榉木柴拿来一大块吧。”比尔说。听得出来，他也想显示出自己没有喝糊涂。

尼克抱着木柴进了屋，经过厨房时，不小心将厨房桌子上的一只平底锅碰到了地上。他把木柴放下，捡起了平底锅。锅里原来盛着杏干，用水浸泡着。他小心翼翼地将掉在地上的杏干一一捡起。有几个杏干滚到了炉子底下。然后，他把杏干放回锅里，从桌旁的桶里舀了些水浸泡。他很为自己感到得意，因为他没有喝醉，头脑十分清醒。

见他抱着木柴走进屋，比尔急忙从椅子上站起，帮着他将木柴加进火里。

“这么一大段木头真棒。”尼克说。

“一直留着呢，留着天气变坏时烧。”比尔说。

“这么一段木柴能烧一整夜。”

“烧剩下来的木炭早晨还可以用来生火。”尼克说。

“一点不错。”比尔赞同地说。

两人越说越投机。

“再喝上一杯吧。”尼克说。

“柜子里可能还有开了瓶的酒呢。”比尔说。

他走到墙角那儿的柜子前，跪在地上，取出一个方形的酒瓶来。

“这是苏格兰威士忌。”他说道。

“我去再弄些水来。”尼克说。说完，他又去了厨房，用水瓢从桶里舀出冰凉的泉水，把水罐灌满。回客厅的路上经过餐厅里的一面镜子，他顺便照了照，发现自己的脸怪怪的。他朝镜中的那张脸笑笑，那张脸也冲他笑笑。随后，他对着它挤了挤眼，就又朝前走了。他觉得那好像就不是他的脸。不过，他才不管那是不是他的脸呢。

此时，比尔已经把酒斟好。

“好大的一杯酒，怪吓人的。”尼克说。

“这对咱俩不在话下，维米奇。”比尔说。

“这次为什么干杯呢？”尼克举杯在手，问了一声。

“就为钓鱼干杯吧。”比尔说。

“好吧。”尼克说，“诸位，我提议为钓鱼干杯！”

“为钓鱼干杯！”比尔说，“祝处处钓鱼成功！”

“干杯！”尼克说，“为钓鱼干杯！”

“这总比为棒球干杯强。”比尔说。

“这中间没有什么可比性。”尼克说，“不明白咱们刚才为什么要对棒球大谈特谈呢？”

“那叫大错特错。”比尔说，“棒球是下等人的运动。”

两人一仰脖子，干光了杯子里的酒。

“接下来该为切斯特顿干杯了。”

“还有沃波尔。”尼克插嘴说。

尼克斟酒，比尔往酒里掺水。两人你看看我，我看看你，感觉好极了。

“诸位，”比尔说道，“我提议为切斯特顿和沃波尔干杯！”

“干杯，诸位！”尼克说。

两人一饮而尽。比尔又把酒斟满。随后，他们在火炉前的大椅子上坐了下来。

“你是非常明智的，维米奇。”比尔说。

“此话怎讲？”尼克问。

“就是了结掉和玛姬的那段感情呗。”比尔说。

“我想是吧。”尼克说。

“只能来个快刀斩乱麻了。假如当初你优柔寡断，那么你现在就得回家埋头苦干，攒钱结婚喽。”

尼克没有吭气。

“男人结了婚就等于跳进了火坑。”比尔继续侃侃而谈，“他会一无所有，丧失掉一切，狗屁都不会给他剩下。一句话：完啦！你也见了结过婚的男人最后的下场。”

尼克一言不发。

“从外表就能看得出哪些是婚后男子。”比尔说，“他们有着婚后男子的那种傻呆呆的表情。他们都玩儿完了。”

“的确如此。”尼克说。

“一刀两断，也许会难过一时。”比尔说，“不过，天涯何处无芳草！旧情会忘掉的。有了新欢，也不要让她们断送掉你。”

“是呀。”尼克说。

“娶了一个女人，就是娶了她全家。别忘了她是有妈妈的，还有她妈妈嫁的那个家伙。”

尼克点了点头。

“想想看，那一家子会在你家团团转。星期天，你到她娘家吃饭，而娘家的人也会来你家聚餐。你岳母会给玛姬出各种各样的馊主意，颐指气使的。”

尼克一声不响地坐着。

“你及时脱身不失为上策。”比尔说，“她可以嫁个跟她气味相投的人嘛，安安心心过她的小日子呗。鱼找鱼虾找虾，油和水是不能掺和在一起的，而我就不能和为斯特拉顿家干活的艾达成为并蒂莲。艾达倒是很愿意跟我喜结连理哩。”

尼克没有作声。此时他酒意全消，倍感孤独，仿佛比尔不在跟前，仿佛他不是坐在火炉前边，仿佛根本没有明天要跟比尔父子去垂钓那档子事。他没有喝醉，心里空荡荡的。他只知道自己曾经拥有过马乔里(8)，后来却失去了她。她走了，是他把她打发走的。这才是问题的关键之处。他再也见不到她了，恐怕今生今世也见不到了。所有的恩恩怨怨都已成为过去。

“再来一杯吧。”尼克说。

比尔把酒斟上，尼克加了些水进去。

“假如你当初走了那条道，咱们今日就不能在此相聚了。”比尔说。

这倒是真的。他最初的计划是回老家找个活干。后来他又打算去沙勒沃伊待上一个冬天，守在玛姬的身旁。而现在他心乱如麻，都不知道该如何是好了。

“那一来，就连明天钓鱼恐怕也去不成了。”比尔说，“你做出了正确选择，这一点无可厚非。”

“我那样也是迫不得已呀。”尼克说。

“这我清楚。事情只能如此。”比尔说。

“眨眼之间，一切都消失了。”尼克说，“我对此都理不出个头绪来了。当时，身不由己地就那样做了。就好像当下刮了三日狂风，树上的叶子都被吹掉了。”

“哦，过去的均已过去。这是问题的关键。”比尔说。

“过错在我身上。”尼克说。

“孰是孰非是没有任何关系的。”比尔说。

“我觉得还是有关系的。”比尔说。

马乔里走了，今生今世恐怕再也见不到她了，这可是件不容忽视的大事。他曾经信誓旦旦，说要和她一道去意大利游玩，说他们一定会度过一段快乐的时光。他还说要和她一起去别的地方观光。如今，这一切都无法实现了。

“了结了一件麻烦事，这才是至关紧要的。”比尔说，“说真的，维米奇，我那时实在为你捏把汗呢。你那样做是正确的。听说她妈妈气得要发疯。她逢人便讲，说你们俩已经订了婚呢。”

“我们没订婚。”尼克说。

“街坊里传得沸沸扬扬，说你们订婚了。”

“他们那样说，我也没办法。”尼克说，“我们的确没有订婚。”

“你们有没有打算，准备结婚呢？”比尔问。

“有，但我们没有订婚。”尼克说。

“那又有什么区别呢？”比尔问道，就像依法断案一样。

“说不清。但区别是有的。”

“我实在看不出来。”比尔说。

“算啦，”尼克说，“还是喝酒吧，喝它个烂醉。”

“好吧，”比尔说，“那咱们就喝个烂醉。”

“来，喝个痛快，然后游泳去。”尼克说。

他说完干光了杯子里的酒。

“对于她，我内疚得要命。可我又有什么办法呢？”他说道，“你也知道她妈妈是个母老虎！”

“是个非常可怕的母老虎！”比尔说。

“突然之间一切都过去了。”尼克说，“我真不该旧事重提。”

“不是你旧事重提，”比尔说，“是我提起了那件往事。就此打住，从今往后谁也不要再提它了。你可不要把这件事挂在心上，否则你又会陷入痛苦的旋涡。”

尼克在这之前没有再想此事，因为覆水难收，事情已无法挽回。比尔的观点让他感觉好了些。

“的确如此，”他说，“的确有这种危险。”

他的心情又好了起来。看来，世界上没有改变不了的局面。星期六的晚上，他可以进城去散散心。今天已经是星期四了。

“机会总是会有的。”他说。

“你自己得去寻找。”比尔说。

“我会留心的。”他说。

他感到很高兴，觉得自己并没有走上绝路，并没有失去什么。星期六他一定要进城去放松放松。他的一颗心顿时觉得轻快了，就跟比尔未提及此事之前一样轻快。活人哪能让尿憋死，出路总是会有的。

“走，咱们拿上枪到岬角那儿找你老爹去。”他说。

“好的。”

比尔说完，从墙上的枪架上取下两支猎枪，把子弹盒打开取出子弹。尼克穿上了他的那件厚呢短大衣，把鞋蹬在脚上。他的鞋已烤干，变得硬邦邦的。他仍然醉醺醺的，但大脑却是清晰的。

“你感觉怎么样？”他问道。

“感觉很好。只是有一点醉意罢了。”比尔一边扣毛衣上的扣子，一边回答说。

“喝得酩酊大醉绝对没有好处。”

“是的。该去外边透透气。”

两人走到了门外。外边狂风大作，刮得正紧。

“看这风势，鸟儿会躲进草丛里的。”尼克说。

他们走下山，朝着果园走去。

“今天早晨我看见了一只丘鹬。”比尔说。

“也许咱们会撞上它呢。”尼克说。

“这么大的风，开枪是打不准的。”比尔说。

到了户外，关于玛姬的那件事好像就不那么惨了，甚至显得无关紧要了。狂风把一切烦恼都吹得无影无踪了。

“这风是从大湖那边刮过来的。”尼克说。

逆着风向，他们听见了砰的一声枪响。

“是我老爹，”比尔说，“他在山下的沼泽地那边。”

“走，咱们到那边去。”尼克说。

“咱们穿过草地走，看是不是能撞上什么猎物。”比尔说。

“好的。”尼克说。

往事已经无关紧要了。狂风吹走了他心里的忧愁。星期六的晚上他可以进城去乐一乐。事情经常会峰回路转、柳暗花明的。

————————————————————

(1) 美国圣路易斯市棒球队。

(2) 美国纽约市棒球队。

(3) 巨人队教练。

(4) 英国作家乔治·梅瑞迪斯的代表作。

(5) 英国作家莫里斯·休利特的长篇小说。

(6) 英国作家沃波尔的作品。

(7) 英国作家。

(8) 玛姬的全称。

拳击手

尼克站起身，发现自己并无大碍。顺着铁轨望去，只见货车末尾列车员专用车厢里那闪烁的灯光转过弯道就消失不见了。铁轨两旁净是水，再往远处则是点缀着落地松的沼泽地。

他摸了摸膝盖，看见裤子都破了，皮肤擦出了伤。他的两只手也伤痕累累，指甲缝里塞满了沙土和煤渣。于是他走下铁轨，沿斜坡走到水边洗手。他在冷水里洗手，洗得很仔细，将指甲缝里的脏东西清除干净。接着，他蹲下身子开始洗膝盖。

那个司闸员真他妈不是个东西。君子报仇十年不晚，早晚都要跟他算这笔账。有仇不报非君子。

“过来，小伙子！”那个司闸员刚才对他这样说道，“我这儿有样东西给你。”

他竟然上当了。那种小儿科般的把戏竟然骗过了他。这辈子他再也不会上那样的当了。

“过来，小伙子，我这儿有样东西给你。”就这么一句话让他上了当。接着，他嗵的一声被扔到了铁轨旁，两手和双膝着地伏在地面上。

他揉了揉眼睛——那儿起了个大包，肯定都青肿了，感觉疼疼的。那个司闸员真他妈是个龟儿子！

他用手指碰了碰眼睛上方的肿块。哦，还好吧，只不过眼睛有些青肿罢了。他受到的损失就是这些了，代价还不算沉重嘛。他很想看看自己此时的面相，只可惜从水里是看不清的。天色已黑，他身处野外，前不着村后不着店。他在裤子上擦擦手，然后站起来，爬上路堤向铁轨走去。

他沿着铁轨朝前走，脚下的石块铺得很均匀，走起来顺顺当当的。枕木间的沙子和砾石极其紧凑，踩在上面觉得很坚实。平展的路基像一条堤坝，穿过沼泽地一直向前延伸。他脚下不停朝前走，心想得赶快找个休息的地方。

他是在沃尔顿枢纽站扒上这列货车的。当时，货车在枢纽站外的调车场减慢了速度。天擦黑的时候，货车开过了卡尔卡斯卡。此刻，他八成是在距离曼瑟洛纳不远的地方。到那儿去，要穿过三四英里的沼泽地。他不敢耽搁，继续向前走着，两脚踩在枕木间的碎石上。雾气越来越浓，而沼泽地在雾气里显得有些狰狞。他眼睛疼痛难忍，腹中饥肠辘辘，而脚下却走个不停，把好长好长的铁轨抛在了身后。铁轨两旁的景色仍没有改变，仍是无涯无际的沼泽地。

前边出现了一座路桥。过桥时，靴子踩在铁轨上发出空洞的响声。从枕木间的缝隙朝脚下看，看见的是黑魆魆的水面。有枚道钉松了，他用脚一踢，那枚道钉掉进了水里。过了桥就是群山了，又黑又高，耸立在轨道两旁。他看见前边有火光。

他沿着铁轨走，小心翼翼地向火光靠近。那火光在铁轨的一侧，远在路堤下方，仅看得见火光却看不见火。铁轨穿过一个山口，进入一片林子，中间的野地被火光照得通亮。他蹑手蹑脚走下路堤进入林子，穿过林海向篝火摸去。这是一片山毛榉树林，在林间走动，掉落的山毛榉坚果踩在脚下感觉毛刺刺的。篝火位于林边，火光熊熊的。在火的旁边坐着一个男子。尼克躲在树后观察了一番。那男子好像是独身一人，双手捧着脑袋，眼睛望着篝火。尼克从树后闪出，走到了火光里。

那男子坐着没动，仍在望着篝火发呆。尼克走到他跟前，停下脚步时，他也没动。

“你好！”尼克说道。

那男子抬起了头。

“你的黑眼圈是怎么回事？”他问。

“是被一个司闸员打的。”

“是货车上的司闸员？”

“是的。”

“我看见那兔崽子了。”男子说，“那趟车大概在一个半小时前从这儿开了过去。那家伙在车厢顶上走来走去，用手拍着胳膊，还唱歌哩。”

“那个狗杂种！”

“他打你，心里一定快活得不行。”男子语气严峻地说。

“我会叫他吃不了兜着走的。”

“下次见了他，就用石头砸他。”男子献计说。

“我一定会找他算这笔账的。”

“看来你是条硬汉子，对不对？”

“算不上吧。”尼克回答道。

“你们这班小子，都有硬汉风格。”

“为人处世，这也是迫不得已呀。”尼克说。

“这正是我要说的。”

那男子看看尼克，笑了笑。借着火光，尼克发现他的脸是一副怪相——鼻子塌陷，眼睛细成了一条缝，嘴唇扭曲得变了形。起初，尼克并没有一下子把这些细节都收入眼底。他只看到男子的脸奇形怪状，被人毁了容，呈铁灰色，在火光里看上去像死人脸。

“你不喜欢我的面相吧？”男子问。

尼克听了觉得很不好意思。

“没有的事。”他支吾了一句。

“叫你看个仔细！”男子说完摘下了头上的帽子。

原来他只有一只耳朵，厚墩墩的，紧贴在脑袋的一侧。脑袋的另一侧没有耳朵，仅有一个耳朵根。

“见过这样的面相吗？”

“没见过。”尼克说。说这话时，他觉得有点恶心。

“这样的命运我能忍受得了。”男子说，“难道你不觉得我能忍受得了吗，小伙子？”

“当然能！”

“他们的拳头雨点般落在我身上，”小个子男子说，“却伤不着我。”

他把尼克打量了几眼，然后说道：“坐下吧。想吃东西吗？”

“不用麻烦了。”尼克说，“我只是路过这儿，要到城里去呢。”

“听着，”男子说，“就叫我阿德吧。”

“明白了！”

“听着，”小个子男子说，“我这人不太正常。”

“怎么啦？”

“我有疯病。”他说着把帽子又戴到了头上。

尼克直想笑，连忙说：“你很正常。”

“不，不正常。我发疯了。问你一句，你发过疯吗？”

“没发过。”尼克说，“怎么会这样呢？”

“我也弄不清。”阿德说，“你一旦发了疯，自己是不知道的。你该认识我吧？”

“不认识。”

“我是阿德·弗朗西斯。”

“这是真的吗？”

“难道你不相信？”

“我相信。”尼克知道对方说的是实话。

“你知道我是怎么把他们击败的吗？”

“不知道。”尼克说。

“我的心脏跳动得很慢，一分钟只跳四十下。你来摸摸脉就知道了。”

尼克一时有点犹豫。

“来呀，”男子一把拉起他的手说，“抓住我的手腕，把手指按在这地方。”

小个子男子的手腕很粗，包在骨头上的肌肉高高隆起。尼克的手指尖可以感觉到他的脉搏跳动得很慢。

“你有表吗？”

“没有。”

“我也没有。”阿德说，“没有表就测不准。”

尼克一听放下了他的手腕。

“这样吧，”阿德·弗朗西斯说，“你再抓住我的手腕。你数脉搏，我数时间——一分钟六十下。”

尼克把手按在他的脉搏上，感受到他的脉搏在有力、缓慢地跳动，接着就开始数数。他听见小个子阿德也在大声数：“一，二，三，四，五……”

“六十。”阿德数完了，“正好一分钟。你数的是多少？”

“是四十。”尼克说。

“这个数是对的。”阿德高兴地说，“从来就没有跳快过。”

这时，一个人下了铁路的路堤，穿过空地向篝火这儿走来。

“你好，巴格思！”阿德招呼道。

“你好！”巴格思答了一声。听声音像是个黑人。尼克从他走路的姿势也看得出他是个黑人。他背对他们站着，俯下身子在烤火。此时直起了腰来。

“这位是我的朋友巴格思，”阿德介绍说，“他也是个疯子。”

“幸会幸会。”巴格思说，“你是哪个地方来的？”

“芝加哥。”尼克说。

“那是个漂亮的城市。”黑人说，“请问尊姓大名。”

“我叫亚当斯——尼克·亚当斯。”

“他说他从未发过疯，巴格思。”阿德说。

“以后他遇到事就会的。”黑人说着话，傍着火光解开了一个包裹。

“什么时候吃饭呀，巴格思？”职业拳击手阿德问。

“马上就吃。”

“你肚子饿不饿，尼克？”

“饿得要死。”

“听见了吧，巴格思？”

“你们的话基本上都听见了。”

“真是答非所问。”

“是的。这位先生的话我听见了。”

巴格思说着话，把切成片的火腿放入煎锅。当煎锅烧热，锅里的油嗞啦嗞啦发响时，他便弯下他那双黑人天生的长腿蹲到篝火旁，翻了翻火腿，往锅里打几个鸡蛋，再将煎锅左晃右晃，用热油慢慢煨熟鸡蛋。

“能不能把包里的面包切几片下来，亚当斯先生？”巴格思从火旁转过头问。

“当然可以喽。”尼克说完，伸手从包里取出一条面包，用刀子切下来了六片。阿德在旁边看着，把身子探了过来。

“把你的刀子给我吧，尼克。”他说道。

“不，别给他。”黑人说，“你把你的刀子拿好，别给他，亚当斯先生。”

职业拳击手阿德又坐了回去。

“把面包递给我好吗，亚当斯先生？”巴格思问。尼克听了把面包递了过去。

“你的面包喜欢蘸点火腿油吃吗？”黑人问。

“喜欢！”

“也许，最好还是等一下再说吧。作为收尾的一道菜效果更佳。来啦。”

黑人拿起一片火腿放在一片面包上，又摊了个鸡蛋在上边。

“请你把这个三明治夹好，递给弗朗西斯。”

阿德接过三明治，吃了起来。

“小心点，别让鸡蛋流下来。”黑人提醒道，“这个是给你的，亚当斯先生。其余的我吃。”

尼克咬了一口三明治。黑人坐在阿德的旁边，跟他面对面。火腿煎鸡蛋热乎乎的，吃起来非常可口。

“亚当斯先生看来真是饿坏了。”黑人说。此时，小个子拳击手一声不吭——尼克早就闻其大名，知道他是个拳击冠军。自从黑人不让尼克把刀子给他那一时刻起，他一直没有开过口。

“给你来片面包，蘸点热火腿油怎么样？”巴格思问。

“多谢啦。”

尼克说话时，小个子白人扫了他几眼。

“你也来点吧，阿道夫(1)·弗朗西斯先生？”巴格思从煎锅里取了片面包说。

阿德没有答话，却仍在盯着尼克瞧。

“弗朗西斯先生？”黑人口吻柔和地叫了一声。

阿德仍未吱声，还在盯着尼克瞧。

“我在和你说话呢，弗朗西斯先生。”黑人又柔声细语地说了一句。

阿德不住眼地盯着尼克，帽檐拉得低低的遮在眼睛上方，让尼克感到心里发毛。

“你是吃了熊心豹子胆了吧？”那个帽檐下传来了阿德冲着尼克发出的喝问，“你他妈觉得自己算老几？你个目中无人的杂种！谁也没请你，你就跑到这儿来，混吃混喝的。别人问你借借刀子，你倒拿腔拿调的。”

他怒视着尼克，脸色发白，眼睛遮在帽檐下，几乎让人看不见。

“你倒成了个香饽饽。究竟是谁把你请到这里来的？”

“没人请。”

“你说的一点不错。没人请你来，也没人请你留下。你大大咧咧跑来，对我的面相嗤之以鼻，抽我的烟，喝我的酒，说起话来大言不惭的。你他妈想怎么样嘛？”

尼克无言以对。阿德站起了身子。

“告诉你吧，你这个胆小的芝加哥的杂种，我要让你吃不了兜着走。明白了吗？”

尼克节节后退，而小个子拳击手却步步紧逼，步伐缓慢，左脚迈前，右脚便紧跟上。

“来打我呀。”他把脑袋一歪说，“来呀，来打呀。”

“我不想跟你打架。”

“你别指望就这么算啦。我要让你好好挨一顿揍，明白吗？来吧，你应该先下手。”

“还是算了吧。”尼克说。

“那好，狗杂种，那就瞧吧。”

小个子说着低头看了看尼克的脚。说时迟那时快，自从他离开篝火旁的那一刻起一直跟在他身后的黑人举起裹着布的金属棒，砰地打在了他的后脑壳上。他一个狗吃屎栽倒了。巴格思将手中的金属棒丢在了草地上。小个子趴在那里，脸埋在草中。黑人将他抱起，抱到篝火旁。他耷拉着脑袋，脸色吓人，眼睛睁开着。巴格思轻手轻脚把他放了下来。

“麻烦你把那桶水给我拎过来，亚当斯先生。”巴格思说道，“恐怕我刚才下手重了点。”

黑人用手往小个子的脸上泼了点水，轻轻扯扯他的耳朵。对方把眼睛合上了。

巴格思直起了腰。

“没事的。”他说道，“你不用担心。对不起了，亚当斯先生。”

“没关系的。”尼克低头看了看脚下的小个子，结果瞧见那根金属棒在草地上，便将其捡了起来。金属棒的柄有点弹性，抓在手里软软的。棒柄上裹着旧旧的黑皮革，沉重的棒端则用手帕包裹着。

“这是个鲸骨柄。”黑人微微一笑说，“这种东西现在已经没人做了。对于你的自卫能力，我一无所知。反正我是不想让你伤着他，给他的脸上添更多的疤痕。”

黑人说完又是一笑。

“倒是你刚才那一下子把他伤着了。”

“我掌握得了轻重。他醒了后狗屁都不会记得了。是在他发疯的时候我才会出手的，让他换一种状态。”

尼克此时仍在低头看小个子，看着他躺在那里，在火光中闭着眼睛。巴格思朝篝火里又加了些木柴。

“你不必再为他担心了，亚当斯先生。他这种样子，我都多见不怪了。”

“他怎么会突然发疯呢？”尼克问。

“哦，其中的原因有许多。”黑人从篝火旁回答说，“想来杯咖啡吗，亚当斯先生？”

他说着把咖啡递给了尼克，然后将刚才放在昏迷不醒的小个子头下的衣服拉展。

“其中一个原因是，他挨打挨得次数太多了。”黑人呷了口咖啡说，“这只是让他的脑子缺了根弦。当时，他的阿妹当他的经纪人，报纸上大秀阿哥和阿妹的恩爱，什么阿妹爱阿哥啦，阿哥心疼阿妹啦。结果，两人在纽约结了婚，弄得满城风雨。”

“这事我记得。”

“当然，他们并非胞兄胞妹，只不过是两个傻瓜罢了。可是，许多人却不管那一套。两人之间也闹起了矛盾。一天，女的跑了，再也没有回来。”

黑人说完，用粉红色的手心抹了一把嘴。

“这就是他发疯的原因。再来点咖啡吧，亚当斯先生？”

“谢谢。”

“那女的我见过几次。”黑人继续叙说着，“她模样儿长得真是俊，和他简直是天设地造的一对儿。他要不是毁了容，原本也是个帅哥呢。”

他打住了话头。故事像是讲完了。

“我是在监狱里遇到的他。”黑人又说了起来，“那女的跑了后，他动辄就打人，于是就进了牢房。我坐牢是因为砍伤了一个人。”

他笑了笑，换上一种温柔的语调继续说道：

“见第一面，我就喜欢上了他，出狱后紧紧跟着他。他老是觉得我有点犯傻，可我一点不在乎。我愿意跟着他，愿意多见世面。跟着他，就不用偷鸡摸狗了。我喜欢过体面的日子。”

“你们平时都做些什么呢？”尼克问。

“哦，什么都不做，只是周游四方。他反正是不愁钱花的。”

“那他的钱一定是很多喽。”

“不错，不过都被他花光了，或者说都被他人拿走了。现在是那女的给他寄钱花。”

说到这里，黑人拨了拨火。

“那女的真是好样的，很了不起。”他继续说道，“她跟他像极了，像一个模子倒出来的。”

黑人望了望小个子——小个子躺在那儿，大口大口呼吸着，一头金发披散在脑门上，毁了容的脸看上去像孩子一样。

“我随时都可以把他叫醒的，亚当斯先生。如果你不介意，我觉得你还是现在就走吧。我这可不是不愿款待你，只是害怕他醒来后见到你又犯老毛病。用棒子敲他是我所不愿做的，可他一发疯，也只有这么做了。如此，只好叫他少接触人。你不会介意吧，亚当斯先生？不用谢我，不用谢我，亚当斯先生。我早该提醒你。让你注意他了。可是话又说回来，他好像挺喜欢你的，所以我觉得不会出事的。沿着铁轨朝北走两英里的样子就到城里了。他们管那儿叫曼瑟洛纳。再见！真希望能留下你过夜，可是这样又是不可能的。愿意带上点火腿和面包吗？不愿带？那你还是带一份三明治吧。”黑人的这一席话说得彬彬有礼，声音柔和，压得低低的。

“好吧。那就再见了，亚当斯先生。祝你好运！”

尼克离开篝火，穿过空地向铁轨那儿走去。走到篝火的光圈之外，他竖起耳朵听了听，听见黑人那低沉、柔和的声音在说话。黑人究竟说了什么，他听不清，却听得到小个子在说：“我的头疼得厉害，巴格思。”

“你会没事的，弗朗西斯先生。”黑人的声音在说宽心话，“把这杯热咖啡喝下去就好了。”

尼克爬上路堤，沿着铁轨走了。这时他发现自己手里还拿着一份火腿三明治，于是就将它放进了衣兜里。铁轨蜿蜒至山里。在未进山之前，他从陡坡上回头看了一眼，看见篝火在空地上熊熊燃烧着。

————————————————————

(1) 阿德的全称。

艾略特夫妇

艾略特两口子想生个孩子，为之付出了很大的努力。他们一次次地尝试，只要艾略特夫人能受得了就不停止。他们婚后在波士顿尝试，即便乘船在海上航行也不放松。乘船时尝试的次数倒不是很多，因为艾略特夫人晕船晕得厉害。一上船就晕，晕了就呕吐——南方的女人都一个样。美利坚的南国女子就是这么一种状况。艾略特夫人也别无二致，晕船晕得稀里哗啦，立刻就垮掉了，可能是因为夜间航行，白天起得太早的缘故吧。船上许多乘客都错把她当成艾略特的妈妈了。知道他们是夫妻的人则以为她怀孕了。其实，她才不过四十岁而已。一出来旅行，她突然间就显出了老相。

以前，她显得非常面嫩。实际上，艾略特跟她喜结连理时，她显得年轻极了，根本看不出她的岁数。艾略特是在她工作的那个茶馆和她相识的，交往了很长一段时间后，一天晚上吻了她，再经过几个星期的追求，最后步入了婚姻的殿堂。

结婚时，休伯特·艾略特正在哈佛大学读法学专业的研究生。他是个诗人，每年有近一万元的进项。他擅长于写长诗，写起来一挥而就。他当时二十五岁，在和艾略特夫人结婚之前，从未跟任何一个女人上过床。他洁身自好，准备把纯洁的心和身体献给妻子——他渴望从妻子那儿得到同样的回报。他称这种生活为“过本分日子”。在亲吻艾略特夫人之前，他跟各种各样的姑娘相恋过，或迟或早都会告诉对方，说自己要过的是洁净无瑕的生活。几乎所有的姑娘一听，都对他失去了兴趣。姑娘们明明知道一些男子不检点，乌七八糟的，却愿意跟他们私定终身，以身相许，这叫他非常吃惊、万分愕然。一次，他试图告诫自己认识的一位姑娘，说她爱的男子在学校里劣迹斑斑，对此有证据可查，结果讨了个没趣。

艾略特夫人的闺名叫科妮莉亚。她却让他称她为卡鲁蒂娜——这是她在南方家中用的小名。婚后，他带着科妮莉亚回家探亲，妈妈见了竟然哭了起来，待到得知他们新婚宴尔要到海外定居时，便破涕为笑，喜色满面。

当他告诉科妮莉亚，说他为了她一直保持着清白之身时，科妮莉亚说了声“你真是个可爱的小男孩”，把他搂得更紧了。科妮莉亚本人也守身如玉。“再亲亲我！”她这样说道。

休伯特向她透露，说他亲吻的技巧还是听一个伙计讲故事，从中学到的。他热衷于实践，于是两人乐此不疲，令这门技巧愈加娴熟。有时他们热吻，一吻就是很长时间。这时，科妮莉亚会让他重申：他保持着清白之身全是为了她。他的重申往往又会叫她激情勃发。

起初，休伯特并无娶她之心。他从未有过与她结婚的念头。他们俩不过是好朋友罢了。一天，科妮莉亚的闺蜜在茶馆的前厅待客，他们俩跑到后边的小房间里跟着留声机的音乐跳舞。跳着跳着，她抬起头凝视着他的眼睛，于是他就吻了她。他记不起他们是何时决定结婚的——反正两人结了百年之好。

他们的新婚之夜是在波士顿的一家旅馆里度过的。两人都有点失望。不过，最后，科妮莉亚睡着了。而休伯特却难以入睡，于是三番五次跑出去，穿着那件专门为蜜月旅行新买的毛织品浴袍，在旅馆的走廊里来回踱步。他看见各房间的门外摆放着形形色色的鞋，有大的，也有小的，不由怦然心跳不止，急忙回到自己的房间里，可是科妮莉亚却在呼呼大睡。他不愿叫醒她。不一会儿，他的心归于平静，接着便安然入梦了。

翌日，两人前去探望了他的母亲。第二天，夫妻俩启程，远航欧洲了。他们渴望要一个孩子，这是他们的天字号愿望，原本可以在船上努力实现的，只可惜科妮莉亚不能够进行多次的尝试。他们是在瑟堡(1)登陆的，然后来到了巴黎。在巴黎，他们又进行了尝试，想怀上孩子。后来，他们决定到第戎(2)去，那儿开了个暑期班，和他们同船而来的乘客有好几个都去上那个班了。到了第戎，他们发现自己无事可做。幸亏休伯特创作了许多诗歌，于是科妮莉亚便为他打字。那些诗全都长得要命。他又是个严苛的人，不允许出错，一旦打字时出现一个错误，她就得把整整一页重新打一遍。为此，她流过不少眼泪。在离开第戎之前，他们又屡屡尝试，想把孩子怀上。

末了，他们返回了巴黎，他们在船上的旅伴也大多来到了这里。大家对第戎都感到厌倦了。反正他们现在可以吹吹牛了，说他们离开美国的大学（或哈佛大学，或哥伦比亚大学，或沃巴什大学）跑到法国的柯多尔省，在该省的第戎大学曾经学习过。如果郎格多克(3)、蒙彼利埃(4)或佩皮尼昂有大学的话，他们当中有许多人情愿到那些地方去。不过，话又说回来，那些地方太远了。第戎距离巴黎只有四个半小时的车程，而且火车上还设有餐厅。

现在回到巴黎，大家齐聚圆顶屋咖啡馆。他们尽量不去街对面的罗敦德咖啡馆，因为那儿人满为患，外来客太多。热闹了几天之后，艾略特夫妇通过纽约《先驱报》上登的一则广告，在都兰租了一座别墅。此时，艾略特已结交了一些朋友，那些人很欣赏他的诗。艾略特夫人说服丈夫寄信波士顿，邀请她在茶馆的那位闺蜜来陪她。闺蜜来后，艾略特夫人的情绪好多了。两人喜相逢，洒下了不少相思泪。闺蜜比科妮莉亚大几岁，一声一声地把她叫作“宝贝”。她也出身于一个古老的南方世家。

他们三人，再加上艾略特的几个朋友（那些朋友把他叫休比(5)），大家一起来到了都兰的别墅。他们发现都兰一马平川，天气炎热，很像美国的堪萨斯。此时，艾略特创作的诗歌差不多都够出一部诗集了。他准备把诗集在波士顿推出，已经给出版商寄了支票，并签了合同。

没过多长时间，那些朋友们陆陆续续回巴黎去了。都兰没有他们初来时所感觉的那么好玩。朋友们一哄而散，跟一个有钱的未婚年轻诗人跑了，跑到特鲁维尔附近的海滨度假地去了，在那儿玩得非常开心。

艾略特继续留在都兰的别墅里，因为他的租期是整整一个夏天。在热烘烘的大卧室里，躺在一张巨大的硬床上，两口子进行了艰苦卓绝的努力，一个心眼要怀上孩子。艾略特夫人在学习打字的指法，可她发现用学到的指法倒是能够加快速度，出错率却也增加了。实际上，现在所有的稿件都由她的闺蜜负责打印。闺蜜打字干净利落，效率高，而且乐在其中。

艾略特喜欢上了喝白葡萄酒，独自住一个房间。他夜间熬夜写诗，白天倦容满面。艾略特夫人和闺蜜睡在那张中世纪的大床上，常常多愁善感地洒几滴眼泪。傍晚时分，三人到花园里坐在一棵法国梧桐树下共进晚餐。艾略特喝着白葡萄酒，艾略特夫人则和闺蜜谈天说地，日子过得倒是相当滋润。

————————————————————

(1) 法国西北部港市。

(2) 法国东部城市。

(3) 法国南部的一个地区。

(4) 法国南部的一座城市。

(5) 休伯特的昵称。

雨中的猫

旅馆里下榻的美国客人仅有两个。他们进出房间，上下楼时遇见的人一个都不认识。他们住的房间在二楼，面向大海。对面还有一个公园和一座战争纪念碑。公园里有参天的棕榈树以及绿颜色的长条凳。遇到好天气，总会看到一个画家拿着画架出现在公园里。画家都喜欢这样的景色：棕榈树参天；旅馆色彩艳丽，面向着公园和大海。总有意大利人赶老远的路跑来瞻仰战争纪念碑。纪念碑是青铜铸成的，淋了雨就闪闪发亮。此时正在下雨，淅淅沥沥的雨水从棕榈树上朝下滴着。砾石路上积了一洼一洼的水。雨幕中，海水排成一长列冲上海滩，再退回去，然后又排成一长列冲过来。停放在战争纪念碑旁广场上的几辆汽车，一辆辆都开走了。广场对面一家咖啡馆的门洞里有个服务生，正站在那儿望着空旷的广场发呆。

那个美国太太站在窗前朝外望着。在屋外的窗户根下有只猫，蜷缩在一张滴着水的绿桌子下。那只猫尽量把身子缩紧，免得让雨水淋着。

“我下去把那只小猫抱回来。”美国太太说。

“还是我去吧。”丈夫从床上说了一声。

“不，我去吧。瞧那可怜的小家伙，躲在桌子下不愿让雨淋着。”

丈夫听了，又继续看他的书了，斜躺在床的一端，身后垫着两个枕头。

“可别让雨淋着。”他叮咛了一句。

妻子下楼去了，路过办公室时，旅馆老板急忙站起来，向她欠欠身子致意。他的桌子摆放在办公室的另一头。他是个老头，身材特别高。

“天下雨了。(1)”美国太太寒暄道。她喜欢这位旅馆老板。

“是呀，是呀，天不好。(2)天气太糟糕了。”

老板站在桌子后边，在办公室远远的另一端，屋里光线昏暗。美国太太喜欢他，喜欢他接到投诉后所表现出来的那种严肃认真的态度，喜欢他的庄重，喜欢他愿意为她服务的热情，喜欢他作为旅馆老板尽心尽职的样子，还喜欢他那张沧桑、凝重的脸以及那双大手。

就是抱着这种心情，她推开了大门，向外望去。雨势比刚才又大了些。只见一个男子身穿橡胶雨衣，经过空旷的广场向咖啡馆走去。那只猫一定在右边的哪个地方。也许，她可以从房檐下走过去。正当她在门洞里盘算时，身后有人为她撑开了一把伞。原来是打扫房间的女服务员。

“可别让雨淋湿了。”服务员嫣然一笑，用意大利语说道。没说的，一定是旅馆老板派她来的。

由女服务员为她撑着伞，她沿着砾石路走去，一直走到他们那个房间的窗户根下。桌子摆在那儿，绿颜色被雨冲洗得鲜亮鲜亮，但桌下的猫已不见了踪影。这叫她大失所望。女服务员抬头看了她一眼。

“你丢东西了吗，夫人？(3)”

“这儿原来是有一只猫的。”年轻的美国太太说。

“一只猫？”

“是的，是有一只猫的。(4)”

“一只猫？”女服务员哈哈笑了起来，“下雨天这里会有一只猫？”

“是的。”美国太太说，“就在这桌子底下。”接着她又说道，“啊，我太想得到它了。我想要只小猫咪。”

她时而说意大利语，时而说英语，说英语时，女服务员脸上的表情不由有些紧张。

“走吧，夫人，”女服务员说，“还是进屋里去吧，会淋湿的。”

“看来只好这样了。”年轻的美国太太说。

两人沿着砾石路返回，走进了旅馆的大门。女服务员在门外停了停，将雨伞收拢。年轻的美国太太路过办公室时，旅馆老板从桌旁站起，又冲她欠了欠身子。她心里很纠结，有一种龌龊的感觉。老板既让她觉得自己乏味得不得了，又叫她感到自身相当了不起。一时间，她产生了一种情绪，觉得自己是个极为了不起的人物。待她上了楼，打开房间的门，见乔治正躺在床上看书。

“抓到那只猫了吗？”他放下手里的书问。

“不见啦。”

“会跑到哪里去了呢？”他说道。他看书看累了，趁此休息着眼睛。

她一屁股坐在了床上。

“我太想要那只猫了。”她说道，“我也不知道为什么，反正我非常想要。我想得到那只可怜的小猫咪。叫一只小猫咪在外边淋雨，可不是什么好玩的事。”

乔治又继续看他的书了。

她走过去，走到梳妆台的镜子前，借助手镜打量起镜中的自己。她观看自己的侧影，看看这边又看看那边，然后又端详自己的后脑勺以及脖子。

“我把头发留起来，你看这想法是不是很好呢？”她问道，一边又观赏起自己的侧影来。

乔治抬头看了看，见她脖后的头发很短，像男孩的头发一样短。

“这种样子我挺喜欢的。”

“这发式我都烦了。”她说，“老看上去像个男孩子，让人都烦了。”

乔治在床上换了个姿势。妻子开口说话时，他的眼睛就一直没有离开过她。

“你这样子看上去是非常漂亮的呀。”他说。

她将手镜放到梳妆台上，然后走到窗前向外张望。外边的天色正在变黑。

“我想留头发，梳拢，光光滑滑的，在后面打一个大发髻，可以时时摸一摸。”她说，“我想有只小猫咪，让它卧在我的膝上，一摸它就喵喵地叫。”

“是吗？”乔治在床上说。

“我想吃饭时用自己的银质餐具，点上蜡烛。我想现在就是春天……我想坐在镜子前梳头发……我想要只小猫咪……我想有几件新衣服。”

“好啦，别说了，你还是找本书看看吧。”乔治说完，又埋头看书了。

他的妻子将目光投向窗外。天已经黑透了，仍在下雨，雨水落在棕榈树上。

“不管怎样，我就是想要只猫。”她说，“我就是想要只猫，现在就想要。既然不能留长发，又没有什么好玩的，要只猫总是可以的吧。”

乔治没理会她，仍在看自己的书。他的妻子朝窗外望着，见广场上亮起了灯。

这时，响起了敲门声。

“请进。(5)”乔治说，同时把眼睛从书上抬了起来。

那个女服务员出现在了门道里，怀里抱着一只三色大猫。那只猫被她抱得紧贴在身上，在她的怀里挣扎着。

“打搅了，”她说道，“这是老板让抱来的，是送给夫人的。”

————————————————————

(1) 原文为意大利语。

(2) 原文为意大利语。

(3) 原文为意大利语。

(4) 原文为意大利语。

(5) 原文为意大利语。

“双心”大河
（第一部）

火车继续朝前开，绕过一座被焚烧过的山丘，从视野里消失了。尼克一屁股坐在了帆布包和铺盖卷上——这些东西是行李员从行李车厢的门内扔出来的。此处没有村镇，什么都没有，只有铁轨和被火烧焦了的土地。锡尼小镇唯一的一条街道上原有十三家酒馆，如今全都不见了踪影。广厦旅馆只剩下了房基，兀立在地面上，基石都被大火烧得崩裂开了。这是锡尼小镇的仅存之物了。甚至连地表层都化成了焦土。

尼克望了望被大火烧秃了的山坡——他原指望可以在那儿看到散落着一些小镇居民的屋舍呢。随后，他抬腿沿着铁路向大河上的那座桥走去。大河依旧，河水在桥下原木的木桩跟前形成了漩涡。尼克低头看了看清澈的褐色河水（由于河床上的鹅卵石是褐色，河水看上去也就成了褐色）。他观望着激流中的鳟鱼，见它们抖动鱼鳍，竭力保持身体的稳定。只见有些鱼猛地换个角度，变动一下位置，就又在湍急的水流中稳定了下来。尼克就这么观望了许久。

他望着鱼儿把鼻子探入激流中，有许多鱼在快速流动的深水里显得有点变形，那是因为他是从凸透镜一般的水面一直朝下看的，而表层的流水与桥下原木木桩的阻力相抵，形成了平缓的涟漪。水潭的底部藏着大鱼，尼克起初没有看到，那是后来才发现的。那些大鱼紧贴砾石河底，隐身于迷宫一样的石头缝里以及激流荡起的沙雾中。

尼克站在桥上，低头望着水潭。这是个炎热的日子。一只翠鸟朝着河的上游飞去。尼克已经有很长时间没有这么望着河水欣赏鳟鱼了。看见那些鱼儿，他心里感到挺舒服的。当翠鸟的映影向上游移动时，一条大鳟鱼逆流而上，朝前一蹿，形成了一道长长的弧度——不过，这只是它的影子在水里构成的弧度，待它跃出水面，被阳光一照，影子也就消失了。随后，它又落回水里，沉入河面之下，顺着河水朝下游漂去，它的影子似乎紧随着它，一路畅行无阻。最后，它回到桥下原来的位置，面朝激流将身子绷紧。

随着那条鳟鱼的一举一动，尼克的心缩成了一团。早年的那种感觉又回来了。

他回转身，举目向下游望去。但见河水向前伸展，看得见鹅卵石的河底和浅滩，看得见一块块的巨石以及一个深水潭——那深水潭是河水流经绝壁脚下的一个拐弯处形成的。

尼克踏着枕木返回放行李的地方——他的行李放在铁轨旁的煤渣路上。他感到很开心。他把行李包的绑绳扯紧，调整了一下背带，然后一抡将行李包放在了背上，再把胳膊塞进背带圈里，前额抵在宽宽的行李带上，以分担肩膀上的一部分扯力。尽管如此，仍感到行李包死沉，简直沉得要命。他把皮质的钓竿匣子提在手中，身子前倾，让行李包的重量压在肩上，随后冒着酷暑，沿着与铁轨平行的那条路走去，将化为灰烬的小镇抛在了身后。绕过一座夹在两座火焚过的高山之间的小山丘，他拐上了一条大路，向乡野间走去。走着走着，他感觉到沉重的行李包勒得他肉疼。这条路顺着山势蜿蜒而上。爬山可不是件容易的事。他肌肉发痛，天气又热，但他心里是快活的。他觉得自己把一切都抛在了身后，再不需要思考，再不需要写作，什么都不需要做了。所有的一切都被他抛在了身后。

自从他下了火车，行李员把他的包囊从敞开的车厢门里扔出来，他发现一切都发生了翻天覆地的变化。锡尼小镇化为了一片焦土。周围的景物也遭到了焚毁，已面目全非。不过，这没什么大不了的，不可能让所有的一切都葬身于火海，对于这一点他笃信无疑。他行走在路上，在阳光下大汗淋漓，盘山而上，准备翻越横亘在铁路和松林覆盖的平原之间的那道山脉。

道路向前延伸，偶尔有段下坡路，除此之外一路爬山。他走啊走的。道路与火焚过的山坡平行，最后抵达山巅。他靠在一截树桩上歇气，将肩膀从背带圈里抽出来。极目远眺，前方就是那个松林覆盖的平原。火焚过的焦土到了左边山脉跟前便戛然而止。只见平原上遍布黑乎乎的松林，那松林一片一片，像一座座小岛。左边的远方，就是那条大河了。他眺望了一眼，但见河水翻波，在阳光下闪闪发亮。

他的面前别无他物，只有那松林覆盖的平原。再往远处看，才能看得到几座青山，那是苏必利尔湖(1)的标记，标志着该湖所处位置的高度。平原上热浪翻滚，那些青山显得遥远、朦胧，几乎难以看得见。如果他定睛使劲看，反而看不见。可是，他如果随便一望，就看得见远处高地的群山了。

他坐下来，背靠烧焦了的树桩，点了根烟抽。他的行李包平放在树桩的顶部，背带呈预备状态，随时都可以背上走，包上有一个被他的脊背顶出的凹痕。他一边抽烟，一边望着前方的原野。不用掏出地图查看，根据河流所处的位置，他也知道自己身在何处。

抽烟时，他的两条腿向前伸展。他注意到有只蚱蜢从地面爬过来，爬到了他的羊毛袜子上。这只蚱蜢是黑颜色的。刚才他走在路上，翻山越岭，把土里的许多蚱蜢都惊动了。它们都是黑颜色的，不过跟那种黑翅板的大蚱蜢不一样——那些大蚱蜢起飞时，翅板上会闪出黑黄色或黑红色的翅膀。而这些都是普普通通的蚱蜢，清一色的烟黑色。刚才在路上看见它们，倒是有几分好奇，却没有认真地把它们往心里放。现在，看着这只黑蚱蜢张开分成四片唇的嘴在啃他袜子上的毛线，他意识到这些蚱蜢是因为长期生活在烧焦的土地上才变成了黑色。他心想大火一定是前一年烧起来的，而今蚱蜢们全成了黑色。真不知道它们的黑颜色会保持多长时间。

他小心翼翼地伸出手，抓住蚱蜢的翅膀，把它翻过来，任它的几条腿在空中乱踢腾，仔细观察了一下它那多节的肚皮。不错，它的肚皮也是黑色的，是变了颜色的，而它的脊背和头是浅灰色的。

“飞吧，蚱蜢，”他第一次出声地说了话，“飞到别处去吧。”

他将蚱蜢抛向空中，看着它飞走，落在了道路对面的一根烧焦了的树桩上。

他立起身，将脊背靠在此时竖放在树桩顶的背包上，把胳膊伸进背带圈里。身挎背囊，他站在山脊上放眼望去，让目光越过原野飘向远处的大河，然后离开大路走下山坡。脚下的坡地很好走。下坡有两百码，到了着火线截止的地方。接下来要穿过齐脚踝深的香蕨木和一簇一簇的短叶松。有好长一段路都是陡峭的原野，一高一低的，脚下全是沙土，大自然又呈现出生机勃勃的景象。

他靠太阳确定方向，知道自己要到大河的哪个地方去。他一路前行，穿过松林覆盖的平原，爬上一个小土包，前边还会看到其他的小土包。时而他会站在一个土包上瞭望，只见左右全是松林，一片一片的，像是一座座大海岛。他折下几枝样子像石楠一般的香蕨木，插在背带之下。香蕨木被背带磨碎，他一边走一边闻着香蕨木散发出的芳香。

走在高低不平、没有树荫的平原上，他感到又累又热。他知道只要向左边一拐，随时都可以抵达河畔。大不了有一英里的路吧。可是他继续朝北走，尽量向河的上游走，预计得走一天的路。

穿过起伏的高地，有段时间，他可以看见前边耸立着一大片松林。于是他下了坡，然后慢慢地爬上坡走到桥头，在那儿转身向那片松林走去。

那片松林里没有灌木丛，树干直插青天，有些则相依相偎。所有的树干都长得笔直，呈棕褐色，没有枝杈。枝杈都长在靠上的树身上，有些交叉在一起，在棕褐色的地上投下浓浓的阴影。林子的旁边是一片空地，也是棕褐色的，走在上面又松又软。这是一片松针铺就的地，超出了高处枝杈投影的范围。树长高之后，枝杈上移，把它们原来用树荫遮盖的空地交给了阳光照耀。这片林地延伸区域的边沿与香蕨木地段紧紧相连。

他放下背包，躺倒在树荫里休息。他仰面朝天，目光射向松树的枝杈，伸展腰肢，让脖子、脊背和后腰得到休息。脊背挨着土地，感觉很惬意。他仰望天空，让目光穿过枝杈，随后闭上了眼睛。接下来，他又睁开眼，又仰望天空。高处的枝杈间有风在吹动。后来，他又闭上了眼睛，这次睡着了。

一觉睡醒，他浑身僵硬，有抽筋的感觉。太阳已快衔山。背上背包，他觉得那包沉甸甸的，带子勒在身上发痛。就这么背着背包，他拎起皮质钓竿匣，离开松林，穿过长满香蕨木的洼地，向河边走去。他知道，到那儿的路程不会超过一英里。

下了遍布树桩的山坡，来到了一片草地上。一直走到草地边，就是潺潺流淌的河水了。到了河边，他感到很开心。随后，他踏着草地向上游走去。走着走着，他的裤脚被露水打得湿漉漉的。炎热的白天一过，就降了天露，露水很重。河流没有声响，因为河水流得太快、太平稳了。走到草地的尽头，他打算登上一块高地扎营。但在去那儿之前，他朝河水里望了一眼，观察正在浮向水面的鳟鱼。鳟鱼之所以浮上来，是要捕食太阳落山时分从河对面沼泽地飞过来的昆虫。鳟鱼会跃出水面进行捕猎。他走过河边那一小段草地时，就已经见有鳟鱼跃出水面了。此刻望着河水，他觉得昆虫一定是栖息在水面上，因为河面上到处都有鳟鱼在不间断地捕食。极目远眺，只见长长的一段河水里，鳟鱼纷纷浮到水面，在水面荡起一圈一圈的水纹，像是天开始落雨了。

来到高处，这儿有树木，脚下是沙地，可以俯瞰草地、河流以及沼泽地。他放下背包以及钓竿匣，想寻找一块平坦的地方。他饥肠辘辘，打算先扎营，然后做饭吃。在两棵短叶松之间，有一块地倒是挺平坦。他从包里取出斧头，将伸出地面的两个树根砍断。这片平地还算宽敞，够睡觉的。他用手把地面的沙土抚平，将碍事的香蕨木全都连根拔起。这一来，他的手有一种香蕨木的馨香。然后，他把翻起的泥土弄平。他可不愿毯子下有任何疙疙瘩瘩的东西。泥土平整完之后，他将三条毛毯铺在地上，一条对折，紧挨地面，另两条覆盖在这一条的上边。

随后，他抡起斧头，从松树桩上砍下一片闪着亮光的木头，把它劈开，做成若干个木钉用来固定帐篷。他想要的是长长的结实的木钉，好把帐篷固定在地上。从包里取出帐篷，摊在地上，这一来，斜靠在短叶松上的背包就显得小多了。他捡起一根用作帐篷横梁的绳子，将一头绑在一棵松树的树干上，拉起另一头，把帐篷从地上拖起，再将这一头系在另一棵松树之上。帐篷悬在绳子上，就像帆布片挂在晾衣绳上一样。他把砍削好的一根杆子撑在这块大帆布后边的顶部，再砸入木钉固定四周，使之成了一顶帐篷。固定四周时，他把木钉砸得很深，用斧头的平面将它们砸进地里，连绳圈都跟着进了土里，将帆布绷得跟鼓面一般紧。

在帐篷的开口处，他挂了一块布阻挡蚊子。接着，他从背包里取出几样东西，从挡蚊子的门帘下爬进帐篷，将东西放在床头（小床置于帆布帐篷倾斜面之下）。天光透过棕色的帆布射了进来。帆布散发出好闻的气味。这儿的气氛有点神秘，却给人以家一样的感觉。钻进帐篷里来，他心情愉悦。这并不是说这一整天他的心情一直不好，只是感觉有所不同罢了。现在，愿望已经实现。这个愿望由来已久，而今一朝实现。旅途劳累，累得他浑身都散了架。愿望实现了，他扎好了营，安顿了下来，什么都不怕了。这是个安营扎寨的好地方，而他现在就在这好地方扎下了营。他给自己建了个家，他就在自己的家里。这工夫，他肚子饿了。

他从门帘下爬出了帐篷。外边已黑透了，帐篷里反而亮一些。

他走到背包跟前，用手在背包里摸索着，在背包底部装钉子的纸袋里找到一枚长钉。他紧紧捏住这枚钉子，用斧头的平面轻轻地敲打，将其砸入松树的树干，然后把背包挂在钉子上。所有的用品都装在背包里，这下子离开了地面，不用担心了。

他肚子饿了，觉得以前从来都没有这么饿过。他打开一听猪肉黄豆罐头和一听意大利面条，一股脑倒进煎锅。

“既然愿意把这些东西大老远拿来，就有权利把它们解决掉。”他自言自语地说。在越来越黑的林子里，他的声音听上去怪怪的。于是，他也就不再说了。

他用斧头从一个松树树桩上砍下几块木头，生了堆火，将一个网状的烤架架在火上，然后用靴子把烤架的四条腿踩进土里。接下来，他把煎锅放在了烤架上，底下是熊熊燃烧的火焰。此时，他肚子更饿了。黄豆和面条加热了。他搅了搅锅，把黄豆和面条掺和在一起。食物开始冒气泡，一些小气泡从底部艰难地翻上来，喷喷香。他取出一瓶番茄酱，切了四片面包。小气泡冒得更快了。他在火边坐下，将煎锅端下来，把锅里的东西倒了大概有一半在白铁盘子上。黄豆面慢慢在盘子上摊开了。他知道现在吃还太烫，于是浇了一些番茄酱在上面。黄豆和面条仍然烫得难以入口。他望望火堆，再看看帐篷。他可不愿把舌头烫伤，坏了兴致。多年来，他一直都不喜欢吃煎香蕉，因为他耐不住性子，无法等到煎香蕉凉下来再入口。他的舌头极其敏感。这当儿，他都快饿死了。河对岸的沼泽地黑魆魆的，他瞧见有一团雾在冉冉升起。他把目光收回来，又看了看帐篷。这下可以进餐了。他从盘子上舀了满满一勺面吃了下去。

“基督呀，”他说道，“我的基督呀。”他快活得不得了。

把一盘面都吃完，他才想起还有面包呢。吃第二盘时，他一边吃面一边吃面包，吃完了还用面包把盘子擦得锃亮。在圣伊格纳斯时，他曾在车站饭馆喝过一杯咖啡，吃过一块火腿三明治。打那以后，他再也没进过食。这倒是一段非常好的经历。以前他也有过饿肚子的经历，但都觉得不够味。按说，只要愿意，几小时前就可以扎营了。河边适合于扎营的地方有的是。不过，还是现在的这个营地好。

他把两大块松木塞进了烤架下的火里。火苗一下子蹿了上来。刚才，他都忘了取水冲咖啡了。于是，他从背包里拿出一个折叠式帆布桶，下了山坡，穿过草地的边缘，向河边走去。河对岸白雾茫茫。他跪在岸边，将帆布桶放进水里，感觉到膝下的草儿湿漉漉、冷冰冰。帆布桶鼓了起来，被水流用劲地拖着。河里的水冰冷刺骨。他把桶洗了洗，盛满水，提着回营地里去。离开了河边，也就感到不那么冷了。

他在树干上又砸进去一枚大钉子，将盛满水的桶挂在了上面。他给咖啡壶里灌了半壶水，又往烤架下的火里塞了几块木柴，然后把咖啡壶放在烤架上。他记不得自己平时都是怎么煮咖啡的，只记得跟霍普金斯为此斗过嘴，却忘了自己持什么样的观点。他决定先把水煮沸再说。此时他想起这是霍普金斯的煮法。曾经有一度，他和霍普金斯不管什么事都争论不休。在等着咖啡煮沸的当儿，他打开了一小听杏子罐头。他很喜欢开罐头的那种感觉。他将罐头里的杏子全倒进了一只白铁杯子里。一边观察着火上的咖啡，一边喝着杏子罐头的甜汁，起初小心翼翼的，生怕甜汁洒出来，后来想着心事，三口两口把杏子吞下了肚。罐头杏子比鲜杏味道好。

看着看着，咖啡就煮沸了。壶盖被顶起来，咖啡和咖啡沫溢出来，顺着壶帮朝下淌。他急忙把咖啡壶从烤架上拿开。这是霍普金斯煮法的胜利。他把糖放进刚才盛杏子的空杯子里，倒了些咖啡进去放凉。咖啡太烫，不好倒，他就用帽子垫在咖啡壶的柄上。用帽子垫柄，是因为他不愿意让帽子浸在壶里。可不能喝第一杯咖啡就把帽子弄脏。应该完全沿用霍普金斯煮咖啡的方法。霍普(2)理应得到这项荣誉。霍普是一个非常认真的咖啡爱好者，也是他所认识的一个最认真的人，并非庄重，而是认真。那是很久之前的陈年往事了。霍普金斯说话不见嘴唇动，喜欢打马球，曾在德克萨斯大发横财，赚了几百万块钱。当初他去芝加哥，还是借的盘缠，而就在这时电报来了，说他的第一口大油井出油了。他原来是可以发电报让汇钱来的，只是那样太慢，怕来不及。大家把霍普的女友叫金发维纳斯。霍普对此并不介意，因为那女孩并非他真正的女友。他坚定地说，对于他真正的女友，任何人都不许胡开玩笑。他这话说得一点不错。电报来时，霍普金斯已经走了。当时，那是在黑河的河畔。等到电报到了他手里，八天已经过去了。他把自己的.22口径的柯尔特牌自动手枪送给尼克，把照相机赠给了比尔，以此让大家对他老有个念想。他们准备第二年夏天再次去钓鱼。酒鬼霍普(3)成了有钱人。他将买一艘游艇，大伙儿一起去苏必利尔湖，沿着湖的北岸航行。他当时很激动，但说话却是认真的。道别时，大家的心情都不太好。后来，那趟旅行告吹了。他们再也没见过霍普金斯。那是很久以前发生在黑河河畔的事情。

尼克喝了咖啡，那是按霍普金斯的方法烹制的咖啡，味道比较苦。尼克不由得笑了。故事这样收尾是很好的。他的大脑很活跃，但他太累了，恐怕半截子会卡壳的。于是他把壶里剩下的咖啡倒掉，抖了抖咖啡壶，将里面的渣子抖进火里。然后，他点起一支烟，走进帐篷，脱掉鞋和裤子，坐在毯子上。接着，他把鞋卷在裤子里当枕头，一出溜钻进了两条毯子之间。

透过帐篷的前侧，他望着闪烁的火光——夜风在朝火里灌。夜非常安静，沼泽地那儿万籁俱寂。他在毯子下舒服地伸了个懒腰。一只蚊子在他的耳边嗡嗡叫了几声。他坐起来，划亮一根火柴，见蚊子落在了头顶的帐篷上，于是赶快过去用火柴烧它。蚊子嘶的一声葬身于火海，让他感到很满意。火柴熄灭了。他又盖着毯子躺了下来，翻个身，合上眼睛。他昏昏欲睡，觉得睡意袭来，将身子在毯子下蜷了蜷，进入了梦乡。

————————————————————

(1) 苏必利尔湖是世界上最大的淡水湖，1622年为法国探险家所发现，现为美国和加拿大共有。

(2) 霍普金斯的昵称。

(3) 原文是Hop Head。美语中的Hophead是“喜欢喝酒的人”。Hop（霍普）是Hopkins（霍普金斯）的昵称。

“双心”大河
（第二部）

次日早晨，太阳升起，帐篷里开始热了起来。尼克从罩在帐篷入口处的挡蚊网下端爬出去，瞭望着清晨的景色。爬出帐篷时，两手触着草地，觉得那草湿漉漉的。他手里拎着裤子和鞋。太阳刚刚爬上山头。眼前是草地、河流以及沼泽。河对岸绿绿的沼泽地里长着一棵棵白桦树。

清晨的河水清澈，水流平稳、湍急。下游大约有二百码的地方架着三根原木，横贯在流水之上，让拦在后边的河水变得又平又深。就在他观看的当儿，一只水貂从原木上跑过河，钻进了沼泽地。他感到很兴奋。清晨的美景以及河水叫他心情激动。他心急火燎的，无意吃早饭，但他知道早饭是必须要吃的。于是他生起一小堆火，将咖啡壶架在上面。

水在壶里热着，他拿起一个空瓶子，从高地的边缘下去，向着草地走去。草地被露水打得湿漉漉的。他想在太阳把青草晒干之前抓几只蚱蜢当鱼饵。他找到了许许多多像样的蚱蜢。它们有的躲在草茎的根部，有的附在草茎上，一个个浑身冰冷，湿湿地沾着露水，要等到阳光温暖了身子才能够跳跃呢。他专挑中等个头的棕褐色蚱蜢，把它们捡起，放进瓶子里。他把一根原木翻起，见原木的边缘下藏着几百只蚱蜢。这儿是蚱蜢的寓所。他将大概有五十只中等个头的棕褐色蚱蜢塞进了瓶子。就在他挑选之际，其他的蚱蜢在阳光下暖和了过来，一只只开始跳走了。它们边跳边飞，一开始只飞一段路，然后就落下来，僵硬地待在那儿，仿佛死去了一般。

他知道，等他吃完早饭，蚱蜢们就会像平时一样活蹦乱跳了。如果草上没有露水，要抓一瓶像样的蚱蜢，得用一整天的时间。用帽子捕捉蚱蜢，非得压死许多不可。在河水里，他把手洗了洗。一接近河边，他就有一种兴奋的感觉。随后，他向帐篷走去。草地上的蚱蜢已在僵硬地蹦跳了。瓶子里的蚱蜢被阳光照暖了身子，炸了窝似的胡蹦乱跳。他取过一截松枝当瓶塞塞在了瓶口，刚好把瓶口堵住，让蚱蜢出不来，同时叫空气充分流通。

他把翻起的原木放回原处，情知每天早晨都可以来这儿抓蚱蜢。

然后，他将盛满活蹦乱跳蚱蜢的瓶子靠在一棵松树的树干上，快手快脚地用水和了些荞麦粉，一杯面粉一杯水，搅和匀。他抓起一把咖啡放进咖啡壶里，从罐头里舀出一勺牛油平摊在烧热了的煎锅上。接下来，他把荞麦面糊均匀地倒在冒着烟的煎锅上，弄得面糊像岩浆一样四散开，牛油嗞嗞啦啦地发出声响。荞麦饼的四周开始变硬、发黄，最后变得脆脆的。饼的表层出现了气泡，气泡又慢慢变成了气孔。他拿起一片刚砍下来的松木当铲子，伸到煎黄了的那一面底下，把煎锅左右晃了晃，让面饼脱离了锅面。“我可不愿甩动煎锅做飞饼！”他心想。于是，他把那片干净的松木铲入饼下，一直伸到头，将面饼整个翻了过来。面饼在煎锅上嗞嗞啦啦响了一阵。

饼子做好之后，他又在煎锅上涂了些牛油，把所有的面糊用完，又做了一个大煎饼和一个小一些的煎饼。

他涂上苹果酱，把一大一小两个煎饼风卷残云般吃下了肚。然后，他给另一个煎饼也涂了苹果酱，对折了两下，用油纸包好，放进了衬衣口袋里。接着，他把那瓶苹果酱放回背包里，将面包切开，够做两个三明治用的。

他在背包里找出一大头洋葱，用刀子一劈两半，剥掉光滑的外皮，将其中的一半切成片，做成了两个洋葱三明治。然后，他把三明治包在油纸里，放入卡其衬衫的另一个口袋，再将口袋的纽扣扣好。他把烤架上的煎锅翻了个过，喝光了咖啡（咖啡里加了炼乳，味道发甜，颜色变成了黄褐色）。接下来，他清理营地，准备行囊。这是一个很不错的营地。

他从皮质钓竿匣里取出飞蝇钓竿，一节节连在一起，然后将钓竿匣塞回帐篷里。接着，他装上卷轴，用导线将钓线布好。布钓线时，他左右开弓，用两手轮流抓紧钓线，否则钓线会由于自身的重量滑回去。这种钓线沉甸甸的，是双股的飞钓线，是很久以前他花了八块钱买的。这种钓线沉，是为了便于朝后往空中甩，往前落下来时能够做到平稳、沉重、笔直，将毫无重量的做钓饵的苍蝇甩进水里。他打开铝质的导绳匣子——那些导绳盘在一起，放在潮湿的法兰绒衬垫之间。在开往圣伊格纳斯的火车上，他用水冷器里的水浇湿了衬垫。羊肠导绳裹在潮湿的衬垫间就变软了。此时，他展开一截导绳，用一个环把导绳的一端连在沉甸甸的飞钓线上，再将一个钓钩固定在导绳的另一端。这是一种小钓钩，很细，富有弹性。

从钓钩匣里取钓钩时，他坐在那儿，将钓竿横放在膝上。他把钓线扯紧，看钓钩系得牢不牢以及钓竿的弹性怎么样。感觉很好。他一举一动都很小心，不让钓钩扎着手指。

他拔腿向河边走去，拎着钓竿，脖子上吊着那瓶蚱蜢——他先用一根皮条套在瓶颈上，打个活扣，然后吊在脖子上。袋网挂在腰带的一个钩上，一条长长的面粉袋搭在肩上，每个角都挽一个结，拴面粉袋的绳子绕在肩上，走起路那面粉袋老是碰腿。

身上丁零当啷挂了这许多东西行路有些不便，但作为一个钓鱼人，他的心里却是快活的。装蚱蜢的瓶子在胸前荡来荡去；衬衣的上排口袋里装着他的午饭以及蝇饵盒，鼓鼓囊囊顶在他身上。

他一抬腿走进了河水里，浑身一激灵。裤腿紧紧贴在他的腿上。他感到鞋子踩在沙砾上。河水冰冷，使他连连打冷战。

水流湍急，冲击着他的腿。他下河的地方，河水没膝。他蹚水前行，沙砾在脚下一滑一滑的。他低头看看在两腿前打旋的水流，将瓶口倒过来，想取出一只蚱蜢。

最上面的一只蚱蜢从瓶口一跃，跳进了水里，被他右腿跟前的漩涡吸进激流，往下游漂了几步路又浮出了水面。它在水面上急速漂流，踢腾着腿。后来猛地出现一圈水纹，水纹划破了平平的水面，它就不见了踪影。一条鳟鱼吃掉了它。

又有一只蚱蜢把脑袋探出瓶口，抖动着触须。它的两条前腿伸出瓶子准备跳跃。尼克一把揪住它的头，抓牢它，用细钩穿透它的下巴，再经过它的胸腔，将钩子穿进它腹部的肠子肚子里。蚱蜢用前脚抓住钓钩，吐出烟油一样的汁液来。尼克一松手，将它丢进了水里。

他用右手握住钓竿，顺着蚱蜢在水里的拉力放出钓线。他用左手从卷轴上拿下钓线，由着它漂去。他可以看见蚱蜢在水里荡起一些小小的波纹，后来就不见了。

有东西扯了一下钓线。尼克急忙把绷紧的线往回拉。这可是他钓到的第一条鱼。他紧握在水上抖动的钓竿，左手往回收钓线。上钩的鳟鱼在激流中左冲右突，把钓竿扯得一弯一弯。他知道是条小鱼，一举钓竿，把钓竿直直举到空中，那钓竿被鱼儿拉得弯了腰。

他看见鳟鱼的头和身子剧烈摆动，以抵消钓线在水里紧一下松一下的拉力。

他用左手抓住钓线，将那条在水流中有气无力扑腾的鳟鱼拉到水面上来。鳟鱼的后背色彩斑驳，跟清澈的河水下沙砾的颜色一样，腰部在阳光下闪着亮光。他把钓竿夹在右腋下，弯下身子，将右手伸进水里，用湿漉漉的右手抓住了一直扭动不已的鱼儿，取下它嘴上的倒钩，扑通一声将其扔回到了河水里。

鳟鱼摇摆不定地漂在水里，后来沉到了河底一块石头旁，他伸手去摸它，水一直浸到胳膊肘。鳟鱼在流淌的水里一动不动，待在一块石头旁的沙砾上。他用手指碰了碰它，觉得它在水下光滑、冰冷。这一碰，鳟鱼游走了，从河底游到了一片阴影里。

他觉得鳟鱼并无大碍，只是太累罢了。刚才摸鱼之前，他先弄湿了手，如此便不至于蹭掉鱼身上那一层薄薄的黏液了。要是用干手摸，鱼身上那一块没有了黏液保护的地方就会被一种白色的霉菌感染。几年前，他到河边钓鱼，那儿身前身后挤满了用飞钩钓鱼的人。他时不时会看见死鱼，身上毛茸茸长满了白色的霉菌，有的漂到岩石跟前，有的翻白肚浮在水潭里。除非跟与自己合得来的人，他不愿和其他人在河边垂钓，因为那会破坏兴致的。

他蹚水向下游走，河水淹过了膝盖，在河上搭的那几根原木前的浅水里走了有五十码远。他没有给钓钩重新下饵，蹚水时把钓钩拿在手中。在浅水里是能够抓到小鳟鱼的，对此他很有把握，但他并不想要小鳟鱼，而一天的这个时候，浅水里却见不到大鳟鱼。

走着走着，河水突然加深，深及大腿根，冰冷刺骨。前面便是被原木拦住的水面，平平展展的。那一片河水平坦，黑黢黢的；左边是青草坡地靠近河岸的边缘，右边则是沼泽地。

他顶着流水身子后仰，从瓶子里取出一只蚱蜢，将蚱蜢穿在钓钩上，在它身上吐了一口唾沫，以求好运降临。随后，他从卷轴上扯下几码长的钓线，扬手将蚱蜢抛到了前方湍急、黑黢黢的水面上。蚱蜢向原木那儿漂去，接着，重重的钓线把这鱼饵拖到了水下。他紧握钓竿，从指头缝里放出钓线。

钓线被水流拖出了很长一截子。他猛一拉，钓竿摇晃了几下，随后出现了险情，竿身弯成了九十度，钓线绷紧，跃出了水面，被扯得紧紧的，沉沉地、持续地扯，相当危险。假如拉力不断加大，导线势必会绷断。他觉得已到了危急关头，于是松开了钓线。

钓线急速蹿了出去，卷轴上的棘轮嘎吱嘎吱尖叫个不停。简直太快了。他都无法控制得了了。钓线急速蹿出，卷轴的叫声也随着钓线的蹿出越来越高。

卷轴的轴心露出来时，他感觉到紧张得心脏都快要停跳了，水更深了，冰冷地刺着他的腿根，身子朝后仰，用左手的拇指使劲按住卷轴。把拇指伸进飞钩卷轴的框子里，真不是个滋味。

他用力一扯，钓线猛然绷紧，绷得硬邦邦的，随后见原木那边有一条大鳟鱼高高地跃出了水面。它跃到空中时，他垂下了钓竿尖。就在他放低钓竿尖以减轻拉力时，他觉得刚才鳟鱼的拉力太大了，钓线绷得太紧了。导线很显然已经被扯断了。当钓线完全失去了弹性，变得干涩、硬邦邦的，这种感觉是错不了的。钓竿尖低垂，钓线松了一些。

他嘴发干，心下沉，开始用卷轴收线。他从未见过这么大的鳟鱼。那重量，那难以遏制的力量，还有跃起来时那庞大的身躯！它看上去简直跟鲑鱼一样宽。

他手发抖，慢慢地收线。刚才的刺激简直太大了。他隐约觉得有点恶心，觉得还是坐下来歇歇好。

导线被扯断了，断在系着钓钩的地方。他把断了的导线拿在手里，心想那条鳟鱼一定嘴里穿着钓钩躲在原木下，远离水面，在流水中稳住身子，藏在河底的沙砾上。他知道鳟鱼的牙齿最终一定会咬断钓钩的钩线的，而把钓钩留在腮帮子上。他敢说那条鳟鱼一定气坏了。那么大的个头，怎么说都会生气的。那可是条大鳟鱼呀！它被钓钩钩得死死的，固定在那儿像块石头。它不游不动，拉钓线也觉得它像块石头。上帝啊，这可真真切切是条大个子鳟鱼呀！上帝啊，这条鳟鱼的个头之大，他前所未闻过。

他爬上岸，站到草地上，裤子上的水和鞋里的水朝下直淌，一动鞋子就嘎吱嘎吱地响。他走过去，坐在那几根原木上。他可不想加剧心里的激动情绪。

他把脚丫子在鞋里的水中扭动了几下，从前胸口袋里掏出一根烟点着，然后将火柴扔进原木下急速流淌的河水里。火柴在激流中打着旋，一条小鳟鱼浮上水面咬它。他见了哈哈一笑。他要在此处把烟抽完，欣赏眼前的情景。

坐在原木上吞云吐雾，晒着太阳，脊背叫阳光晒得暖暖的，望着前边浅浅的河水流进树林，蜿蜒曲折，闪着亮光，河床上点缀着一块块被水冲得很光滑的巨石，岸上有香柏和白桦树，屁股下的原木被太阳晒得发暖，没有树皮，摸着很舒服，坐上去光溜溜的，心里原有的失望感就慢慢消失了。这种失望感来得快，是在他肩膀疼的时候突然出现的，消失的时候却慢如抽丝。现在这些都过去了。钓竿放在原木上，他给导线上又拴了个新钓钩，将羊肠线抽紧，使之形成一个硬结。

他穿好鱼饵，然后拿起钓竿走到原木的另一端，打算从那儿下水，因为那儿的水不太深。原木下的另一侧是一个深水潭。他绕过沼泽地跟前的浅滩，一直走到浅水处的河床上。

左首，草地的尽头是林边，那儿躺着一株被连根拔起的大榆树。它是在一场暴风雨中倒下去的，树身倒向了林中，而根部连带着泥块，上面长着小草，横在河边，构成了一段坚实的河岸。河水冲刷着这棵被连根拔起的大树的边缘。他从自己所站的地方可以看到浅水河床上有一道道的深槽，那是水流冲出来的，像车辙一样。他所在之处是鹅卵石河床，远处则密密麻麻净是大石块，夹杂着鹅卵石。河水在树根附近转了个弯，此处的河床呈泥灰色，深水下的槽与槽之间长着绿色的水草，在激流中左摆右晃的。

他把钓竿从肩膀头朝后一抡，再向前一甩，钓线前弯，将蚱蜢鱼饵送到了水草间的一个深槽里。一条鳟鱼咬住了蚱蜢，被他钩住了。

他握紧钓竿，将钓竿伸向那棵被连根拔起的树，在激流中连连后退，弄得水花四溅。鳟鱼左跳右跳，让拉弯了的钓竿激烈晃动着。他急忙扯钓竿，将鳟鱼从水草间安全地拉到了开阔的水域。钓竿迎着激流剧烈地晃动，而他抓紧钓竿，把鳟鱼往怀里拉。鳟鱼挣扎着想跑，但每一次都被拉了回来，具有弹性的钓竿一弯一直的。钓钩有时被扯到水下，却总是会把鳟鱼再拉回来。他一边收线，一边向下游走，最后将钓竿举过头顶，把鳟鱼吊到网兜上方，再张开网接住。

鳟鱼沉甸甸挂在网兜里，网眼里露出它那斑驳的脊背和银白色的腹部。他解下了钓钩。鳟鱼的腹部很厚实，大大的下颌突出，容易抓得牢。他一松手，让一口一口喘息着的鳟鱼滑落进了搭在他肩上的长形布袋里，那布袋从他的肩头一直垂到水里。

他迎着激流张开布袋口，灌满水，把布袋灌得沉甸甸的，然后一提，底部仍留在水中，布袋里的水从旁边倾泻而出。这样，布袋底部的鳟鱼浸在水里，仍可以存活。

他朝下游移动，挂在前胸的布袋浸在水里发沉，拉扯着他的肩膀。

天气越来越热，阳光照得他的脖颈发烫。

他已经钓到了一条挺不错的鳟鱼。至于能不能钓到多条鳟鱼，他并不在乎。此处的河段又浅又宽，两岸树影婆娑。左岸的树木于午前的阳光下在水面遮出了一道一道短短的阴影。他知道每一道阴影里都藏有鳟鱼。午后，阳光移向群山，鳟鱼就到对岸去，躲在对岸凉爽的阴影里。

那些超级大的鳟鱼一般会躲在靠近河岸的地方。在黑河钓鱼的时候，这种大鳟鱼一抓一个准。太阳一落山，鳟鱼们会倾巢而出，游到激流中来。太阳下山之前，水面上波光闪耀，刺人眼目，此时在激流里任何一个地方都可以抓到大鳟鱼。只是抓不成而已，因为水面在阳光下亮得刺眼，像一面镜子。当然，你可以到上游去抓喽。不过，不管是在黑河还是这样的河蹚水往上游走，你得顶着激流逆行，踏进深水区，河水会把你淹没的。在这种湍急的激流中到上游去钓鱼，可不是闹着玩的。

他一边走过浅水滩，一边眼睛盯着河岸边，看那儿有没有深水潭。紧靠河水长着一棵山毛榉，枝叶垂下来，浸到了水中。河水在枝叶下产生了回流。这种地方总是会有鳟鱼的。

他不愿到那潭水里钓鱼，因为他情知钓钩一定会缠在树枝上的。

不过，那儿的水看上去倒是挺深的。他投下蚱蜢，水流把它吸到了水底，随后又将它送到了低垂的树枝下。钓线绷紧了，他往回一拉，上钩的鳟鱼用力地扑腾着，在枝叶之间露出水面半个身子来。钓线被缠住了。他用力一拉，鳟鱼脱钩了。他用卷轴收回钓线，将钓钩拿在手中，向下游走去。

前边靠近左岸有一根大大的原木，看得出是空心的，朝着上游横放在那里，河水缓缓地流进去，仅在原木的两侧激起一圈小小的涟漪。越往前走，河水就越深。空心原木的顶部呈灰颜色，是干燥的，有一部分隐没在阴影里。

他把蚱蜢瓶的瓶塞拔出，有一只蚱蜢附在瓶塞上。他把它拿在手中，穿到钓钩上，然后甩了出去。他将钓竿伸得远远的，让蚱蜢从水上漂到那股钻进空心原木的水流里。接着，他把钓竿放低，于是蚱蜢便漂进了原木空心里。钓线被沉沉地拉紧了，他往回抽钓竿以抵抗那股拉力。他觉得就好像钓钩钩在了原木上一样，只是那上钩的东西是活的罢了。

他竭力想把鳟鱼拉出来，拉进外边的水流里。鳟鱼出来了，分量重重的。钓线一下子变松了，他以为鳟鱼溜掉了，可随后他看见了它，近在咫尺，在水里摆动着头，企图将钓钩甩掉。它的嘴被钩得死死的。它在清澈的流水里拼命挣扎，和钓钩殊死搏斗。

他用左手将钓线绕成圈，一圈一圈朝回拉。他抖抖钓竿，把钓线扯紧，想把鳟鱼向网兜跟前引，可是鳟鱼一出溜跑了，不见了踪影，钓线却在晃动着。他顶着激流跟它搏斗着，钓竿一弹一跳，而它随之扑腾个不停。他将钓竿转移到左手，然后把鳟鱼往上游一拉，提起钓竿，任它悬在钓竿上挣扎，最后将它丢进了网兜里。他拎起网兜，鳟鱼沉甸甸的，弯成了半圆形，而网兜不时朝下滴着水。他解下钓钩，把它丢进了布袋里。

他张开布袋口，低头看了看，见那两条大鳟鱼在水中扭动着。

他蹚过渐深的河水，向那根空心原木走去。随后，他绕过头顶将布袋取下。鳟鱼一离开水，就胡乱拍打起来。他找个地方将布袋挂起，让鳟鱼深深地浸在水中。然后，他爬上原木，坐下来，裤子上的水和靴子里的水哗哗朝下淌，汇入河水里。他放下钓竿，转移到原木有阴凉的另一端，从衣袋里掏出三明治，将三明治在冰冷的水里浸了浸。河水把一些面包屑冲走了。他吃了三明治，然后用帽子盛水喝，把帽壳里灌满了水，喝的时候，帽壳里的水直从嘴边朝外流。

坐在阴凉地的原木上倒是挺凉爽的。他取了根烟，划着火柴。火柴掉在灰色的木头上，烧出一个小凹痕。他向着原木的一侧歪了歪身子，找块坚实的地方，又划了根火柴，坐在那儿边抽烟边观望河景。

前方，河水变窄，弯进了沼泽地里，水面平缓，但很深。沼泽里长着香柏，看上去像陆地。香柏一棵挨一棵，枝杈密密麻麻。这样的沼泽地是不可能穿越的。树的枝杈长得太低，动弹起来恐怕得贴近地面才行。这样的枝杈是硬冲不过去的。他心想：难怪生活在这片沼泽地的动物都弯腰曲背的。

真希望当初带本书来就好了。这会儿，他觉得自己很想拿本书看看。他不愿再往前走到沼泽地里去了。朝河面上望了一眼，只见有棵巨大的香柏树横贯河面，搭在两岸之上。远处可见河水蜿蜒流进沼泽。

此刻他不想进沼泽地。去那儿得走深水区，水深可达腋窝处，在那种地方就是钓到大鱼，也无法弄上岸的，所以他有一种排斥心理。在沼泽里，岸上光秃秃的，巨大的香柏树抱成团遮在头顶，阳光洒不进来，只可见一些斑驳的光点。这样半明半暗的光线，在湍急的深水里钓鱼是会很惨的。到沼泽地里钓鱼是一种悲惨的冒险。他可不愿冒这种险。反正今天他是不愿再往下游走了。

他取出折刀，将折刀打开，一刀扎在原木上，然后拎起布袋，伸手进去拿出一条鳟鱼。他用手抓紧鳟鱼的尾巴根——那鳟鱼胡乱挣扎，很难抓得牢。随后，他把鳟鱼在原木上狠劲摔了一下。那鱼抖动了几下，最后僵硬了。他把这条鳟鱼放在原木上的阴凉处，又以同样的方式摔断了另一条鱼的脖子。他将两条鱼并排放在原木上。这可是两条相当棒的鳟鱼！

他把它们大开膛，从肛门剖至下颌，剔了个干净。所有的内脏、鱼鳃和舌头都一股脑儿剜了出来。两条鱼都是雄性，灰白色的输精管长长的，又平展又干净。鱼的内脏被干净利落地全取了出来，他将那些废弃了的东西扔到岸上供水貂觅食。

他把鳟鱼拿到河水里清洗。在河水里，他让鱼儿背朝上。两条鳟鱼看上去像活的一样，颜色都没有变。接着，他洗了洗手，把手在原木上蹭干。随后，他将鳟鱼放在摊在原木之上的布袋上，卷起来，扎了个捆，置入袋网里。他的折刀还扎在那儿，刀刃嵌入原木。他拔出折刀，在原木上蹭了蹭，放进了衣袋里。

他在原木上站起身，握紧钓竿，将沉甸甸的袋网挎在肩上，然后踏入水中，一路溅着水花向岸边走去。他爬上岸，钻进林子，朝着高地进发，取道返回营地。回首望去，透过树木那条河流隐约可见。来日方长，他总有机会可以到沼泽地里钓鱼的。

暴风雨过后

那时不为了什么大不了的事情，不值得动拳头，可我们俩却厮打在了一起。我脚下一滑摔倒在地，他用膝盖顶住我的胸口，两手掐住我的脖子，掐得我透不过气，好像非得把我掐死不可。我试图从衣袋里掏出刀子捅他一刀，好让他松手。旁边的人都喝得酩酊大醉，没有人出手把他拉开。他掐住我，把我的头往地上碰。我终于将折刀掏了出来，打开，在他的胳膊上划了一刀，把他胳膊上的肌肉都划裂了，于是他一下子松了手。就是他想抓住我不放，也力所难及了。只见他就地一滚，用手捂紧受伤的胳膊，竟然呜呜哭了起来。我在一旁说：

“见鬼啦，你想掐死我吗？”

我恨不得一刀子捅死他算啦。他掐得我喉咙疼，害得我一星期咽不下饭去。

话说当时，我一拍屁股逃离了那儿。他们人多势众，当中有几个跑过来追我。我拐了个弯，从码头旁夺路而逃。路上遇到一个人，他说出人命了，街上有个人被杀了。我问：“是谁杀的？”他说：“不清楚是谁杀的，反正人已经死了。”此时天色已黑，街上到处是积水，没有路灯，住家户的窗户玻璃碎了一地，狂风把船刮到了街道上，树木被吹倒，所有的一切都被大风刮得面目全非。我弄到一只划子，划着它出了码头去寻找我的船。我把那只小船停泊在曼格礁石湾里了。它平安无事，只是船舱里灌满了水。于是我动手清理船舱，用水泵把水抽干净。天上有月亮，但乌云遮顶，风势依然猛烈。我将小船划开，天亮时分已离开了东港。

兄弟，那场暴风雨真够味。我的船是第一个出来的，从没见过浪头那么大。海浪汹涌，颜色白得就跟碱水一样，从东港滚滚向西南礁石湾冲来，使人连海岸都看不清了。劲风掠过海滩，在海滩上刮出一条大沟。树林倾伏，中间被风刮出一条通道，那儿满都是水，白得像粉笔，水上什么东西都有，树枝啦，整棵树啦，死鸟啦，全都漂浮在水面上。好像全世界的鹈鹕以及其他各种各样的飞鸟都躲进了礁石湾里。它们一定是提前知道暴风雨要来才藏身于此处的。

我在西南礁石湾待了一天，没见那伙人追过来。我的船是来这儿的第一条船。我看见一根船柱漂浮在水面，心想一定有船沉了，于是便四处寻找，结果找到了它。那是一条三桅纵帆船，可以看得见几根船柱的残桩从水里冒出头来。船在水里沉得太深，里面的东西弄不出来。于是我继续寻找，想捞到一点油水。对于自己找到的东西，我是有权拥有的。不管是什么，我都应该先弄到手。我离开那条三桅纵帆船，在沙洲上搜寻开去，结果一无所得。我跑出了很远的路，朝着流沙滩前进。在那儿也没找到任何东西，于是又继续向前走。后来望到吕蓓卡灯塔，只见那儿群鸟聚集，在围着什么东西。我走过去探究竟，想看看到底是什么东西。鸟儿黑压压一片，像乌云一样。

可以看见一个像船柱一般的东西从水里戳了出来。我划船向前时，所有的鸟都飞到了空中，围着我盘旋。海水清澈，果真有根船柱什么的在水面上冒出了个尖。我凑到跟前，看见它黑黢黢地沉在水下，像一条长长的黑影。我把船划过去，只见水下有一艘邮轮，静静地躺在水底世界，简直大极了。我的小船就漂浮在这艘巨轮的上方。它身子侧翻，尾部深深下沉，舷窗全都关得死死的。可以看到水下有玻璃在闪光，还可以看到巨轮的整个轮廓。这是我一生中所见过的最大的轮船，而它就躺在那里。我先划着小船从巨轮的这头跑到那头，然后找个地方停好船，再将甲板上的划子拖过来，一推把划子推下水，动手划了起来，飞鸟云集在我的周围盘旋。

我有一副水下观察镜，跟我们捞取海绵动物时戴的防护镜很像。我的手抖得厉害，几乎都拿不稳观察镜了。从轮船的上方划过去，可以看见所有的舷窗都紧闭着。不过，贴近海底的某扇门窗肯定是开着的，因为不时有七零八碎的东西浮上来。说不清那是些什么东西，反正都是些零碎玩意儿吧。那些鸟儿要的就是这些玩意儿。以前从未见过这么多的鸟。它们围着我盘旋，疯狂地聒噪个不停。

一切都看得清清楚楚。只见它躺在水下，看上去有一英里长。它的身下是洁白的沙地。它是侧身斜躺着的，于此可见露出水面的柱子是前桅杆什么的，或者是某种索具吧，斜着伸出了水面。船头位于水下不太深的地方，我可以站在刻在船头的船名那几个字母上，脑袋刚刚露出水来。不过，最近的舷窗也在水下十二英尺远的地方，用杆子刚能够得着。于是我就用杆子击打舷窗，可就是打不破，舷窗上的玻璃太结实了。后来，我划着划子返回小船，取来一把扳子绑在木杆头上击打，可玻璃还是打不碎。用水下观察镜低头看看巨轮，那里边可是藏着宝贝呢。我是发现它的第一人，可惜就是进不去。轮船里的东西恐怕能值五百万元。

一想到那价值连城的宝贝，我就浑身发抖。从离得最近的那扇舷窗望去，可以看到里面有样东西，不过用水下观察镜却分辨不清那究竟是什么东西。用手里的杆子又砸不破舷窗，于是站在那儿深深吸了两口气，然后手持扳子从船尾一个猛子扎入水里，向水下潜去。到了那扇舷窗的边缘跟前，我憋了一会儿气，可以看见里面有个女人，她的头发散开漂浮在水中。她漂浮的样子我看得一清二楚。我用扳子使劲砸玻璃，连砸了两下，耳朵里听得到咣咣的两声响，玻璃却没有砸碎。我只好浮到了水面上。

我紧紧抓住小船喘了口气，然后爬上小船，又一个猛子扎入水里。我向下潜游到那扇舷窗跟前，用手指抓住舷窗的边，然后使出吃奶的力气用扳子猛砸玻璃。透过玻璃，我可以看见那个女人漂在水里，曾经扎起来的头发全都散开了，浮在水中。看得见她的一只手上戴着戒指，就在贴近舷窗的地方。我又连砸两下，而玻璃却连条裂纹都没有。浮上水面时，我心想：这次不到非得换气，就绝不上来。

我又潜入水中，又奋力砸玻璃，可是砸也是白砸。再次浮到水面上，我的鼻子流血不止。我站在轮船的船头，光脚丫子踩在船名的那几个字母上，脑袋刚刚露出水面，在那儿休息了一下，游到划子跟前，爬进划子，坐在划子里等着头疼症消失，一边低头看了看水下观察镜，见上面有鼻血，于是把观察镜在水里洗了洗。接下来，我就躺在划子上，把手堵在鼻子下止血。我躺在那儿仰面望去，见天上足有一百万只鸟在盘旋来盘旋去。

鼻血止住之后，我又检查了一眼观察镜，然后把划子划到我的船跟前，想找一样比扳子更重一些的家伙，却一无所得，连捞海绵动物用的铁钩都没有找到。我返回原处，见海水仍一如既往的清澈，飘落在白沙海底上的东西一览无余。我四处看看，没发现有鲨鱼。有鲨鱼出现，老远都能看得到的。水清极了，沙子白极了。划子上有个泊船用的抓钩，我把它砍了下来，拿着它从划子边扎入水中。铁钩拖着我下沉，经过那扇舷窗时，我用手去抓，却什么也没抓住，于是就继续下沉，沉啊沉的，沿着弯弯的船身一直下沉。最后，我不得不松开了铁钩，听见了嗵的一声响。等我浮上水面时，觉得好像已过了一年之久。划子顺着海潮漂走了。我见状急忙游了过去，一边游一边鼻血直流。十分让人庆幸的是周围没有鲨鱼。不过，我已经精疲力竭了。

我头疼欲裂，于是躺在划子上休息了一下，然后划回小船那儿去。时间在行进，已到了下午时分。我又拿着扳子潜入水中，还是一无所成，因为那扳子太轻了。除非有一个大铁锤，或者有一样重得能干事的家伙，否则潜到水里来屁用都不顶。我把扳子又绑到了杆子上，透过水下观察镜看着，在玻璃上又是击又是砸，最后导致扳子脱落。我从观察镜里看得清清楚楚，看见它顺着轮船的船身滑过，一直朝下落，最后落进了流沙里。我无计可施，只能眼睁睁看着。扳子不见了，铁钩也遗失了，我悻悻地划着划子返回小船。我累坏了，都没有气力把划子拉上小船了。此时，太阳已经很低了。水鸟在撤退，纷纷离开轮船。我把划子向西南礁石湾划去，前后都有水鸟在飞行。我累得浑身都散了架。

那天夜里刮起了大风，连着刮了一个星期。无法再到沉船的地方去。他们从城里跑来，说那个被我砍了一刀的家伙，除了胳膊受了点伤，一点事都没有。于是我回到了城里。他们拿出五百块钱，跟我签了份打捞沉船的协议。结果并不如人意，他们中有我的朋友，信誓旦旦地说要拿把斧头跟我去，可是等我们到了沉船的地方，希腊人早已将船体炸开了，把里面的东西洗劫一空。保险柜也被炸开了，没人知道他们拿走了多少钱。船里装的有金子，都被他们拿走了。他们将东西洗劫了个干净，一点不剩。沉船是我发现的，我却一分钱也没得到。

这场海难真是惨极了。据说暴风袭来时，轮船就在哈瓦那港口外，只是无法进港，或者说船主不允许船长冒险把轮船开进港。船长说想试试也不顶用。就这样，轮船只好接受暴风雨的袭击。天黑时，它顶着狂风试图穿过吕蓓卡灯塔和托尔图加斯之间的海峡，结果撞上了流沙。也许船舵被风刮掉了，或者说没人掌舵，反正稀里糊涂就撞上了。船进流沙时，船长发布了一道命令，叫打开压载舱，好让船固定位置。可是，那可是流沙呀！压载舱一打开，船尾便首先下沉，船体随之侧翻，船舷着地。船上有四百五十名乘客和船员，我发现沉船时，他们肯定都还困在船上。当时的情况一定是这样的：船进流沙，他们立刻打开了压载舱，船体落地之后，被流沙吸了进去。后来，八成是锅炉发生了爆炸，结果弄得碎片到处漂浮。奇怪的是，沉船的地方居然没有鲨鱼。连一条鱼也没有。那么洁白的沙子海底，要是有鱼，我是能够看得见的。

眼下鱼儿倒是不少，都是些大海鲈，个头非常大。沉船的大部分船体埋进了沙子，而这些鱼便游进了船体，全都是巨大型的海鲈。有的鱼一条就重达三四百磅。以后哪一天，就来这儿捕上几条。从沉船处，可以看见吕蓓卡灯塔。灯塔那儿设有浮标。沉船位于流沙地的尽端，紧挨海峡的边缘，再差四百码就能闯过去了。黑灯瞎火地在暴风雨中挣扎，结果功亏一篑。当时雨太大，他们没能看见吕蓓卡灯塔。这种情况对他们来说是不常见的。那样风驰电掣的速度叫轮船的船长很不适应。轮船是有自己的航道的。他们告诉我，说船上安装有可以自动导航的罗盘。暴风雨袭来时，他们大概弄不清自己所处的位置。不过，话又说回来，他们当时差点成功脱险。还有一种可能——船舵被风刮掉了。说来说去，只要进了那个海峡，一直把船开到墨西哥都不会再有什么灾难了。在狂风暴雨之中，一定是遇到了什么险情，船长才命令打开压载舱的。那么大的风雨，甲板上不可能有人，所有的人肯定都进了船舱。待在甲板上会没命的。船舱里肯定出现了哄堂大乱，才导致轮船急速下沉。光看看扳子怎么落进沙子，便知道当时的情况。船长又不熟悉这片水域，不可能知道轮船撞上了流沙。他只知道轮船所撞的不是礁石。他当时一定在船桥指挥室，把一切都看在了眼里。轮船一下沉，他恐怕就已经意识到劫数到了。真不知当时轮船下沉得有多么快。大副是不是跟船长在一起呢？灾难降临时，他们俩是在船桥指挥室里，还是在外边呢？事后，没有发现任何尸体，连一具也没找到。海面上没有浮尸。有救生圈，是可以漂浮很远的路的。看来，灾难降临时，船长和大副一定在指挥室里。希腊人把东西洗劫一空，什么都没有留下。他们来得可真够快的，把轮船洗劫了个干干净净。水鸟先到，接下来是我，然后才是希腊人。就连水鸟得到的东西也比我得到的多。

一个干净明亮的地方

天色已晚，咖啡店里人去屋空，只剩下了一个老人坐在树叶遮出的路灯的灯影里。白日里，街上尘土飞扬，而晚间降了露水，尘土就落下去了。老人喜欢在咖啡店里独坐至很晚，因为他耳聋，晚间清净，他会有不同的感受。店里的两个侍者知道老人有点醉了。老人固然是个好顾客，但他们知道万一他喝得酩酊大醉，走时可能会忘记付账，于是两人就在跟前盯着他。

“上星期他差点没自杀。”一位侍者说。

“为什么？”

“绝望了呗。”

“为什么绝望？”

“什么也不为。”

“你怎么知道什么也不为？”

“他有许多的钱。”

两个侍者坐在墙跟前的一张座子旁，靠近咖啡店的大门，不住眼张望着阳台。阳台上的桌子全空了，只有老人独自坐在随风摇曳的婆娑树影里。一个姑娘和一个士兵从街上走过。路灯的灯光洒在士兵领子上的号码铜牌上。姑娘头上没戴帽子，步履匆匆地随在他的身旁。

“宪兵会把他抓起来的。”一个侍者说。

“如果得到了自己追求的人，抓起来又有什么关系？”

“他最好别在街面上待，不然宪兵会抓他的。这儿五分钟之前还有宪兵走过呢。”

此时，坐在阴影里的老人用玻璃杯碰了碰茶托。年龄较轻的侍者见状走了过去。

“你需要什么？”

老人看了看他，然后说：“再来杯白兰地。”

“你会喝醉的。”侍者说。老人瞥了他一眼。后者抽身离去了。

“他会泡上一夜的。”这位侍者对他的同事说，“我的眼皮子都打架了。我从没在三点之前睡过觉。他上个星期自杀，死了就好了。”

他从店里的柜台取过一瓶白兰地和一个茶托，大步走向老人的桌子，放下茶托，给对方的杯子斟满了白兰地。

“你上个星期自杀，死了就好了。”他冲着耳聋的老人说。老人伸出一个手指，摆了摆说：“再加一点。”侍者又给他加了许多酒，弄得酒液外溢，顺着杯子朝下淌，流进了摞在最上面的茶托里。老人说：“多谢。”侍者拎起酒瓶，回到了店里，在同事的身旁又坐了下来。

“现在他可是喝醉了。”他说。

“他每天晚上都喝醉。”

“他为什么想自杀呢？”

“我怎么知道？”

“他是怎么自杀的？”

“用绳子上吊。”

“是谁把他放下来的？”

“他侄女。”

“为什么放他下来？”

“是怕他的灵魂得不到解救。”

“他有多少钱？”

“多得很。”

“他一定有八十岁了。”

“要让我说，他该有八十岁了。”

“真希望他赶快回家去。三点钟之前我都没有睡过觉。那么晚才睡，该是什么滋味！”

“他熬夜不睡觉，那是因为他喜欢这样。”

“他孤独呗。我可不孤独。家里有个老婆在床上等我呢。”

“他以前也是有老婆的。”

“现在有老婆，对他就没什么意思了。”

“这可说不来。有个老婆，他的境况也许会好一些的。”

“他有侄女照顾呢。你刚才说是她把他从吊绳上放下来的。”

“这我知道。”

“我可不愿活那么长。老了就邋里邋遢的。”

“并不一定。这个老人就干干净净的。他喝酒从不把酒洒出来。即便现在喝醉了也是这样。你可以瞧瞧嘛。”

“我才不愿看他呢，只希望他赶快回家去。人家还得工作呢，他一点也不为别人考虑。”

老人将目光从酒杯移开，看了看广场，然后又看了看这两位侍者。

“再来一杯白兰地。”他指了指酒杯说。急着回家的那个侍者走了过去。

“完事了。”他说道。这话说得缺乏文法，属于大老粗对醉汉或外国人说话的那种方式。“今晚够了。要打烊了。”

“再来一杯。”老人说。

“不行。完事了。”侍者用毛巾擦着桌沿，一边摇了摇头。

老人站起身，慢条斯理地数了数茶托，从衣袋里取出一个装硬币的皮夹子，付了酒钱，留下半个比塞塔作为小费。

侍者目送着他走上大街——一个年迈的老人，脚步不稳，但气质不凡。

“你为什么就不能让他再待待，再喝上一杯呢？”那个不急着回家的侍者问。说话间，两人正在关门窗。“还不到两点半呢。”

“我想回家睡觉呢。”

“迟睡一个小时又算什么？”

“对他不算什么，对我就不一样了。”

“反正就是一个小时的时间么。”

“你说话好像你也七老八十了一样。他可以买瓶酒回家喝么。”

“那是不一样的。”

“是的，是不一样。”家里有老婆的侍者同意了对方的说法。他并不想以不公正的态度待人，只是急着回家罢了。

“你呢？还没到时间就回家，你就不怕吗？”

“你是不是想损我？”

“哪里的话，伙计。只不过开个玩笑嘛。”

“我没什么可怕的。”急着回家的侍者说，一边拉下金属卷门，随后站起了身，“我是有底气的，完全有自信心。”

“你有青春，有底气，有工作，应有尽有呀。”年纪稍大的侍者说。

“你缺什么？”

“除了工作什么都缺。”

“我有的你也都有呀。”

“错了。我从来就没有过底气，而且我也不年轻了。”

“好啦，别说些不着边的话了。快把门锁上吧。”

“我属于那种喜欢在咖啡店泡到很晚的人。”年纪稍大的侍者说，“我喜欢跟那些不愿意睡觉的人在一起，喜欢跟那些夜间需要灯光的人在一起。”

“我是想回家睡觉去了。”

“你我不是一类人呀。”年纪稍大的侍者说。此刻，他已在更衣准备回家了。“虽然青春和自信心是非常美好的东西，但此处并不仅仅涉及这些因素。每天夜间我都不愿关店门，觉得很可能会有人需要来喝上一杯。”

“伙计，他们可以去通宵营业的店呀。”

“你不懂。这家店环境干净，令人愉悦，明明亮亮的。这儿灯光充足，还有婆娑的树影。”

“再见。”年轻的侍者说。

“再见。”年纪稍大的侍者说。他一边关电灯，一边嘴里在自言自语着。灯光固然重要，但干净和令人愉悦的环境也是必需的。你不需要音乐，当然不需要音乐了。你不可能带着自尊站到吧台前，虽然这种时辰也只有自尊跟你相伴了。有什么害怕的呢？其实这不是害怕，也不是恐惧。这是他所熟悉的一种虚空感。万物都是虚空的，就连人也是虚空的。在这个虚空世界里，需要有灯光，还需要有一个干净、整齐的环境。有的人生活在其中，却感觉不到。他知道nada y pues nada y nada y pues nada(1)。名字是虚空，国家是虚空，意志也是虚空，虚空中套着虚空。日常生活是虚空，芸芸众生是虚空，我们从虚空走向虚空，再转移向另一个虚空。欢呼吧，虚空，让世界充满虚空，愿虚空与你同在。冥想期间，他笑盈盈地站在一个吧台前，台上放着一个亮光闪闪的气压咖啡机。

“你要什么？”酒吧招待问。

“虚空。”

“Otro loco más.(2)”酒吧招待嘟哝了一句，就把身子转开了。

“来一小杯吧。”侍者说。

酒吧招待给他倒了杯酒。

“灯光非常明亮，环境令人愉悦，只是吧台应该擦得再亮一些。”侍者说。

酒吧招待瞥了他一眼，但没有搭腔。夜已深，不适合于交谈了。

“想再来一杯吗？”酒吧招待问。

“不了。谢谢。”侍者说完走了出去。他不喜欢酒吧，也不喜欢酒馆。一个干净、明亮的咖啡店可就完全不一样了。他没有再多想，他要回自己的房间去了。他要躺在床上，天亮时分他最终总会入睡的。他对自己说：“没什么了不起的，只不过是失眠症罢了。失眠的人肯定多着呢。”

————————————————————

(1) 西班牙语。大意是：虚空，虚空，除了虚空还是虚空。

(2) 西班牙语。意思是：又是一个神经病。

世界之光明

酒保见我们进门，抬头扫了我们一眼，急忙伸手把玻璃罩罩在了两碗免费的菜肴上。

“给我来杯啤酒。”我说了一声。他打开啤酒桶的龙头放了一杯，用抹刀刮掉上面的一层泡沫，然后将酒杯端在手中。我把五分镍币放在吧台上，他这才将啤酒杯推给了我。

“你要什么？”他问汤姆。

“啤酒。”

他放了一杯，刮掉泡沫，见汤姆付了钱，才把酒杯推给了他。

“怎么啦？”汤姆问。

酒保没吱声，从我们头顶上方望去，冲着一个刚进门的汉子问道：“你要什么？”

“黑麦威士忌。”那汉子说。酒保摆出一瓶酒和酒杯，另外还有一杯水。

汤姆一伸手，把免费菜肴碗上的玻璃罩拿掉。原来是一碗腌猪蹄，里面还有一件木质食具，样子像剪刀，末端有两个木叉，用来叉猪蹄吃。

“这可不行。”酒保说完，将玻璃罩又盖回了碗上。汤姆却把剪刀一样的木叉拿在了手里。“放回去。”酒保说。

“去你的吧。”汤姆说。

酒保把一只手伸到吧台下，怒目望着我们俩。我把五毛钱放到吧台上，他这才把弯下去的腰又挺直了。

“你要什么？”他问。

“啤酒。”我说。他揭开了两个碗上的玻璃罩，然后去放啤酒。

“这他妈的猪蹄子是臭的。”汤姆说完，呸的一口把吃到嘴里的肉吐到了地上。酒保没吱声。那个刚进门的汉子把黑麦威士忌喝完，付了账，头也不回地走了。

“你自己才是臭的呢。”酒保说，“你们这帮无赖全都臭烘烘的。”

“他说咱们是无赖。”汤姆对我说。

“好啦，”我说，“咱们走吧。”

“你们这帮无赖快滚蛋吧。”酒保说。

“我说过要走的，”我说，“不是你撵我们走就走。”

“我们还会再来的。”汤米(1)说。

“不，你们可别来了。”酒保冲着他说。

“瞧他把咱们冤枉的。”汤姆对我说。

“快走吧。”我说。

到了外边的感觉很好。天色已经黑了下来。

“这鬼地方是哪儿？”汤姆问。

“我也不知道。”我说，“咱们还是到车站去吧。”

我们是从一个方向进的城，现在则从另一个方向出城。四处飘散着皮革味、树皮味，以及大堆大堆的锯末散发出的气味。进城时，天刚擦黑，而此时天已黑透。空气寒冷，路上有水洼，水洼的边都结上了冰。

车站上有五个烟花女子在等火车进站，另外还有五个白人男子和四个印第安人。候车室里显得很拥挤，炉子烧得热烘烘的，烟雾缭绕。我们进屋时，没有人说话，售票窗的窗口关着。

“请把门关上，好不好？”有个人说道。

我张目望去，想看看说话的是何人。原来是那几个白人男子当中的一个在发声。他下穿沾着木屑的裤子，脚蹬伐木工橡胶鞋，上身穿的是方格厚呢衣，跟另几个人装束一样，只是没戴帽子，脸色发白，两只手又白又瘦。

“你到底关不关呀？”

“当然要关。”我说完把门关上了。

“谢谢。”他说。

那些人当中，有一个扑哧笑了，对我说道：“你跟厨子拌过嘴吗？”

“没有。”

“那你可以跟这个厨子拌拌嘴。”他说着用眼瞅了瞅那位“厨子”，“他喜欢跟人拌嘴。”

那个厨子把脸掉开不去看他，嘴唇绷得紧紧的。

“他把柠檬汁涂在手上，”那人说，“死也不愿把手放进水里洗碗。你瞧瞧，这手多白。”

一个烟花女子哈哈大笑出了声。我一辈子都没见过块头这么大的烟花女子，也没见过块头这么大的良家女。她身穿一种能改变颜色的绸缎服装。另两个烟花女子也同样身躯庞大，不过，发笑的这位论体重一定有三百五十磅。你看她的时候，简直都不敢相信她是个有血有肉的真人。她们三个穿的都是能改变颜色的绸缎服装，并排坐在凳子上，块头大得似小山。另外的两个看上去与普通妓女无异，金色的头发都用化学剂漂染过。

“诸位瞧瞧他的手哟。”那位调侃的男子一边说，一边冲着厨子摇头晃脑的。大块头烟花女子又哈哈大笑起来，笑得浑身发抖。

厨子转过身来，用急速的语调对她说：“你这个让人恶心的肥婆娘！”

大块头仍大笑不止，浑身颤抖着。

“哎呀，我的基督呀！”她的声音很好听，“哎呀，我可爱的基督呀！”

另两个烟花女子，一对大块头，却一声不吭，表现得文文静静，就好像没感觉似的。不过，虽说她们表现得文雅，块头却太大了，跟身躯最为庞大的那个差不了多少。她们少说也有两百五十磅，一个个装出很体面的样子。

那几位男子，除了厨子和那个调侃的，还有两个伐木工，一个在听，兴趣盎然的，但很是腼腆，另一个则跃跃欲试，似乎想插话。这群人里面，还有两个瑞典人。两个印第安人坐在长凳的另一头，还有一个靠墙根站着。

那个想插话的男子用非常低的声音对我说：“骑在上面，就像躺在干草堆上。”

我听了笑得肚子疼，把这话传给了汤米。

“我对天发誓，我可从来没有睡过这样的干草堆。”汤米说，“你瞧瞧她们三个的身段！”

此时只听厨子问道：“你们二位多大了？”

“我九十六，他六十九。”汤米说。

“哈！哈！哈！”大块头烟花女子又爆发出一阵笑声，浑身颤抖着。她的声音的确非常好听。另两个女子却面无笑意。

“喂，你就不能正经点吗？”厨子诘问，“我问你话可是客客气气的。”

“我们俩一个十七岁，一个十九岁。”我说道。

“你这是咋啦？”汤米转过头来问我。

“没什么。”

“你们叫我爱丽丝好啦。”大块头烟花女子说完又笑得浑身发抖。

“这是你的名字？”汤米问。

“当然喽。”她说，“就是叫爱丽丝，对不对？”她转身问坐在厨子旁边的那个男子。

“是叫爱丽丝。一点不错。”

“你就应该有这样的名字。”厨子说。

“这是我的真实名字。”爱丽丝说。

“敢问另两位姑娘的芳名？”汤米问。

“一个是黑兹尔，一个是埃塞尔。”爱丽丝说。黑兹尔和埃塞尔嫣然一笑。她们俩都不十分机灵。

“敢问你的芳名？”我问其中的一个金发女。

“弗朗西斯。”她说。

“弗朗西斯什么？”

“弗朗西斯·威尔逊。你问这干什么？”

“你的芳名呢？”我问另一位金发女子。

“得啦，别太放肆了。”对方说。

“他只不过想让大家交个朋友么。”那位调侃男说道，“难道你不想交朋友吗？”

“不想。”用化学剂染过头发的这位女子说，“不想跟你们交朋友。”

“简直就是个小辣椒。”调侃男说，“一个地地道道的小辣椒。”

这位金发女瞅了瞅另一位金发女，摇了摇头，口中骂了一句：“真是一群土包子。”

爱丽丝又哈哈大笑起来，笑得浑身发抖。

“没什么滑稽可笑的。”厨子说，“你们就知道笑，但没什么滑稽可笑的。你们这两个小伙子，准备到哪儿去呀？”

“你这是要到哪儿去？”汤姆反问道。

“我要去凯迪拉克(2)。”厨子说，“你们去过吗？我妹妹住在那里。”

“他本人也是个小妹妹哟。”裤子上沾有木屑的那个男子说。

“你能不能说话别这么阴阳怪气的？”厨子问，“大家就不能说些正经话吗？”

“凯迪拉克是史蒂夫·凯奇尔的老家，阿德·沃尔卡斯特(3)也是那儿的人。”那位腼腆的男子说。

“提起史蒂夫·凯奇尔，”其中的一个金发女提高嗓门说，就好像这个名字点着了她心里的一个火药桶似的，“他被杀死了，是他亲老子开枪打死的。天呀，虎毒都不会食子呀。像史蒂夫·凯奇尔这样的男人再也找不到了。”

“他的名字该不会叫斯坦利·凯奇尔(4)吧？”厨子问。

“得啦，你给我住口！”金发女说，“提起史蒂夫，你知道个什么呀？还说叫斯坦利呢！他不叫斯坦利！史蒂夫·凯奇尔是天底下最潇洒、最英俊的男子汉，是个天下无双的好男儿。他虎虎生威，风流倜傥，花钱极为豪爽。”

“你认识他吗？”那些男子当中的一位启口问道。

“认识他？问我是不是认识他？还问我是不是爱他吧？这是你要问的吧？我认识他，就跟你认识天下任何人；我爱他，就跟你爱上帝一样。史蒂夫·凯奇尔是最伟大、最潇洒、最白净、最英俊的男子汉，可是他的亲老子却开枪打死了他，像打死一条狗一样。”

“你和他一起到海边去过？”

“没有。在这之前我就认识他了。他是我唯一爱过的男人。”

这个用化学剂染过头的金发女说得绘声绘色，产生了舞台效应，令大家肃然起敬，而爱丽丝却又浑身抖了起来。我就坐在她身旁，感觉得到。

“你当时应该嫁给他呀。”厨子说。

“我不愿耽误了他的事业。”染过头的金发女说，“我不愿拖他的后腿呀。他所需要的不是老婆。哎，上帝，他是个多么了不起的人啊！”

“这样看待问题是很好的。”厨子说，“不过，杰克·约翰逊(5)还不是把他击倒了么？”

“那是搞阴谋诡计。”染过头的金发女说，“那个大个子黑人来了个突然袭击。当时他已经击倒了杰克·约翰逊，战胜了那个大个子黑杂种。可是那个黑杂种却搞偷袭，取得了胜利。”

说话间，售票窗的窗口打开了。那三个印第安人走了过去。

“是史蒂夫击倒了他。”金发女说，“史蒂夫还扭过头冲我笑呢。”

“记得你刚才说你没有去过海边呀。”旁边有人插话说。

“哦，为了那场比赛，我专门去了一趟。当时史蒂夫冲我笑，而那个黑杂种趁机一跃而起，出其不意地给了他一个冷拳。正面交锋，那样的黑杂种就是来上一百个，都可以被史蒂夫放翻。”

“他是个了不起的拳击手。”那个伐木工说。

“凭良心说，他的确如此。”金发女说，“凭良心说，如今再也没有那么出色的拳击手了。他就像个天神一样，那么白净、英俊，动作如行云流水，或者像一道闪电，虎虎生威。”

“我在拳击电影里看到过他。”汤姆说。

此时，大伙儿无不动容。爱丽丝又浑身发抖了，我偏头一看，却发现她在哭。那几个印第安人买了票，已经出了候车室到站台上去了。

“若论当丈夫，他比哪个丈夫都要强。”金发女说，“在上帝的眼里，我们已喜结良缘。我现在属于他，以后永远属于他。我整个人都是他的。对于我的肉体，我并不在乎，他们可以占有我的肉体，而我的灵魂却属于史蒂夫·凯奇尔一人。上帝啊，他是个真正的男子汉！”

大家都感到心里不是个滋味。此时的气氛有点伤感和尴尬。后来，仍在浑身颤抖的爱丽丝开了腔。“你睁着眼说瞎话。”她低着嗓门说，“你这一辈子从来就没有跟史蒂夫·凯奇尔睡过觉。这你自己清楚。”

“你怎么能这么说？”金发女带着几分傲岸之气说道。

“我这么说，因为这是事实。”爱丽丝说，“这里只有我一人认识史蒂夫·凯奇尔。我来自曼瑟洛纳，在那里我就认识他了。这是事实，人人都知道这是事实。如有半句瞎话，我就遭天打五雷轰。”

“如撒谎，我也愿遭天打五雷轰。”金发女说。

“我说的是事实，是铁的事实，这你应该是知道的，并非捏造出来的。我还记得他对我说的话来着。”

“他说什么？”金发女趾高气扬地问。

爱丽丝泣不成声，浑身发抖，话都快说不出来了。“他说：‘你是个小可爱，爱丽丝。’这是他的原话。”

“信口雌黄。”金发女傲气凌人地说。

“绝非信口雌黄，而是实话，是大实话。我可以对基督和圣母玛利亚发誓。”

“史蒂夫不可能说这话。那不是他说话的风格。”金发女高兴地说。

“这是事实。”爱丽丝以她那种好听的声音回了一句，“你相信不相信，反正对我都无所谓。”她不再哭了，心情平静了下来。

“史蒂夫说那话，可就成了天方夜谭了。”金发女不依不饶地说。

“他的确说了。”爱丽丝说完，脸上涌出了笑容，“当时的情景我还记着呢。我当时正如他说的那样，的确挺可爱的。就现在而言，我也比你强。看你干巴巴的，连点水分都没有。”

“不许你侮辱我，”金发女说道，“你这个大肉山。我对过去有自己的回忆。”

“得了吧。”爱丽丝以她那种甜蜜蜜、好听的声音说道，“除了你跟张三李四睡觉是真的，其他的回忆都是子虚乌有，都是你从报纸上看来的。我为人清正，这你心里有数。虽然我块头大，可是男人们都喜欢我。你知道得很清楚。我没说过半句瞎话，这你也清楚。”

“我的回忆就是我的回忆，”金发女说，“是真实的回忆，美好的回忆。”

爱丽丝看看她，再看看我们，脸上的那种受伤害的神情不见了，而是笑盈盈的，一张脸显得无比漂亮。她脸蛋漂亮，细皮嫩肉，声音悦耳，待人亲和，简直友好极了。不过，她的身躯太庞大了，大得能顶三个女人。汤姆见我盯着她瞧，便在一旁说了一声：“好啦，咱们走吧。”

“再见。”爱丽丝说，声音听上去的确像莺声燕语。

“再见。”我说。

“你们两位小伙子去哪儿呀？”厨子问。

“跟你走的不是一条路。”汤姆回话说。

————————————————————

(1) 汤姆的昵称。

(2) 美国密歇根州一城市。

(3) 美国拳击冠军。

(4) 美国拳击手。

(5) 美国黑人拳王。

愿诸位快乐，先生们

那些日子跟现在截然两样，差距很大。现在，那些山头被削平了，而当时山头上的尘土被风刮得满世界都是，把个堪萨斯城弄得和君士坦丁堡差不多了。有件事也许你不会相信，没人会相信的，然而却是真的。那天下午雪花飞舞，天黑得早，汽车商行的橱窗里亮着灯，陈列着一辆赛车，通体银色抛光，引擎盖上印有Dans Argent字样。我觉得这几个字母的意思是“银舞”或“银舞者”。它们究竟是什么意思，我心里还是有些拿不准的。不过，看见漂亮的赛车，我感到一阵高兴，并且对自己懂一门外语颇为得意。我踏雪前行。沃尔夫兄弟酒家每逢圣诞节和感恩节就提供免费火鸡大餐，我这是刚离开那儿，往市立医院走。那座医院位于高高的山丘上，俯瞰城里的万家炊烟、住房以及街道。医院的接待室里有两个救护医生——费希尔医生和威尔科克斯医生，一个坐在桌旁，一个坐在靠墙根的椅子上。

费希尔医生瘦瘦的，沙黄色头发，薄嘴唇，双眼含笑，有着两只赌徒的手。威尔科克斯医生矮矮的个子，肤色黝黑，手里拿着一本附有索引的书，书名是《青年医生之友和指南》，是百事通般的参考书，介绍各种症状和疗法。书里还附有对照索引，可以对照着参考本书诊断的症状。费希尔医生曾建议今后再版时应该再增加些对照索引，这样参考疗法时，可以同时了解疾病本身以及症状。按他的话说是为了“帮助记忆”。

威尔科克斯医生对这本书不太感兴趣，但离了它又寸步难行。此书是软皮革面的，适合于放入外套衣袋中。他是听了一位教授的建议才买下的。那位教授曾对他说：“威尔科克斯，你没有做医生的资格，我曾竭尽全力阻止你获得资格证。现在你既然成了这个需要学识的行业的一个成员，我从人道主义的立场出发建议你买一本《青年医生之友和指南》，照着里面的要求做。威尔科克斯医生，要学会用这本书。”

威尔科克斯医生没吱声，但他当天就把这本软皮革面的指南买来了。

“你好，贺拉斯。”我进接待室时，费希尔医生打了声招呼。接待室里真是五味俱杂，有纸烟味、三碘甲烷味、焦炭味，还有一种热得发烫的暖气片的味。

“先生们好。”我回了一句。

“市场上有什么新闻吗？”费希尔医生问。他说话拿腔拿调，带点夸张的气味，但我却觉得他温文尔雅的。

“沃尔夫兄弟酒家有免费火鸡大餐。”我回答说。

“你去吃啦？”

“大快朵颐。”

“咱们的同事有许多都去了吧？”

“全班人马。所有的人都去了。”

“圣诞节那种欢快的气氛很浓吧？”

“不太浓。”

“威尔科克斯医生在这里也算大快朵颐了哟。”费希尔医生说。威尔科克斯医生抬头望望他，然后又看看我。

“想喝一杯吗？”他问。

“不了。谢谢。”我说。

“那好吧。”威尔科克斯医生说。

“贺拉斯，”费希尔医生说道，“叫你贺拉斯，你不介意吧？”

“不介意。”

“贺拉斯老兄，出现了一个病例，简直有意思极了。”

“是这样的。”威尔科克斯医生说。

“你知道昨天到这来的那个小伙子吧？”

“哪一个？”

“就是想做阉割手术的那个。”

“知道。”他来的时候，我在场。那是个十六岁光景的小伙子，来时没戴帽子，情绪极为激动，一副害怕的样子，但却决心很大。他卷头发，虎背熊腰，双唇外凸。

“你看什么病，小伙子？”威尔科克斯医生当时问他。

“我想做阉割手术。”小伙子回答。

“为什么？”费希尔医生问。

“我做了祷告，什么措施都采取了，可就是不管用。”

“对什么事情不管用？”

“就是那种可怕的情欲。”

“什么可怕的情欲呀？”

“就是那种冲动，一种无法遏制的冲动。我一个劲儿祈祷，祈祷了一夜。”

“到底是怎么回事？”费希尔医生问。

小伙子一五一十把情况讲了。

“听我说，小伙子，”费希尔医生说道，“你一点毛病也没有，这种情况很正常，是无可指摘的。”

“这是可悲的，”小伙子说，“是一种罪恶，一种不洁行为，一种反天主和救世主的罪恶。”

“不对。”费希尔医生说，“这是一种自然现象，合乎人之常理，以后想起来你会觉得自己没做阉割是很幸运的。”

“哎，你是不明白。”小伙子说。

“还是听我的吧。”费希尔医生说。随后，他给小伙子介绍了一些常识。

“不，我不听。你别想让我信这些。”

“请你听我的劝告。”费希尔医生说。

“你是个十足的大傻瓜。”威尔科克斯医生对小伙子说道。

“那么，你们是不愿做了？”小伙子问道。

“做什么呀？”

“给我做阉割手术呗。”

“听着，”费希尔医生说道，“没有人会给你做这种手术的。你的身体一点毛病都没有。你的身体很棒，不要再胡思乱想了。如果你是个信徒，你所不满的其实并非罪恶现象，而是一种完成圣礼的途径罢了。”

“它说来就来，让我无法遏制。”小伙子说，“我不分日夜地祈祷都不管用。这是一种罪恶，挥之不去的罪恶，是不贞洁的。”

“行啦，得了吧……”威尔科克斯医生说道。

“你这样说话我可不愿听。”小伙子不卑不亢地对威尔科克斯医生说。接着，他又央求费希尔医生道：“你能不能把手术做了？”

“不行。”费希尔医生说道，“我已经告诉过你了，小伙子。”

“让他从这里出去。”威尔科克斯医生说道。

“我会出去的。”小伙子说，“你别碰我，我会出去的。”

以上的情况出现在昨天五点钟左右。

“后来怎么样啦？”我问。

“今天凌晨一点钟，”费希尔医生说，“我们收治了一个用剃刀自残的青年。”

“是给自己做阉割？”

“不是阉割。”费希尔医生说，“他就不懂阉割是怎么回事。”

“他也许会因此送命的。”威尔科克斯医生说。

“怎么送命？”

“因为失血呗。”

“这位优秀的医生——威尔科克斯医生，我的同事，当时接诊，却在这本指南里找不到应急措施。”

“去你的吧，乱讲个啥劲。”威尔科克斯医生说。

“我的医生，我说此话并无恶意。”费希尔医生说道，一边看了看自己的两只手——由于乐意为人效力，又无视联邦法律，这双手老是给他找麻烦。“贺拉斯在此可以做证，我说此话并无恶意。那个年轻人做的是切割手术，贺拉斯。”

“好啦，希望你不要再挖苦我了。”威尔科克斯医生说。“何必要挖苦人呢。”

“挖苦你，医生？在咱们救世主的诞辰这么一个日子挖苦你？”

“咱们的救世主？你不是个犹太人么？”威尔科克斯医生说。

“我是犹太人，我是犹太人。我老忘记这一点，还是重视不够吧。谢谢你的好心提醒。是你们的救世主。这就对了。是你们的救世主，毫无疑问是你们的救世主。在棕枝主日(1)也是不行的。”

“你也太聪明了吧。”威尔科克斯医生说。

“这个诊断妙极了，医生。我的确太聪明了些。在这个区域当然显得太聪明了些。你可要引以为戒，贺拉斯。你并无意出人头地，但有时可见端倪。那个诊断真够神的——而且没有参考指南。”

“下地狱去吧。”威尔科克斯医生说。

“时候到了我会去的。”费希尔医生说。“时候到了我会去的。假如有这样的地方，我肯定会去的。我甚至还往那儿看过一眼呢，只不过是匆匆一窥罢了。看过之后，我急忙将目光移开了。贺拉斯，这位优秀的医生收治那个年轻人时，你知道那个年轻人说什么来着？他说：‘哼，我曾求过你们做这个手术，不知求了多少次了。’”

“而且是在圣诞日苦苦央求来着。”威尔科克斯医生说。

“至于什么特殊的日子并不重要。”费希尔医生说。

“也许对你来说不重要。”威尔科克斯医生说。

“听见了吧，贺拉斯？”费希尔医生说道。“听见了吧？这位医生发现了我的软肋，即所谓的‘阿喀琉斯脚踵(2)’，于是便乘胜追击。”

“你也太聪明了吧。”威尔科克斯医生说。

————————————————————

(1) 复活节前的星期日。

(2) 阿喀琉斯：希腊神话里的勇士，出生后其母握其脚踵倒提着在冥河水中浸过，因此除未浸过的脚踵之外，浑身刀枪不入。

你们决不愿这样

洼地公路和那片农房的机枪扫射曾阻住了部队的进攻，但他们最终还是穿过田野进了小镇。小镇上没有遇到抵抗，他们又一路打到了河边。尼古拉斯·亚当斯骑自行车走在路上，遇见路面太坑洼，就下车推着走。只见尸横遍野，他猜得到战况是多么惨烈。

那些尸体横七竖八躺在田野上的荒草中或者路面上，口袋翻出，苍蝇乱飞，无论是零星尸体还是堆放着的尸体，旁边纸片狼藉。

路旁的草地上和庄稼地里，以及道路的一些路面上，七零八碎地乱扔着军用物资，其中有：一台行军灶（一定是战况好的时候随军用的）；许多带有小牛皮盖的粗帆布背包、手榴弹、钢盔、步枪（有的步枪枪托朝天，刺刀倒插在泥土里，据此判断此处最后还大力挖战壕呢）；除了手榴弹、钢盔、步枪，还有挖战壕用的工具、弹药箱、信号枪以及散落一地的信号弹，另外也可见药品箱、防毒面具、装防毒面具用的空筒、一挺躺在那儿的三脚架机枪和一堆空弹壳、从弹药箱里露出来的装得满满的子弹夹、侧翻了的冷却水空桶；机枪的枪栓不见了，几个机枪手东倒西歪地横尸于旁边，周围的草地上跟他处一样也纸片狼藉。

乱纸堆里有几本祈祷书和几张合影照片，照片上的人正是这几位机枪手，站得整整齐齐，满面红光，兴高采烈，就像是一张大学年刊刊用的校足球队的合影。眼下，他们歪七扭八横尸于荒草地，尸体已有些发胀。乱纸堆里还有一些印有宣传画的明信片，上面画着一个身穿奥地利军服的士兵正把一个女子压倒在床上；该宣传画采用的是印象派技法，画面极为生动，只是与通常的强奸状况不符，因为施暴者通常要将女子的裙子撩起蒙在她的脸上，让她喊不出声来，有时会有帮衬者骑在女子的头上。这种带有教唆味道的明信片到处可见，显然是进攻之前发给士兵们的。现在，它们与淫秽明信片及照片一道散落在战场上。此外，还可见乡下照相馆为农村姑娘拍的小照片，有时还能看到几张小孩的照片，再下来就是家信了，一封封的到处都是。打仗时，凡是有尸体的地方必定纸片狼藉，这次进攻战的战场上也不例外。

对于这些刚刚阵亡的将士，活着的人漠不关心，只关心他们衣袋里的东西。尼克(1)注意到，我方阵亡人数（他一直将这支军队视为我军）少得让人感到意外。死者的衣服也被撕开，衣袋被掏空。根据他们躺着的姿势，可以判断出进攻部队采用的是什么方式和战术。由于天气太热，死者不分国籍，都有些发胀。

显然，奥地利军在洼地公路那儿设有防线，对小镇进行防御，一直坚持到了最后，退回小镇的人寥寥无几，或者说无一生还。小镇的街道上只有三具尸体，看来是逃跑时被打死的。一幢幢的房屋毁于炮火，街上到处是破碎的水泥块和砖瓦，处处可见残梁断壁及炮弹坑（有些弹坑的边缘被芥子气熏得发黄）。碎弹片遍及四处，瓦砾堆里散落着大大小小的弹壳。镇上空无一人。

自从离开福纳西，尼克·亚当斯在路上连个人影也没看到过。不过，沿着公路骑行，穿过郁郁葱葱的田野，倒是可以在路的左侧瞧见一些大炮藏在用桑叶编织的伪装网之下——他是发现太阳把金属的炮身照得发烫，因而伪装网的上方升腾起热浪，才注意到那些大炮的。此刻从镇上走过，见小镇已成了空城，不禁感到有些意外。镇外的河岸旁，就是那条洼地公路。出了镇，有一片光秃秃的空地，那条路从空地顺坡而下，放眼望去，可以看见平静的河面以及对岸弧形的矮堤，还可以看到奥地利军队挖战壕挖出来的泥土——那些泥土已被太阳晒得发白。久别故地，只见眼前一片青翠，绿意盎然，历史的车轮从这儿碾过，并没有使这儿发生变化，低地的河流依然在潺潺流淌。

部队的防线沿河岸一字排开，向左侧延伸。堤岸的顶上挖了些掩体，掩体里有几个士兵。尼克注意到阵地上架着机关枪，信号火箭放在架子上处于待发状态。堤岸侧腰上的掩体里也有士兵，都在呼呼大睡。没有人询问他。他放开步子前行，沿着土堤走，转了个弯。就在这时，一个年轻的少尉闪了出来，一脸的胡茬，眼里布满了血丝，眼皮红肿，把手枪的枪口对准了他。

“你是什么人？”

尼克介绍了自己的身份。

“我怎么知道呢？”

尼克出示了通行证，上面有他的照片、姓名以及第三军的印章。

少尉将证件抓在手里说：“把这个留在我这里吧。”

“这恐怕不行。”尼克说，“把证件还给我，收起你的枪。好啦，把枪放回枪套里去。”

“我怎么知道你是什么人呢？”

“证件上都写着呢。”

“万一证件是伪造的呢？这个证得留在我这里。”

“请别开玩笑了，”尼克笑盈盈地说，“还是带我去见你们的连长吧。”

“我得带你到营部里去。”

“那好吧。”尼克说，“问一声，你认识不认识帕拉维西尼上尉？高高的个子，留着小胡子。他曾经是建筑师，会说英语。”

“你跟他熟？”

“有点熟。”

“他指挥的是哪个连？”

“第二连。”

“现在他指挥一个营了。”

“太好了。”尼克说。一听说帕拉(2)安然无恙，他心里的一块石头落了地。“那就到营部里去吧。”

尼克走出小镇时，曾有三颗榴霰弹在一幢被炸毁了的房屋的右上方爆炸，那以后就再也没有了炮击。可是这位少尉哭丧着脸，好像饱受炮击之苦似的。他说话的声音也显得很紧张，听上去有点不自然。他持枪在手，叫尼克觉得心里不安。

“把枪收起来吧。”他说，“跟敌人隔着一条河呢。”

“万一你是个奸细，我会一枪毙了你的。”少尉说道。

“得了吧。”尼克说，“咱们到营部再理论吧。”这个军官让他的一颗心老是悬着。

营部设在防空洞里，代理营长帕拉维西尼上尉坐在办公桌后，比以前瘦了些，英国味也更浓了些。尼克冲他敬礼，他起身迎迓。

“你好呀！”他说道，“都认不出你来了。穿这身军装干什么？”

“是他们叫我穿的。”

“见到你非常高兴，尼古拉(3)。”

“是呀。你的气色很好。战况如何？”

“我们发动了一次非常漂亮的进攻。简直漂亮极了。让我来给你讲一讲吧。你瞧！”

他指着作战图，介绍了那场进攻战的战况。

“我是从福纳西过来的，”尼克说，“一路可以看得清当时的战况。这一仗打得的确很精彩。”

“不是一般的精彩，简直精彩极了。你的关系现在挂靠在团部吗？”

“不是的。我的任务是到处游走，让他们看看这身军装。”

“真是咄咄怪事。”

“他们看见这身美国军装，就一定会想到大批的美国兵在源源不断赶来。”

“他们怎么知道这是美国军装呢。”

“你做做宣传呗。”

“啊，是的，我明白了。我派个下士给你带路，陪你视察前线。”

“都快成了个肮脏的政客了。”尼克说。

“你穿便装，才更招眼呢。在这儿，那才叫与众不同呢。”

“再戴一顶卷边毡帽哟。”尼克说。

“或者戴一顶毛茸茸的软呢帽。”

“按说，我的口袋里应该塞满香烟、明信片之类的东西。”尼克说，“还应该有满满一口袋巧克力。我应该把这些东西分发给士兵们，外加一句亲切的话语，同时友好地拍拍他们的脊背。可惜我既无香烟和明信片，也无巧克力。于是他们就会说我的视察是摆谱。”

“我觉得你露露面对部队就是莫大的鼓舞。”

“劝你别这么想。”尼克说，“我心里觉得挺不是滋味的。按道理，我应该给你带来一瓶白兰地才对。”

“没什么道理可按的。”帕拉说完，笑了笑。这一笑，露出了他的满口黄牙，这之前他并未笑过。“这话说得十分入耳。来杯格拉巴酒(4)怎么样？”

“不了。谢谢。”尼克说。

“这酒一点乙醚也不含。”

“直到现在，我的嘴里还有那种味道呢。”尼克突然忆及往事，当时的情景历历在目。

“那次搭乘卡车返回营地，要是不听你说胡话，我根本还不知道你喝醉了呢。”

“每次进攻之前，我都要醉他一通。”尼克说。

“我就不行。”帕拉说，“第一次冲锋之前我倒是喝过一次痛快酒。那可是我参加的第一场战斗！喝了酒反倒让我情绪极为低落，后来又渴得要命。”

“你不需要酒壮胆。”

“你冲锋打仗，比我要勇敢多了。”

“过奖了。”尼克说，“我知道自己的斤两，所以老靠酒壮胆。我觉得这没什么丢人的。”

“以前可没见你喝醉过。”

“真的？”尼克说，“一次也没见过？那一次呢？就是咱们一道乘车从梅斯特雷到格兰德港去的那天夜里。当时我想睡觉，便醉醺醺地将自行车当成了毯子，竟然拉过来盖在了身上。”

“那又不是在前线。”

“我怎么样，咱们就不谈了。”尼克说，“我是个什么样的人，我自己最清楚，此时不愿再多想了。”

“你可以在这儿先休息一下。”帕拉维西尼说，“想睡就睡一会儿。炮弹是落不到这儿来的。反正天气正热，是出不去的。”

“我看也不用鬼吹火似的赶。”

“你到底怎么样？”

“很好。一切都很好。”

“算啦。我问的是真话。”

“一点问题都没有。只是睡觉时没有灯光就睡不着。就这么一点小毛病。”

“我早就说过应该做个手术。我虽然不是医生，但这种症状我是知道的。”

“哦，他们认为最好还是让它慢慢吸收。反正就是这么回事了。怎么啦？你是不是觉得我不正常？”

“你看上去正常极了。”

“你如果被诊断为不正常，麻烦可就大了。”尼克说，“那时，没有人会信任你了。”

“我要是你，就睡上一会儿，尼古拉。”帕拉维西尼说，“在这个营部里，情况跟以前是不一样的。我们原地待命，时刻准备开拔。这大热天不能出去——那是犯傻。劝你在那个铺上睡一会儿吧。”

“那我就躺一躺吧。”尼克说。

他在铺上躺了下来。他心绪不宁，这叫他很失望，最叫他失望的是，他的心事让帕拉维西尼一眼就看了出来。这个防空洞不如以前的那个大。在以前的那个防空洞里隐蔽着一个排的士兵，全都是1899年出生的新兵，都是刚上前线，冲锋前一有炮弹落下就叽里哇啦乱叫。帕拉当时让他带新兵出洞锻炼胆量，每次带两个。他自己也害怕，便将钢盔的细带紧紧勒在嘴上，不让嘴唇打哆嗦。新兵们歇斯底里地发作，也是身不由己呀。都知道新兵怕打炮么。如果他们叽里哇啦乱叫，就兜头揍他们一拳，令他们不再胡思乱想。要不然就来个杀鸡给猴看，枪毙他一个。不过，此时以儆效尤恐怕太晚了，情况可能会更糟的。揍他们一拳就行了。进攻的时间提前到了五点二十分，只剩下四分钟了。对待那些窝囊废，揍他们几拳、踢他们几脚就是了。这能让他们克服恐惧？假如还不管用，就枪毙两个，把其余的都赶出去冲锋。中士呀，你可要在后边压阵。你打头阵，后边却无人跟上，那样作战是不行的。你冲锋，也得带着他们一道冲。管什么枪林弹雨！对，就这么行动！你可以看看表，然后以平静的语气，以一丝不乱的平静语气说：“出发！”这次，他没有喝酒，没时间找酒喝。防空洞的一头彻底坍塌了，于是就找不到酒了。正因为没喝酒，他才能够督战。大家冲上了山坡——这是他唯一的一次没喝醉酒便上了战场。返回时，他们发现索道房被大火烧毁了。四天之后，一些伤员撤下了山，还有些没有撤下来。战斗成了拉锯战，攻一攻，守一守，最后全都撤了下来。戈比·德里斯的样子太怪了，满身羽毛。一年前你曾把我叫作芭比娃娃，说很高兴和我认识，有羽毛也罢，没有羽毛也好。戈比可真是好样的。我的名字叫哈里·皮尔瑟。每次攀爬陡峭的山坡，我们都会掉队，远远落在后边。夜夜他在梦中都会看到那座山，梦见圣心堂(5)，白白的，像吹起来的肥皂泡沫。有时他和女友一道去圣心堂，有的时候女友却陪别的人一起去，这叫他困惑不解。女友不在跟前的那些夜晚，河水泛滥，河面格外的宽、格外的平缓；步出福萨尔塔(6)，可见一座低矮的房屋，房屋用油漆漆成了黄色，四面杨柳婆娑，旁边有一个低矮的马棚，附近运河流淌。这地方他来了都有一千次了，却从未发现有这么一座房屋。现在则每一夜都看得到它，跟那座山一样清清楚楚，不过他每次见了都有些害怕。这房屋的意义似乎无比深刻，他每天夜里都能梦见。他渴望见到这房屋，可是见了又害怕。特别是运河上的树影里静静地停泊着一条小船，而河岸变了样，这些就更叫他害怕了。运河的河岸低极了，和格兰德港那儿的一样。记得在格兰德港时，眼见得士兵们涉过泛滥的河水，手里高举着枪，后来连人带枪淹没在了水里。那是谁下的命令来着？要不是心里乱成了一团麻，他是可以想起来的。正因为如此，他才关心细节，让事情脉络清晰，免得迷失方向。可是，怎么就突然无缘无故地糊涂了起来？此刻，他躺在营部的一张铺上；营长是帕拉；他身穿倒霉的美国军装。他坐起身，举目四看，见大家都在盯着他瞧，而帕拉出了门，于是便又躺了下来。

巴黎的那段经历发生在早一些时间，他对此从未有过任何忧虑。他只是为跟别人跑了的女友担心过，害怕他们又遇到先前的那个汽车司机。要说忧虑，就这一点了。至于前线的那点事，他从不为之提心吊胆。他现在做梦，再不会梦见前线的事情了，真叫他害怕，而且梦中无法摆脱的是那幢狭长的黄颜色房子和宽得离奇的河面。眼下，他旧地重游，又来到了河边，又从小镇走过，却没有看见那幢房屋。眼前的河流也跟梦中的大不相同。那么，他夜夜梦中游历的是什么样的地方，遇见的是什么样的危险呢？为什么醒来会冷汗淋漓，对于一幢房屋、一个狭长的马房和一条运河的恐惧，甚至会甚于狂轰滥炸呢？

他一个鲤鱼打挺坐起身，小心地将两条腿从铺上放到地面。两条腿每次伸直的时候，时间一长，就会变得僵硬。那个副官、信号兵以及两个站在门口处的传令兵都在直着眼看他，他也回敬了他们几眼，然后将蒙着布罩的钢盔戴在了头上。

“可惜身上没带巧克力、明信片和香烟，”他说，“只是穿了这身军装来。”

“营长马上就回来。”副官说。在这支军队里，副官并非委任的军衔。

“这套军装不太合身，”尼克说道，“不过，它让大家知道：几百万美国大军马上就要开过来了。”

“你认为他们会把美国人派到这儿来？”副官问。

“哦，这是一定的了。美国兵个个膀大腰圆，块头比我大一倍，身体健康、心地纯洁，夜里睡得香，刀枪不入，不畏炮弹，从不龟缩在洞里，天不怕地不怕，不酗酒，对于留在国内的女友忠心耿耿，多数身上不生虱子，全都是好样的。你们见到就知道了。”

“你是意大利人吧？”副官问。

“不是。我是美国人。你瞧这身军装就知道了，斯帕尼奥利尼公司生产的，只不过不太合身。”

“你是北美人还是南美人(7)？”

“是北美人。”尼克说。他觉得怒从心头起，硬把怒气压了下去。

“可是你说的是意大利语呀。”

“意大利语怎么啦？我说意大利语，难道你不愿意？我就没有权利说意大利语吗？”

“你连意大利的勋章都拿到手了。”

“只是一些绶带和证书罢了。勋章过后补发。勋章是作为纪念的，是作为离别时的奖励，往往会随行李一道失落的。丢了，就到米兰去买几枚。重要的是那些证书。你可不要感到不高兴。你在前线待久了，也会获得这些玩意儿的。”

“按说，我是个老兵了，参加过厄立特里亚(8)战役，”副官语气生硬地说，“还在的黎波里(9)打过仗。”

“和你认识真是莫大的荣幸。”尼克伸出手说，“那些日子一定非常艰苦了。我看到你也有绶带的。顺便问一声，你参加过卡尔索战役吗？”

“那次战役，我年龄太大，不能冲锋陷阵了。这次战争，也是硬把我召来的。”

“我也曾经服过役，打过仗，”尼克说，“如今已解甲归田了。”

“那你为什么还来这儿？”

“演演戏，展示一下美国军装。”尼克说，“你不觉得这样做意义非凡吗？穿在身上领口虽说有点紧，但你很快就会看到几百万美国兵穿着同样的军装蜂拥而至，多得像蝗虫一样。你知道有种虫，我们美国人称其为蚱蜢，其实就是一种蝗虫。真正的蚱蜢个头小，是绿颜色的，气力要弱一些。你可不要把蝗虫和知了弄混了。知了会发一种很特殊的、长长的叫声。它们是怎么叫的来着？一时想不起来了。再怎么想也想不起来了。那叫声仿佛响在耳旁，却又顿然消失。对不起，话说多了，容我歇口气好吗？”

“你去把营长找来！”副官对其中的一个传令兵说道，“看得出你曾经负过伤。”他转过身来对尼克说。

“多处挂彩。”尼克说，“如果你对伤疤感兴趣，我身上倒是有些值得一看。不过，我倒是愿意谈谈蚱蜢。我们称其为蚱蜢，其实就是蝗虫。这种昆虫在我的生活中曾经扮演过十分重要的角色呢。这个你很可能会感兴趣的。你不妨一边听我讲给你听，一边看着这套军装。”

副官摆了摆手，另一个传令兵也出去了。

“你把这身军装可看好啦，是斯帕尼奥利尼公司产的。你们也可以过来看看。”尼克对那几个信号兵说，“其实我并没有军衔，而是在美国领事馆管制下工作。要看，尽管看好了。如果愿意，也可以盯着看。接下来，听我讲讲美国的蝗虫吧。我们一向比较喜欢的是那种所谓‘中褐色’的蝗虫。它们浸在水里很长时间都不会腐烂，鱼儿爱吃。还有一种蝗虫个头大一些，飞的时候发出嘎啦嘎啦的声音，有点像响尾蛇发出的那种声音，听上去干巴巴的。它们的翅膀色彩鲜艳，有的是红艳艳的，有的则是黄底黑条的，但它们的翅膀一遇水就烂掉，当鱼饵用糟透了。中褐色的蝗虫则不然，它们丰满、结实、肉质鲜美，这可是难得一见的好鱼饵，我强力推荐给你们几位先生。不过，我必须提醒一下，如果用手去抓或者用网拍去扑，那你怎么忙活，捉到的虫子也不够你一天钓鱼用的。那纯粹是愚蠢的举动，完全是浪费时间。我要再次提醒诸位先生，那样的捕捉法会得不偿失的。正确的方法是使用围网，或者使用拿普通蚊帐制成的网。要让我提建议（说不定我哪天真会提这种建议呢），我会说：上轻武器课时，应该向年轻军官传授这种技法。两个军官将网张开，对角拉紧，或者说一人扯一头吧，躬下腰，一手拽住网的下端，另一只手拽住网的上端，逆风跑起来。蚱蜢是顺风飞的，于是迎面撞在网上，这就被网住了。这样子，不费吹灰之力就能捕捉到一大堆蚱蜢。依我所见，所有的军官都应该随身带上一块蚊帐纱布，随时可以制成网捕捉蚱蜢。但愿我把话说清楚了，先生们。有问题吗？这门课如果有不懂之处，请尽管提问。把问题提出来好啦。没问题吗？那我就说几句结束语吧。我想引用伟大的战士和绅士亨利·威尔逊爵士的一句话：要么统治别人，要么被统治。请允许我再重复一遍。先生们，这一点我敦请诸位务必记住。离开此处之后，也务必牢记在心里：要么统治别人，要么被统治。我的话完了，先生们，再见！”

他把蒙着布罩的钢盔从头上拿下，然后再戴上，一弯腰从防空洞的矮门里走了出去。只见帕拉在那两个传令兵的陪同下正沿着洼地公路走过来。艳阳热如火炙，尼克摘下了钢盔。

“应该有套设备给这些东西浇点水。”他自言自语道，“我还是拿到河水里弄湿吧。”随后，他抬腿向河的堤岸上爬去。

“尼古拉！”帕拉维西尼喊道，“尼古拉！你这是到哪儿去？”

“其实我也没必要非得弄湿。”尼克又自言自语了一句，从坡上走了下来，手里拎着钢盔，“不管是湿的还是干的，戴在头上都是个累赘。你老戴着钢盔吗？”

“老戴着呢。”帕拉说，“把头都磨秃了。进去吧。”

进了防空洞，帕拉让他坐下。

“戴这东西屁用都不顶。”尼克说，“记得初次戴的时候，对心里到是一种安慰，后来却经常见戴着钢盔照样被打得脑袋开花。”

“尼古拉，”帕拉说道，“我认为你应该回国去。没有物资供应，最好别来前线。这里没有你做的事情。就算你有东西发给大家，四处乱走，引得大家聚在一起，会招来炮弹的。我可不愿发生这样的事情。”

“我也知道来此处并非明智之举。”尼克说，“这不是我的主意。听说旅部驻扎在此地，于是我就想来这儿能见到你或者别的什么熟人。我本来是可以去曾宗或圣多纳的。我很想重返圣多纳，再看看那座桥。”

“我是不想让你漫无目的地在这儿瞎转悠罢了。”帕拉维西尼上尉说。

“那好吧。”尼克支吾了一声。他觉得怒气又在从心头升起。

“这你理解不理解？”

“当然理解。”尼克说。他强忍住心里的怒气。

“这一类的活动应该在夜间进行。”

“自然喽。”尼克说道。他觉得自己已到了忍无可忍的地步。

“你知道，我指挥着一个营的人马。”帕拉说。

“这有什么呢？”尼克说着，怒从心头起，“你读得懂文件，写得了命令，这有什么难的呢？”

“不错。”帕拉温和地说。

“你的症结在于现在指挥了一个缩编的营。他们一旦恢复了元气，就会叫你回去继续当你的连长的。那些阵亡的人，为什么不掩埋呢？我都看见了，恐怕回过头还会看见。愿意什么时候埋就什么时候埋吧，反正也不关我的事，都是为了你们好。要不然，你们会染上瘟疫的。”

“你把自行车放在哪儿了？”

“在镇边一幢房屋的屋里。”

“放在那里不会有什么问题吧？”

“别担心，”尼克说，“我马上就走。”

“再躺一会儿吧，尼古拉。”

“好吧。”

他合上了眼睛。这次出现在眼前的不再是那个大胡子眯着眼用步枪的准星瞄准他，一脸镇静地时刻准备扣动扳机，而是一道白光闪过，像有一记闷棍砸在了他的膝盖上，一股火辣辣、甜丝丝的东西呛在喉咙里，呛得他一口吐在了石头上；与此同时，部队从身边开过，他看见了那幢狭长的黄房子、低矮的马棚和那条河面极其宽、水流异常平缓的大河。“基督呀，”他叫了一声，“我还是走了吧。”

他忽地站了起来。

“我该走了，帕拉。”他说，“我今天下午就骑车回去。如果有了物资，我就连夜送来。拿不到物资，我哪天夜里还是要来的，顺便带些礼品来。”

“现在走，天还是太热。”帕拉维西尼上尉说。

“你不必担心。”尼克说，“这工夫没事了。刚才有点难受，不过不太严重。现在好多了。我心里清楚，只要说话一多，就会出现这种情况。”

“我派个传令兵送送你。”

“我看就不必了。我认识路的。”

“你很快还要再来的吧？”

“一定的。”

“还是让我派个……”

“不必了。”尼克说，“算是信任我的一种表示吧。”

“好吧，那就再见了。”

“再见。”尼克说。然后，他迈步走上洼地公路，朝着放自行车的地方前行。过了运河，下午时分的公路上浓荫覆盖。再往前走，路两边绿树成行，丝毫没有受到炮弹的轰击。一次在那段公路上行军，与萨伏伊第三骑兵团擦肩而过，但见骑兵们踏雪飞驰，战马喷出的气在寒冷的空气中如缕缕白烟。错了，这恐怕是别的哪个地方的情景吧。究竟是哪个地方呢？

“算啦，我还是赶快去找回我的自行车吧。”尼克自言自语道，“可别迷了路，到不了福纳西了。”

————————————————————

(1) 尼古拉斯的简称。

(2) 帕拉维西尼的昵称。

(3) 尼古拉斯的昵称。

(4) 用酒渣酿制的白兰地。

(5) 圣心大教堂，白颜色，位于巴黎的蒙马特高地。

(6) 意大利一城市。

(7) American一词既有“美国人”的意思，也有“美洲人”的意思。

(8) 非洲国家。

(9) 利比亚首都。

向瑞士致敬

第一部
惠勒先生在蒙特勒留下的影像

车站咖啡店里温暖而明亮。木桌的桌面擦得铮亮，桌上的食品篮里放着椒盐卷饼，而卷饼装在抛光纸纸袋里。椅子是雕花的，虽旧却舒适。墙上有一个雕花木钟，吧台设在大堂的尽端。窗外雪花飘舞。

木钟下方的桌旁坐着两个车站的搬运工，正在喝新酿的酒。又有一个搬运工进来说辛普伦开来的东方快车在圣莫里斯晚点一个小时。他说完就出去了。咖啡店的女服务员听了，走到了惠勒先生的桌旁。

“列车晚点一个小时，先生，”她说，“给你来杯咖啡吧？”

“如果你觉得咖啡不会让我睡不着觉就可以。”

“来一杯好吗？”女服务员又问了一声。

“那就来一杯吧。”惠勒先生说。

“谢谢。”

服务员去厨房端来了一杯咖啡。惠勒先生眺望窗外，看着雪花在车站站台的灯光下漫天飞舞。

“除了英语，你还会说别的语言吗？”他问女服务员。

“哦，会的，先生。我还会说德语、法语和地方方言。”

“你想喝点什么吗？”

“哦，不了，先生。店里是不允许陪客人喝酒水的。”

“抽支雪茄怎么样？”

“哦，不抽了，先生。我不会抽烟，先生。”

“那好吧。”惠勒先生说。他又望了一眼窗外，喝口咖啡，点上了一根烟。

“小姐(1)！”他叫了一声。女服务员闻声走了过来。

“你需要什么，先生？”

“要你。”他说。

“你不该和我开这种玩笑。”

“不是开玩笑。”

“这种话你是不该说的。”

“我没时间绕弯子，”惠勒先生说，“火车四十分钟就进站了。如果你陪我上楼，我就给你一百法郎。”

“你不该说这种话，先生。我去叫那个搬运工过来跟你说话吧。”

“我不需要搬运工，”惠勒先生说，“不需要警察，也不需要卖香烟的杂役。我需要的是你。”

“再这样说话，就请你出去。不允许你留在这儿，说这样的话。”

“那你为什么不走开呀！你一走开，我就跟你说不成这种话了。”

女服务员转身走了。惠勒先生盯着她，看她是不是会去找搬运工。她没有去。

“小姐(2)！”他叫了一声。女服务员走了过来。“给我拿一瓶西昂酒来。”

“好的，先生。”

惠勒先生目送着她出去，看着她把酒拿来，走到了他的桌子跟前。这时，他望了一眼木钟。

“我会给你两百法郎的。”他说道。

“请你别说这种话。”

“两百法郎可是一大笔钱呀。”

“不许你说这种话！”女服务员说道。她的英语越说越蹩脚。惠勒先生饶有兴趣地打量着她。

“给你两百法郎。”

“你真讨厌。”

“那你为什么不走开？你不在跟前，我就不能和你说这种话了。”

女服务员走了，到吧台那儿去了。惠勒先生喝着酒，暗自笑了一阵子。

“小姐(3)！”他叫了一声。女服务员假装没听见。“小姐！(4)”他又叫了一声。女服务员走了过来。

“你想要什么？”

“要你，很想要。我给你三百法郎。”

“你真讨厌。”

“给你三百瑞士法郎。”

她转身走掉了。惠勒先生望着她的背影。一个搬运工推开了门，他是负责为惠勒先生拿行李的。

“火车来了，先生。”他用法语说道。惠勒先生站了起来。

“小姐(5)！”他叫了一声。女服务员走了过来。“酒钱是多少？”

“七法郎。”

惠勒先生数了八法郎，放在了桌子上，穿上外套，随搬运工走向站台——那儿大雪纷飞，满地琼花。

“再见，小姐。(6)”他说。

女服务员望着他离去，心想：“这人真坏，讨厌死啦。那种事本来就不花钱的，他偏要给三百法郎。我不知做了有多少次了，分文都不取的。店里是没有地方干那种事的。他要是有脑子，就该知道这儿没地方。竟要花三百法郎！这些美国人真是摆阔气。”

惠勒先生站在水泥站台上自己的行李旁，顺着铁轨望去，但见火车亮着大灯穿过风雪开进站来。他盘算着，觉得自己消费一场，真是划算得很，除了饭钱，实际上只花掉了一瓶七法郎的酒钱和一法郎的小费。要是给七十五生丁(7)的小费就更好了。当时要是给七十五生丁的小费，他现在的感觉会更好的。一个瑞士法郎值五个法国法郎呢。他现在要去的地方是巴黎。他在钱的方面精打细算，对女人毫无兴趣。这个车站他以前来过，知道咖啡店里并无“楼上”可去。有风险的事，他从来都不会做的。

第二部
约翰逊先生在沃韦吐露了心事

车站咖啡店里温暖而明亮。桌子擦得铮亮，有几张桌子上铺着红白格子桌布。所有的桌子上都有食品篮，篮里放着椒盐卷饼，而卷饼装在抛光纸纸袋里。椅子是雕花的，虽旧却舒适。墙上有一个挂钟，镀锌的吧台设在大堂的尽端。窗外雪花飘舞。挂钟下方的桌旁坐着两个车站的搬运工，正在喝新酿的酒。

又有一个搬运工进来说辛普伦开来的东方快车在圣莫里斯晚点一个小时。他说完就出去了。咖啡店的女服务员听了，走到了约翰逊先生的桌旁。

“列车晚点一个小时，先生，”她说，“给你来杯咖啡吧？”

“如果不太麻烦就行。”

“来一杯好吗？”女服务员又问了一声。

“那就来一杯吧。”

“谢谢。”

服务员去厨房端来了一杯咖啡。约翰逊先生眺望窗外，看着雪花在车站站台的灯光下漫天飞舞。

“除了英语，你还会说别的语言吗？”他问女服务员。

“哦，会的，先生。我还会说德语、法语和地方方言。”

“你想喝点什么吗？”

“哦，不了，先生。店里是不允许陪客人喝酒水的。”

“抽支雪茄怎么样？”

“哦，不，先生。”她哈哈一笑说，“我不会抽烟，先生。”

“我也不会抽，”约翰逊说，“抽烟是个坏毛病。”

可是女服务员一走，约翰逊就点了支烟，喝了口咖啡。墙上的挂钟是差一刻十点钟。他的表走得有点快。火车应该十点半抵达——晚点一个小时意味着十一点半抵达。

“小姐(8)！”

“你需要什么，先生？”

“你愿不愿陪我玩玩？”约翰逊问。女服务员飞红了脸。

“不，先生。”

“我不是指那种胡来的事情。你愿不愿做个伴，看一看沃韦的夜生活？如果愿意，可以带上你的闺蜜一起去。”

“我得工作呢，”女服务员说，“现在我当班。”

“这我知道。”约翰逊说，“你就不能找个人替班吗！内战时期，这种现象是常有的。”

“哦，不行，先生。我本人得亲自在这儿值班。”

“你的英语是在哪儿学的？”

“在贝立兹学校，先生。”

“讲给我听听。”约翰逊说，“贝立兹的学生是不是都很野？她们是不是喜欢搂脖子亲嘴？是不是那儿有许多讨女人欢心的家伙？你碰见过斯科特·菲茨杰拉德(9)没有？”

“请问你说什么来着？”

“我是说大学的那些日子是你一生中最幸福的时光了吧？去年秋天有什么球队到贝立兹去过吧？”

“你是在开玩笑吧，先生？”

“只是个小小的玩笑罢了。”约翰逊说，“你是个相当不错的女孩子。你不愿陪我玩吗？”

“哦，不行，先生。”女服务员说，“想让我给你拿点什么吗？”

“好吧。”约翰逊说，“能把酒单拿给我吗？”

“好的，先生。”

约翰逊拿上酒单，朝着三个搬运工坐的那张桌子走去。那几个都是老人，抬头望着他。

“你们想喝酒吗？(10)”他问道。其中的一个搬运工点了点头，微微一笑。

“是的，先生。(11)”

“你会说法语？”

“是的，先生(12)。”

“喝什么好呢？你懂得香槟酒吗？(13)”

“不懂，先生。(14)”

“她应该是懂的(15)。”约翰逊说。“小姐(16)，”他高声叫那位女服务员道，“我们要喝香槟酒。”

“喝哪种香槟，先生？”

“喝最好的。”约翰逊说。“哪一种最好呢？(17)”他问那几个搬运工。

“最好的吗？(18)”最先开口说话的那个搬运工问。

“没错。”

那个搬运工从外套口袋里取出一副金丝边眼镜，扫了一眼酒单。他的手指顺着那四个打印出来的酒名和价格上划过。

“运动员牌的吧，”他说，“运动员牌的最好。”

“你们同意吗，先生们？”约翰逊问另两位搬运工道。一个搬运工点了点头，还有一个用法语说：“我没喝过这些酒，不过我倒是常听人说过起运动员牌香槟。这是好酒。”

“来一瓶运动员牌香槟。”约翰逊对女服务员说。他看了看酒单上的价格——十一个瑞士法郎一瓶。“来两瓶吧。”随后，他问那个建议选运动员牌香槟的搬运工道：“我和你们坐在一起，你不介意吧？”

“请坐，快请坐。”那个搬运工冲他微微一笑说，然后将眼镜折起，放进眼镜盒里，“今天是先生的生日吧？”

“不是，”约翰逊说，“不是庆祝生日。我妻子决定要和我离婚了。”

“遗憾，”那个搬运工说，“希望别离。”

另两个搬运工，一个听了直摇头，还有一个似乎有点耳聋。

“毫无疑问，这是个很寻常的事情，”约翰逊说，“就跟第一次去看牙科医生，或者女孩子家第一次来例假一样。不过，我还是感到很纠结的。”

“可以理解。”年龄最大的那个搬运工说，“我理解你的心情。”

“你们几位先生没人离过婚吧？”约翰逊问。此刻，他的法语已不再打绊了，变得纯正了起来。这种纯正的法语他说了好一会儿。

“没人离过。”那个点运动员牌香槟酒的搬运工说，“这里的人不太离婚。离了婚的男人倒是有一些，但是不多。”

“我们那儿就不一样了，”约翰逊说，“实际上人人离婚。”

“那倒也是。”那个搬运工证实道，“我在报上看到过。”

“我离婚都算晚的了。”约翰逊继续说道，“我今年三十五岁。这是我第一次离婚。”

“你还年轻。(19)”那个搬运工说道。随后，他又对另两位搬运工解释说：“先生只有三十五岁。(20)”那两个点了点头。其中的一个说：“他的确很年轻。”

“你真的是第一次离婚？”那个搬运工问。

“确确实实。”约翰逊说，“请把酒打开吧，小姐。”

“离婚很费钱吧？”

“得一万法郎。”

“瑞士法郎吗？”

“不。是法国法郎。”

“哦，是这样的。那就是两千瑞士法郎。不管怎样，反正是不便宜。”

“是的。”

“那么，为什么要离婚呢？”

“是对方提出来的。”

“为什么提呢？”

“是为了另嫁新欢呗。”

“真是愚蠢之举。”

“英雄所见略同。”约翰逊说。女服务员为他们四个斟满了酒。大家一起举杯在手。

“干杯！”约翰逊说。

“为你的健康干杯，先生。(21)”那个搬运工说。另两个搬运工说：“为你干杯！(22)”香槟酒入口，味道就像那种粉红色的甜苹果汁。

“瑞士是不是有一种约定俗成的规矩：答话时用另一种语言？”

“没有。”那个搬运工说，“法语比较高雅罢了。再说，此处是瑞士的法语区。”

“可是，你说德语？”

“是的。我们那地方都说德语。”

“明白了。”约翰逊说，“你说你从没有离过婚？”

“是的。离婚太费钱。再说，我从没有结过婚。”

“哦。”约翰逊说了一声，“另外两位先生呢？”

“他们是结了婚的。”

“你喜欢结婚吗？”约翰逊问其中一个结了婚的搬运工。

“什么？”

“你喜欢这种婚姻状态吗？”

“喜欢。这是正常的状态。(23)”

“一点不错。”约翰逊说，“而你呢，先生？(24)”

“这很好。(25)”另一个搬运工说。

“对我来说(26)，”约翰逊说，“可就不好了(27)。”

“先生马上就要离婚了呀。”头一个搬运工说了这么一句。

“是呀。”第二个搬运工说。

“是啊。”第三个搬运工随声附和地说。

“好啦，”约翰逊说，“这个话题似乎没什么再说的了。你对我遇到的麻烦并不感兴趣。”他的后半句话是冲着第一个搬运工说的。

“可是……是这样的。”那个搬运工说。

“好吧，那就换个话题吧。”

“听你的。”

“说什么好来着？”

“你喜欢体育运动吗？”

“不喜欢。”约翰逊说，“我妻子倒是挺喜欢的。”

“那么，你都喜欢干什么？”

“我是个作家。”

“当作家能挣很多钱吗？”

“不能。不过，你出了名，挣的钱就多了。”

“有意思。”

“没意思，”约翰逊说，“没什么意思。对不起，先生们，我得告辞了。另一瓶酒你们也喝了吧，好吗？”

“可是，火车来还有三刻钟呢。”

“这我知道。”约翰逊说。女服务员过来，他付了酒钱和饭钱。

“你要出去，先生？”女服务员问。

“是的，”约翰逊说，“出去走走。我把行李留在这儿。”

说完，他围上围巾，穿上外套，戴上帽子。外边正飘着鹅毛大雪。他回头望望，透过窗户他看见那三个搬运工仍坐在桌旁。女服务员拿着那瓶打开了的酒，将剩下的酒倒进他们的杯子。然后，她把没开瓶的酒送回了吧台。约翰逊心想：这下子，他们几个每人可捞三个法郎。他一转身，沿着站台走开了。在咖啡店里。他原以为说说心事可以让它冲淡些，谁料心事并没有冲淡，却觉得心里堵得慌。

第三部
一个会员的儿子在泰里特

泰里特的车站咖啡店里暖洋洋的，简直有点太暖和了；店里灯火辉煌，桌子擦得亮光闪闪。桌子上摆着食品篮，篮里放着椒盐卷饼，而卷饼装在抛光纸纸袋里。另外，桌上还有一些硬纸板的啤酒杯垫，以防湿杯子在木头桌面上留下水印。木头椅子是雕花的，虽旧却相当舒适。墙上有一个挂钟，吧台设在大堂的尽端。窗外雪花飘舞。一位老者坐在挂钟下方的一张桌子旁边喝咖啡边看晚报。一个搬运工进来说辛普伦开来的东方快车在圣莫里斯晚点一个小时。咖啡店的女服务员走到了哈里斯先生的桌旁。哈里斯先生刚刚吃完了晚餐。

“列车晚点一个小时，先生。给你来杯咖啡吧？”

“如果你乐意的话。”

“来一杯好吗？”女服务员又问了一声。

“那就来一杯吧。”哈里斯先生说。

“谢谢，先生。”女服务员说。

她去厨房端来了一杯咖啡。哈里斯先生加了糖，用汤匙把糖块捣来捣去，捣得嘎吱响，一边眺望窗外，看着雪花在车站站台的灯光下漫天飞舞。

“除了英语，你还会说别的语言吗？”他问女服务员。

“哦，会的，先生。我还会说德语、法语和地方方言。”

“你最喜欢的是哪一种？”

“都差不多吧，先生。我也说不准自己偏爱那一种。”

“你想喝点酒或咖啡什么的吗？”

“哦，不了，先生。店里是不允许陪客人喝酒水的。”

“抽支雪茄怎么样？”

“哦，不，先生。”她哈哈一笑说，“我不会抽烟，先生。”

“我也不会抽，”约翰逊说，“对于大卫·贝拉斯科(28)的观点我是不赞成的。”

“请问你说谁来着？”

“贝拉斯科。大卫·贝拉斯科。他的尊容叫你一见就能认出来，因为他老把衣领倒着穿。对于他的观点，我不敢苟同。话又说回来，他已离别了阳世。”

“对不起，先生，我能走了吗？”女服务员问。

“当然可以。”哈里斯说。他坐在椅子上，身子前倾，眼睛望了望窗外。大堂那一端坐着的老者此时将报纸一折，看看哈里斯先生，端起咖啡杯和杯碟，来到了哈里斯的桌前。

“请原谅，打搅了。”他用英语说道，“我刚才想了想，觉得你可能是美国国家地理学会的会员。”

“你请坐。”哈里斯说。老者坐了下来。

“再喝杯咖啡或者酒吧？”

“谢谢。”老者说。

“陪我喝杯樱桃酒吧？”

“也好。不过，还是我请吧。”

“不行，我是要请的。”哈里斯说完，喊了一声女服务员。

老者从外套口袋里掏出一个皮夹子，将捆在外边的一条宽宽的皮筋取掉，抽出几片纸，从中选了个纸片递给哈里斯。

“这是我的会员证。”他说，“你认识美国的弗雷德里克·杰·罗素吧？”

“恐怕不认识。”

“我认为他是个非常杰出的人物。”

“他是哪里的？是美国哪个地区的？”

“当然是华盛顿的了。学会的总部不就设在那儿吗？”

“我想是的。”

“你想是的？你拿不准吗？”

“我出国的时间久了。”哈里斯说。

“你不是他们的会员吗？”

“不是。我父亲是的。他是多年的老会员了。”

“那他应该认识弗雷德里克·杰·罗素的。罗素先生是学会的一个理事。你会注意到，我是经他提名才成为会员的。”

“真为你感到高兴。”

“可惜你不是个会员。不过，你能不能经你父亲提名加入？”

“我想是可以的。”哈里斯说，“我一回去就办理此事。”

“我建议你一定办理。”老者说，“你肯定见过学会的杂志(29)吧？”

“当然喽。”

“带彩色插图的关于北美动物志的那一期你看了吧？”

“看了，是在巴黎看的。”

“还有刊登了阿拉斯加火山全景的那一期呢？”

“那可真是一种奇观。”

“我还非常喜欢乔治·西拉斯第三拍摄的那些野生动物照片。”

“简直是美轮美奂。”

“对不起，你说什么来着？”

“那些照片很精彩。西拉斯那家伙……”

“你怎么叫他‘家伙’呢？”

“我们是老朋友。”

“原来如此。原来你认识乔治·西拉斯第三。他一定是个十分风趣的人物。”

“的确如此。他恐怕是我所认识的最为风趣的人了。”

“你认识乔治·西拉斯第二吗？他也很风趣吧？”

“哦，他不太风趣。”

“我还想着他也是个非常风趣的人物呢。”

“说来也怪，他并非一个十分风趣的人。为此，我心里常常感到纳闷。”

“原来是这样，”老者说，“我还以为那家里的人个个都很风趣呢。”

“撒哈拉沙漠的那幅照片你还记得吗？”哈里斯问。

“撒哈拉沙漠？那一期差不多是十五年前的。”

“对。那一期最受家父的青睐。”

“他不喜欢比较新一些的照片？”

“也许喜欢吧。但他尤其喜欢那幅撒哈拉的全景照。”

“好极了。不过，我觉得照片的艺术价值要远远超过它的科学趣味。”

“这我说不清。”哈里斯说，“我只记得照片上狂风卷起漫天黄沙，一个阿拉伯人和他的骆驼跪在地上，面朝麦加方向。”

“根据我的记忆，阿拉伯人是站着的，手里牵着骆驼。”

“你说得一点不错。”哈里斯说，“我刚才心里在想着劳伦斯上校(30)的那本书来着。”

“我相信，劳伦斯的那本书讲的是阿拉伯的事情。”

“一点不错。”哈里斯说，“正因为讲的是阿拉伯的事情，才勾起了我对那幅照片的回忆。”

“他一定是个非常风趣的年轻人。”

“我相信他一定是的。”

“你知道他现在在干什么吗？”

“在皇家空军服役呢。”

“他为什么要加入空军呢？”

“他喜欢呗。”

“据你所知，他是不是美国国家地理学会的人？”

“这我也说不清。”

“他要是加入，一定能成为出类拔萃的成员。学会需要的就是这样的人。如果你觉得学会有意吸收他，我将非常乐意为他提名。”

“我觉得他们会愿意吸收的。”

“我曾为沃韦的一个科学家提名，还为洛桑我的一个同事提名，结果两人都当选了。我相信，我要是为劳伦斯上校提名，学会一定会非常满意的。”

“这是个很好的主意。”哈里斯说，“你常来这家店里喝咖啡吗？”

“饭后就来此处喝上一杯。”

“你在大学里教书？”

“不再执教了。”

“我是等火车的，”哈里斯说，“要到巴黎去，然后乘船从勒阿弗尔前往美国。”

“我没去过美国。不过，我非常想去上一趟。也许，有朝一日我会去参加学会的会议的。见到令尊大人，我会非常高兴的。”

“我敢肯定，他也一定很高兴见到你。不过，他于去年过世了，是开枪自杀的。说来也真够怪的。”

“对此我感到非常难过。我敢说，他的离世无论是对科学界还是他的家庭都是沉重的打击。”

“科学界很轻松地接受了这一现实。”

“这是我的名片。”哈里斯说，“我的名字缩写用E. D.，而家父的缩写是E. J.。他要是在世，一定会很高兴认识你的。”

“那将会是我莫大的荣幸。”老者说着从皮夹里取出一张名片递给哈里斯。名片上写着：

美利坚合众国华盛顿特区

美国国家地理学会会员

西格斯蒙德·维亚尔（哲学博士）

“我一定精心保存。”哈里斯说。

————————————————————

(1) 原文为德语。

(2) 原文为法语。

(3) 原文为法语。

(4) 原文为法语。

(5) 原文为法语。

(6) 原文为法语。

(7) 一瑞士法郎等于一百生丁。

(8) 原文为意大利语。

(9) 美国著名作家，其代表作是《了不起的盖茨比》。

(10) 原文为德语。

(11) 原文为法语。

(12) 原文为法语。

(13) 原文为法语。

(14) 原文为法语。

(15) 原文为法语。

(16) 原文为德语。

(17) 原文为法语。

(18) 原文为法语。

(19) 原文为法语。

(20) 原文为法语。

(21) 原文为法语。

(22) 原文为法语。

(23) 原文为法语。

(24) 原文为法语。

(25) 原文为法语。

(26) 原文为法语。

(27) 原文为法语。

(28) 大卫·贝拉斯科（1853—1931），美国戏剧制片人、导演和编剧。

(29) 指美国《国家地理杂志》。

(30) 原英军北非情报员，人称“阿拉伯的劳伦斯”，曾怀着热情与自信率领阿拉伯人抗击土耳其军队。作为一个英国人，他在语言、服装和生活习惯上却能完全地融入阿拉伯人中，他的形象因此而蒙上了神秘的面纱。他也是一个作家，主要作品有《七根智慧柱》等。

等死日

我们还躺在床上的时候，他走进屋里来关窗户。我看了看，见他一脸病容。他浑身哆嗦，面色苍白如纸，步态缓慢，仿佛动一动就会感到疼痛。

“你怎么啦，莎兹？”

“我头疼。”

“你最好回到床上去。”

“不。我没事的。”

“快回到床上去。我把衣服穿好去看你。”

可是，等我下了楼，却见他已穿上了衣服坐在炉火旁，显得病怏怏的，脸上带着九岁小男孩患病时的那种可怜相。我摸摸他的额头，发现他在发烧。

“快到床上去，”我说，“你生病了。”

“我没事的。”他说。

医生赶来，给孩子量了体温。

“多少度？”我问医生。

“一百零二度(1)。”

到了楼下，医生留下三种药——三种不同颜色的药丸，并交代了服用方法。这三种药，一种是退烧的，一种是泻药，还有一种是控制酸性环境的。据他解释，流感病菌只能存活在酸性环境里。他对流感似乎无所不知，说体温只要不超过一百零四度就不用担心。他说这是轻度流感，不出现肺炎并发症便无危险。

送走医生，我回到屋里，用笔将孩子的体温记下来，还分别记下了服各种药丸的时间。

“想让我给你念书听吗？”

“你愿意念，那我就听吧。”孩子说。他脸色煞白煞白，眼睛下方出现了黑圈，静静躺在床上，一副超然的样子，好像自身与周围的环境无关似的。

我大声为他读霍华德·派尔(2)写的《海盗集》，可是却发现他没有用心去听。

“你感觉怎么样了，莎兹？”我问他。

“截至目前，还是那个样。”他说。

我坐在床脚跟前，一边自管自地看书，一边等着时间一到就给他再服另一种药。按说，他也应该睡着了，可是我抬头却见他在盯着床脚看，神情很是异常。

“你为什么不睡一会儿呢？吃药时我会叫醒你的。”

“我愿意这样醒着。”

过了一会儿，他又对我说：“爸爸，你心烦，就不用在这儿陪我了。”

“我不烦。”

“不，我是说，假如这令你心烦的话，就不用陪了。”

我想着他也许有点头晕了，于是在十一点钟给他吃了医生开的药丸，就出去了一会儿。

天气晴冷，地面上的雨雪结成了冰，就好像所有光秃秃的树、灌木丛、修剪过的灌木篱、草坪以及空地都消失在了冰的世界里。我带着那条爱尔兰小猎犬溜达，沿着一条结冰的小溪在路上走着。路面光滑如镜，无论是走还是停都成了难事。红毛小猎犬滑倒了几次，我也两次滑倒，摔得很重，有一次猎枪都掉在了地上，在冰面上出溜到了老远的地方。

高高的土堤跟前的灌木丛里有一群鹌鹑被我们惊起，就在它们飞到土堤的上方，眼看就要消失时，我开枪打死了两只。有些鹌鹑躲在树上，而大多数则零零散散匿身于灌木丛中，得在结了冰层的灌木覆盖的土堤上蹦几蹦，弄出很大响动才会把它们惊起。而我走进结着冰凌、富有弹性的灌木时，它们却飞了出来。由于脚下不稳，得努力保持平衡，给射击增加了难度。我打死了两只，有五只没有射中。竟然有鹌鹑群离家门近在咫尺！这叫我在归家的路上心里有了几分喜悦，心想哪一天去打猎还会发现许多呢。

回到家，屋里的人说那孩子不允许任何人进他的房间。

“你们不能进来，”那孩子是这样说的，“不许你们把我的东西拿走！”

我二话没说，上楼去见他，发现他跟我离开他时一个样，还是那种姿势，脸白如纸，只是脸蛋由于发烧而红通通的，两眼发直，直呆呆望着床脚。

我给他测了体温。

“多少度？”

“像是一百度吧。”我说，其实是一百零二度四分。

“是一百零二度。”他说。

“谁说的？”

“医生说的。”

“你的体温没问题，”我说，“没什么可担心的。”

“我不是担心，”他说，“只是由不得想想罢了。”

“别胡思乱想，”我说，“心情放松些。”

“我的心情是放松的。”他说着话，眼睛直视前方，显然心里隐藏着不便说出的心事。

“你用水把这药咽下去。”

“你觉得这药顶用吗？”

“当然顶用。”

我坐下来，打开那本《海盗集》，开始念给他听，后来发现他没有在听，于是也就不念了。

“你看我何时会死呢？”他问。

“你说什么？”

“我还能活多长时间？”

“你不会死的。你这是怎么啦？”

“哦，会的，我会死的。我听医生说我的体温是一百零二度。”

“一百零二度是死不了人的。你说这话是冒傻气。”

“我知道会死人的。在法国上学的时候，同学们说体温到了四十四度就活不了了。而我都一百零二度了。”

原来他从早晨九点开始，一直在等死，等了一整天。

“莎兹呀，你这个小可怜，”我说道，“可怜的小莎兹呀。测体温的换算是不一样的，犹如英里和公里之比。你不会死的。那是两种不同的温度计。按法国的温度计，三十七度属于正常。而这儿的温度计，正常的体温是九十八度。”

“你敢肯定？”

“百分之百肯定。”我说，“测体温的换算是不一样的，犹如英里和公里之比。你知道咱们开车的时速为七十英里，等于多少公里吗？”

“这个嘛……”他支吾了一声。

不过，他那紧盯着床脚的目光渐渐缓和了，心里紧绷着的弦也终于放松了。到了第二天，他的紧张情绪完全消失了，为了一些鸡毛蒜皮的小事就乱哭乱叫的。

————————————————————

(1) 该篇中均指华氏度。

(2) 美国儿童文学作家。

关于亡者的博物学研究

我一直觉得博物学家忽略了战争，没有将它作为观察的领域。已故的威·亨·哈德森(1)针对巴塔哥尼亚(2)的植物群和动物群有过陈述，引人入胜、精彩纷呈；吉尔伯特·怀特(3)牧师描写过戴胜鸟如何光顾塞耳彭村(4)，偶尔飞临，却意义非凡，写得真是妙趣横生；斯坦利主教撰写了《鸟类的历史》，通俗易懂、弥足珍贵。难道我们就不能心怀希望，给读者提供一些有关亡者的合情合理、生动有趣的事实吗？希望能够做到这一点。

那位百折不挠的旅行家芒戈·派克(5)曾经在广袤无垠的非洲沙漠遭困，一度昏厥，浑身一丝不挂，孤独身处绝地，想来大限将到，无出路可寻，只好躺下等死。就在这时，一朵异常美的小青苔花吸引住了他的目光。他过后回忆说：“那朵花整个儿还没有我的一根手指粗，可是看到它的根茎、叶片和花荚构造得那般精美，由不得心生赞叹。在这个无人注意的区域，上帝种植、浇灌了这么一个看上去微不足道的小东西，并使之完美，难道他会对一个按照自己的形象创造的生灵所面临的处境和困苦置若罔闻吗？绝对不会的。这样的念头是不会允许我甘于绝望的。于是我跳起身，不顾饥饿和劳累，继续向前走去，坚信出路就在眼前。结果我没有失望。”

如斯坦利主教所言，有这种欣赏和赞叹之心，无论从事任何领域的博物学研究，势必会增添研究者的信念、热情和希望。那么，我们在穿过人生的荒漠时，我们当中的每一位是不是也都需要有同样的信念、热情和希望呢？我们不妨先研究一下亡者吧，看从中能获取什么样的灵感。

战场上的亡者，就人类而言通常是男性，但对畜类便言之不实了。雌性战马战死沙场是司空见惯的事。战争另有非常有趣的一面——只有在战场上博物学家才有观察死骡子的机会。在平常的生活中，我观察了二十年都没有见过一只死骡子，于是开始产生了怀疑，觉得骡子都是不死之身。有那么一两次，我以为自己看到了死骡子，可是走近细瞧，结果每一次都发现那是活骡子，只是睡得太死了，才看上去像死了一样。可是在战争中，这种动物跟寻寻常常、不那么吃苦耐劳的战马同样会捐躯疆场。

我在战场上见到过的死骡子大都出现在山路上或者横尸于陡峭的斜坡脚下——那是人们害怕死骡子挡道，把它们推下去的。在大山里，死骡子是常见的，这种现象似乎倒也挺合适的，可后来我在士麦那所见就不那么协调了——在士麦那，希腊人把辎重牲口的腿全都打断，再将它们从码头推下浅水里活活淹死。众多骡子和马被打断腿，淹死在浅水里，这场面真是值得戈雅(6)一画。不过，严格地说，戈雅恐怕是叫不来了，因为世界上只有一个戈雅，他早已是作古之人，再说，这些牲口如果会说话，它们愿意不愿意叫人用画面表现它们的惨景，得打一个大大的问号。话又说回来，牲口们假如能用语言表达，它们很可能会寻求帮助减轻它们的痛苦。

关于亡者性别的问题，我们习惯看见亡者皆为男性，此乃不争的事实，见到一个亡故的女性，一定会觉得触目惊心。我第一次看见亡者性别颠倒的现象是在一个军工厂爆炸之后——那家军工厂位于意大利米兰城附近的乡下。我们乘坐卡车赶往出事现场，一路白杨树浓荫如盖，路边的水沟里有无数微小的生物，只可惜卡车扬起漫天的尘土，让我无法观察得清。到了军工厂所在之处，我们当中的一些人奉命巡逻，围着大堆不知何故没有爆炸的军火查看，另一些人则被分派去灭火（此时火势已蔓延至临近的荒草地里）。这些任务完成之后，我们又奉命在军工厂跟前以及周围的田野里寻找尸体，找到后就抬往临时停尸房（死的人真不少）。说实话，看见死者多为女性，男性较少，我心里吃惊不小。当时的女性还没有开始留齐耳短发，欧美大陆女性留短发是以后几年的事情了。看见长发亡者让人感到极为不安，也许是因为极不习惯的缘故吧，而不留长发的亡者只是偶尔一现，就更叫人心里翻腾不息了。记得我们彻底搜寻完了全尸，又着手找残骸。许多残尸碎片都是从工厂四周密密麻麻的铁丝网上取下来的，还有一些是从存留下来的厂房里找到的。我们寻来的残骸堆积如山，充分地说明了当时爆炸的威力十分巨大。许多残骸是在老远的野地里发现的，它们是被爆炸的气浪抛到那儿去的。

返回米兰的途中，记得有一两个人讨论起了这次事故，一致认为此次事故在性质上有些不现实，还说现场未发现伤员。这就大大降低了恐怖色彩，否则要可怕得多呢。还有一点：爆炸发生得过于直接，结果搬运尸体和处理尸体就不那么让人感到不舒服了，这与通常战场上的经历天差地别。卡车行驶在风景秀丽的伦巴第乡下，虽尘土飞扬，却也赏心悦目，算是对这次窝心的差事一种补偿吧。归途中，我们交换了看法，一致认为突发的大火在我们赶到之前就迅速地得到了控制，没有让大火殃及那些看上去堆积如山的尚未爆炸的军火，实在是天大的幸事。我们还认为收集残骸是件非同寻常的差事。令人诧异的是，按说人体应该分结构被炸得一块一块的，可是在强力炸药爆炸的威力下，却被炸得血肉横飞，随着弹片飞向四方。

为了实现观察的精确性，博物学家应该将目光聚焦在某一特定的时期。我首选奥地利军队在意大利发动攻势之后的一九一八年六月作为特定的时期。当时，亡者人数众多。意大利军队先是被迫撤退，后又反攻收复失地。一场拉锯战之后，阵地依旧，亡者却变了样。在下葬之前，死人每天都多少有些变样。白种人死后，面色由白变黄，再转为黄绿色，最后发黑。死尸在高温下放得太久，尸体上的肉就变得像煤焦油一样（尤其是伤损部分），而且还明显带有焦油的那种亮色。亡者会逐日膨胀，有时膨胀得让军装都包不住了，鼓胀胀的，好像马上会爆炸开似的。亡者的腰身会变粗，粗到令人无法相信的程度，面皮绷紧，肿胀得像气球。除了死尸发胀，还有一种现象也叫人惊讶——亡者身旁乱扔着许多纸片。涉及安葬的问题，亡者的姿势要根据他军装上口袋的位置而定。奥地利的军装，军裤的口袋开在屁股后边，要不了多久，亡者便会被折腾得面朝地，两个屁股口袋被掏空，装在口袋里的各种证件被掏出来，散落在荒草中。高温，苍蝇，荒草中尸体横七竖八，纸片满世界都是，这些就是给人留下的印象。大热天战场上的气味是让人回忆不起来的。你就是记得住那种气味，却再无同样的遭遇令你想得起它。这跟军队里的气味是不一样的。你在乘坐电车时，也许会突然想起军队的气味，于是你看看对面的一位军人，发现原来是他使你想起来的。而战场的气味消失了，荡然无存了，就像你热恋，过后记得起发生的事情，却记不清那澎湃的激情了。

在这么个天气热烘烘的战场上，真不知那位百折不挠的旅行家芒戈·派克看到什么样的景象才会重拾信心。六月底和七月份，麦地里总会出现罂粟花，桑树长得枝繁叶茂，阳光透过绿叶伪装网照在炮筒上，看得见炮筒上升起一股股热浪；芥子毒气弹炸出一个个弹坑，弹坑边缘的土变得黄灿灿的，破屋烂房固然不美观，但是比遭炮击的房屋好看。不过，旅行家身临此地，深深呼吸一口这初夏的空气，可能不会产生芒戈·派克那样的想法，想到上帝按照自己的形象创造生灵什么的。

你看见亡者，第一感觉就是，他们死得好惨，像畜生一样送了命。有的受了点小伤即刻毙命——你恐怕会觉得连兔子受那点伤也不会死的。他们死于小伤，就像兔子有时中了两三颗似乎连皮毛都伤不了的霰弹碎粒而丧命一样。还有一些死状如猫一般——脑壳被击中，铁片嵌入脑浆，像猫一样躺在那儿躺上两天都不死（凡猫者，脑浆里有了子弹，会爬进煤箱躲起来，得用刀将它们的头剁掉才会一命呜呼）。即便如此，它们也不会呜呼的，都说它们有九条命嘛。这我就不清楚了，我只知道大多数亡者死状像畜生，而非人。所谓的自然死亡，我一个都没有看见过。要怪就得怪战争。我像那位百折不挠的旅行家芒戈·派克一样不甘心，知道会有新的情况出现的，柳暗的时候总会出现花明。这种状况总算被我看到了。

那是我所见过的唯一一个自然死亡的例子了，失血并不严重，是死于西班牙流感。患此病者浑身大汗淋漓、气短，死状如下：临终时虽有成年人的气力，却呈幼童状，小便浸湿床单，似幼童便溺于尿布，过世之后床上仍见大量黄色液体流淌、滴落。我倒想看看自称为人道主义者的人是怎么死的。芒戈·派克那样的百折不挠的旅行家，或者我，就是要活下来看看以后的情况，也许真能活到那一天，看到那些文学流派的成员是怎么死的，看看他们高贵的结局。作为一个博物学家，我在思考问题时曾想到过，讲究体统固然是美德，但人类要繁衍下去，必然会有不成体统的现象，因为传宗接代的那种姿势就不成体统，十分不成体统。我心想，这些人也许就是（或者曾经是）出生于高雅共居的子女。不过，暂且不管这一小撮人是如何诞生的，我倒是希望能看到他们的结局，看看寄生虫们是怎样解决那个长期悬而未决的不育问题。他们那离奇的宣传手册已变为废纸，他们关于肉欲的理论也付之东流。

也许，在针对亡者从事博物学研究时，评论几句这些自封的“公民”是合理合法的，即便在本文发表时此封号无任何意义可言，但是这样评论在大热天里看到的那些嘴里嘴外有半品脱蛆虫在乱爬的亡者便有失公道了，他们年纪轻轻就死去，而且并非出于自愿，他们又不经办杂志，许多人肯定连篇评论都没有看过。亡者并非总是出现于大热天，很多时候都是出现于雨天——雨水会把雨地里的他们冲洗干净，也会将掩埋他们的土壤化软，有时大雨下个不停，会将土壤化为泥浆，把亡者从坟坑里冲出来，此时就得再次掩埋。还有的人亡于冬天，亡于群山之间，草草用积雪掩埋，春天雪融，自会有人看到后给他们下葬。大山里的下葬地风景优美，群山间的战争是最美丽的战争。有位将军头部被一个狙击手打穿，埋在了一个叫波科尔的地方。作家们写过这方面的书，书名叫《将军死于床上》，显然是搞错了，因为这位将军死于雪地里的战壕中，身处高山之上，头戴登山帽，帽子上插一根鹰翎，脑门前弹孔小，连小拇指都塞不进去，脑袋后的弹孔大，拳头都能塞得进去（如果你拳头小，并且想塞进去的话），雪地上血迹斑斑。他是一个杰出的将军。冯·贝尔也是一位出类拔萃的将军，此人指挥巴伐利亚阿尔卑斯军团参加卡波雷托战役，身先士卒地乘坐他的指挥车冲进乌迪内城中时，叫意军的后卫部队给打死了。如果追求精确性，写这类书，书名应该用《将军通常死于床上》。

在群山里，急救站设在隐蔽处，有大山挡着，炮弹打不到那儿去。急救站的外边，有时停放着亡者，雪花纷纷扬扬落在他们身上。他们都被抬进了一个坑里——那个坑是大地冰冻之前提前挖好的。在这个坑里有个伤员，脑壳被弹片打碎了，情状就跟碎了的花瓶一样。他的头被用薄膜包裹起来，而且技术含量很高地扎了绷带（绷带凝着血块，都变硬了），脑组织里却有一块碎钢片没取出来。他躺在那里挺过了一天一夜，接着又是一天。担架员请求医生进坑里去瞧瞧他。他们每次抬死人过来都看见他躺在那里，甚至不用把眼睛转过去瞧他都可以听见他的呼吸声。医生眼睛通红，眼皮肿胀，被催泪瓦斯熏得都快睁不开了。他来看过这个伤员两次，一次是在白天，一次是夜间打手电看的。这情景真可以同样成为戈雅很好的绘画素材——我是说打手电看望伤员的场面。医生在第二次查看之后，才相信了担架员的话，相信这位伤员还活着。

“你们想让我怎么处理？”他问道。

担架员也说不出个所以然来。可过了一会儿，他们提出要把这个伤员抬出去，跟那些重伤员放在一起。

“不，这可不行！”忙得不可开交的医生说，“怎么回事？难道你们还怕他不成？”

“我们不愿听他喘着气躺在死人堆里。”

“那就别听呀。如果你们把他抬出这个坑，很快还会把他抬回去的。”

“这我们不在乎，上尉医生。”

“不行！”医生说，“我说不行就不行。难道你们没听见我的话吗？”

“何不加大剂量，给他注射吗啡呢？”一位胳膊负伤，在一旁等待包扎的炮兵军官建议道。

“你以为我的吗啡没别的用处，只用在这里吗？做手术时不用吗啡，这你愿意吗？你手里有枪，干脆出去给他一枪不就得了。”

“他已经中过弹了。”军官说，“要是中弹的是你们医生，你的态度就不一样了。”

“亏你说得出来。”医生在空中挥舞着手术钳说，“对你的话，我得千恩万谢了。你看看这眼睛是怎么啦？”他用手术钳指了指自己的眼睛说，“你觉得怎么样呢？”

“那是催泪瓦斯弹熏的。中的是催泪瓦斯弹，我们称之为幸事。”

“你离开了火线，”医生说，“离开火线跑到这里来，声称要清除眼里的瓦斯。你那是把葱头揉进眼里罢了。”

“你发疯了。这是对我的侮辱，我可不跟你一般见识。简直疯疯癫癫的。”

两人说话间，担架员走了进来。

“上尉医生。”其中的一个担架员启口说道。

“快出去！”医生说。

几个担架员出去了。

“我一枪结果了那个可怜人算啦。”炮兵军官说，“我是个讲人道的人，不愿让他活受罪。”

“那就开枪好啦。”医生说，“去开枪打死他。责任由你承担。我写份报告，就说一位伤员在急救站被炮兵中尉开枪打死了。去呀，去打死他呀！”

“你说的这就不是人话。”

“我的职责是救死扶伤，而非要人性命。杀人则是炮兵队的老爷们干的事。”

“那你为什么不救救他呢？”

“我救了。能做的我都做了。”

“你为什么不用缆车把他送下山去？”

“你算老几，竟敢责问我？你是我的上司吗？这个急救站归你指挥吗？请你回答我！”

炮兵中尉无言以对。屋里其他的人都是士兵，没有别的军官在场。

“请你回答我的话。”医生边说边用手术钳夹起一个针头，“请你回答我的问题。”

“操你！”炮兵军官骂了一声。

“好吧，”医生说，“这可是你说的。算你厉害。算你厉害。咱们走着瞧。”

炮兵上尉霍地站起，朝他走了过来。

“操你！”他口里骂着，“操你！操你妈！操你妹！”

医生端起满满一盘子碘酒朝他脸上泼了过去。中尉一时眼睛看不见了，却仍向他走来，一边去掏手枪。医生快步蹿到他身后将他绊倒，狠狠踹了他几脚，然后用戴着橡皮手套的手捡起了那把枪。中尉坐在地上，用没受伤的那只手捂住眼睛。

“我要杀了你！”他说，“眼睛一能看见，我就杀了你。”

“我是头儿，”医生说，“你要是承认我是头儿，一切都可以搁过不提。你是杀不了我的，因为你的枪在我的手里。中士！副官！副官！”

“副官去缆车那儿了。”中士说。

“用酒精和水给这位军官清洗一下眼睛，他的眼睛里进了碘酒。把盆子端过来让我洗手。我下一个就给这位军官治伤。”

“不许你碰我。”

“抓紧他。他的脑子有点糊涂了。”

这时，一个担架员走了进来。

“上尉医生。”

“怎么啦？”

“死人坑的那个人……”

“你给我出去！”

“他死了，上尉医生。我以为你听了会很高兴的。”

“听见了吧，可怜的中尉？咱俩争来争去，全都白争了。在战争中，争什么都是白争。”

“操你！”炮兵中尉骂了一句。他的眼睛仍然看不见东西。“你把我的眼弄瞎了。”

“没事的，”医生说，“你的眼会没事的。没事的。一场毫无意义的争论。”

“哎哟！哎哟！哎哟！”中尉尖叫了起来，“你把我的眼弄瞎了！你把我的眼弄瞎了！”

“抓紧他！”医生说，“他这是疼的。抓紧不要放松！”

————————————————————

(1) 威廉·亨利·哈德森（1841—1922），英国作家、鸟类学家。

(2) 南美一地区。

(3) 英国牧师、博物学家。

(4) 吉尔伯特·怀特的故乡。

(5) 苏格兰探险家，曾深入非洲腹地。

(6) 西班牙浪漫主义画派画家，画风奇异多变。

赌徒、修女和收音机

他们被人送来时，大约是在午夜时分。后半夜，走廊里的人都可以听见那个俄国人的叫喊声。

“他是哪里中的枪？”弗雷泽先生问值夜班的护士。

“大概是在大腿上。”

“另一个情况怎么样？”

“哎，恐怕活不了了。”

“他是哪里中的枪？”

“肚子上中了两枪。只找到了一颗子弹。”

他们俩都是种甜菜的工人，一个是墨西哥人，一个是俄国人。事发时，他们正坐在一家通宵营业的饭馆里喝咖啡。一个人走进门，对着墨西哥人就开枪。墨西哥人肚子上中了两枪，倒在了地上。俄国人吓得躲到了桌子底下，可还是被一颗射向墨西哥人的流弹所击中。报上就是这么说的。

墨西哥人向警方提供口供时说，他也不清楚开枪的是何人。他认为这是一次偶然的事故。

“还说是事故！他向你开了八枪，两枪打在了你身上！”

“是事故，先生。(1)”这位叫卡耶塔诺·瑞兹的墨西哥人说。

“他开枪打我，只是一次事故，那个混账东西(2)。”他对译员说。

“他说什么？”警官看了看站在病床另一侧的译员问。

“他说那是一次事故。”

“让他实话实说。他快要死了。”警官说。

“死不了的。”卡耶塔诺说，“不过请你告诉他，我感到很难受，不想再多说了。”

“他说他讲的句句是实话。”译员说。随后，他又自信地对警官补充了一句：“他搞不清开枪的是何人。子弹是从后边射向他的。”

“是呀，”警官说，“这我知道。可是，子弹为什么是从前边射进他的身体里的。”

“也许他晕了头了。”译员说。

“你给我听着！”警官说话时，晃动着手指，几乎把手指戳到了卡耶塔诺的鼻子上——那个鼻子蜡黄蜡黄，高高嵌在死人一般的脸上，眼睛却鹰眼一样炯炯有神。“我才不管是谁开枪打你，只需要把事情搞个水落石出。难道你就不想把开枪打你的凶手绳之以法吗？你把这话讲给他听。”他对译员说。

“他说让你说出向你开枪的人。”

“让他下地狱去吧。(3)”已经精疲力竭的卡耶塔诺说。

“他说他压根就没有看见枪手。”译员说，“我可以肯定地说，枪手是从背后开的枪。”

“你问他是谁开枪打的那个俄国人？”

“可怜的俄国佬，”卡耶塔诺说，“他趴在地上，双手抱头，中弹时叽里哇啦乱叫，直到现在还在叫呢。可怜的俄国佬。”

“他说他不认识那个枪手，也许和开枪打他的是同一人吧。”

“你给我听着，”警官说，“此处不是芝加哥，你也不是黑帮，不用像演电影一样装腔作势。把开枪打你的人供出来就万事大吉。供出凶手是每一个人的责任。这是正确的选择。假如你不说，他还会去伤害别人的。也许他还会射杀女人或孩子呢。不能就这么叫他逍遥法外。你把这话讲给他听。”他冲着弗雷泽先生说道，“那个可恶的译员不能叫我信任。”

“我是完全可以信任的。”译员说。

卡耶塔诺把目光转向弗雷泽先生看了看。

“听着，朋友，”弗雷泽先生启口说道，“这位警官说此处不是芝加哥，而是蒙大拿州的黑利。你不是黑帮，跟演电影的不着边。”

“我相信他的话。”卡耶塔诺轻声说，“我敢说是这样的。(4)”

“告发凶手是光荣的职责。他说这儿人人如此。他说凶手开枪打了你，再去打女人或孩子，那该如何是好？”

“我没结婚。”卡耶塔诺说。

“他是说去杀任何一个女人或孩子。”

“那个人并不是疯子。”卡耶塔诺说。

“他说你应该告发他。”弗雷泽先生最后说道。

“谢谢你。”卡耶塔诺说，“你是个非常好的翻译。英语我也会说，就是差了些，不过听还是能听懂的。你的腿是怎么断的？”

“从马上摔下来摔断的。”

“真不走运。很遗憾。疼得厉害吗？”

“现在不厉害了。一开始倒是挺疼的。”

“听我说，朋友，”卡耶塔诺说道，“我现在非常虚弱。对不起了。而且伤口疼得厉害，疼得死去活来。我很可能会去见阎王爷的。请你让这位警官出去吧，我累得要命。”他动了动，像是要翻过身去了，随即收住了口。

“我把你的话原原本本说给他听了。他让我转告你，说他真的不知道谁开的枪。他说他虚弱得厉害，希望以后再问他吧。”弗雷泽先生说道。

“以后他闹不定会死了的。”

“这很有可能。”

“正因为如此，我才想现在问清他。”

“依我看，凶手是从背后开的枪。”译员说。

“哦，请别这么肯定。”警官说着话，一边将笔录本放进了口袋。

出了病房来到走廊里，警官和译员站在弗雷泽先生的轮椅旁边。

“你大概也认为凶手是从后边开的枪吧？”

“是的。”弗雷泽说，“是从背后开的枪。依你所见呢？”

“你可别生气噢，”警官说，“真希望我会讲西班牙语。”

“那你为什么不学呢？”

“你不必生气。用西班牙语问来问去，结果难以叫人满意。如果我会说西班牙语，情况就不一样了。”

“这就大可不必了。”译员说，“我的翻译是十分能叫人信赖的。”

“哦，请别这么肯定。”警官说，“好啦，告辞啦。回头我来看你。”

“多谢。我一直都在这儿呢。”

“我想你现在的状况是不错的。出那样的事实在是不走运，倒霉透了。”

“把骨头接起来后，情况就好转了。”

“是呀，但恢复起来得用很长时间。不是一时半会儿就能好的。”

“可别叫人从背后打你的冷枪。”

“说得对，”他说，“说得对。哦，很高兴你没有生我的气。”

“再见喽。”弗雷泽先生说。

弗雷泽先生有好长一段时间都没有再见到卡耶塔诺，但每天早晨塞西莉亚修女都带来他的消息。修女说他的状况很糟，却极少唉声叹气。他患上了腹膜炎，都认为他活不了了。修女说他真是可怜。他的手是那样的漂亮，脸蛋是那样的英俊，从来没听他说过抱怨的话。眼下，他的伤口散发的气味难闻得刺鼻。她说他老是用手指指指自己的鼻子，咧嘴一笑，然后摇摇头。他对自己身上的气味感到难堪，塞西莉亚修女说他为此很是窘迫。啊，他真是一个讨人喜欢的病人，脸上老挂着微笑。他不愿对神父做忏悔，但是答应会念祈祷词。自从他进了医院，没有一个墨西哥人来探望他。那个俄国人周末就要出院了。塞西莉亚修女说她对那个俄国人一点感觉都没有。那家伙也受够了洋罪。射中他的是一颗涂了油的脏子弹，伤口感染了，但他的叫声也太搅扰人了。修女说她一向喜欢坏人，而卡耶塔诺就是个坏人，一个地地道道的坏人，一个彻头彻尾的坏人。他谈吐优雅，身材秀美，好像从来没有干过体力活。他不可能是种甜菜的工人，绝对不可能是！他的手光滑细腻，没有一个茧子，一看就知道是某一种类型的坏人。修女说这就下楼为他做祈祷去。可怜的卡耶塔诺呀，遭受了那样的痛苦，却一声也不吭。凶手向他开枪，究竟是为了什么？天呀，可怜的卡耶塔诺！这就下楼为他做祈祷去！

修女说完下楼去为卡耶塔诺做祈祷了。

医院里有架收音机，在暮色垂降之前音响效果一直都不太好。据说是因为地底下矿石太多的缘故，或者是因为大山阻隔的缘故，反正音效就是不好，直到外边天擦黑时才改善。这之后的一整夜，它的音效又好极了，一个电台停止播音后，可以再选西边的台，收听另一个电台的节目。最后一个停播的是华盛顿州的西雅图台。由于时差的关系，他们的信号中断是在凌晨四点钟，而此时医院里的时间则是凌晨五点。到了六点钟，则可以收听到明尼阿波利斯(5)电台在上午播放的狂欢曲，这也是因为时差的缘故。弗雷泽先生常常遐想连篇，想象着那些制作狂欢曲的音乐人在上午抵达电台的情况，想象着他们带着乐器天还没亮走下电车的画面。也许他的想象与事实不符——音乐人的乐器是存放在电台里的。可是，在他的想象中音乐人们总是随身携带着乐器。他从未去过明尼阿波利斯，而且觉得自己恐怕这辈子都不会去的，可他知道那座城市一大早是怎样一种情状。

从医院的窗口，可以看见田野里白雪皑皑，雪中露出一簇簇滚草，还可以看见一座光秃秃的土山丘。一天上午，医生想让弗雷泽先生看外边的雪地里有两只野鸡，把他的床向窗口拖，结果床头铁架上的台灯掉下来砸在了弗雷泽先生的脑袋上。这事现在听上去并不可笑，但当时却显得非常滑稽。大伙都凑上去向窗外看，那个医生（一个出类拔萃的医生）一边手指野鸡的那个方向，一边把床朝着窗口拖。就像滑稽连环漫画里画的那样，台灯的铅座直直砸在弗雷泽先生的脑门上，把他给砸昏了。这似乎与医院救死扶伤的准则唱对台戏，或者说也不符合医护人员的行为，反正大家都觉得怪滑稽的，是上天跟弗雷泽先生和那个医生开了个玩笑。在医院里，一切事情都非常简单，连开玩笑也是如此。

如果把床转个方向，从另外一个窗口可以看见市景，看见城市上空轻烟袅袅，还可以看见道森群山，山上冬雪皑皑，看上去真是地道的雄山峻岭。如果坐轮椅还太早，就只能看这两处景色了。在医院里，最好是卧床观景。在一个温度可以自控的房间里消消停停地观两处景色，要比在一个热烘烘、空荡荡的房间里匆匆忙忙观若干处景色强得多了——那样的空房间是等病人入住的，或者是刚刚腾空的，你坐着个轮椅进进出出，哪有心思观景。在一个房间待久了，不管观的是什么景，那个景都会产生巨大的价值，变得无比重要，让你受不了它的变化，连变个角度都不情愿。听收音机跟这同出一理，有些节目听惯了就割舍不了，心生依恋，而讨厌新的节目。这年冬天，他们最喜欢听的曲子是《唱一件简单的事情》、《献歌的女孩》和《小小的善意谎言》。弗雷泽先生觉得别的曲子都不如意。《女生贝蒂》也不失为一首好曲子，只是歌词落了俗套，不可避免地进入弗雷泽先生的心房，逐渐让他觉得粗俗，别的人也不愿再听，最后他干脆弃而不听，又回过头去重新听橄榄球球赛。

早晨九点钟左右，医院里开始使用X光机，此时收音机只能收到黑利台，成了无用的摆设。许多有收音机的黑利人提出过抗议，怪医院使用X光机使他们听不清上午的节目。尽管大家都觉得医院不像话，说他们完全可以在别人不听收音机的时候再使用X光机，可是院方并未采取任何措施。

差不多就在需要关掉收音机的时候，塞西莉亚修女走了进来。

“卡耶塔诺的情况怎么样啦，塞西莉亚修女？”弗雷泽先生问。

“哦，情况很糟。”

“昏迷了吗？”

“没有。不过，他恐怕保不住命了。”

“你怎么样？”

“我挺为他担心的。你知道吗，没有一个人来看望过他。他会像一条狗一样死去的，那些墨西哥老乡们才不管呢。那些人真是可怕。”

“今天下午你愿意过来听橄榄球球赛吗？”

“哦，不了。”她说，“听球赛太让人兴奋了。我还是到教堂里做祈祷吧。”

“下午应该能听得很清的。”弗雷泽先生，“他们正在太平洋沿岸比赛，由于时差的关系，比赛的时间在这儿已经很晚了，是可以听得清的。”

“哦，不了，我不能再听了。上次听世界职业棒球大赛，差点没要我的命。运动员击球时，我就大声祈祷：‘主啊，引导一下他们击球的目光吧！啊，主啊，保佑他击中吧！啊，主啊，保佑他一击便中吧！’第三局他们竟然打了个满垒，你该记得，那情景真让我承受不了。‘啊，主啊，愿他把球打出场地！啊，主啊，愿他把球打出围栏！’轮到红雀队击球时，我的感觉可怕极了。‘啊，主啊，愿他们看不见球！啊，主啊，愿他们连球的影子也看不见！啊，主啊，愿他们三振出局！’这次比赛会叫我更受不了的。参赛的有圣母玛利亚队。那是我们的队。不行，我还是去教堂里吧，在那儿为圣母祈祷。他们打比赛是为了圣母而战。希望你哪一天能写篇东西赞美圣母。你可以写出来的。我知道你有这个能力，弗雷泽先生。”

“关于圣母，我不知该写什么好。基本上能写的都有人写了。”弗雷泽先生说，“再说，你不会喜欢我的笔风的，圣母也不会喜欢的。”

“你哪一天写一篇就是了。”修女说，“我知道你一定会写的。你必须写篇东西赞美我们的圣母。”

“劝你最好还是来听听比赛吧。”

“那会叫我受不了的。不行，我还是去教堂做自己力所能及的事情吧。”

这天下午，比赛进行了大约有五分钟的时间，一个见习护士走进病房说：“塞西莉亚修女想知道比赛进行得怎么样了。”

“告诉她，就说圣母队已经触底得分。”

没多大一会儿，那个见习护士又来病房里了。

“告诉她，圣母队打得对方乱了阵脚。”弗雷泽先生说。

片刻之后，他摇铃叫来当班护士说：“你能不能到教堂里去一趟，给塞西莉亚修女捎个话，就说在头一场四分之一决赛结束时圣母队以十四比零领先。状况很好。让她不用再祈祷了。”

过了没几分钟，塞西莉亚修女自个儿跑了来，情绪非常激动，说道：“十四比零是什么意思？这种赛事我是一无所知。要说棒球比赛，这可是压倒一切的优势。而橄榄球比赛，我就一窍不通了。也许这个比分算不了什么吧。我还是到教堂里去继续祈祷吧，一直祈祷至比赛结束。”

“对手已被彻底打翻在地。”弗雷泽说，“我保证他们已被击败。你留下来跟我一起听吧。”

“不行，不行，这万万使不得。”修女说，“我还是去教堂做祈祷吧。”

此后，圣母队一得分，弗雷泽先生就托人送消息去教堂，等到最后将比赛结果托人送去，天色已经黑下去许久了。

“塞西莉亚修女怎么样？”

“她们都还在教堂里呢。”送消息的人说。

翌日晨，塞西莉亚修女走进病房，满面春色，显得信心十足。

“我就知道对方打不过圣母队。”她说道，“他们休想。卡耶塔诺也好了些，状况好多了。就要有人来探望他了。他目前还不能见人，但他们会来的。有人来，会叫他心里好受些；由此他知道自己没有被同胞忘掉。我下楼去，瞧见警察总部的那个年轻警官奥布莱恩，让他去找几个墨西哥人来看望可怜的卡耶塔诺。他今天下午就去找几个来。到了那时，这个可怜人心里会感到好受些。受了伤，竟然没一个人来看望，真是太可恶了。”

这天下午五点钟左右，三个墨西哥人走了进来。

“能喝上一杯吗？”块头最大的墨西哥人问道。此人厚嘴唇，胖得不得了。

“当然可以！”弗雷泽先生回答，“都请坐，先生们。都喝上一杯吗？”

“多谢了。”大块头说。

“那就谢谢了。”皮肤最黑、个头最小的一个说。

“谢谢，我就不喝了，”一个瘦子说，“喝了上头。”他说着还用手在头上拍了拍。

护士取来了几个玻璃杯。“请你把酒瓶递给他们。”弗雷泽说，“这是从‘红房子’买的。”他解释了一句。

“‘红房子’的酒最好，”大块头说，“比‘大树木’的酒强多了。”

“这是秃子头上的虱子明摆着的，”个头最小的那个说，“只是价格也贵。”

“‘红房子’的酒价物有所值。”大块头说。

“这台收音机是几个管的？”不喝酒的那个问道。

“七个。”

“好漂亮呀。”他说，“这得值多少钱？”

“我也不知道，”弗雷泽先生说，“是租来的。”

“你们几位先生是卡耶塔诺的朋友吧？”

“不是。”大块头说，“我们是打伤他的那个人的朋友。”

“是警察叫我们来的。”个头最小的那个说。

“我们的地位低下。”大块头说，“我和他都一样。”他指了指那个不喝酒的，“他也地位低下。”这次他指的是皮肤黝黑的小个子，“警察叫我们来，我们就来了。”

“你们能来，我很高兴。”

“彼此彼此。”大块头说。

“再来一小杯吧？”

“恭敬不如从命。”大块头说。

“大家干杯！”个头最小的那个说。

“我可不行，”瘦子说，“喝了就上头。”

“这酒是非常好的酒。”个头最小的那个说。

“何不尝上一杯。”弗雷泽先生劝说瘦子道，“就是上点头又何妨。”

“酒劲一过就头疼。”瘦子说。

“难道就不能找几个卡耶塔诺的朋友来看望一下他吗？”弗雷泽问。

“他压根就没有朋友。”

“人生在世都是有朋友的呀。”

“这个人却没有。”

“他是干什么的？”

“纸牌手。”

“牌术高吗？”

“我认为很高。”

“他赢过我的钱，”个头最小的那个说，“赢过我一百八十块钱。一百八十块钱就这么打了水漂。”

“也赢过我的钱，”瘦子说，“赢了我二百零十一块钱。这可不是个小数目。”

“我没跟他打过牌。”大块头说。

“他一定非常有钱喽。”弗雷泽先生说。

“他比我们还穷呢，”小个子墨西哥人说，“除了身上那件衣服，他什么都没有。”

“那件衣服不值什么钱，”弗雷泽先生说，“上面净是窟窿眼。”

“完全如此。”

“打伤他的那个人也是个纸牌手？”

“不是的。他是个种甜菜的工人。这下子，他只得被迫离开这座城市了。”

“想想这多叫人伤心吧。”个头最小的那个说，“他可是这座城市里最优秀的吉他手呢。简直无与伦比。”

“真是叫人嗟叹。”

“是这样的。”大块头说，“他把吉他弹得出神入化。”

“他一走，就没有好的吉他手了吗？”

“好的吉他手恐怕连影子也找不到了。”

“有个风琴手倒是表现不俗。”瘦子说。

“还有几个人是多面手，会玩几种乐器。”大块头说，“你喜欢音乐？”

“哪能不喜欢呢！”

“我们哪天晚上来演奏一下怎么样？依你看，修女会同意吗？她看上去挺和气的。”

“只要能让卡耶塔诺听上音乐，我敢肯定她会允许的。”

“她是不是有点疯疯癫癫的？”瘦子问。

“谁？”

“那个修女呀。”

“没有的事。”弗雷泽先生说，“她是个大好人，脑子聪明，富于同情之心。”

“反正对于牧师啦，僧侣啦，修女啦，我全都不信任。”瘦子说。

“他年轻时有过一段痛苦的经历。”个头最小的那个说。

“我当过牧师的助手。”瘦子带着几分得意的神色说，“现在我什么都不相信了，也不去做弥撒了。”

“为什么？莫非做弥撒会上头？”

“哪里的话。”瘦子说，“只有喝酒才会上头的。宗教是穷人的鸦片。”

“我原以为大麻才是穷人的鸦片呢。”弗雷泽说。

“你抽过鸦片吗？”大块头问。

“没抽过。”

“我也没抽过。”他说，“那玩意儿好像非常可怕，一旦抽上就戒不了了。实在害人不浅。”

“跟宗教一样。”瘦子说。

“这家伙对宗教持坚决反对的态度。”个头最小的那个墨西哥人说。

“不喜欢，就有必要持坚决反对的态度。”弗雷泽先生有礼貌地说。

“我尊敬的是那些虽然无知，但有信仰的人。”瘦子说。

“说得好。”弗雷泽先生称赞道。

“我们来时给你带什么好呢？”大块头墨西哥人问道，“你缺什么呢？”

“如果有好啤酒能买一些来，我将会很高兴的。”

“那我们就带啤酒来。”

“临走之前，再来上一杯这雪莉酒怎么样？”

“非常好。”

“让你破费了。”

“我喝不成，会上头的。酒劲一过就会头疼，而且胃里翻江倒海的。”

“再见，先生们。”

“再见。谢谢款待。”

这几个墨西哥人走了。弗雷泽先生吃过晚饭，然后听收音机，尽可能调低音量，调到刚能听得见的程度。最后，各地的电台按以下的次序停止了播音：丹佛、盐湖城、洛杉矶和西雅图。听收音机，弗雷泽先生无从得知丹佛是怎么样一幅情景。从《丹佛邮报》上，他倒是可以看到丹佛的画面，再从《洛基山新闻报》上对他的印象加以校正。至于盐湖城和洛杉矶，他只有所耳闻，却一点感觉都没有。对于盐湖城，他唯一的感觉是那儿环境干净但却枯燥乏味；要说洛杉矶，那儿大酒店多如牛毛，酒店里歌舞厅也多得不得了，让他无法想象那究竟是怎样一座城市。光凭歌舞厅，他无法对一座城市产生感觉。不过，对于西雅图他却了如指掌——出租车公司拥有清一色的白颜色大型号的出租车（每辆出租车里配备有收音机），他想象着自己每天晚上都乘车去加拿大境内的那家路边旅馆里去，在那儿根据客人打电话点的乐曲了解诸多晚会的进程。从下午两点钟起，他每天晚上都置身于西雅图，听着形形色色的人所点的曲子。他知道，明尼阿波利斯的那些狂欢曲演奏人黎明即起，匆忙赶到电台里。而西雅图和明尼阿波利斯同样的真实。对于华盛顿州的西雅图，弗雷泽先生简直心醉神迷。

那几个墨西哥人来了，把啤酒也带来了，只不过不是好啤酒。弗雷泽先生接待了他们，可是却没情没绪，不愿多说话。客人走后，他情知他们再也不会来了。他的神经变得很脆弱，一旦出现这种状况，他就不愿见人。五个星期结束时，他的神经已经一团糟。他为自己的神经能撑这么久而感到欣慰，却也有几分气恼——明明知道有这样的结果，他竟然还违背心愿地接受了这样的实验。这一套过程，他以前早就经历过了。对他而言，唯有听收音机有尝鲜的味道。听收音机，他一听就是一宿，将音量调低，低到几乎刚能听得见的程度。他逐渐学会了只听收音机，而不浮想联翩。

那天上午十点钟左右，塞西莉亚修女来到了病房里，把他的信件送来了。修女长得花容月貌，弗雷泽先生喜欢看她，也喜欢听她说话，但信件像是来自于另一个世界，分量要更重些。可惜的是信的内容引不起他任何兴趣。

“你看上去气色好多啦，”修女说，“用不了多久便可以出院了。”

“是呀。”弗雷泽先生说，“今天上午你满脸的喜色。”

“哦，是这样的。今天上午我有一种感觉，觉得自己好像成了圣徒。”

弗雷泽先生一愣，一时没回过神来。

“是这样的，”塞西莉亚修女喋喋不休地说，“成为圣徒是我的夙愿。当我还是个小姑娘时，我就渴望当一名圣徒。小的时候，我觉得只要出家进修道院当修女，有朝一日就可以成为圣徒。那是我朝思暮想的愿望，唯有如此才能实现这一愿望。我盼啊盼，只盼成为圣徒。我有十二分的信心，认为自己必将成功。刚才，我产生了一种感觉，觉得自己成了圣徒。我感到幸福极了。那一切似乎来得十分简单，十分容易。早晨一醒来，我就指望着脱胎换骨成为圣徒。只是始终没有脱离凡胎。我是多么渴望立地成为圣徒啊。心怀这一夙愿由来已久。今天上午，我觉得自己好像已成为圣徒。啊，真希望我美梦成真，成为圣徒啊。”

“你会如愿以偿的。有志者事竟成嘛。这是前辈的谆谆教导。”

“现在我有点吃不准了。小的时候事情似乎简单得很，觉得自己一定能成为圣徒。后来发现这一愿望不能在一朝一夕实现，我便想到这是个旷日持久的过程。现在却觉得这一目标可望而不可即了。”

“依我看，你大有可能实现。”

“你真的这么想？算啦，我可不想只听听鼓舞人心的话。你就不用给我打气了。我反正心里只想当圣徒，这是我的一个强烈的愿望。”

“你肯定会成为圣徒的。”弗雷泽先生说。

“哎，恐怕这一愿望难以实现了。啊，只要能当上圣徒，那该有多好呀！我会感到无比幸福的。”

“你有压倒一切的机会成为圣徒的。”

“算啦，请不要再说鼓舞人心的话了。啊，只要能当上圣徒，那该有多好呀！只要能当上圣徒，那该有多好呀！”

“你的朋友卡耶塔诺怎么样啦？”

“伤情会好起来的，只是瘫痪了。一颗子弹击中了大腿上一根主要的神经，那条腿算是瘫痪了。他伤情好转，可以挪动时，才发现了这一情况。”

“也许神经可以再生吧。”

“但愿能再生。”塞西莉亚修女说，“你应该见见他。”

“我不想见人，任何人都不想见。”

“可是他，你一定想见的。可以让她们用轮椅把他推到这儿来。”

“那好吧。”

护士用轮椅将他推了来。只见他面容消瘦，皮肤透明，一头黑发欠剪理，眼里饱含笑意，一笑就露出一口坏牙。

“你好，朋友！怎么样呀？(6)”

“你也看到了，就这个样。”弗雷泽先生说，“你怎么样？”

“活下来了，但腿瘫痪了。”

“真糟糕。”弗雷泽先生说，“不过，神经是可以再生的，再生出来的跟原来的一样管用。”

“他们也是这么对我讲的。”

“伤口现在还疼吗？”

“目前已不疼了。有段时间肚子上的伤疼得要死，差点没叫我发疯。我觉得再那么疼下去，准会要我的命。”

此时，塞西莉亚修女在一旁看着他俩，一脸的幸福。

“修女告诉我，说你吭都没有吭一声。”弗雷泽先生说。

“病房里人多，不能乱叫。”墨西哥人不在意地说，“你疼得厉害不厉害？”

“够厉害的了。不过跟你相比就小巫见大巫了。护士一走开，我就喊叫上一两个小时，然后就安静下来。现在我的神经不行了，控制不了了。”

“你可有收音机做伴呀。如果我有自己独立的房间和一台收音机，我就使劲地喊，使劲地叫，彻夜不息。”

“我不信。”

“朋友，我会叫的(7)，叫出声来就舒服一些。可是周围人多就不能这样做了。”

“最起码，”弗雷泽先生说，“你的手完好无损。据说你是靠双手糊口的。”

“还靠脑袋。”卡耶塔诺说着拍了拍脑门，“不过，若论价值，脑袋是不如手的。”

“你的三个老乡曾到这儿来过。”

“是警察让他们来看我的。”

“他们带来了一些啤酒。”

“恐怕是劣质啤酒。”

“是劣质的。”

“今晚，他们奉警察之命要来给我演奏小夜曲呢。”他哈哈大笑起来，后来轻轻拍拍肚皮说，“有伤口，不敢笑了。要说音乐师，他们可真是滥竽充数。”

“向你开枪的那个人呢？”

“也是个蠢货。我打牌赢过他三十八块钱，可那也不值得置人于死地呀。”

“那三个老乡说你赢了许多钱呢。”

“我还不是比别人穷嘛。”

“怎么回事？”

“我是个可怜的理想主义者，是幻想的牺牲品。”他哈哈大笑起来，随即咧咧嘴，又轻轻拍了拍肚皮，“我是个职业赌徒，而且喜欢赌博，喜欢真正的赌博。小打小闹的赌博凭的是抽老千，而真正的赌博需要有运气。我所缺的就是运气。”

“历来如此吗？”

“历来如此。我是个一点运气都没有的人。说说那个向我开枪的蠢蛋吧。他会打枪吗？不会的。他第一枪打空了，第二枪击中了那个倒霉的俄国人。这样，似乎我的运气还不错吧？可后来呢？他两枪打在了我的肚子上。他是个幸运儿，而我无好运可言。要是让他踩着马镫，他恐怕连马的肚皮都不会踢。他凭的全是运气。”

“我还以为他先击中了你，然后才是那个俄国人呢。”

“不对。先击中俄国人，后击中我。报社的记者搞颠倒了。”

“你为何不开枪打他呢？”

“我身上从不带枪。凭我这臭运气，如果带枪在身，一年恐怕会被绞死十次。说到底，我只不过是个卑微的纸牌手罢了。”他中间停顿了一下，随后又说了下去。“我一有钱就赌，一赌就输。掷骰子，我输了三千块钱，次次输，没有中过六点。掷骰子可没有抽老千，运气欠佳非止一次。”

“为什么还要赌下去？”

“总觉得只要活着，运气会变的。十五年来，坏运如影随形跟着我。一旦好运降临，我就会一朝成为富佬。”他咧嘴笑了笑。“我是个出色的赌徒，赢了钱我会乐在其中。”

“你不管赌什么，都运气不好吗？”

“事事倒运，情场上也一样。”他又笑了笑，露出了一口坏牙。

“真的吗？”

“真的。”

“这该如何是好？”

“继续干呗，悠着点，等待着峰回路转。”

“情场上呢？”

“没有一个赌徒是情场得意的。他太专注于自己的事业，晚上需要跟女伴在一起，他却忙碌于赌场。晚上下赌场的人是拴不住女人的心的——如果那个女人有可取之处的话。”

“你可真是个哲学家哟。”

“过奖了，朋友。鄙人只不过是一个小地方的赌徒，云游四方，以四海为家，跌倒了再爬起来。”

“后来肚子上中了枪。”

“那可是破天荒第一遭儿。”他说，“这事只发生过一次。”

“这么说话，你累了吧？”弗雷泽先生问。

“不累。”他说，“肯定让你累着了。”

“腿怎么样？”

“这条腿对我用处不大，有没有它都无所谓。反正我是有办法走动的。”

“祝你好运，真诚地、打心眼里祝你好运。”弗雷泽先生说。

“彼此彼此。”他说，“祝你疼痛全消。”

“它持续不了多久的，会消失的。区区小事一桩。”

“愿你的疼痛感迅速消失。”

“彼此彼此。”

那天晚上，几个墨西哥人来病房演奏手风琴及其他乐器，引起一片欢腾。悠扬的手风琴声、铃声、管弦乐声和鼓声响彻了整个走廊。病房里有个马戏团的飞车手。在一个炎热、尘土飞扬的下午，在“午夜剧场”表演时，观众人山人海，他飞车时从滑道上跌落，摔断了脊梁骨。伤好出院后，他恐怕得改行当皮匠或藤椅工了。还有个病号是木匠，搭脚手架时和脚手架一道摔在了地上，两个脚踝和两个手腕全都摔断了。他像猫一样摔在了地上，却没有猫的柔韧性。医生倒是可以将他修理好，让他能够重新工作，但这得用很长的时间。病人中还有个小伙子，是农村来的，大约十六岁，断腿给接错了茬，得敲断重新接。再下来就是卡耶塔诺·瑞兹——一个小地方的赌徒，一条腿瘫痪了。弗雷泽先生可以听见这些人欢快的笑声回荡在走廊里，他们被警察差来的那几个墨西哥人演奏的音乐逗得乐翻了天。那几个墨西哥人大显身手。他们按捺不住激动的心情，跑到弗雷泽先生的病房里来，询问他有没有自己想听的曲子需要他们演奏。过后，他们不请自来，又主动在晚间来演奏了两场。

他们最后一次演奏时，弗雷泽先生躺在自己的病房里，敞着门，耳朵听着那热闹、拙劣的音乐，心里禁不住陷入了沉思。当那几个人过来问他想听什么曲子时，他点了《蟑螂曲》(8)，此曲里的许多调子轻快、活泼，人们喜欢得要命。几位乐手把这个曲子演奏得热闹而富于感情。在弗雷泽先生的心目中，《蟑螂曲》比大多数同类曲子都感人，可这几位乐手演奏的效果却雷同。

尽管情绪受到了感染，弗雷泽先生的心里仍在苦苦思索着。通常，除了在写作时，他能不思考问题就不去费这个脑筋，可此刻他却苦思不已，想着这些演奏乐曲的人以及瘦子所说的那一席话。

宗教是人民的鸦片。他相信这话，相信那个肠胃不好、瘦小的皮包骨头的人。对啦，音乐也是人民的鸦片。那个喝酒就上头的老哥可没有想到这一点。经济问题也是人民的鸦片。在意大利和德国，连同爱国主义全都是人民的鸦片。性交呢？性交是不是人民的鸦片？对有些人是的。对一些最优秀的人而言，性交就是人民的鸦片。喝酒是人民最好的鸦片，啊，多么好的鸦片啊。有些人喜欢听收音机，而这也是人民的鸦片，是他正在吸食的廉价鸦片。赌博和这些是同类，也是人民的鸦片（如果有鸦片的话），一种最古老的鸦片。抱负也算其中的一种，也是人民的鸦片，连同对新类型统治的信仰都是一个样。人们所需要的是最低限度的统治，越少统治越好。我们所信仰的自由如今成了麦克菲登(9)出版的一本杂志的名字。我们信仰那一事业，虽然尚未为它找到一个新的名称。不过，真正的自由是什么呢？真正的、地道的人民的鸦片又是什么呢？答案他知道得很清楚——它就在他心里一拐弯的地方，在一个亮亮堂堂的地方。自从傍晚喝了两三杯酒后，它就一直在那儿。他知道它就在那儿（当然并非真的在那儿）。答案是什么来着？反正他清楚得很。那是什么来着？当然喽，面包是人民的鸦片。他能记得住吗？天亮时还明白其中的含义吗？面包是人民的鸦片！

“听我说，”弗雷泽先生见护士走进来，便对她说道，“请你把那个瘦小的墨西哥人找来，好不好？”

“你喜欢听那曲子吧？”那个墨西哥人来时，站在门跟前说。

“非常喜欢。”

“那个曲子具有历史意义，”墨西哥人说，“是真正的革命曲子。”

“听着，”弗雷泽先生说，“给人做手术时为什么不打麻药？”

“这些我不懂。”

“为什么并非所有人民的鸦片都是好鸦片？对于人民，你想采取什么措施呢？”

“应该把他们从愚昧中拯救出来。”

“你可别乱放空炮。教育是人民的鸦片。对此你应该知道的。你自己不就受过一点教育嘛。”

“你不相信教育？”

“不相信。”弗雷泽先生说，“对于知识嘛，我倒是相信的。”

“我不明白你的意思。”

“我经常连自己都不明白呢，倒也开心。”

“下一次还想听《蟑螂曲》吗？”墨西哥人面带几分忧虑问道。

“是的。”弗雷泽先生说，“下次还演奏《蟑螂曲》吧。这比听收音机强。”

弗雷泽先生心里在思索，革命不是鸦片。革命是一种净化剂，是一种只有通过暴力才能够延续的狂热。鸦片往往用于革命前和革命后。他的这一想法很好，简直有点太好了。

他心想，那几个墨西哥人马上就要走了，将把《蟑螂曲》一起带走。那时，他就来上一小杯烈性酒，打开收音机，把音量调得低低的，调到刚能听得见的程度。

————————————————————

(1) 原文为西班牙语。

(2) 原文为西班牙语。

(3) 原文为西班牙语。

(4) 原文为西班牙语。

(5) 美国明尼苏达州最大城市。

(6) 原文为西班牙语。

(7) 原文为西班牙语。

(8) 墨西哥流行舞曲。

(9) 美国出版商，他所出版的《自由》杂志影响力很大。

父亲们和儿子们

城市通衢大道的中央竖着一面牌子，要车辆绕行，可是汽车却公然不顾，偏要直直穿过去。据此，尼古拉斯·亚当斯认为那儿曾经修路，现已修完，于是也就沿着那条空荡荡、砖砌的大街把车子朝前开去，穿城而过。星期天车辆少，红绿灯却换来换去，他只好走走停停的。财政上要是支付不起这套指示灯系统，这红绿灯明年可就亮不起来了。小城的树木郁郁葱葱，遮在道路两旁。你要是当地人，在树下散散步，倒是满可心的，但外地人则不然，他会觉得树荫太浓，挡住阳光，屋里难免受潮。尼古拉斯·亚当斯驾车驶过最后的一幢房屋，驶上了一起一伏向前延伸的公路，红土路堤修得平平整整，两旁排列着新培育出的树苗。此处不是他的家乡，但时值仲秋，满眼秋色，开车路过倒也赏心悦目。地里的棉花已摘完，空地上种了一片片的玉米，有的玉米地块之间还种了几排红高粱。汽车行驶得很顺当；儿子在身旁的座位上熟睡着；一天的行程已经结束；对于歇宿的那座城市他是很熟悉的。在这种情况下，尼克(1)看着景色，留意着哪块玉米地里夹杂着黄豆或豌豆，留意着林子和垦地的布局，留意着小木屋和住宅在田头及林间的分布情况，一路行驶一路想象着如何在这一带打猎；每每驶过一片林间空地，他都要心里做个评估，看猎物会在哪儿觅食和筑巢，看在何处能发现鸟群，看它们会朝哪个方向飞。

猎杀鹌鹑时，猎犬一旦发现它们，你可千万别挡住它们的归巢之路，否则，它们会一哄而起，直直地向你冲来，有的直飞高空，有的则噌地从你耳边掠过，呼呼带着风声，身影和它们在空中相比显得无比巨大。唯一的办法就是背过身去，让它们从你的肩头飞过，待它们收翅，眼看就要入林时，你就开枪。在这种地区打鹌鹑的方法是他的父亲教给他的。此时此刻，尼古拉斯·亚当斯不由思念起了自己的慈父。一想到慈父，必然会想起那双眼睛。父亲身材魁梧，动作敏捷，宽肩膀，鹰钩鼻，尖瘦的下巴上留着一把胡子——可是，总是令他难以忘怀的是那双眼睛。那双眼睛遮在两道浓眉之下，深深嵌在头颅里，好像是一种稀世珍宝以这样的布局受到特殊保护似的。这双眼睛比任何人眼都要看得远，目光都要敏锐得多，是上天赐给父亲的珍贵礼物。实际上，父亲的一双眼敏锐如巨角山羊之眼，又如雄鹰之眼。

当年他和父亲站在湖岸边（那时，他的眼力是非常好的），父亲常对他说：“对面把旗子升起来了。”尼克却怎么看也看不见旗子，也看不见旗杆。接下来，父亲又会说道：“那是你妹妹多萝西升的。她把旗子升起，现在在朝码头上走。”

尼克向湖对岸望去，可以看见林木葱茏的长长的湖岸线以及背后的那些参天大树，能看见护卫着湖湾的岬角，看得见田头轮廓清晰的山丘和他们家树影婆娑的白色房子，但就是看不见任何旗杆或码头，所见的只是白色的沙滩和弯曲的湖岸。

“你能看得见岬角那边山坡上的羊群吗？”

“看得见。”

它们看上去只是灰绿色山丘上的几个白点而已。

“我能数得清有几只。”

跟所有具备超常能力的人一样，父亲是很神经质的。而且，他还喜欢感情用事——和大多数感情用事的人一样，他能狠得下心来，却也常常受人欺负。另外，他老是厄运缠身，而有些厄运并非他自己招来的。他是因为一个圈套丧的命（这个圈套也有他作恶的成分在里边）——那些家伙在他生前曾耍出各种花样欺骗他。感情用事的人老是被人欺骗。尼克目前还不能写东西纪念他，不过以后会写的。只是看见眼前的这片鹌鹑狩猎地，他触景生情，想起了父亲而已。他小的时候，尤其感谢父亲的有两点：钓鱼和打猎。父亲对这两件事是行家里手，对两性方面的事见解却不高明（只是举例而已），这种状况倒是让尼克挺高兴的。当他需要拥有枪和使用枪的时候，正是父亲给了他第一支猎枪，给他提供了开枪的机会；当他需要学打猎和钓鱼的时候，正是父亲能让他住在有猎物可打，有鱼可钓的地方。如今三十八岁，他仍喜欢钓鱼和打猎，热情不减于当年第一次跟随父亲去钓鱼、打猎时。这是一种激情，一种从未消减过的激情。他对父亲心存十二分的感激，因为正是父亲让他尝到了甜头。

至于另一件事，也就是父亲的见解不太高明的那件事，每个人生来都已具备了先决条件，自然而然都会无师自通，不管住在何处都是无所谓的。关于这些，父亲只给他提供过两点知识，至今他仍记忆犹新。一次父子两人出猎，尼克一枪打中了铁杉树上的一只红松鼠。松鼠受伤落地。尼克过去将它捡起，而它结结实实一口咬在了尼克的拇指肚上。

“你这个可恶的小bugger(2)！”尼克骂道，砰地把松鼠的脑袋在树上磕了一下，“看它把我咬的。”

父亲瞧了瞧伤口说：“用嘴把流出来的血吸干净，回家后涂点碘酒。”

“这个小bugger真可恶！”尼克说。

“你知道bugger是什么意思吗？”父亲问。

“这是我们小孩骂人用的。”

“bugger是指与兽类性交的人。”

“为什么和兽类性交？”尼克问。

“我也不知道。”父亲说，“这是一种十恶不赦的罪过。”

尼克因此胡思乱想了一通，心里觉得怪可怕的。他想到了各种各样的动物，觉得没有一种是具有吸引力的，好像不切合实际。除了另一件事父亲也发表过看法，这就是父亲直接传授给他的全部性方面的知识了。

一天上午，他在报上看见恩里科·卡罗素因mashing(3)罪而遭到了逮捕，于是便问父亲：“mashing是什么意思？”

“是一种十恶不赦的罪过。”父亲回答。

尼克的脑海里出现了那个著名男歌唱家的身影，见他用捣土豆泥的棒杵抡向一个漂亮女子（该女子长得像雪茄盒里安娜·海尔德(4)的画像），行为古怪、可怕。他心里怕得不得了，但他决定在自己长大后也要至少来那么一次mashing。

在总结这类事情时，父亲说自淫会导致眼盲、精神错乱和死亡，而嫖娼则会染上肮脏的花柳病，所以不应该胡来。再说说父亲的眼睛，那样的好眼力尼克从来都没有见过。尼克非常爱他，这种爱长久不衰。如今，过去的事如在眼前，他甚至能记得起横祸飞来之前早期的那段岁月，心里不由五味杂陈。如果用笔将其写出来，倒是可以吐出心中的块垒。对于许多事情他都是如此，以笔排忧愁。可是，要写出此事的来龙去脉，还为时过早。这会牵扯到很多人。于是，他决定暂时搁置不提。对于父亲的事他无能为力，往事他千思万想，不知想了有多少遍了。父亲死后，那个殡葬承办人为父亲整理遗容，干得一手好活，这情景仍清晰地留在他心里，其他的场景也历历在目，自己当时承担的责任他也记得很清楚。他对殡葬承办人说了些美言美语，后者听了极为高兴，面露得色。不过，父亲的遗容并不是由殡葬承办人定型的，殡葬承办人只不过描了几笔整理了一下而已，其艺术价值有待商榷。父亲的面容早已定型，此事由来已久。在近三年，定型的速度更为快速。这件事很有写头，只是许多事中人仍活在世上，不便动笔。

在人生的启蒙阶段，尼克的大课堂就是印第安营地后边的那片铁杉林。从他们家有一条小道通往林子，穿过林子就是农田，再走上一条弯弯曲曲的路经过荒地就可抵达印第安营地。此时，他真想再光着脚走一走那条小道，再感受感受。记得家宅后的铁杉林里松针铺地，倒地的树木已化为木头碎末，有的树杈遭电击裂开，长长的，一条一条挂在树上，看似标枪。小溪上搭着一根原木，过桥时一脚踏空，就会踏进沼泽地黑黑的淤泥里。翻过一道栅栏就出了林子，田间小道被太阳晒得发硬，处处可见草茬、酸模和天蕊花。左侧有一片泥塘水，是溪水泛滥时灌入造成的，在缓慢流动，那儿是喧鸻(5)的觅食地。瞭望棚就建在溪畔。粪棚里既有还冒着热气的新鲜牲口粪，也有陈粪，陈粪堆的顶端已经干得结成了块。再翻过一道栅栏，走完从粪棚到住宅那条坚硬、烫脚的小路，然后就是一条热烘烘的沙土路，一直通向林子，中间跨过一条小溪（这条小溪是有桥的），溪畔生长着猫尾草。夜间叉鱼，你可以把这猫尾草浸透煤油，点着当杰克灯(6)用。

大路擦着林子向左拐，蜿蜒翻过山头。进林子走的是一条宽宽的板岩土路，在树荫下倒是凉爽——此路之所以拓宽是为了便于将印第安人剥下的铁杉树皮外运。铁杉树皮堆积如山，排成一长列一长列的，上面搭了些铁杉树皮为盖，看上去像一座座房屋。剥光了皮的树身巨大、发黄，乱扔在伐木原场地，就这么躺在林子里烂掉，甚至连树梢都懒得砍，懒得烧。他们要的只是树皮，把树皮卖给博因城的制革厂。冬天湖上结冰，他们将树皮源源不断拖过湖去。树林逐年减少，荒地一年年扩大，空旷、炎热，没有树荫，杂草丛生。

不过，当时的森林还是挺大的，并且是原始森林，那些树都是蹿得很高了才分出枝杈。森林里没有灌木，走进去脚下踩的是棕色的松针地，洁净，富于弹性。大热天，森林里凉爽宜人，他们三个背靠一棵铁杉树的树身席地而坐——那棵树之粗，比两张床并起来还要宽，树梢间微风习习，斑驳的阳光洒进来已有了几分凉意。只听比利开口说了话：

“你又想要特鲁迪啦？”

“你想了吗，特鲁迪？”

“这个嘛……”

“咱们走开吧。”

“不行，就在这里吧。”

“可是，比利在……”

“我不在乎比利在跟前。他是我哥哥嘛。”

一番对话之后，三个人坐在那儿听见一只黑松鼠叫了一声，那松鼠在顶梢的枝头，眼睛看不见。他们等待着，等着松鼠再发出叫声。松鼠一叫就会翘尾巴，尼克看见动静就开枪。每天打猎，父亲只给他三发子弹。他有自己的猎枪，是单管的二十口径的猎枪，枪管非常长。

“那龟儿子一动不动。”比利说。

“你先开一枪吓吓它，尼基(7)。看见它一跳动，你就补一枪。”特鲁迪说。她说话很少说这么长的句子。

“我只有两发子弹了。”尼克说。

“那个龟儿子。”比利又骂了一声。

他们三个背靠大树坐着，一时谁也没说话。尼克觉得有点空落落的，心情却是高兴的。

“埃迪放出话，说哪天夜里他要来跟你妹妹多萝西睡上一觉。”

“什么？”

“他就是这么说的。”

特鲁迪点了点头。

“他的确想这么做。”她说。埃迪是她和比利的异母同父哥哥，今年十七岁。

“只要埃迪·吉尔比夜里敢来，哪怕是对多萝西说上一句话，你们知道我会把他怎么样吗？我会像这样一枪崩了他。”尼克说完枪口一斜，几乎连瞄准也没有就扣动了扳机，仿佛一枪打在了那个杂种埃迪·吉尔比的头上或肚子上，留下了一个能塞进去拳头的大窟窿。“就像这一个样。我会这么一枪崩了他。”

“他还是别来的好。”特鲁迪说完，把一只手伸进了尼克的口袋。

“最好叫他小心点。”比利说。

“他就喜欢吹牛。”特鲁迪一边说一边用手在尼克的口袋里摸索着。“你可别杀了他，那会惹上大祸的。”

“我会就这么一枪崩了他的。”尼克说。那架势就好像埃迪·吉尔比中枪倒地，胸口被打了个稀巴烂，而尼克得意扬扬地把一只脚踩在他身上。

“我还要剥下他的头皮。”他兴高采烈地说。

“别那样，”特鲁迪说，“那多脏呀。”

“我剥下他的头皮，送去给他的妈妈。”

“他妈妈早死了。”特鲁迪说，“求你别杀了他，尼基。看在我的面上，求你别杀他。”

“剥下他的头皮，把他的尸体让野狗吃。”

比利听了脸色沉了下来。“他最好还是小心点。”他闷闷不乐地说。

“野狗会把他撕成碎片的。”尼克说道。他为自己想象出的情景颇感得意——他把那个王八蛋剥了头皮，看着野狗将其撕成碎片，脸上面不改色。突然，他朝后一倒靠在了树身上，脖子被人搂得紧紧的。原来是特鲁迪搂住了他的脖子，让他透不过气来，嘴里哭叫着：“求你别杀他！求你别杀他！求你别杀他！别杀他！别杀他！别杀他！求你啦，尼基！求你啦，尼基！求你啦，尼基！”

“你这是怎么啦？”

“求你别杀他。”

“我非杀不可。”

“他只不过喜欢吹吹牛罢了。”

“那好吧，”尼基说，“他只要不来我家，我不杀他就是了。你松开手吧。”

“这样就好。”特鲁迪说，“你想不想现在干上一次呢？我现在有情绪了。”

“只要比利走开就行。”尼克说。他原来要杀埃迪·吉尔比，后来又饶他不死，一下子觉得自己成了个顶天立地的男子汉。

“你走开，比利。你怎么老缠在这里。快走开。”

“你个龟儿子，”比利说，“让人烦死啦。来这里到底是干什么的？来打猎还是干什么的？”

“你可以把枪拿走。还剩下一发子弹。”

“那好吧。我一定能打到一只又大又黑的松鼠。”

“过一会儿我喊你。”尼克说。

之后过了很长时间，比利仍没有露面。

“你看咱们会不会生出个孩子来？”特鲁迪蜷起两条棕色的腿，一脸的快活，小鸟依人地偎在他身上。尼克似有心事，显得心不在焉。

“我看不会的。”他说。

“生上一大堆孩子，那才好呢。”

这时，他们听到了比利的枪声。

“不知他打中了没有。”

“别操那份心了。”特鲁迪说。

说话间，就见比利穿过林子走了过来，肩上扛着猎枪，抓住一只黑松鼠的前爪把它拎在手里。

“瞧，”他说，“个头比猫还大。你们俩干完了吧？”

“你是在哪儿打到的？”

“就是在那边。看见它跳动，我就开了枪。”

“该回家去了。”尼克说。

“还不该呢。”特鲁迪说。

“我得赶回家吃晚饭呢。”

“那好吧。”

“明天还想来打猎吗？”

“好吧。”

“你们可以把松鼠拿回去。”

“好吧。”

“晚饭后还出来吗？”

“不了。”

“你感觉怎样？”

“好着呢。”

“那就好。”

“在我脸上亲亲。”特鲁迪说。

尼克正驾车行驶在公路上，天色在渐渐变黑。对于父亲的事，他已不再苦思冥想了。每当白日将近，他都会把父亲的事搁下不想。天擦黑的这个时候他沉浸在一个人的世界里，一胡思乱想就感到浑身不舒服。每至秋天或初春，慈父的身影都会频频出现于他的脑海。这种季节，小鹬飞临大草原，看得到玉米秆束成捆堆在那里，看得到波光粼粼的湖水，看得到马车，看得到大雁飞行，听得见大雁鸣叫，可以隐身于芦苇丛中打野鸭；记得在一个大雪天，一只老鹰从空中俯冲下来抓帆布篷里的诱鸟，拍翅飞起时，爪子缠在了帆布上——这一幕幕情景都会令他想起自己的父亲。只要走进空无一人的果园，只要踏上刚刚犁过的土地，只要步入小树林，只要攀上山丘或者踏过满地枯草，每当劈柴、取水时，每当走过磨坊、榨苹果汁的作坊、水坝，特别是看到篝火时，父亲的形象总会浮现在他眼前。他所住过的城市并非为他的父亲熟悉，因为他十五岁时便离开家门，没有再和父亲在一起生活。

天气寒冷时，父亲的胡子上会结霜，而热天他则大汗淋漓。他喜欢顶着太阳在地里干活，这倒不是说他不得不这样做，而是因为他喜欢干体力活。尼克则不然，他不喜欢干体力活。他爱父亲，却不爱闻他身上的气味。一次，父亲的一件内衣穿在身上太小了，让他穿，衣服上的气味叫他感到恶心，于是他脱下来投入溪水，上面压了两块石头，回家说衣服丢了。父亲让他穿这件衣服的时候，他就说过上面有气味，父亲却说是才洗过的（此话是真的）。他让父亲自己闻闻，父亲生气地拿过去闻了闻，强调说衣服是干干净净的，没有气味。他钓鱼回来不见了衣服，声称弄丢了。父亲嫌他撒谎，抽了他几鞭子。

事后，他坐在柴房里，敞开着门，给猎枪上了子弹，打开保险，眼睛望着在装了纱窗的阳台上看报的父亲，暗自思忖：“我一枪就可以送他见阎王，要了他的命。”最后，他气消了的时候，想起猎枪还是父亲给他买来的，不由心里感到一阵难过。随即，他摸黑走到了印第安人营地，想摆脱那股气味。家里，只有一个人的气味他爱闻，那就是妹妹的气味。其他的人，他能躲开就躲开。待他抽上了烟，嗅觉也随之变得迟钝了。这倒是件好事。捕鸟的猎犬有灵敏的嗅觉是好事，而人的嗅觉过于灵了不一定好。

“爸爸，你小的时候和印第安人一起去打猎是怎么打的呀？”

“我也说不好。”尼克吃了一惊。他耽于遐想，甚至没注意到儿子已经醒了，不由看了看坐在身旁座位上的儿子。他刚才感到自己是孤身一人，其实儿子就在跟前。不知这种状况持续了多长时间。“我们常常去打黑松鼠，一打就是一天。”他说道，“我父亲一天只给我三发子弹。他说这会叫我精于打猎，说小孩子乱开枪是成不了器的。跟我一道打猎的有个男孩叫比利·吉尔比以及他的妹妹特鲁迪。一年夏天，我们几乎天天都去。”

“印第安人起这样的名字，听上去怪怪的。”

“是呀，是有些。”尼克说。

“给我讲讲他们是怎样的人。”

“他们是奥吉布瓦族人，”尼克说，“是些非常好的人。”

“跟他们在一起，你觉得他们是怎么一种情况？”

“难以说得清。”尼克·亚当斯说。难道能跟儿子讲起她让他初尝到的欢愉吗？难道能讲那两条棕色的丰满的腿、平平的肚皮、坚挺的小乳房、搂得紧紧的胳膊、急速伸来伸去的舌头、单纯的眼以及味道甜美的嘴吗？难道能讲那种涩涩的、紧紧的，却又美美的、湿湿的（有点紧，有点疼，有点胀）感觉吗？那种感觉绵长，似乎永无止境，后来却戛然而止。有只大鸟在林子里飞起，飞起来就像日暮时分的猫头鹰，只不过当时仍是大白天，铁杉树的针叶贴在肚皮上。你只要去印第安人住过的地方，你便可以嗅到他们留下的气味——空酒瓶子以及嗡嗡叫的苍蝇，这些都压不住香草味、炊烟味以及一种类似刚刚剥下的貂皮散发出的气味。不管世人怎样取笑他们，不管他们如何没落，那种感觉是消除不了的。不管他们身上好闻还是难闻，不管他们结局如何，这种感觉依旧。他们结局如何不在话下，反正都免不了走下坡路——昔日状况良好，今日好景不再。

再说说打猎吧。你打下一只飞鸟，如同打下天上所有的飞鸟。飞鸟固然形形色色，飞翔的姿势也各不相同，但是打第一只鸟和打最后一只鸟，那种激动的心情是不变的。他接受这样的启蒙教育，得归功于他的父亲。

“你也许不会喜欢他们，”尼克对儿子说，“但以后你一定会的。”

“爷爷小的时候也和他们生活在一起，是不是？”

“是的。我曾经问他印第安人怎么样，他说他在印第安人中有许多朋友。”

“将来我是不是也和他们住在一起？”

“这我就不知道了。”尼克说，“这得取决于你。”

“我长到多大才能有杆猎枪自己去打猎？”

“如果小心别出事，十二岁就可以了吧。”

“真希望我现在就十二岁了。”

“你很快就会如愿的。”

“爷爷是怎样一个人？我记不清他了，只记得那次从法国回来，他给过我一支气枪和一面美国旗。他是怎样一个人呢？”

“很难形容。他是个神枪手，钓鱼钓得好，眼力极好。”

“难道他比你还棒吗？”

“他的枪法要神多了。他的父亲也是个打飞鸟的神枪手。”

“我敢打赌，他肯定不如你。”

“哦，还是他强些。他打枪出手快，百发百中。看他射击比看任何人都过瘾。对于我的枪法，他总是很不满意。”

“为什么咱们从来没有去给爷爷上过坟？”

“天各一方，住的地方距离太远。”

“在法国这就不是个问题。法国人都是去上坟的。我觉得应该去给爷爷上上坟。”

“找个时间去吧。”

“但愿咱们不会住得天各一方，那样你死了以后，弄得我给你上不了坟。”

“此事可以从长计议。”

“你不觉得家里人死了都应该埋在一个比较方便的地方吗？可以埋在法国嘛。那该多好呀。”

“我不想被埋在法国。”尼克说。

“哦，那就在美国国内找块方便的墓地吧。能不能都埋在牧场上呢？”

“这想法不错。”

“这样，在去牧场的路上，我就可以顺便为爷爷上坟了。”

“你想得挺周到的。”

“哦，给爷爷连一次坟也没上过，总觉得不舒服。”

“会去的，”尼克说，“放心吧，咱们一定去。”

————————————————————

(1) 尼古拉斯的简称。

(2) 英语：兽奸犯。

(3) 英语：性骚扰。

(4) 法国籍波兰女歌唱家。

(5) 一种水鸟。

(6) 万圣节的吉祥灯。

(7) 和尼克一样，也是尼古拉斯的昵称。

海上的一趟生意

哈瓦那的清晨，流浪汉仍躺在墙根睡大觉，送冰车尚未把酒吧需要的冰块送去——此时此刻的状况你想象得出来吗？哦，当时我们从码头穿过广场去旧金山明珠咖啡馆喝咖啡，只看见一个乞丐已经醒了，正在泉眼那儿饮水。可是，待我们走进咖啡馆坐定，却见那些人当中已经有三个在等我们了。

我们落座后，他们当中的一个走了过来。

“怎么样？”他问道。

“我无能为力。”我告诉他说，“我倒是很想帮这个忙，可我昨夜就告诉你们了，说过我无法从命。”

“你可以开个价嘛。”

“这跟价钱不着边，而是我办不到。情况就是如此。”

另外的两个早已走了过来，他们几个站在那里，面露愁容。他们看上去都是挺不错的人，能帮忙我还是愿意出手相助的。

“每个人给你一千块。”一个操一口流利英语的人说。

“请别这么说话，让我觉得自己龌龊。”我说道，“我说的是实话，的确帮不上忙。”

“将来时局变了，这会对你很有好处的。”

“这我知道。我深表同情，只是此忙实在帮不上。”

“为什么？”

“我得靠这条船糊口。没有了船，就没有了口粮。”

“有钱在口袋里，可以再买一条嘛。”

“进了监狱就买不成了。”

他们一定以为费些口舌还是可以把我说得回心转意的，只听那位继续说道：

“你将拿到三千块钱，以后有你的好日子过的。目前的局势是长不了的。”

“听着，”我说，“我不管这儿谁当总统，只认定一点：凡是会说话的，绝不送到美国去。”

“你的意思是我们会把此事讲出去？”他们当中一个一直没开口的人说道，露出一脸的怒容。

“我指的是任何会说话的。”

“你以为我们是长舌头(1)吗？”

“没那个意思。”

“你知道长舌头(2)是什么意思吗？”

“知道，指的是舌头很长的人。”

“你知道我们怎样对付这类人吗？”

“不必撂狠话。”我说，“是你们找我帮忙，又不是我求你们。”

“闭上你的嘴，潘乔。”先前说话的那个呵斥这位怒容满面的说。

“他说咱们会把此事讲出去。”潘乔说。

“听着，”我说道，“我说的是：凡是会说话的，绝不送到美国去。装在坛子里的酒不会说话。酒坛子也不会说话。还有许多东西都不会说话。唯独人会说话。”

“你说中国人会不会说话？”潘乔恶声恶气地问。

“会，可是我听不懂。”我回答。

“如此看来，你是不答应啦？”

“昨夜已直言相告，说过难以从命。”

“你不会讲出去吧？”潘乔说。

他可能是产生了误解，才窝了一肚子的火。另外，希望变成了失望，这大概也是叫他生气的原因。对于他的话，我甚至懒得回答。

“你该不会是个长舌头(3)吧？”他问道，语气仍恶狠狠的。

“我想不会是的。”

“怎么？这是威胁吗？”

“听着，”我说道，“大清早的，别这么凶嘛。我相信你割断过很多人的喉咙。我咖啡都没有喝呢，饶了我吧。”

“这么说，你认为我割断过很多人的喉咙？”

“算啦，”我说道，“我才不管你割谁的喉咙呢。生意归生意，你能不能别发火？”

“我现在憋了一肚子火，”他说，“真想杀了你。”

“哈，得啦，”我说道，“别把话说过了头。”

“到此为止，潘乔。”最先说话的那个喝止道。随后他又对我说，“很遗憾。我还是希望你能送送我们。”

“我也很遗憾，恕难从命。”

那三个人拂袖而去，朝着门外走去，我目送着他们。他们看上去是几个挺不错的年轻人，穿着挺不错的衣服，都没有戴帽子，似乎很有钱。至少，他们说起话像是很有钱，操一口只有有钱的古巴人才会讲的流利英语。

他们当中有两个像是兄弟，再一个就是潘乔。潘乔个头稍高，派头跟另两位相似，细条条的身材，衣着考究，头发亮光光的。他说话不饶人，可我觉得他并非一个难缠的人，可能是情绪太激动才出言不逊。

他们出了门向右拐，这时我看见一辆窗户紧闭的汽车从广场冲了过来。随后，咖啡馆的一块窗户玻璃砰的一声碎了，一颗子弹射进来，打在右首靠墙放的酒柜上的一排酒瓶上。接着又听见啪啪啪几声枪响，墙根的那些酒瓶子被打得碎片乱飞。

我一个箭步躲到了左边的吧台后面，从那儿可以从吧台后探头向外望。那辆汽车已经停了下来，有两个家伙蹲下身子躲在车后，一个手持汤普森枪，另一个拿的是锯短了的自动式猎枪。手持汤普森枪的是个黑人，另一个身穿白颜色的司机工作服。

刚从咖啡馆出去的年轻人中，有一个摊开四肢，面朝下扑倒在人行道上，就在那扇被子弹击中的大窗户的跟前。另外的两个躲到了一辆停放在隔壁丘纳德酒吧门前的“热带啤酒”送冰车后。拉车的马，一匹中弹后连着马具倒在了地上，四蹄乱蹬，另一匹死命挣扎，想挣脱辕架。

一位年轻人从车尾开枪还击，子弹打在人行道的路面上，然后弹起。手持汤普森枪的黑人匍匐在地，脸几乎都贴到了路面上，贴着地面给马车尾部送去了一梭子子弹，车后有个年轻人应声倒在人行道上，脑袋刚好伸出人行道的边缘。他双手抱头躺在那儿。那个拿猎枪的司机朝他开了几枪，黑人趁机给弹仓里又装满了子弹，随后射出去一阵弹雨，看得见子弹倾泻在路面上，像是银水四溅。

另一个年轻人拽住中弹的那个，将他拖回马车后。我看见黑人把脸又贴到地面准备扫射。就在这时，只见潘乔从马车后冲出，蹿到了那匹没有倒下去的马的背后。随即，他又从那儿闪出，脸色惨白如纸，双手握紧一支大型号的鲁格尔手枪，一枪射中了那个司机。接着，他走上前去对着黑人开枪，两颗子弹从黑人的头顶飞过，还有一颗打低了。

有一枪打在了汽车轮胎上，只见轮胎里的气扑哧扑哧外泄，把路面上的尘土都吹了起来，升起一团尘云。他走到距离黑人有十英尺远的地方，后者用汤普森枪给了他一枪，打在了他的肚子上。那肯定是黑人的最后一颗子弹了，因为我看见他射击后就把枪扔了。潘乔扑通一屁股坐在了地上，身子向前一栽。他抓住鲁格尔手枪不松手，还试图直起身来，然而却连头也抬不起来了。黑人捡起司机倒地时滚落到汽车轮子旁的猎枪，一枪就把潘乔的脑袋崩掉了半个。好一个黑人！

见跟前有瓶开了瓶的酒，我拿起来就喝了一口，也不顾喝的是什么酒。刚才那一幕叫我觉得心里很不舒服。从吧台后边我溜进厅堂后面的厨房，再从那儿出去，一溜烟跑了。我擦着广场的边绕着走，对于咖啡馆门前迅速聚集的人群甚至回头看也没看一眼，穿过码头的大门，上了码头，然后登上了船。

租船的那个人已在船上等候了。我把发生的事情跟他讲了讲。

“埃迪在哪儿？”租船人约翰逊问我。

“枪战一开始，我就再也没见过他。”

“你看他会不会被打中呢？”

“绝对不会。告诉你，射进咖啡馆里的子弹全都打在了酒柜上。当时汽车是从他们身后开过来的，第一个是在外边的窗户前中弹的。枪手冲过来的角度就像这样……”

“你像是对什么都很有把握似的。”他说。

“我在现场看着呢。”我说道。

说到这里，我一抬头见埃迪从码头过来了，个头显得比以前高了些，样子也邋遢了些。看他走路的姿势，像是全身的骨头都散了架似的。

“他来了。”

他在清晨历来无精打采，而此刻却是一副惨象。

“你到哪儿了？”我问他。

“在地上趴着呢。”

“都看见了吗？”约翰逊问他。

“还是别提了吧，约翰逊先生，”埃迪说，“光想一想就让人感到不舒服。”

“最好喝上一杯压压惊。”约翰逊对他说完，又问我道：“怎么样，该出发了吧？”

“你决定吧。”

“今天天气怎么样？”

“跟昨天一样。也许会好一些。”

“那咱就走吧。”

“好的。鱼饵一拿来就出发。”

我们驾驶着这条船到河里钓了三个星期的鱼。他事先倒是给过我一百块钱到领事馆办理各种手续、买食物和加油，除此之外再也没见他拿出过一分钱。船上乱七八糟的杂费由我出，他则每天花三十五块钱的租船费。他夜里在一家旅馆住宿，早晨到船上来。租船是由埃迪牵的线，于是我还得把他也带上，一天付给他四块钱的辛苦费。

“我得给船加些油。”我对约翰逊说。

“好的。”

“加油需要用些钱。”

“多少？”

“一加仑是两毛八。怎么也需要加四十加仑的油。总共十一块零两毛钱。”

他掏出了十五块钱。

“剩下的钱是不是需要买些啤酒和冰块？”我问他。

“好的。”他说，“从我的欠账里扣除就是了。”

我心想，让他欠三个星期的账，时间是长了些，可他既然能还得清，又有什么关系呢？按理，每个星期都应该清账的。可是我却让他欠一个月后再还钱。我是有些失算，不过先拿到一些租钱也还是叫人高兴的。只是最近几天他令我有些不安，不过我不愿把心里的想法说出去，怕把事情弄僵。如果他付得起钱，就叫他租吧，租的时间越长越好。

“来一瓶啤酒吧？”他打开啤酒箱问我。

“不了。谢谢。”

就在这时，去买鱼饵的黑人回来了，从码头上走了过来。我告诉埃迪准备解缆起航。

等到买鱼饵的黑人上了船，我们就启航，驶出了港口。黑人用作鱼饵的是几条鲭鱼，先把鱼钩从鱼的嘴里穿过鱼鳃，再将鱼钩从鱼身的一侧扎入，从另一侧取出，把合拢的鱼嘴绑在铁丝导线上，将鱼钩也绑牢以避免脱钩，如此一来，鱼饵就能保持平稳，不至于打旋。

他是个真正的黑透了的黑人，脑子够用，却老是郁郁寡欢，衬衣里的脖子上挂着一串伏都教(4)的念珠，头戴一顶旧草帽。他在船上只喜欢干两件事：睡觉和看报。不过，他做得一手好鱼饵，动作很麻利。

“这种做鱼饵的活你干不了吗，船长？”约翰逊问我。

“干得了，先生。”

“那你为什么还要弄个黑人来？”

“等到大鱼群出现了，你就知道为什么了。”我告诉他。

“此话怎讲？”

“这个黑人的手脚比我快。”

“埃迪干不了吗？”

“干不了，先生。”

“我觉得这是一笔没有必要的花销。”他一天付给黑人一块钱，黑人拿上钱夜夜都去跳伦巴舞(5)。看得出，此时他已困意蒙了。

“雇他来是有必要的。”我说。

说话间，我们的船已经驶过了停泊在卡巴纳斯码头前的那些配有鱼舱的渔船，驶过了那些停下来在岬角旁的石头海床上捕捉双色笛鲷(6)的小艇。我掌舵，将船开向海湾深处，那儿远看似一条黑线。埃迪把两个大大的引料(7)抛了出去，黑人已给三根钓竿装好了鱼饵。

湾流接近完美，行驶到跟前时，看得见湾流里的水几乎呈紫色，漩涡很多。从东边吹来轻轻的海风。我们的船惊起了不少飞鱼，有的个头大得飞起来像架飞机，像是一幅林德伯格(8)驾机飞越大西洋的画面。

大个头飞鱼的出现是个好兆头。放眼望去，可以看到一小簇一小簇发蔫发黄的马尾藻，说明湾流的主流已近在眼前。前方有海鸟在追食一群小金枪鱼。不时有鱼儿跃出水面——都是些小鱼，每条只有两三磅重。

“你随时都可以放入钓竿了。”我对约翰逊说。

于是，他系好保险带和保险绳，将那根大钓竿放进了水里——钓竿上装有耐寒卷轴，卷轴上缠着六百码长的三十六号鱼线。我回头看看，见他下的鱼饵状况良好，随着海波一上一下的，那两个引料也时沉时浮。船速不快不慢，差不多刚好。我转了一下舵盘，将它开进了湾流。

“你把钓竿插在椅子上的插座里，”我对他说，“不用把钓竿沉甸甸地握在手里。鱼线不要扯紧，这样鱼上钩时可以让它拖着走。否则，上钩的鱼一使劲，会把你拉进海里的。”

每天我都要重复这些话，但我不厌其烦。租船钓鱼的客人，五十个人里，恐怕只有一个是懂行的。即便是懂行的，也会脑子糊涂，买的鱼线不够结实，钓到大鱼就吃不消了。

“天气怎么样？”他问我。

“好得不能再好了。”我告诉他说。此话不虚，天气的确不错。

我把舵盘交给了黑人，让他把船沿着湾流的边朝东开。交代完，我回到了约翰逊身边，见他正坐在那儿观鱼饵随波沉浮。

“需要我再放入一根钓竿吗？”我问他。

“我看不需要了。”他说，“我喜欢自己做，自己钓住鱼，自己和它搏斗，自己将它擒到手。”

“那好吧。”我说道，“需要不需要埃迪下钓竿？鱼上了钩再交给你，由你来钓它上来。”

“不需要。”他说，“一根钓竿就够了。”

“那好吧。”

黑人驾着船仍在湾流外行驶，我一看，原来是他在上流不远处发现了一大群飞鱼。回头望去，只见哈瓦那在阳光下显得颇为壮观，一艘轮船正出了港口驶过岬角。

“看来你今天能钓到大鱼放手一搏了，约翰逊先生。”我说道。

“也该钓到了。”他说，“咱们钓鱼有多长时间了？”

“到今天正好三个星期。”

“时间够长的了。”

“这些鱼很滑稽。”我说道，“你怎么盼它们都不来。可是，不来则已，一来就是一大片，而且持续不断。如果现在不见个影子，那恐怕就不来了。夜里月光好，湾流也不错，还会有好风，按说它们会来的。”

“刚来的时候，见过一些小鱼呢。”

“是的。”我说道，“正如我所言，小鱼少了，不再出现了，接着就该大鱼登场了。”

“你们当船长的再怎么都一样。鱼群来早来晚，风向顺不顺，月光亮不亮，你们照样是收钱的。”

“糟糕的是，”我说道，“鱼群不是来得太早，就是来得太晚，风向也常常不对劲。遇上一个顺风顺水的好日子，却偏偏没有租客来。”

“你觉得今天是个好日子吗？”

“这个嘛，”我说道，“反正我今天够忙活了。我敢说也会叫你忙个够。”

“但愿如此。”他说。

接下来，我们静下心来守候。埃迪到了船头那儿，一歪身子躺下了。我则直直站在那儿观察鱼情。黑人连连打盹，昏昏欲睡，我还得用眼睛瞅着他。我敢说，这几个夜晚他没少折腾。

“船长，能不能给我拿瓶啤酒来？”约翰逊问我。

“好的，先生。”我边说边伸手从冰块下给他取了瓶冰镇啤酒。

“你也喝一瓶吧？”他问道。

“不了，先生。”我回答说，“晚上再喝吧。”

我打开啤酒递给他。就在这时，我看见一条棕褐色的大鱼朝着做鱼饵用的鲭鱼冲了过来，头和肩露出水面，背上的鱼鳍像根长矛，比人的胳膊还长，腰身圆鼓鼓，看上去就像是锯木厂的原木。

“把渔线松开！”我吼了一声。

“它还没有上钩呢。”约翰逊说。

“那就等一等。”

大鱼是从深水里蹿出来的，一口没有咬住鲭鱼。我心里有数，知道它不会甘心，还会拐回来的。

“做好准备，它一咬钩，就放线。”

接下来，我瞧见大鱼在水下从背后摸了上来。可以看见它的鱼鳍张开，像是紫色的翅膀，棕褐色的身子上有着紫色的条纹。它看上去像是一艘潜水艇，鱼鳍的顶梢突出水面，划破层层碧波。随即，它冲到了鱼饵的后边，它的“长矛”也露了出来，像是还抖了抖水。

“让它把鱼钩咬死。”我说道。

约翰逊把手从卷轴上拿开，卷轴飞快地开始放线。那条大马林鱼一转身没入水里。当它侧身向海岸那边快速游去时，整个儿一览无余，银光闪闪的。

“把线稍微收紧一些，”我说，“不要收得太多。”

他用卷轴开始收鱼线。

“不要收得太多。”我说。看得见鱼线斜着在绷紧。

“好，该收紧了，让它知道厉害。”我说，“给它点颜色瞧瞧。让它好好跳一跳。”

约翰逊收了收鱼线，又回来查看钓竿的情况。

“叫它吃点苦头。”我说道，“让钩子钩紧它，多拉几下。”

他拉鱼钩，一连拉了好几次。此时，钓竿向下弯，卷轴开始发出吱扭吱扭的响声。哗的一声，大鱼一跃跃到了空中，阳光下通体银光闪闪，落入水里时发出巨大的声响，像是一匹马被人推下了悬崖坠地时发出的声音。

“把线松一些。”我吩咐道。

“它跑了。”约翰逊说。

“哪里的话。”我说道，“你赶快把线放松些就是了。”

随后便见鱼线松了些。大鱼再次跃出水面时，是在船的后面，接着便向远处游去。不一会儿，它又出水了，溅得白浪滚滚。可以看见，鱼钩钩住了它的腮帮子。它身上的条纹清晰可见。多么棒的一条鱼，此刻全身显银色带有紫色条纹，圆滚滚像根原木。

“它跑啦。”约翰逊说。鱼线呈松弛状态。

“收线吧。”我说。“钩子钩得紧紧的。开足马力，把船朝前开！”后一句话是喊给黑人听的。

大鱼又露出水面一两次，直撅撅的像根木柱，排山倒海向我们冲来，每次落入水里时，溅起老高的水柱。鱼线被扯紧，只见它又朝着岸边游去，一路上身子翻来翻去。

“它要溜之大吉了。”我说，“只要不脱钩，就追得上它。把渔线放开，咱们有的是鱼线。”

马林鱼管自向西北方向游去——大个头的鱼都是这么个劲，也不顾身上还有鱼钩呢。它一蹿就是老远，弄得浪花四溅，像是一艘快艇行驶在大海上。我们驾船追去。我让船打了个转，使它处于船尾旁边的位置（此时已由我掌舵），一边冲着约翰逊大喊大叫，让他别拖得太紧，赶快收线。突然，只见钓竿猛地一弹，鱼线一下子松了。鱼线在水里有一股拉力，变松了的时候，一般是看不出来的。可是我却看出来了。

“这次它真跑了。”我说道。大鱼一蹦一蹿的，不停地跳跃前进，直至从视野里消失。没说的，这是一条非常棒的鱼。

“我仍能感觉得到它的拉力呀。”约翰逊说。

“那是因为鱼线本身的重量而产生的。”

“卷轴几乎转动不了了。也许它已经死了吧。”

“你睁眼瞧瞧嘛，”我说，“它活蹦乱跳的。”只见大鱼在半英里开外乱扑腾，掀起冲天的浪花。

我试了试约翰逊的卷轴，发现他把螺丝拧得太紧，线都扯不出来了，有扯断的危险。

“我不是说过，叫你别扯得太紧吗？”

“它在一个劲朝外拉呢。”

“朝外拉又怎么样？”

“所以我就拧紧了呀。”

“听着，”我说道，“鱼一上钩，如果你不把线放松，就会被扯断的。光靠鱼线是拉不住大鱼的。它们拉，你就得放。鱼线是不能扯得太紧的。靠打鱼为生的渔民用的是鱼叉绳，即便如此也不敢扯得太紧。咱们钓鱼的，钓上的大鱼一旦扯着线跑，就只能驾着船跟在屁股后面追，等到它们跑不动了就会停下来，那时你再扯紧鱼线，把渔线朝回收。”

“这么说，假如鱼线不断，便可以将其捕获吗？”

“很有可能。”

“它总不能一直撑下去吧？”

“事情很难说。战斗一开始，非得等它挣扎不动了，才万事皆休。”

“好。这次非得抓住一条不可。”

“你得先把卷轴上的线整理好。”我告诉他说。

我们钩上了大鱼，又失去了它，自始至终都没有把埃迪吵醒。此时他却醒了，来到了船尾。

“发生什么事啦？”他问道。

埃迪以前不酗酒，在船上是个好帮手，而今他屁用都不顶。我瞧了一眼他的熊样：高个子，脸颊凹陷，耷拉着嘴唇，眼角沾着白色眼屎，头发被太阳晒得没有了色泽。我知道他一醒来，就会犯酒瘾的。

“你喝瓶啤酒吧。”我对他说。他毫不客气地从箱子里取出一瓶，一饮而尽。

“哦，约翰逊先生，”他说道，“我看我还是继续睡我的觉吧。谢谢你的啤酒，先生。”

埃迪真是麻木不仁。我们钓上钓不上鱼他根本不往心里去。

中午时分，我们又钓上一条，结果又溜掉了。只见这条大鱼一挣扎甩掉了钓钩，把钓钩甩到空中有三十英尺高的地方。

“这次又是哪个地方出岔了？”约翰逊问。

“没出岔子。”我说，“是它一甩把钓钩甩掉了。”

“约翰逊先生，”一觉醒来，又喝了瓶啤酒的埃迪说道，“约翰逊先生，只怪你运气不佳。也许，在情场上你能交上好运呢。约翰逊先生，今晚咱们出去玩玩怎么样？”说完，他回去，倒头又睡了。

大约在下午四点钟，我们逆着湾流返航，渐渐靠近岸边，湾流之水犹如驱动水磨的水一样哗哗流淌，太阳晒在我们的脊背上。就在这时，一条马林鱼咬上了约翰逊的鱼饵，黑黑的颜色，个头之大我一辈子都没有见到过。在这之前，我们用毛鱿鱼做饵钓到了四条小金枪鱼，黑人拿其中的一条装在钓钩上当鱼饵，拖在船后沉沉的，但是却掀起来大大的浪花。

约翰逊老是握着钓竿，胳膊都累酸了，于是干脆取掉卷轴套，这样就能把钓竿放在膝上了。由于鱼饵大，拖力大，他两手拽卷轴的线，累得不得了，趁我不注意把螺栓拧紧了。这种情况我一直没发现。我看着他拿钓竿的样子心里不舒服，可是又不愿对他唠叨个没完。再说，只要螺栓没拧紧，必要时就可以放线，不会出危险的。只不过这样钓鱼未免有些吊儿郎当了。

当时我在掌舵，驾船行驶在湾流的边缘，到了老水泥厂对面的海域，这里的水很深，紧靠岸边，漩涡一个接一个，小鱼特别多。突然，海水哗的一声四溅开去，像爆炸了一颗深水炸弹。接着，一条黑色的马林鱼出现了，露出了鱼鳍、鱼眼，露出了一个血盆大口和一个巨大无比的紫黑色脑袋。

它背上的鱼鳍完全露出了水面，看上去有一艘帆船那么高。它一甩镰刀状的尾巴，朝着金枪鱼饵扑了过来。尖尖的鱼嘴像棒球棒，向上噘起，撕咬金枪鱼时，简直把海水都劈成了两半。它通体紫黑色，眼睛有碗口般大。它简直就是一个巨无霸。我敢打赌，它准有一千磅重。

我大喊一声，让约翰逊赶快放线。可是，未等我话出口，就见约翰逊离了椅子，飞到了半空，就好像被吊车吊起来了一样。刹那间，他紧抓住钓竿不松手，钓竿弯得像一张弓，结果钓竿的柄戳在了他的肚子上，钓竿上的配件纷纷落水。

都怪他把螺丝拧得太紧，大鱼袭来，将他从椅子上吊起，他如何能顶得住呢。结果，钓竿柄别在了他的腿下，而钓竿扫过膝盖，要是他没有把卷轴套取掉，恐怕连他本人也被扯进大海里了。

我关掉引擎，回到船尾看究竟，只见他捂着肚子上被钓竿柄击打过的地方。

“看来今天的戏演完了。”我说道。

“那是什么玩意儿？”他问我。

“是条黑色马林鱼。”我说。

“怎么成了这样？”

“咱们把账算一下吧。”我说，“卷轴钱是两百五十块。按现在的价钱更高哩。钓竿花掉我五十五块。三十六号鱼线总共是六百码差一点。”

这时，埃迪拍了拍他的背说：“约翰逊先生，你的运气不好呀。我活了这么大，从没见过这种怪事。”

“别说风凉话，你这个酒鬼。”我呵斥道。

“听我说，约翰逊先生，”埃迪自管自地说了下去，“这种怪事可是百年不遇呀，从来都没有看到过。”

“我被大鱼拖住了，你说我该如何是好？”约翰逊说。

“跟鱼搏斗，这不正是你想要的嘛。”我开口说道，语气中有许多的懊恼。

“它的个头太大了。”约翰逊说，“哎，跟它搏斗，有我的苦头吃的。”

“实不相瞒，”我说道，“这么大的鱼，弄不好会要你的命的。”

“这种大鱼也是有人抓住的。”

“那可是些懂行的人呀。而且，别以为他们会少吃苦头。”

“我见过一幅照片，上面有个女孩抓住了一条大鱼。”

“此事不虚。”我说，“但那还属于钓鱼一类——让大鱼吞下鱼饵，拉出它的肠子肚子，结果它就浮上来死去了。我所说的是让鱼钩钩在鱼嘴上，一路拖着它走。”

“哦，”约翰逊说道，“鱼的个头太大。抓这种鱼享受不到乐趣，何必要自找苦吃呢？”

“说得好，约翰逊先生。”埃迪在一旁说，“抓这种鱼享受不到乐趣，何必要自找苦吃呢？这是大实话，约翰逊先生。你算说到点子上了。抓这种鱼享受不到乐趣，何必要自找苦吃呢？”

见了刚才的场面，我此刻仍余悸未消，再加上损失了钓具，心里极不畅快，对于他们的话根本听不进去，于是吩咐黑人把船开到岬角那儿去。我一句话也没说，而他们俩也干坐在那儿——埃迪坐在椅子上，手里拎着瓶酒，约翰逊也拎着瓶酒。

“船长，”过了一会儿，约翰逊说道，“能不能给我调杯酒——威士忌加苏打水？”

我给他调了一杯，一声未吭，然后给我自己来了杯没掺水的。我心里暗想，这个约翰逊没出息，钓鱼钓了十五天，好不容易遇上一条别人一年都难得一见的大鱼，却让它跑了，连我整套的钓具也不见了，出尽了洋相，但他可好，竟然自得其乐地坐在那儿和一个酒鬼推杯换盏呢。

船靠了码头，黑人仍逗留不去。

我问约翰逊：“明天还去不去？”

“我看就算啦。”约翰逊说，“这样的钓法揪心揪肺的。”

“能不能付钱让这位黑人走？”

“该付给他多少钱？”

“一块钱。如果想给小费也可以。”

约翰逊给了黑人一块钱的工钱和两枚二十分的古巴币的小费。

“这是什么钱？”黑人拿着两枚硬币问我。

“是小费。”我用西班牙语告诉他，“你的活儿干完了。这是他的一点小意思。”

“明天就不来了吗？”

“不用来了。”

黑人收拾起他的用来捆扎鱼饵的麻线团和墨镜，戴上草帽，连声招呼也不打就走了。他虽然是个黑人，却根本不把我们放在眼里。

“你打算何时结账，约翰逊先生？”我启口问道。

“明天上午我到银行去，”约翰逊说，“咱们明天下午结吧。”

“你知道该是多少天吗？”

“十五天呗。”

“不对。加上今天，有十六天，再算上两头各一天，总共十八天。另外还有今天损失的钓竿、卷轴和鱼线。”

“钓具的钱不该我出。”

“错了，先生。是你弄丢的，就该你出。”

“每天的租赁费我都付清了。就不该再出了。”

“错了，先生。”我说道，“假如是鱼弄坏的，就不怪你，那会是另一码子事。这次只怪你粗心大意，才导致损失掉了整套的钓具。”

“那是大鱼把它硬从我手里拖走的。”

“还不是因为你把螺丝拧紧了，没有把鱼竿放在插座上。”

“你这样乱收费，好没有情由。”

“如果你租了辆汽车，汽车掉下了悬崖。你说你该不该赔偿损失？”

“如果我坐在车里，就不该赔偿。”约翰逊说。

“说得妙，约翰逊先生。”埃迪喝彩道，“你明白其中的意思了吗，船长？如果他在车里，那就是车毁人亡。他就不用赔偿了。说得真妙！”

我没搭理这个酒鬼。“对于钓竿、卷轴和鱼线的损失，你该付两百九十五块钱。”我对约翰逊说。

“哦，这不合情理哟。”他说，“不过，你既然这么说，咱们各让一点怎么样？”

“再怎么你付的钱也不能少于三百六十块。鱼线的钱就不收你的了。那么大的鱼自然会把线全都拖走，责任不在于你。如果不是个酒鬼在这儿，而是别人，就一定会告诉你我对你是极为公道的。我知道这笔钱似乎是很大的数目，可我买钓具也花了大笔的钱呢。不舍得花钱买最好的钓具，哪能惬意地钓鱼。”

“约翰逊先生，他说我是个酒鬼，也许我就是酒鬼。不过，我得说他是公道的，既公道又合情理。”埃迪在一旁帮腔说。

“我就不再争了。”约翰逊最后说道，“我付钱就是了——即便我并不同意你的说法。总共十八天，每天船租三十五块，再加上两百九十五块的钓具钱。”

“你付过一百块了。”我说道，“我把花费列一张清单，吃剩下的食物不算在内。来回路上的用度得由你掏腰包。”

“这也算合理。”约翰逊说。

“实不相瞒，约翰逊先生，”埃迪说道，“你要是知道他对外乡人要价要得有多狠，就会明白这不仅仅是合理了。你知道这算什么吗？这是特殊待遇！船长待你亲如爹娘。”

“我明天去银行一趟，下午来结账，后天乘船离开。”

“你可以和我们一起回去，省一张船票。”

“不了，”他说，“乘轮船走能节省些时间。”

“那好吧。”我说道，“一起干一杯怎么样？”

“好的。”约翰逊说，“你现在对我心里还有气吗？”

“哪能有气呢，先生。”我说道。

随后，我们三个坐在船尾觥筹交错，一道喝了一通加了苏打水的威士忌。

次日，我在船上忙活了一上午，给主机加了油，又干了些七零八碎的活。中午时分，我去住宅区的一家中餐馆进餐——在那儿花四毛钱就能美美吃上一顿。吃完饭，我买了些东西带回家给妻子和三个女儿。其中包括香水、几把扇子和两个高高的发梳。采购完，我拐进多诺万酒馆喝了杯啤酒，跟老板聊了一会，然后徒步走回旧金山码头，一路上又进了三四家酒馆饮酒。在丘纳德酒吧遇见弗兰基，请他喝了几杯，然后心情愉悦地回到船上。上了船，我发现口袋里只剩下了四毛钱。回船上时，弗兰基也跟来了，于是我们两人坐在那儿等约翰逊。我从冰块箱子里取出几瓶冰镇酒，和弗兰基一道慢斟慢饮。

埃迪一夜没露面，白天一天也没见他的影子。不过我知道，一旦他无法再赊账，早晚都会来的。多诺万告诉我，说埃迪和约翰逊昨晚到他的酒馆坐了一会儿，埃迪请客喝酒还赊了账。我和弗兰基继续等他们，我心里升起了疑团，怀疑约翰逊不会来了。我曾经在码头上留过话，说见到他就让他来船上等我。可码头上的人说他一直未来。我却仍未死心，想着他大概昨夜回旅馆晚了，今天恐怕到中午才会起床。银行下午三点半关门。我们眼看着航班都起飞了。五点半的时候，我已经高兴不起来了，心里急得直打鼓。

到了六点钟，我打发弗兰基到旅馆去看他在不在。我仍心存侥幸，觉得他很可能出去找乐子去了，要不然就是在旅馆里，身体不舒服卧在床上呢。我等啊等，等到很晚的时候。我等得心急火燎，因为他还欠我八百二十五块钱呢。

弗兰基去了大约有半个多小时。他回来时，只见他步履匆匆，还一个劲地摇着头。

“他搭乘航班走了。”他说。

好呀，真是把事情做绝了。领事馆已关门，而我身上只有四毛钱。估计航班此时已到了迈阿密了。我连发封电报的钱都没有了。约翰逊先生真是把我逼上了绝路。都怪我疏忽大意了。我早应该提防着。

“事已至此，”我对弗兰基说，“就不管它了，咱们干一杯，喝上一杯冰镇啤酒。这还是约翰逊先生掏钱买的呢。”总共还剩下三瓶啤酒，都是“热带”牌的。

弗兰基和我一样觉得心里发堵。我也不知道他是否真的心里不痛快，但从表面看的确如此。他不时拍我的脊背，把头摇来摇去的。

现实很清楚：我已经一贫如洗。五百三十块钱的租船费已化为泡影。要重新购置钓具，没有三百五十块是绝对不行的。我心想，在码头周围晃悠的帮仔，其中有几个得知此事，不知会多高兴呢。那些“海螺”(9)一定会乐得不得了。就在昨天，只要送三个外国人去基斯群岛，就可以赚三千块钱，可我却一口回绝了。其实，不一定去基斯群岛，只要把他们送出这个国家即可。

这下可好了。接下来该怎么办呢？去贩运一趟酒吧，得有钱先把酒买下，再说现在贩运酒无利可图。如今，城里酒馆遍地开花，买酒的人却寥若晨星。回家去吧，身无分文。留下来吧，一个夏天都得饿肚子，真是上天无路入地无门。更惨的是，一家人还等着我养活呢。出入关口的费用来的时候交过了。代理人一般都是预先收取费用，然后帮你进关和出关。天呀，我就连给船加油的钱也没有了。真是到了山穷水尽的地步。约翰逊先生真缺德！

“得找个贩运的活儿，弗兰基，”我说，“挣点钱以解燃眉之急。”

“我想想办法看。”弗兰基说。他老在岸边转悠，平时干些零活，耳朵聋得厉害，一到晚上就酗酒。不过，比他更为忠诚，比他心眼更好的人，你恐怕见都没见过。自从我一来此地谋生，就跟他认识了，他多次帮过我装货。后来我有了游艇，做起租船的生意，招揽顾客来古巴钓鱼，常在码头和咖啡馆见到他。他好像是个哑巴，见人不说话，而是莞尔一笑——其实，那是因为他耳朵聋的缘故。

“贩运什么货物都可以？”弗兰基问。

“是的。”我说，“我现在不能挑三拣四的。”

“什么货物都可以？”

“是的。”

“我去想想办法吧。”弗兰基说，“在哪里找你？”

“我到明珠咖啡馆去。”我告诉他说，“得把肚子填饱。”

在明珠咖啡馆，花两毛五就可以饱餐一顿。菜单上的菜全都是一毛一份，除了汤收五分。我和弗兰基一道走到了咖啡馆，然后分手，我进去了，他则继续前行。临别，他握了握我的手，又在我的背上拍了拍。

“别发愁，”他说道，“我弗兰基足智多谋，懂行情，就是爱喝酒，口袋里没钱。不过，我够朋友讲义气。别发愁。”

“再见，弗兰基。”我说，“你也别发愁，伙计。”

说完，我进了明珠咖啡馆，拣一张桌子坐下。此前被子弹打碎的窗户玻璃已换上了新的，样酒柜也修好了。一群西班牙人在吧台喝酒，也有几个吃饭的。一张桌子玩起了多米诺骨牌。我点了份黑豆汤和一份土豆炖牛肉，花了一毛五，又要了瓶哈土依(10)啤酒，总共两毛五。我和服务员聊起枪战的事，对方缄口不语。他们全都把胆吓破了。

吃完饭，我把身子向后一靠，抽了一根烟，满肚子的忧愁。突然，只见弗兰基走进了门，后边跟着个人。我心想，是“黄货”。原来是要我运“黄货”！

“这位是辛先生。”弗兰基说，脸上堆着笑容。他办事实在太麻利了，为此他很是得意。

“你好！”辛先生说。

这位辛先生看上去恐怕是我所见过的最为圆滑的人了。他虽为中国人，但说话的派头倒像个英国佬，身穿白西装，配一件丝绸衬衣，脖系黑领带，头戴一顶价值一百二十五块钱的巴拿马帽。

“喝杯咖啡好吗？”他问我。

“乐意奉陪。”

“谢谢。”辛先生说，“跟前没有别的人吧？”

“全都是咖啡馆的客人，别无他人。”我告诉他说。

“这就好。”辛先生说，“你有一条船吧？”

“有一条三十八英尺长的船，”我说，“一百马力的，科马斯船厂(11)制造。”

“哦，”辛先生说，“我还以为是条小帆船呢。”

“我的船装两百六十五个货箱绰绰有余。”

“愿意租给我吗？”

“你出什么价？”

“你不必亲自去。我提供船长和船员。”

“这可不行。”我说，“船到哪儿我就跟到哪儿。”

“明白了。”辛先生说，“能不能让我们单独谈谈？”他转过头对弗兰基说。弗兰基一副兴趣盎然的样子，冲他一笑。

“他耳朵聋。”我说道，“他的英语也不怎么样。”

“明白了。”辛先生说，“你会说西班牙语，请你告诉他，让他过一会儿再来。”

我用拇指向弗兰基打了个手势。他起身到吧台那儿去了。

“你不会说西班牙语吗？”我问道。

“哦，会倒是会。”辛先生说，“你是遇到了什么情况，竟然愿意考虑……”

“我现在囊空如洗。”

“明白了。”辛先生说，“这条船有没有欠账？会不会遭到扣押？”

“不会的。”

“那就好。”辛先生说，“我的不幸的同胞搭你的船，一次能装多少人？”

“你是说装人？”

“是的。”

“有多远的路程？”

“一天的航程。”

“这可说不准。”我说，“如果不带行李，可以装十来个人吧。”

“他们不带行李。”

“把他们运到哪儿去？”

“那就看你了。”辛先生说。

“你是说由我决定把他们运往何处？”

“你先把他们装上，往托尔图加斯开，那儿有条纵帆船接他们。”

“听着，”我说道，“托尔图加斯的罗格海德岛有座灯塔，灯塔里有电台，两个方向都在其范围之内。”

“不错。”辛先生说，“只有傻子才会把人运到那儿去。”

“此话怎讲？”

“我是叫你把船往那儿开。送到那儿就完事。”

“好吧。”我说。

“到时候你见机行事，随便把他们卸到哪里都可以。”

“纵帆船会到托尔图加斯接他们吗？”

“当然不会去的。”辛先生说，“那也太傻了。”

“每个人多少钱？”

“五十块。”辛先生说。

“不行。”

“七十五块怎么样？”

“每个人你自己拿多少钱？”

“这是两件风马牛不相及的事情。就拿签发通行证来说吧，里面用钱的地方很多，或者说关系牵扯到的很多。我不是一个人吃独食。”

“是呀。”我说，“可我也不能为了几个小钱去冒这个险吧？”

“你的意思我完全明白。”辛先生说，“每个人一百块怎么样？”

“听着，”我说道，“你知道我要是被抓住，会蹲多少年的监狱吗？”

“十年，”辛先生说，“至少十年。不过，怎么可能会叫你蹲监狱呢，亲爱的船长？你只有一点风险——那就是让乘客登船的时候。接下来就看你如何随机应变、见风使舵了。”

“如果再把他们运回来交给你呢？”

“这很简单。我就对他们说是你耍了我。我会退还一部分钱，然后再找船送他们走。他们当然知道走这趟水路困难重重。”

“你会把我怎么样？”

“我可能会把情况通报给领事馆。”

“明白了。”

“能挣一千二百块钱呢，船长，在当下可不是个叫人小觑的数目。”

“什么时候能拿到钱？”

“同意后，先付给你两百块，把人装上船时，再付你一千。”

“要是我拿上两百块的预付金跑路了呢？”

“那我也没办法。”他笑了笑说，“不过，我知道你不会做这种事的，船长。”

“你把两百块的预付金拿来了吗？”

“那还用说。”

“把钱放到盘子底下。”

他按照要求做了。

“好吧。”我说，“明天上午我办理离港手续，天一黑就出发。让他们在哪个地方上船？”

“在巴库蓝澳怎么样？”

“一言为定。”我说，“你是不是都安排好了？”

“当然喽。”

“好，再说说怎么上船吧。”我说道，“你到岬角去亮起两盏灯，一上一下，我看见灯光就把船开过去。你用一条小船把他们送过来，叫他们从那儿上我的船。你要亲自来，而且要把钱带来。我是不见兔子不撒鹰，见了钱才让他们上我的船。”

“好的。”他说，“他们上船时付给你一半，等全部上了船，再付另一半给你。”

“很好，”我说，“这样合乎情理。”

“就这样决定啦？”

“我想是的。”我说，“不许带行李，不许带凶器——枪、匕首或剃刀什么的。这一点必须说清。”

“船长，”辛先生说道，“难道你不信任我吗？咱俩的利益是一致的。”

“你敢肯定是一致的吗？”

“请别说扫兴的话。”他说，“咱俩是一根绳子上拴的蚂蚱，难道你看不出来吗？”

“好吧。”我说道，“你什么时候到那儿？”

“午夜之前。”

“一言为定。”我说，“该说的都说了。”

“你想要什么样票面的钱？”

“就要百元钞吧。”

他起身离去，我目送他出了门。临别时，弗兰基冲他笑了笑。这个中国人看上去很圆滑，是个精明强干的人。

弗兰基回到了餐桌跟前。“怎么样？”他问道。

“你是在哪里认识辛先生的？”

“他是贩运华人的，”弗兰基说，“做的是大生意。”

“你认识他多久了？”

“他来这儿大概有两年之久。”弗兰基说，“在他之前有过一个人也是贩运华人的，后来被人杀死了。”

“总有一天辛先生也会被杀死的。”

“免不了呀，”弗兰基说，“早晚都会的。树大招风嘛。”

“是有些来头呀。”我说。

“他的生意大着呢。”弗兰基说，“他贩运的华人一去不返。只听那边华人写信说日子很好过。”

“那就好。”我说。

“这些华人目不识丁。凡是肚子里有墨水的华人都发了。这些华人别的什么都不吃，只吃大米。算起来，男性华人有几十万，而女性只有三个。”

“为什么？”

“政府不让女的来呗。”

“这样的日子可是难熬呀。”我说。

“你和他把生意谈成了？”

“差不多吧。”

“这是好生意，”弗兰基说，“比搞政治强，能挣大钱，财源滚滚。”

“来喝杯啤酒。”我对他说。

“现在不发愁了吧？”

“不发愁了。”我说，“这是笔赚大钱的生意。多谢你了。”

“满意就好。”弗兰基说着拍了拍我的脊背，“我比什么都高兴。只要你快活我就心满意足了。贩运华人的生意不错吧？”

“棒得很。”

“这话我听了高兴。”弗兰基说。

看得出由于事情办得极为顺利，他高兴得都快要哭了，于是我在他的背上轻轻拍了拍。弗兰基真是个好人！

次日上午，我做的第一件事就是揪住代理人，让他给我办出港的手续。他问我要船员的名单，我说没有船员。

“你单枪匹马独闯大海，我的船长？”

“一点不错。”

“你的那个同伴呢？”

“他喝醉了。”我对他说。

“一个人去是很危险的。”

“不过就是九十英里的路嘛。”我说，“你以为船上带着个醉汉就不危险了吗？”

我把船开到了港口对面的标准石油公司的码头，将两个油箱都加满了油，差不多有两百加仑。一加仑两毛八的价钱我嫌贵，可又不知还能到哪儿去加。

自从见过那个中国人，收了他的预付金，我的心里就七上八下的，担心会出事，夜里睡觉都睡不安稳。当我把船开回旧金山码头时，埃迪正在那儿等我。

“你好，哈利。”他喊了一声，挥了挥手。我把缆绳扔给了他，他拴牢后，纵身跳上了船，显得比以前个子更高了，目光更无神了，醉意也更浓了。我一句话也没对他说。

“约翰逊那家伙脚底板抹油一溜了之，你打算怎么办，哈利？”他问我，“他的下落你知道吗？”

“快给我滚开，”我对他说道，“看见你，我就感到恶心。”

“兄弟，我不是跟你一样也心里不是滋味吗？”

“快滚下船去！”我呵斥道。

他却没加理会地往椅子上一靠，将两条腿一伸。“听说今天要过海去了。”他说道，“哎，光滞留在这儿是生不出钱来的。”

“不要你去。”

“怎么啦，哈利？你没理由冲着我发火呀。”

“没理由？快给我滚下船去！”

“喔，别发火哟。”

我二话不说，给了他脸上一拳。他站起身，连滚带爬到了码头上。

“哈利，我要是你，就不会这么绝情绝义。”他说道。

“反正我不会带你去。”我告诉他说，“这就是我的决定。”

“哼，那你也没有必要打我呀。”

“打你，是为了让你相信我的话。”

“你让我咋办呢？坐在这儿等着饿死？”

“饿死个屁。”我说道，“你可以在渡口打工嘛，可以打工挣回国的路费。”

“你对我太不公道了。”他说。

“那么，你对谁公道了，酒鬼？”我反唇相讥道，“你连你的老娘都会出卖的。”

这话可没有冤枉他。不过，打了他还是叫我心里挺过意不去的。出手打一个酒鬼，给人一种恃强凌弱的感觉。可是，事已至此，我即便想带他去，也不能带了。

他悻悻地顺着码头走了。看他那瘦麻秆样，像是几天没吃饭饿的。走到半截，他又拐了回来。

“给我几块钱让我带在身上好吗，哈利？”

我从那个中国人付的预付金中抽了一张五块钱的钞票甩给了他。

“我早就知道你够哥们。哈利，这次为何不带上我一起去呢？”

“你是个扫把星。”

“这是在说气话。”他说道，“没关系，老伙计。你早晚都会乐意见我的。”

说完，他转身走了，口袋里有了钱，步点也轻快了许多。实话说，连他走路的姿势叫我看着也恶心。他走起路来，活似全身的关节都错了位。

他走后，我去了明珠咖啡馆，跟代理人碰了面，他把手续给了我，我请他喝了一杯。随即，我留下来吃午饭。饭间，弗兰基走进了门。

“一个家伙叫我把这个交给你。”他说着递给我一个卷状的玩意儿，外边包着张报纸，用一根红线绳扎好。打开报纸时，我觉得可能是幅照片，大概是哪个人在码头上给我的船拍的照片。

展开一看，果然是幅照片，是给一个死了的黑人的脑袋和胸膛拍的近照——黑人的喉咙被横着割断后又精心缝合，胸口上挂着个牌子，牌子上用西班牙文写着：“这就是长舌头(12)的下场。”

“是什么人给你的？”我问弗兰基。

他指了指一个常在码头上干活的西班牙小伙子，此刻那小厮正站在午饭柜台旁喝酒呢。

“让他过来。”

小伙子走了过来，说东西是在十一点左右两个年轻人交给他的。当时那两人问他认识不认识我，他说认识。后来，他就让弗兰基将东西转交给我。那两人给了他一块钱，吩咐说一定要把东西交到我的手里。他说那两人的穿着很讲究。

“这事来得蹊跷。”弗兰基说。

“是啊，来者不善，善者不来。”我说。

“他们可能是觉得你把那天上午的事情告诉了警方，说你跟那几个家伙接头来着。”

“是啊，是这样的。”

“这潭水深着呢。”弗兰基说，“三十六计走为上计。”

“他们留什么口信了吗？”我问那个西班牙小厮。

“没有。”他回答说，“光让我把这个交给你。”

“现在我是不得不走了。”我对弗兰基说。

“世情险恶呀，世情险恶呀！”弗兰基连连说道。

接下来，我将代理人给我的手续卷成一个卷，付了饭钱，大步流星出了咖啡馆，穿过广场，经过仓库，来到码头上，这才长长松了口气。那帮小子显然把我给盯上了。他们真是死脑筋，竟然怀疑我把他们出卖了。他们和潘乔是一丘之貉，一害怕就情绪激动，情绪一激动就想杀人。

我上了船，发动引擎让它预热。弗兰基站在码头上观看，脸上挂着他的那种傻傻的耳聋人的微笑。我下了船，回到了他身旁。

“听着，”我说道，“你可千万别引火烧身卷进这件麻烦事。”

他听不清我的话，我只好大声喊了几句。

“我会小心的。”弗兰基说。

他解掉缆绳，把船一推。我挥手告别，他把缆绳抛到了船上。我驾船驶出泊位，沿水道前行。一艘英国货轮正在驶出港口。我先是跟它并行，继而超越。出了海港，过了岬角，我驾船向北航行，驶上了前往基维斯特(13)的航道。这时，我离开船舵，到船头把缆绳缠绕好，然后又回来继续把舵。哈瓦那耸立在船尾，不久便被远远地甩在了身后，眼前只有巍巍群山。

过了一会儿，岬角淡出了视野，接着国家大酒店匿去了身影。最后只剩下了国会大厦的圆顶仍依稀可见。和钓鱼的最后一天相比较，今天的水流不算急，只有一丝微风。我看见几只帆船正驶向哈瓦那。它们是从西边来的，由此判断水流是平缓的。

我闭了开关，关了引擎，觉得没必要浪费汽油。就让船随波逐流漂吧。天黑了，总还是可以看见岬角的灯光的，即便船漂得太远了，仍有科希玛的灯光指引航向，那时我将驾船向巴库蓝澳开。按水流现在的流速，天黑前估计船能漂出十二英里，顺利抵达巴库蓝澳，刚好看得到巴拉克阿华灯初上。

关上引擎后，我摸到船头向四下里瞭望，只能看得到两只帆船向西驶向港口，还看得见老远处国会大厦的圆顶，白白的，耸立在大海的边缘。湾流里漂着一些马尾藻，寥寥几只海鸟在觅食。我坐到船舱的顶上观望了一会儿，只能看得见一些棕色的小鱼围着马尾藻游来游去的，不见大鱼的踪影。朋友，要是有人说哈瓦那和基维斯特之间的水域不算辽阔，你可不要相信那套鬼话。我的船行驶了老半天，还只是在这片水域的边缘呢。

过了一会儿，我又回到了驾驶舱里，不料埃迪却在那儿！

“出什么事啦？引擎怎么啦？”

“坏了。”

“你怎么没把舱门关上？”

“哼，少来这一套！”我说了一声。

你猜这家伙是怎么出现的？他是溜回来的，悄悄进了前舱，钻进卧室睡大觉去了。他带来了两瓶酒——他在路边见了个商店就把酒买下带到了船上来。开船时，他一度醒来，后来又睡着了。到了海湾里，我关掉引擎，船随波有些晃动，把他给晃醒了。

“我就知道你会带上我的，哈利。”他说。

“带上你个屁。”我说道，“船员名单上根本就没有你的名字。我真想看着你跳进大海里去。”

“你真会开玩笑，哈利。”他说，“大家都是‘海螺’嘛，遇到困难应该同舟共济。”

“坏就坏在你这张嘴上，头脑一发热就嘴上不把门，看谁还敢信任你。”我说道。

“我是个好人，哈利。你可以考验一下我，看我可信不可信。”

“把那两瓶酒拿过来。”我说道。我心里有事，没跟他多啰唆。

他把酒拿了来。我拎过一瓶打开了的酒喝了一口，然后将两瓶酒都放在了船舵旁。他仍站在那儿，我看了他一眼，为他心里感到难过，也为自己迫不得已如此对待他而感到难过。唉，刚认识他的时候，他可是好端端一个人。

“这船出什么毛病了，哈利？”

“它没有毛病。”

“那究竟出什么事啦？你为什么用那种眼光看我？”

“兄弟，”我心里为他感到难过，嘴里说道，“你的麻烦大着呢。”

“这话是什么意思，哈利？”

“现在还说不清。”我说道，“情况复杂，我还没有理出个头绪呢。”

我们在那儿坐了一会儿。我心里觉得不愿意再和他说下去了。此念一起，这场谈话便难以为继了。于是我下到船舱里，把藏在那里的气枪和一支30-30温彻斯特步枪取出来，挂在驾驶舱顶平时挂钓竿的架子上，正处于船舵的上方，随手可拿。我一直把步枪上足油，放在一个短羊毛枪套里。船上潮湿，唯有如此才可以防止步枪生锈。

我打开气枪的气泵，给枪打了几下气，把气充满，将一颗子弹装入枪膛，给温彻斯特步枪的枪膛也装了颗子弹，再将弹仓装满。然后，我从坐垫下抽出那支我在迈阿密当警察时佩带的史密斯-文森38式手枪，擦拭一番，上了油，顶上子弹，挂在我的腰带上。

“这是怎么回事？”埃迪问，“这到底是怎么回事？”

“没什么。”我说道。

“那你摆出这么多枪干什么？”

“在船上我总是带枪的。”我说，“遇见有鸟来吃鱼饵，或者有鲨鱼出没于基斯群岛，我就开枪打它们。”

“活见鬼，搞的是什么名堂？”埃迪说，“这到底是怎么回事？”

“没什么。”我告诉他说。我坐在那儿，船一晃动，腰带上挂的那支38式手枪就顶一下我的腿。看着他，我不由心想，跟他闹僵没有多大意思，说到底还是要用到他呢。

“咱们要去办点小事。”只听我启口说道，“地点是在巴库蓝澳。到时候我再告诉你是什么事吧。”

我不想事先让他知道得太多，因为那会叫他提心吊胆，吓得魂不守舍，就派不上用场了。

“当你的帮手，谁都比不上我，哈利。”他说道，“我是最佳人选。我会跟着你上刀山下火海。”

看了看他那副窝囊样——傻高个，睡眼惺忪，颤颤巍巍，我一句话都没说。

“听我说，哈利。能不能叫我喝上一口？”他央求道，“不喝酒，我就浑身发抖。”

我让他喝了些酒，然后我们俩就坐在那儿等天黑。夕阳很壮观，清风拂面让人感到惬意。太阳彻底沉入大海后，我发动引擎，驾船徐徐向陆地驶去。

夜色里，我们在离岸大约有一英里的地方停了下来。太阳一落下去，潮水就涨了。我注意到潮水在向岸边涌动。只见远处的岬角亮起了灯光，哈瓦那则是一片灯海，对面的利康和巴拉克阿也灯光闪烁。我驾船逆流而行，经过巴库蓝澳，一直驶到了科希玛跟前。然后，我就让船由着自己漂。四下里漆黑一片，但我知道船漂到了哪里。这时，我把船上的灯全熄灭了。

“这是干什么呀，哈利？”埃迪问道。他老毛病又犯，又害怕了起来。

“你看这是干什么？”

“不知道。”他说，“你让我感到害怕。”看他那样子，吓得都有点发抖了。他挨近我身边时，嘴里发出一股恶臭，就像秃鹰身上的那种气味。

“几点啦？”

“我下去看看吧。”他说。他下到船舱里，回来后说已经九点半了。

“饿不饿？”我问他。

“不饿。”他回答说，“你知道我不吃饭可以，不喝酒是不行的，哈利。”

“那好吧，”我说道，“那你就喝一口吧。”

等他喝了口酒，我问他感觉如何，他说感觉棒极了。

“过会儿再让你来上几口。”我告诉他说，“我知道你不喝酒便没有胆量。可船上的酒不多，你就省着点喝吧。”

“告诉我这是要去干什么。”埃迪说。

“听着，”我在黑咕隆咚的夜幕中对他说道，“咱们到巴库蓝澳接十二个华人。到时候听我的吩咐，由你掌舵，叫你干什么你就干什么。先让那十二个华人上船，再将他们反锁到前边的船舱里。现在你过去，先把舱门从外边插上。”

他听后就去了，夜空下可以看见他黑黑的身影。他返回时，便对我说：“哈利，现在可以喝上一口了吧？”

“不行。”我说道，“到时候还要你靠酒壮胆呢。我需要的不是酒囊饭袋。”

“我是很能干的，哈利。你瞧着吧。”

“你是个酒鬼。”我说，“你给我听好了。到时候一个华人会把那十二个人带过来的。一开始，他会给我一部分钱，等所有的人都上了船，他还会给我一部分钱。见他第二次给钱，你就把船开走，掉转船头往公海开。你不要管周围发生什么事情。哪怕天塌下来，你也不要停，照直朝前开。明白了吗？”

“明白了。”

“那些华人如果有谁往外冲，或者说破门而出，你就拿起气枪打他们，让他们退回去。气枪你知道怎么用吧？”

“不知道。不过，你可以教我嘛。”

“教你你也记不住。温彻斯特步枪知道怎么用吧？”

“只要扣动扳机，开枪就是了。”

“对。”我说，“只是有一点：不要在船上留下弹孔。”

“这下子该让我喝一口了。”埃迪说。

“好吧，就让你喝一小口吧。”实际上，我让他美美地喝了一口。我情知这工夫他不会醉的，他心里害怕得不得了，会把醉意驱赶跑的。可是，喝上一口，也只能暂时管点用。喝下这口酒后，他好像心情开朗了，只听他说：“这么说，咱们这是去运送华人。上天有眼。我不是早就说过，口袋里没有钱就去运送华人赚钱么。”

“以前难道你口袋里有钱吗？”我夹枪带棒地对他说。他说话倒是挺滑稽的。

我又让他喝了三口酒壮胆，让这份胆量一直持续到十点半钟。望着他，我觉得怪有趣的，免得我胡思乱想。想不到要等这么长时间。我原打算天黑后就走人，躲开人们的目光，沿海岸一直驶向科希玛。

快到十一点的时候，岬角上亮起了两盏灯。我稍等了一小会儿，然后就把船慢慢靠了上去。巴库蓝澳是个小海湾，以前有过一个装沙子的大码头。一条小河在此处汇入大海，雨季河水上涨，会将河口的沙坝冲开。冬天刮起北风，风力又会把沙子堆起，将缺口封死。以前有纵帆船在河上来往，贩运来番石榴，此处形成了一座小镇。可是飓风袭来，将整个小镇都卷走了，现在只剩下一座房屋了，那还是一些西班牙人在飓风肆虐之后在废墟上盖起来的。星期天，他们从哈瓦那过来游泳和野餐，把这座房屋用作俱乐部。还有一座房屋是管理员住的，不过那儿离海滩挺远的。

在沿海地区，像这种小地方哪儿都有政府的管理员。不过，我觉得那个中国人肯定弄到了自己的船，而且把此处的管理员买通了。船驶近海湾时，我闻到一股海葡萄的芳香，那是陆地上海葡萄灌木散发的香气。

“你起来，到前边去。”我对埃迪说。

“靠这边不会撞上什么东西的，”他说，“而那边有礁石，小心撞上。”

嗬，这小子这次说话还挺在理呢。

“你小心看着点。”我说道。随后，我把船开进了海湾，在此处估计他们能看得见我们。这儿没有海浪拍岸的声音，引擎的声音清晰可闻。我不知道他们到底看见了我们没有，不愿瞎等，于是便将船灯亮了亮（只亮的是红灯和绿灯），然后就关上了。接着，我掉转船头，将船开出海湾，引擎不熄火，让船漂在海上。一阵阵小小的海潮不断涌来。

“你回到这边来吧。”我对埃迪说，而后让他痛快地喝了几口。

“开枪时，是不是先用拇指扣扳机？”他低声问我。此时他坐在船舵跟前，而我已经将两个枪套都打开，枪柄露出来大约有六英寸长。

“是这样的。”

“哈，原来如此。”

几口酒下肚立竿见影，让这家伙茅塞顿开。

我们候在那里，可以看见管理员的房子里射出一线灯光，穿透了灌木丛。只见岬角上的那两盏灯下去了，其中的一盏绕过岬角，另一盏可能是被他们熄灭了。

过了一小会儿，我看见有只船出了海湾，由一个人划着桨靠了过来。根据桨手一前一后晃动的身影判断，他划的是只大桨。我觉得心里挺高兴的，因为既然是划桨而来，那就说明只来了一个帮手。

等那条船划到跟前，辛先生说：“晚上好，船长。”

“把船划到后边，和我的船靠拢。”我说道。

他冲着桨手说了几句什么，可是桨手无法把船朝后划，于是我便抓住船舷上缘，把那条船拉到了我的船的尾部。他们的船上共八人——六位华人乘客，外加辛先生和那个桨手。我伸手把他们的船朝后拉时，真担心头上会挨一家伙，幸好平安无事。于是我直起腰，让辛先生抓紧船的尾部。

“让我先验验货。”我说道。

他把钱递给了我，我拿到正守在船舵旁的埃迪跟前，打开罗经柜灯，仔仔细细查看了一番，觉得没问题，便关上了灯。此时，埃迪吓得浑身抖如筛糠。

“你去给自己倒上一杯喝吧。”我说道。

我看见他取过一瓶酒，仰脖子就喝。

我又回到了船尾。

“好啦，”我说道，“让这六个人上船吧。”

虽然风浪并不大，辛先生和那个划船的古巴人费了很大劲才将小船稳住，免得两船相碰撞。我听见辛先生用中文说了句什么，那些中国乘客便争先恐后开始往我的船上爬。

“一个一个地来。”我说。

辛先生又说了句什么，那六个人便依次上了我的船，一个个高矮不等，胖瘦不均。

“带他们到前边去。”我对埃迪说。

“请到这边来，先生们。”埃迪说。好家伙，我知道他刚才喝的真不少。

“把舱门锁上。”待那些人进了船舱，我吩咐道。

“好的，先生。”埃迪说。

“我去把另外的几个也送过来。”辛先生说。

“好的。”我说。

然后，我把他们的船推开，那个桨手便吱呀吱呀把船划走了。

“听着，”我对埃迪说，“你不用再喝酒了，因为你现在的胆量已经够大了。”

“遵命，头儿。”埃迪说。

“你这是怎么啦？”

“这样的活儿我喜欢干。”埃迪说，“正如你所言，大拇指一勾就完事。”

“你这个臭酒鬼。”我说道，“把酒拿过来，让我喝一口。”

“全喝完了。”埃迪说，“对不起，头儿。”

“听着，你一定要擦亮眼睛盯着点。他把钱一交给我，你就将船开走。”

“遵命，头儿。”埃迪说。

我伸手把另一瓶酒取了出来，又拿来开塞钻将瓶塞打开，痛痛快快喝了几口，然后回到了船尾，把瓶塞又塞紧，将酒瓶放在了盛满了水的柳条壶后面。

“辛先生过来了。”我对埃迪说。

“看到了，先生。”埃迪说。

只见他们的船划了过来。

辛先生吩咐把船靠近我们的船尾。我让他们用手抓牢。于是，辛先生抓住了横在船尾上的滚筒（平时抓到大鱼，都是利用这滚筒将其拖上船的）。

“让他们上船吧，”我说，“一个一个地上。”

又是六个形形色色的中国人，依次爬上了船尾。

“打开舱门，领他们过去。”我对埃迪说。

“遵命，先生。”埃迪说。

“把舱门锁上。”

“遵命，先生。”

接下来，我看见他守在了船舵旁。

“好啦，辛先生，”我说道，“把其余的钱让我看看。”

他伸手从口袋里取出钱递给我。我没接钱，却一把揪住他的手腕，将他拽上船尾，用另一只手卡住他的脖子。我感觉得到船启动了，嘟嘟嘟地朝前开。虽说我对付辛先生已忙得不得了，但我还是向那个桨手瞧了一眼，看见那个古巴人站在小船的尾部，手里拿着船桨，眼睁睁看着辛先生扑腾来扑腾去的。辛先生拼命挣扎，那股折腾的劲要比上了钩的海豚还要厉害。

我反扭住他的一条胳膊，用劲地扳，可由于用力过猛，把那条胳膊给扳断了。只听他小声怪叫了一声，向前一冲，尽管我依然卡着他的脖子，他还是一口咬在了我的肩膀上。一感到他被反扭的那条胳膊断了，我便松了手。那条胳膊对他已没有用了。随即，我便用两只手卡他的脖子。朋友，辛先生扑腾起来真跟鱼差不多，那条废了的胳膊晃来晃去的。我用劲一拖，让他跪倒在地，将两个拇指抠进他的喉管，咔嚓一声把气管什么的全都抠断了。那声音清晰可闻。

他没有了动静。片刻之后，我松了手，将他放倒在船尾上。他仰面朝天静静躺在那儿，穿着考究的衣服，两只脚伸进驾驶舱里。最后，我丢下他走了。

我把散落在驾驶舱地板上的钱一一捡起，放到罗经柜上清点。点完钱，我接过船舵，吩咐埃迪到船尾那儿去找几个铁块。平时，一旦在礁石区或者岩底海域钓鱼，抛锚怕坏了锚钩，我就拿铁块当锚使用。

“我是找不到的。”埃迪说。他显然是害怕去，因为那儿躺着个辛先生。

“你来掌舵。”我说道，“把船往公海上开。”

此时，船舱里窸窸窣窣有了一阵动静。不过，我并没有为此而担心。

我找到了两个自己所需的铁块（这铁块是从托尔图加斯的煤炭码头上弄来的），取过一些粗鱼线，将这沉沉的两个大铁块绑在辛先生的脚踝上。当船开到距离岸边大约有两英里的地方，我把他推了下去——他从滚筒上一出溜就进了海水里。我甚至都没有检查他的口袋看里面有什么东西。我不愿再跟这家伙打交道了。

他刚才鼻子和嘴出血，滴在了甲板上。我用水桶从海里取了些水，从船尾的底下拿来个板刷，将甲板擦洗干净。取水的时候，船速过快，差点没把我甩下船。

“开慢点。”我对埃迪说。

“他要是浮上来怎么办？”埃迪说。

“我把他沉下去了，大约有七百英寻深呢。”我说，“他一直沉到底了。深着呢，兄弟。要是不产生气体，他是浮不上来的。他会跟着水流走，全当是鱼饵啦。让他见鬼去吧。”我说，“你不用再操辛先生的心了。”

“你和他有什么过意不去的？”埃迪问。

“没什么过意不去的。”我说，“他是我见过的最容易谈生意的人。不过我总觉得里边有什么鬼把戏。”

“你为什么要杀他呀？”

“是为了阻止他断送另外十二个中国人的命。”我回答说。

“哈利，”埃迪说，“我感到胃里翻腾得厉害，你得让我喝上一口。看见他耷拉着脑袋的样子，我觉得挺恶心的。”

于是我就让他喝了一口酒。

“这些中国乘客你打算怎么办？”埃迪问。

“尽可能赶快放他们走。”我回答说，“别让他们弄脏了船舱。”

“你准备把他们送到哪里？”

“在岸边找个地方让他们上岸就是了。”我回答说。

“现在就靠岸？”

“一点不错，”我说，“慢慢向岸边开。”

我们把船慢慢开过礁石区，开到一处能看见闪闪发亮海滩的位置。礁石区的水很深，海底是沙地，形成一个坡度通向海岸。

“你到前边去，把水的深度告诉我。”

他拿上测量杆开始测水深，一边测一边向我通报。最后，他回到我身边，让我把船停下。我把船倒着退了一下，然后停了下来。

“此处水深大约是五英尺。”

“就在这里抛锚吧。”我说，“万一有意外情况出现，来不及起锚，就把缆绳砍断或者挣脱缆绳。”

埃迪一点点把缆绳放出去，直至船锚触底，再将缆绳拴牢。船的尾部朝着岸边。

“这地方是沙地。”他说道。

“船尾那儿的水深是多少？”

“不超过五英尺。”

“你把步枪拿到手里。”我吩咐道，“小心点。”

“让我喝上一口吧。”他说。他显得紧张极了。

我让他喝了口酒，然后将气枪从架子上取了下来，走过去开了舱门的锁，把门拉开，高喊一声：“都给我出来！”

舱里没有任何动静。

后来，一个中国人探出头看了看，见埃迪荷枪实弹站在那儿，就又缩了回去。

“都出来。你们不会受到伤害的。”我说道。

仍不见人出来。只听见里面有人在用中文叽里呱啦说话。

“快出来！”埃迪吼了一声。我的老天，一听就知道他偷喝酒了。

“不许再喝了。”我对他说，“不然我就崩了你，送你下海喂鱼鳖。”

“都给我出来！”我又冲那些中国人喊道，“不出来我就开枪了。”

只见他们当中的一个朝门角那儿望了望，显然是看到了沙滩，因为他叽里呱啦对同伴们讲了一通中文。

“快点，”我说道，“不然我就开枪了。”

他们乖乖地出来了。

实话讲，要杀害这么一群手无寸铁的中国人，恐怕黑心肠的人也难以下手，更何况这绝对不是件容易办到的事，就别提还会把船弄脏了。

他们一个个走出了船舱，吓得似惊弓之鸟。他们虽然没有枪，但毕竟有十二个人呢。我端着气枪，步步倒退，一直退到船尾。“都给我下船去。”我命令道，“水不深，淹不过头顶。”

没有人听令而行。

“快给我下去。”

还是没人遵命。

“你们这些吃老鼠肉的黄种人，”埃迪呵斥道，“都下船去。”

“闭上你的嘴，酒鬼。”我对埃迪说道。

“不会游泳。”一个中国人说道。

“不需要游泳，”我告诉他，“水不深。”

“快点，快下船去。”埃迪说。

“你到船尾这边来，”我说，“一只手拿枪，一只手拿测量杆，让他们亲眼看看水的深度。”

埃迪照我的话做了。

“不需要游泳？”刚才的那个中国人问道。

“是的。”

“真的吗？”

“真的。”

“这是哪儿。”

“古巴。”

“你这个可恶的骗子。”他说完便下了船，先是拉着船帮不放，后来松了手，结果一下子没于水中。不过，他马上又露出了头，下巴能露出水面。

“可恶的骗子。”他连声说，“可恶的骗子。”

他失去了理智，但是胆量却不小。他又说了几句中文，其他的中国人也从船尾纷纷跳下了水。

“好啦，”我对埃迪说，“起锚吧。”

我们驾船离开岸边时，月亮露出了脸，可以看见那些中国人头露出水面在向岸上走，还看得见闪着亮光的沙滩和沙滩后的灌木丛。

船驶过礁石区，到了公海上。我回头一望，沙滩和群山清晰地映入了眼帘。随后，我们驶上了前往基维斯特的航程。

“现在，你可以睡大觉了。”我对埃迪说，“且慢！你先去船舱把舷窗都打开，跑跑里面的臭气，再把碘酒给我拿来。”

“怎么啦？”他把碘酒拿来时问道。

“手指给割破了。”

“想让我掌舵吗？”

“你去睡吧。”我说，“到时候我叫醒你。”

他就在驾驶舱里的小床上躺了下来——那小床和墙壁连为一体，位于油箱的上方。过了一小会儿，他就呼呼大睡了起来。

我用膝盖顶住船舵，解开衬衣查看辛先生咬我的伤情。那一口咬得真厉害，我在伤口上涂了些碘酒。接下来，我坐在那儿掌舵，心里胡思乱想起来，怀疑那个中国人咬那一口是有毒的。后来，听着悦耳、平稳的引擎声以及哗哗的海水声，我心里渐渐静了下来，觉得那一口不会有毒的。辛先生那样的人可能一天要刷两三次牙呢。论做生意，他肯定是个门外汉。不过，他也许精通做生意呢，只是轻信了我，才落了个这样的下场。实话说，对于他，我实在猜不透。

现在，除了埃迪，其他的事情都很简单了。那家伙是个酒鬼，一喝得上了头，嘴上就不把门。我一边开船一边望了他一眼。心想他还不如死了的好，那样我就可以高枕无忧了。起初在船上看到他，我就起了杀机，想把他干掉，后来见事情办得顺风顺水，也就狠不下心去了。此刻见他躺在那里，杀他的念头又被兜了起来。不过，转念一想，觉得杀他会把事情搞糟，过后会后悔的。可是，船员名单上没有他的名字，带上他就得交罚款，真叫人伤脑筋，不知怎样处置他才好。

对于此事，我斟酌了许久，一边驾船在航道上行驶，时不时把他拎上船的那瓶酒拿起来喝上一口。那瓶酒所剩不多，喝完后我就把我自己仅有的一瓶打开了。告诉你吧，驾着船在海上兜风的感觉是很好的，这样的夜晚夜色迷人呀。这桩生意起初屡屡出现不祥之兆，但结局却符合人意。

天亮时，埃迪睡醒了。他说他感到浑身不舒服。

“你来掌一会儿舵，”我吩咐他说，“我到那边查看一下。”

我回到船尾，在上面泼了些水冲洗。其实那儿很干净，没有留下污痕。接下来，我用刷子把船帮刷了刷，将两支枪的子弹都退出来，再把它们藏在船舱里。不过，手枪我还是继续挂在腰带上。船舱里空气清新，完全符合我的心意，没有一点点异味。只是从右舷窗进了些海水，溅在了一张小床上。我走过去把舷窗关上了。天下没有一个海关官员能嗅得出这儿曾经关过中国人。

查看间，我望了一眼船只驾驶执照的镜框，见装着清关手续的网兜仍挂在下方——那是我上船时随手挂在那儿的。我取出手续，又浏览了一遍，然后就回驾驶舱里去了。

“我问你，”我对埃迪说，“你是怎么把你的名字填在船员名单上的？”

“我碰见了代理人，他正要到领事馆去，我就说我也跟你一块出海。”

“上帝可真会照应酒鬼！”我说完，就从腰带上解下那支38式手枪，拿到船舱里去藏好。

我在船舱里煮了些咖啡，然后上来接过船舵说：“下边有咖啡，你去喝点吧。”

“哥们，咖啡对我一点不管用。”

看他的那副样子，你会不由得动恻隐之心——他看上去惨极了。

九点钟左右，我们在正前方看见了桑德基岛的灯塔。在这之前，早已见有油轮行驶在海湾水域上了。

“快要靠岸了。”我对他说，“还是按约翰逊的那个价，我每天付给你四块钱。”

“昨夜的生意你赚了多少钱？”他问我。

“仅仅六百块。”我告诉他说。

我也不知道他信不信我的话。

“难道没有我的一份吗？”

“刚才说的就是你的一份。”我告诉他说，“昨夜的事你要是泄露出去，让我知道了，我会要你的命的。”

“你清楚，我不是个口风不严的人，哈利。”

“你是个酒鬼。我可不管你喝多少酒，醉成什么程度，反正只要你说出去，就没有你的好果子吃。”

“我可是个守诚信的人。”他说，“你不该这般对我说话。”

“事物变化多端，谁知道你的诚信能不能守得住。”我对他说。不过，我不再为他担心了，因为他的话没人会相信的。辛先生不会再出声了，那些中国乘客也不会说的。还有那个划船的人，肯定也不会乱讲的。哪怕埃迪保不定什么时候说出去，可有谁会相信一个酒鬼的话呢？

嗬，谁都拿不出一点证据的！有人看见船员名单上有埃迪的名字，如果不见埃迪，自然会有不少话头。幸好我没有将他干掉。我可以说是他自己掉进海里了，可那会引得人说闲话的。埃迪可真是个幸运儿，可谓福星高照。

我们把船开到了湾流的边上，这儿的海水由蓝变成了淡色，微微发绿。放眼望去，可以看见长礁和西干岩上的标桩以及基韦斯特的无线电天线杆，可以看见高耸入云的拉孔查饭店鹤立鸡群于一片低矮房屋之间，还可以看见垃圾焚烧场那儿浓烟滚滚。桑德基岛的灯塔已近在眼前。灯塔旁边的船库和那个小码头也看得见了。我知道只剩下四十分钟的路程了。回家的感觉真好。如今钱囊充盈，足够夏日享用的了。

“干上一杯怎么样，埃迪？”我说道。

“哈，哈利，”他说，“我就知道你是个贴心的好伙计。”

————————————————————

(1) 原文为西班牙语。

(2) 原文为西班牙语。

(3) 原文为西班牙语。

(4) 西非原始宗教。

(5) 古巴黑人民间舞蹈发展而成的一种交际舞。

(6) 为辐鳍鱼纲的其中一种，被列为易危保育类动物，分布于西大西洋区，栖息深度25—95米，体长可达94厘米，栖息在水质清澈的珊瑚礁、岩礁区。

(7) 吸引鱼的诱饵，本身没有带鱼钩。

(8) 美国飞行员，是世界上单独驾机飞越大西洋的第一人。

(9) 指欧洲裔的巴哈马居民，以海螺为食（多含贬义）。

(10) 古巴地名，啤酒酿造地。

(11) 该船厂位于美国底特律。

(12) 原文为西班牙语。

(13) 美国佛罗里达州的一个小岛。

告发

在那些日子，马德里的奇科特酒吧有点像鹳鸟夜总会那种去处，只是没有乐队伴奏和年轻女子相陪，又有点像华尔道夫酒店的男士酒吧。男士酒吧是不接待女士的，而奇科特酒吧有女士出入，可这儿毕竟是男人的世界，女士是没有地位的。酒吧老板叫佩德罗·奇科特。有个性的酒吧，老板必有个性，而佩德罗·奇科特就是这样的一个老板。他精通吧台的业务，待人和蔼可亲，总是满面春风的，谈吐优雅风趣。优雅风趣如今极为罕见，这类人如凤毛麟角。这种风度可不能跟逢场作戏混为一谈。奇科特是真的优雅风趣，而非做作，也非假装。而且，他谦虚朴素，以友谊示人。他真真切切是个大好人，一个叫人心情舒畅的人，论高超的处事能力，可比巴黎里兹酒吧的侍者乔治（业内能与奇科特媲美者唯有乔治了），所以他生意兴隆。

那年头的富家子弟，附庸风雅者混迹于一个叫新潮俱乐部的地方，而有主见的人则出入于奇科特酒吧。此处固然有许多人我都不喜欢，情况就跟鹳鸟夜总会一样，可每一次我都尽欢而归。其中有一个原因：此处不谈政治。有些酒吧成了光谈政治的场所，其他的话题一概不涉及，然而在奇科特酒吧人们闭口不谈政治。对于别的五花八门的话题，客人们则津津乐道。到了晚上，城里那些楚楚动人的年轻女子便纷纷而至，此处的夜生活很丰富，客人们各个都玩得很开心。

此处是交际场所，可以了解某某某在城内，如果出了城，那么究竟去了何方。假如是在夏天，人去城空，你尽可以来这儿消停地喝上一杯，因为此处的侍者待人和颜悦色。

此处又是个俱乐部，只是你不用付会员费，说不定你在这儿还会有艳遇呢。这儿肯定算得上是西班牙最好的酒吧了，我想恐怕也是全世界最好的酒吧，我们都喜欢来这儿消磨时光，对它有着深厚的感情。

再者，此处的酒称得上是香醪美酿。你不妨点一杯马丁尼——那可是用最好的酒料酿造出来的，别处拿钱也难买得到。奇科特酒吧供应的威士忌是来自于苏格兰的原桶装的好酒，比那些广而告之的品牌强多了，更会将普通的苏格兰威士忌比得无地自容。国内的叛乱爆发时，奇科特老板身在圣塞瓦斯蒂安，在那儿经营自家的夏日连锁店。这家店至今仍在他手里，据说是佛朗哥(1)占领区的头牌酒吧。马德里的这个分店由侍者代为管理，至今状况依旧，可是那些香醪美酿却绝了踪迹。

奇科特酒吧的老顾客多半拥护佛朗哥，有些则站在政府一边。由于该酒吧是个极为欢快的场所，顾客是真正的极为欢快的群体，欢快的人通常勇敢无畏，而勇者易于战死疆场，于是众多奇科特酒吧的老顾客已成作古之人。原桶装的威士忌数月前已售罄，杜松子金酒也于1938年5月被我们喝得点滴不剩。此处已风光不再，魅力大减，我觉得路易斯·戴尔卡多再晚一些时候来马德里，也许就不会来喝酒，也就不会惹祸上身了。可他是在1937年9月的那个月份来马德里的，那时该酒吧竟然还有杜松子金酒，竟然还有印度奎宁水。喝杯好酒，似乎也不值得豁上自己的身家性命。也许，他仅仅是想旧地重游，饮酒怀旧罢了。了解他这个人，了解昔日的奇科特酒吧，他的行为也就完全可以理解了。

那天，大使馆宰了头牛，门房打电话到佛罗里达旅馆告诉我们，说给我们留了十磅鲜肉。我穿过马德里冬日的薄暮，一路走过去取肉。大使馆门外有两个荷枪实弹的突击队员坐在椅子上，肉就放在门房小屋里等候领取。

守门人说牛是瘦了些，但切下来的这块肉相当不错。我从短大衣外套的口袋里掏出一些炒葵花子和橡子请他吃，两人就站在门房外的砾石车道上说笑了一会儿。

我把沉甸甸的牛肉夹在腋下，溜达着往回走。遇到格兰维亚大街(2)遭到轰炸，于是我便拐进奇科特酒吧躲避。这儿挤满了人，闹哄哄的。我走到一个角落里，紧靠用沙袋堵起来的窗户在一张小桌子旁坐了下来，将牛肉放在身边的板凳上，要了杯金汤力(3)喝。也就是在这个星期，我们发现这儿竟然还有奎宁水呢。自从战争爆发以来，没见有人喝过呀。此时的奎宁水仍卖的是老价钱，一如叛乱发生之前。喝酒间，晚报还没有印出，我便从一个老太太手里买了三份政党的党报，每份十分钱。我给了她一个比塞塔，叫她不用找零了。她说上帝一定会保佑我的，对此我倒是心存怀疑。之后，我便一边看那三份党报，一边喝金汤力。

一个我在过去早就认识的侍者走了过来，对我说了几句话。

“不会吧，”我说，“我不相信。”

“确有其事。”他语气坚定地说，一边将托盘斜了斜，脑袋歪了歪，指的都是同一个方向，“你别用眼睛看。他就在那里。”

“这不关我的事。”我告诉他说。

“跟我也没有关系。”

他说完就走开了。此时又有一个老太太进入店里卖刚出版的晚报，我买了份看了起来。毫无疑问，侍者没认错人。那家伙是我们俩再熟悉不过的了。我心里连连在说，真是傻呀，傻得简直不透气。

就在这时，一个希腊的战友走过来，在桌旁坐下。他是第十五旅的一个连长，一次空袭中被炸弹掀起的土埋了起来，另有四个军人当场毙命，而他却大难未死。后来，他被送进医院观察了一阵子，接下来转入一家疗养院什么的。

“你好吗，约翰？”我问他，“来喝上一杯尝尝味道。”

“这叫什么酒呀，埃德蒙兹先生？”

“金汤力。”

“金汤力是什么酒呀？”

“是加了奎宁水的。你喝一杯尝尝。”

“现在我不太喝酒了，不过，奎宁水对防治热病大有好处。我喝口尝尝吧。”

“对于你的病情，医生是怎么说的，约翰？”

“没必要去看医生。我没事的，只是头里有点嗡嗡叫罢了。”

“你应该去看医生的，约翰。”

“去倒是去了。可他不了解病情，说我没有证明不给看。”

“我打个电话通融一下。”我说，“医院里的人我认识。医生是不是个德国人？”

“没错，”约翰说，“是个德国人。他的英语说得不太好。”

闲聊间，那个侍者又走了过来。他是个谢了顶的老头，举止老派，战争也没有改变他待人接物的方式。此时的他脸上愁云密布。

“我有个儿子上了前线，”他说，“还有一个已经战死。现在又摊上了。”

“那是你自己的事。”

“那你呢？我可是已经告诉你了呀。”

“我来这儿是喝酒的，是在吃饭前来这儿喝上一杯。”

“我是来工作的。再怎么说，也得听听你的指教。”

“你的事你自己掂量。”我说，“我是不过问政治的。”

“你懂西班牙语吗，约翰？”我问那位希腊战友。

“不懂，几乎听不懂。我只会说希腊语、英语和阿拉伯语。有段时间，我的阿拉伯语还说得很好呢。我问你，你知道我是怎么被埋在了土里吗？”

“不知道。只知道你被土掩埋了。仅此而已。”

他脸膛黑黑的，一表人才，一双手黑透了，说起话把手挥来舞去的。他来自于一座海岛，一开口便情绪激昂。

“那好。我讲给你听听。你也知道，我曾身经百战。之前在希腊军队服役，我就是个上尉了。我可是个勇敢的战士。所以，那天在富恩特斯-埃布罗的战壕里见敌机俯冲过来，我躲也没躲，近距离观看它。眼看着它飞到我们的头顶，哗地来了个急转弯——就像这样……（他说着用手比画了一下飞机掉头的样子）它从空中观察我们。我对其他人说：‘啊哈，是奔着总参谋部来的，是来侦察的。马上还会有别的飞机来。’

“果不其然，又有一些敌机飞来了。我就站在那儿观察，一边仰头看一边把情况指给连里的弟兄们看。有两组敌机，每组三架。队形是一架在前，两架在后。一组三架飞过去之后，我对弟兄们说：‘看见了吧？一个编队飞过去了。’

“另外三架飞过时，我说道：‘现在好啦，没有事啦。不用再害怕了。’以后的情况我就不知道了，一连昏迷了两个星期。”

“这事发生在什么时候？”

“约莫一个月之前。炮弹掀起的土把我埋住的时候，头盔恰好遮在了我的脸上，于是我就呼吸头盔里的那点空气，直至被人挖出，当时具体的情况我便不得而知了。头盔里有空气，但里面含着爆炸后产生的硝烟，呛得我生了很长时间的病。现在身体康复了，只是脑袋里有嗡嗡叫的声音。这酒叫什么酒呀？”

“叫金汤力，是加了舒味思印度奎宁水的。战前这家酒吧是高消费场所，当时一美元换七个比塞塔，而一瓶金汤力就卖五个比塞塔。这家店仍有奎宁水，我们也是才发现的。价钱还是原先的价钱。只剩下一桶了。”

“味道还是挺不错的。给我讲讲这座城市战前的情况怎么样？”

“好的。其实和现在差不多，只是吃的东西很丰富。”

那个侍者又走了过来，朝我跟前探过身子。

“我要是袖手旁观恐怕不行吧？”他说，“我有这个责任呀。”

“既然你愿意插手，那就去打个电话，拨这个号码吧。你把它记下来。”

他用笔记了下来。

“你找皮珀听电话。”我说。

“我和他前世无冤今世无仇。”侍者说，“但此事关系重大，这样的一个人势必会危害我们的事业。”

“别的侍者没有认出他吧？”

“我想是的。没听谁说什么。他是过去的老顾客。”

“我也是老顾客呀。”

“也许他现在也站在咱们这一边了。”

“情况并非如此，”我说道，“这我很清楚。”

“我可从来没告发过任何人。”

“告发不告发由你决定。你不告发，也许别的侍者也会告发的。”

“不会的。这里只有老侍者认识他，而老侍者是不会告发的。”

“再来一瓶杜松子金酒，加点苦艾水。”我说道，“瓶子里还有些奎宁水呢。”

“他说什么来着？”约翰问，“我仅仅听懂了一点点。”

“店里来了一个人，是我们俩过去认识的老熟人。他经常打鸽子，是个神枪手。我亲眼见识过他百步穿杨的枪法。他是个法西斯分子，竟然敢在这儿抛头露面，不管出于什么原因，反正都是极为愚蠢之举。他是个天不怕地不怕的人，就是愚蠢至极。”

“你指给我看看。”

“就是和飞行员坐在同一张桌旁的那个。”

“哪个呀？”

“就是那个紫脸膛的，帽檐遮住了一只眼，此刻正在笑的那个。”

“他是个法西斯分子？”

“是的。”

“自从离开了富恩特斯-埃布罗，如此近距离看一个法西斯分子，我这还是第一次。这儿的法西斯分子很多吗？”

“时多时少。”

“他喝的酒跟你喝的一样。”约翰说，“喝这种酒，别人会不会也把咱们当成法西斯分子呢？我问你，你去过南美洲西海岸的麦哲伦(4)吗？

“没去过。”

“那地方挺好，就是涨鱼有点太多了。”

“什么太多了？”

“就是涨鱼呗。”他重音念错了，把“章”念成了“涨”。“你知道就是那种有八条腿的鱼。”

“噢，”我说，“那是章鱼。”

“是的，是涨鱼。”约翰说，“你也知道，我还是个潜水员呢。那可是个潜水的好地方，挣的钱也不少，就是涨鱼太多了。”

“它们碍你的事了吗？”

“谁说得清呢。第一次在麦哲伦港口下海我就看见了涨鱼。它就像这样直直站立在那儿。”约翰说着将手指撑在桌子上，把手掌向上提，同时耸耸肩膀，眉头上扬，“它站起来比我还高呢，眼对眼地看着我。我一拉绳子，让他们赶快把我拽了上去。”

“多大的章鱼，约翰？”

“我说不准确，因为头盔上的潜水镜视物有点扭曲。不过，它的头围怎么说也超过了六英尺。它站在那里，像是踮着脚尖似的，样子跟这差不多。（他摆出架势，直盯住我的脸。）所以我赶紧出了水。他们取下我的头盔，我就说再也不下去了。管事的工头对我说：‘你这是怎么啦，约翰？你害怕章鱼，但章鱼更害怕你哩。’我回答说：‘无稽之谈！’这种法西斯酒，咱们再喝点怎么样？”

“好的。”我说。

我一直在观察着那边桌旁的那个人。他叫路易斯·戴尔卡多。上次见他是在1933年，在圣塞瓦斯蒂安的一次打鸽子比赛场上。记得决赛时，我和他一道站在看台上观望。我们都下了注——我下的注已超出了我的能力；而他下的注，如果输了，我相信他一年也缓不过劲来。他付清了下注的钱，我记得他满脸春色，好像输钱对他是莫大的荣幸似的。记得后来我们还在吧台一起喝了一杯马丁尼酒呢。我当时押赌输了钱，反而有一种财去人安乐的感觉，却不知他心里是怎么承受的呢。那个星期，我的枪法很臭，而他打得极为精彩，几乎打不到的鸟儿都会被他击落。我们之间赌钱，每次都是由他提出来。

“咱们比赛抛银圆吧？”他提议说。

“你真的想赌？”

“是的，如果你愿意的话。”

“赌多少？”

他掏出钱夹，朝里边看了看，哈哈一笑。

“你说赌多少，咱就赌多少。”他说，“不过，还是赌八千比塞塔吧。钱夹里好像就这么多了。”

这笔钱当时近乎一千美元。

“好吧。”我说。一说赌博，原来的那种静谧安然的心情顿时消失，那种空落落的感觉又回来了。“谁做庄？”

“我先来吧。”

我们各把一枚沉甸甸的五比塞塔的银圆放在手里，再将手圈成杯状摇摇。然后，各自把银圆放在左手的手背上，再用右手捂住。

“你的是哪一面？”他问道。

我拿开右手，露出了那枚大大的银圆，上面有阿方索十三世(5)的侧身像，就像小孩玩游戏一样。

“是正面。”我说。

“把这些臭钱拿走吧。别小气，请我喝杯酒吧。”他把钱夹里的钱一股脑儿倒给了我，“你不想用这钱买支漂亮的珀迪牌子的枪吗？”

“不想。”我说，“你听我说，路易斯，如果你需要钱的话……”我手里拿着那几张硬硬地折在一起，纸张发亮且手感重，票面为一千比塞塔的绿钞票，直朝他跟前推。

“别犯傻，恩里克，”他说，“赌博就是赌博。”

“不错。可咱们是老熟人了。”

“还没有熟悉到彼此不分的程度。”

“好吧，”我说，“就听你的吧。想喝什么酒呢？”

“来一杯金汤力怎么样？这可是美酒佳酿呀。”

于是，我们一起喝了杯金汤力。让他落了个囊空如洗，我心里老大不忍，然而将钱赢到了手里，那种感觉特别好。我一生都没觉得金汤力的味道竟如此爽口。赢钱感觉很好，没必要说假话，没必要假惺惺地做出不乐意赢钱的样子。话又说回来，路易斯·戴尔卡多那家伙是个输得起钱的赌徒。

“依我看，输得起多少钱就赌多少，那样的玩法意思不大。你说呢，恩里克？”

“不得而知，因为我历来都没有多少钱可输。”

“哪里的话。你的钱多着呢。”

“我没钱，”我说，“这是真的。”

“得了吧。谁还能没点钱呢。”他说，“问题在于你愿不愿把某样东西出售给别人，卖掉东西你不就有钱了。”

“我没有多少钱。这是真的。”

“得啦，别说傻话。我所认识的美国人，没有一个是没钱的。”

我想此言不虚。当年无论是在里兹酒吧还是在奇科特酒吧，他是碰不上没钱的美国人的。而今他重返奇科特酒吧，所遇到的美国人正是他昔日绝不会碰见的那一类。我则另当别论——我真不该来这里。我说什么也不愿在此处看见他。

假如他愿意干这种蠢不可及的事情，那是咎由自取。不过，望着店里的桌子，遥想当年，我心里不禁感到一阵阵的难过。更叫我难过的是，我竟然把安全总部反间谍局的电话号码给了那位侍者。侍者自己打个电话也是可以找到安全总部的。但是我却给他指出了一条逮捕戴尔卡多最便利的捷径。这里面牵扯到的因素极为复杂——其中包括公道、正义、彼拉多(6)手腕以及观察人们遇到心理矛盾时如何行为的那种肮脏的心态。作家之所以能散发出迷人的魅力，靠的就是罗织这些复杂的因素。

这时，那个侍者走了过来。

“你觉得这样妥当吗？”

“要是我，我绝不会告发他。”我说。解铃还须系铃人——我在排除由于提供电话号码而产生的症结了。“不过，我是个外国人，打仗是你们在打仗，问题得由你们自己解决。”

“可是，你是站在我们这一边的呀。”

“自始至终，坚贞不渝。不过，此事关系到的是告发一个老朋友。”

“那我呢？”

“你的情况不一样。”

我认为自己讲的是实话。此时，再也没有别的话可说的了。真希望这种事情压根就没有进入我的耳朵里。

我曾有过好奇心，想了解人们在这类情况中会采取什么样的行动，说来惭愧，这种好奇心早已得到了满足。此时的我转向约翰，不去看路易斯·戴尔卡多坐的那张桌子。据我所知，路易斯·戴尔卡多当了一年多的法西斯飞行员，而今却在此处现身，穿着政府军的军装，在跟三个受训于法国最近才返回的年轻的政府军飞行员交谈着。

那几个新来的小伙子没人认识他。我怀疑他来此处，目的是想偷架飞机或者干别的什么勾当。不管他目的如何，现身于奇科特酒吧纯粹是愚蠢之举。

“你感觉怎么样，约翰？”我问道。

“感觉不错。”约翰说，“这酒很好，喝了稍微有些晕乎，能压住一些脑袋里嗡嗡叫的声音。”

那个侍者走了过来，情绪显得非常激动。

“我告发了他。”他说。

“那就好。”我说，“你的问题解决了。”

“是的。”他颇为自豪地说，“我把他告发了。他们正赶过来逮捕他。”

“咱们走吧。”我对约翰说，“这里要出事了。”

“那就最好走人。”约翰说，“麻烦事真是太多了，让你躲都来不及。酒钱是多少呢？”

“怎么？你不留下吗？”侍者问。

“是的。”

“可是，电话号码是你给我的呀。”

“我恰好知道这个号码，就给了你。在城里生活，总得记许许多多电话号码的。”

“对于我，则是义不容辞的责任。”

“是呀。谁说不是呢？责任是非常强烈的义务。”

“接下来怎么才好呢？”

“哦，此时你有一种心安理得的感觉，是不是？这种心态也许还会持续下去。你会引以为自豪的。”

“你把这包东西忘记拿了。”侍者说着，把装在两个大信封里的牛肉递给了我。信封是《鞭策》杂志社用来寄送杂志的——那些杂志同别的刊物一道堆放在大使馆的一个办公间里。

“我理解你，”我对侍者说，“真的很理解。”

“他是老主顾，一个很好的主顾。以前我从未告发过任何人。这次破例告发可不是为了从中取乐。”

“有句话说出来可不是小看你，不怀有恶意。你就对他说是我告发了他。反正由于政见不同，他对我已怀恨在心。如果他知道告发人是你，一定怨恨你的。”

“不。一人做事一人当。可你真的理解我吗？”

“我真的理解。”我说完，又随口撒了个谎，“我非但理解，还赞同。”兵荒马乱的，撒谎是司空见惯的事。这样的谎话需要脱口而出，而且应该滴水不漏。

跟侍者握手后，我和约翰便走出了店门。出门前，我回头望了望路易斯·戴尔卡多坐的那张桌子，见他的面前仍摆放着一杯金汤力，桌旁的人都在为他说的什么事情哈哈哈大笑。他那黝黑的脸上喜气洋洋，闪动着一双猎手的眼睛。真不知他又在扮演什么角色了。

现身于奇科特酒吧确是愚蠢之举。不过，对于这样的冒险他乐此不疲，为的是回到朋友中去好吹吹牛皮。

待我们出了门，走上大街时，见一辆安全总部的大型轿车吱的一声停在了奇科特酒吧门前，接着下来八个人——六个端冲锋枪的在外边站岗，另两个穿便衣的径直走了进去。一个站岗的要看我们的证件，我说是外国人，便让我们走了，说是没我们的事。

格兰维亚大街上光线很暗，大轰炸后人行道上又出现了许多碎玻璃碴，脚下瓦砾成片。空气中弥漫着硝烟，街头巷尾到处都闻得到烈性炸药爆炸的气味，以及被炸飞的花岗岩散发出的气味。

“你打算去哪里吃饭？”约翰问。

“这儿有些肉够咱俩吃的，回去做着吃吧。”

“让我掌勺吧。”约翰说，“我的厨艺很好。记得以前还在轮船上当过厨子呢……”

“这肉老了些，”我说，“不过是刚宰杀的。”

“哦，不老。”约翰说，“战争期间能吃上肉就不错了，没有老不老之说。”

黑暗中，一些人步履匆匆地往家赶——他们待在电影院，等到轰炸过后才出来。

“那个法西斯分子是怎么啦？跑到奇科特酒吧来，就不怕别人认出来？”

“他是发了疯了。”

“都是战争惹的祸。”约翰说，“弄得许多人都丧失了理智。”

“约翰，”我说道，“你这话不无道理。”

回到旅馆，走过为了保护服务台而堆起的沙袋，我问服务员要房间的钥匙，可他说有两个同僚上楼到客房里洗澡，他把钥匙给了他们。

“你先上去吧，约翰，”我说，“我想去打个电话。”

我去电话亭，拨了我给那位侍者的号码。

“喂，是皮珀吗？”

听筒里传来了一种薄嘴唇发出的声音：“你好吗，恩里克？(7)”

“喂，皮珀，你们在奇科特酒吧抓了个名叫路易斯·戴尔卡多的人吧？”

“是的，兄弟，是的，都很顺利。(8)一帆风顺。”

“他不知道是那个侍者告发的吧？”

“不知道，兄弟。他不知道。”

“那就别告诉他。你对他讲，就说是我告发的，好不好？不要提那个侍者。”

“是谁告发的又有什么关系呢？他是个间谍，反正是要被枪毙的。这种事，他只有死路一条。”

“这我清楚。”我说，“不过，关系还是有的。”

“那就听你的，兄弟。那就听你的。什么时候能见你？”

“明天你来吃午饭。我们这儿搞到一些牛肉。”

“饭前还有威士忌喝。太好了，兄弟，太好了。”

“再见，皮珀。谢谢你啦。”

“再见，恩里克。别客气，没什么。再见。”

听筒里的声音有点怪，含着杀气，让人听上去很不习惯。不过，上楼时，我的心情好多了。

但凡出入于奇科特酒吧的老顾客，对那儿都有一种特殊的感情。我知道正是出于这种感情，才使得路易斯·戴尔卡多铤而走险，返回酒吧。按说，他完全可以不来。可是，回到马德里，他便身不由己，一定会来了。如那个侍者所言，他是个好顾客，而我们彼此是朋友。人生中，不应该因为善小而不为。我很高兴自己给安全总部的老朋友皮珀打了电话——路易斯·戴尔卡多是奇科特酒吧的老顾客，我可不愿让他在临死之前坏掉对那个酒吧的美好印象或者对那里的侍者心怀怨恨。

————————————————————

(1) 西班牙内战期间推翻民主共和国的民族主义军队领袖。此人于1936年发动西班牙内战，自1939年开始到1975年统治西班牙长达三十多年。

(2) 马德里最重要的商业街。

(3) 一种经典鸡尾酒。

(4) 智利的海港城市。

(5) 西班牙国王。

(6) 钉死耶稣的古代罗马的犹太总督。

(7) 原文为西班牙语。

(8) 原文为西班牙语。

忠贞的公牛

从前有头公牛，它的名字不叫费迪南德(1)，对鲜花丝毫不感兴趣。它所喜欢的是战斗，跟所有同龄的公牛斗，也跟其他年龄段的公牛斗，而且战无不胜。

它的犄角和硬木一样坚硬，同豪猪的刺那般锋利。决斗时，它的犄角根会发痛，但它毫不理会。它颈部的肌肉隆起，聚成一大团，西班牙语叫作morillo。它准备冲锋陷阵时，这团morillo便高高耸起，似一座小山——它时时刻刻都在准备着上阵拼搏。它的毛皮黑亮黑亮，一双眼睛非常清朗。

它一旦因故产生了战斗的欲望，那它一定会认认真真地拼死一搏，其认真的态度就跟有些人吃饭、读书和上教堂那样一板一眼的。每次战斗，它都一斗到底，非得置对手于死地不可。别的公牛也不怕它，因为它们都是些良种牛，都是天不怕地不怕的好牛。不过，那些牛并不愿招惹它，不想跟它一决雌雄。

它并非一头专横跋扈的牛，也非坏心眼的恶牛，只是喜欢战斗而已，这就跟人们喜欢唱歌，喜欢当国王或者总统一样。它从不思考。战斗是它的义务，是它的责任和欢乐。

它在石头高地上战斗，在栓皮栎树下战斗，也在河边丰茂的草场上战斗。每一天，它都会从河边走十五英里的路到石头高地上寻斗。别的公牛哪怕看它一眼，它也会与之战斗。

要说它从不恼怒，那可是与事实不符，因为它的心里会怒火燃烧。它恼怒，却不知发怒的原因，因为它不善于思考。它是一头高贵的牛，一头喜欢战斗的牛。

知道它后来发生了什么事吗？它的主人（这般高贵的牛竟然还从属于他人）心里明白它是头了不起的公牛，但这头公牛跟别的牛搏斗，使得他损失惨重，这叫他忧心忡忡。一头价值一千多美元的牛，跟这头了不起的牛斗上一场，身价会暴跌，连两百美元都值不了了，有的时候会少于这个数。

它的主人是个心软的好人，不愿把它送到斗牛场上战死，而是决定将它留在自家牛群里交配，以传宗接代。就这样，它被选中做了种牛。

可是这头种牛行为古怪。第一次把它放到牧场去，跟那些育龄母牛在一起，它一眼就看中了一头年轻漂亮的母牛——那母牛与别的母牛相比身材更苗条，肌肉更发达，毛皮更光亮，样子更可爱。既然不能再去战斗了，于是它就移情母牛，爱上了这头漂亮的母牛。对于其他的母牛它看也不看一眼，只想守在这头母牛的身边，别的母牛它都不屑一顾。

养牛场的主人希望它有所改变，希望它学会和别的母牛相处，或者说脱胎换骨。可这头公牛是个死心眼，对爱情特别专注，只爱自己的心上人。它只想跟心上人在一起，对于别的母牛视若无物。

万般无奈，主人只好把它和另外的五头牛送到斗牛场上迎接死亡。它不但在情场上感情忠贞，在斗牛场上也毫不含糊。它表现得极为出色，赢得了所有人的钦佩，而最为钦佩它的当数那个最终杀掉它的人。结果掉它性命的那个人叫斗牛士，战斗结束时已大汗淋漓，连外衣都湿透了，喉咙里干得直冒烟。

“这头公牛真勇敢。(2)”斗牛士把手里的剑递给助手时说了这么一句。他递剑时剑柄朝上，剑锋上滴着血，而每一滴血都来自那头勇敢公牛的心脏。那头公牛毙命后所有的问题都迎刃而解了，此时正被四匹马拖出斗牛场。

“不错，它就是比利亚马约尔侯爵的那头公牛。由于它对爱情过于忠贞，侯爵只好把它打发掉了。”那位无所不知的助手说。

“也许，我们人类也应该对爱情忠贞不渝。”斗牛士说。

————————————————————

(1) 美国一部动画片里的公牛，很受小朋友们欢迎。

(2) 原文为西班牙语。

一段非洲的往事

他在等着月亮升起，一边用手抚摸着他的狗基博，让它不要作声，可以感觉到狗毛都竖了起来。人和狗都在观望，都在倾听，眼看着月亮冉冉升起，由月光把他们的身影投在地上。他用胳膊搂住狗脖子，感觉得到它在发抖。夜间万籁俱寂。他们没有听见大象的脚步声。直待那条狗转头一望，吓得一缩身子紧靠他，戴维这才发现了大象。大象近在咫尺，身影遮住了他们，走过时悄无声息。山里吹来一股微风，将大象的气味送入了他们的鼻孔——那是一种刺鼻、陈腐、酸臭的气味。它擦身而过，戴维看见它左边的那根象牙特别长，好像都快触着地面了。

戴维和狗又等了等，见再没有别的象过来，于是便在月光下撒腿跑了起来。狗紧随在戴维的后面。戴维一停下来，狗鼻子就会撞在他的腿肚子上。

戴维决意要追上那头公象。到了森林边时，他们终于撵上了它。公象在朝山里走，迎着夜间阵阵微风缓步而行。戴维靠近，又看到了它月光下的影子，闻到了它身上的那股陈腐的酸臭味，却看不见它右边的象牙。他不敢再带着狗往近处走，于是顺着风向将狗引开，让它贴着一棵树的树根卧下，竭力想让它理解自己的意图。他以为狗会卧在那儿不动，谁知当他朝着大象那巨大的身躯靠近时，却感到湿湿的狗鼻子又贴在了他的腿肚子上。

他们俩如影随形地跟着大象，随它走到了林间的一片空地上。但见它站在那儿，摆动着巨大的耳朵。它的身子隐没在阴影里，而头部却沐浴在月光下。戴维悄悄从后边摸上去，轻轻用手箍住狗的嘴不让它出声，蹑手蹑脚前行，擦着夜风的边把头转向右呼吸，只感到微风吹拂在脸上——他始终顺着风向擦边走，绝不逆风而行让自己的气味飘到大象那儿。到了跟前，他可以看见大象在徐徐摆动着脑袋和巨大的耳朵，可以看见右边的象牙跟他的大腿一般粗，有点弯曲，几乎能挨着地面。

他和基博朝后退去；这下子，风吹在了他的脖子上，他们顺原路走出森林，来到了空旷的野地。狗跑到了他前边去，在小径旁的两根猎矛跟前停了下来。这两根猎矛是戴维跟踪大象时插在那儿做标记的。他把猎矛连同上面的皮圈皮套一起扛上肩，手里拿着他那根从不离身的最得意的长矛顺着小径返回营地去。此时月亮已爬高。营地那儿静悄悄，听不到鼓声，这叫他感到纳闷。如果父亲在营地，却不闻鼓声，这就让人觉得蹊跷了。

刚刚寻觅到大象踪迹的时候，戴维已经感到浑身疲倦了。在这之前的很长一段时间，他都显得比那两个大人精力充沛，身体状态良好。寻象的过程当中，那两人慢慢腾腾的，父亲规定每一个小时休息一次，这叫他很不耐烦。他原本是可以跑到前边去的，速度可以比父亲及朱马快得多。可是，等到他感到累了的时候，那两人状况依旧。中午时分，他们按照惯例又只休息了五分钟。之后，他发现朱马的脚步加快了一些。也许并没有加快，只是看上去提速罢了。此时，象粪比以前新鲜了，尽管摸上去仍没有热气。上次见到一堆象粪之后，朱马将猎枪交给他扛，可是扛了有一个小时的时间，朱马看看他疲惫的面色，又把猎枪要了回去。他们一行沿着山坡一路穿行，可是后来大象的足印下山去了，从森林的缺口可以望得见远处坑洼不平的原野。“下来的路可就难走了，戴维。”父亲说道。

这时他才意识到，在戴维领着他们找到大象的踪迹时，就应该让戴维回营地了。朱马老早就知道这是有必要的，而作为父亲的他是方才醒悟过来的。开弓已没有回头之箭了。这是他犯下的又一个错误，现在没有办法，只有赌一赌运气了。

戴维低头看看大象留下的巨大、扁平、圆圆的足印，发现有一簇凤尾草被踩倒，一株断了茎的杂草正在枯死。朱马捡起那株杂草，抬头看了看太阳，然后将杂草递给了戴维的父亲，而父亲将杂草拿在手里左看右看的。戴维注意到杂草结出的白花已经发蔫，在渐渐凋零，却仍没有被太阳晒干，花瓣尚没有脱落。

“快找到了。”戴维的父亲说，“咱们走吧。”

下午天色渐晚，他们仍行进在坑洼不平的原野上。戴维早已犯困了，望一望身边的两个大人，情知困意成了他的头号大敌。于是紧跟上大人的步点，尽量不掉队，竭力要摆脱掉袭上身来的困劲。追踪大象，两个大人轮流换班，一小时一班，下了班的那个会时不时回头查看，看戴维是不是仍跟在后边。天黑后在森林里选了块干燥的地方扎营。戴维倒头便睡，醒来时看见朱马手拿软皮平底鞋，光着脚片在检查脚上是否有血泡。他睡着后，父亲脱下外套盖在了他身上，此时坐在他旁边正在吃一块煮熟的冷肉和两片面包。见他醒来，父亲将装有凉茶的水壶递给他让他喝。

“大象也是需要吃喝的。”父亲说，“你的脚没事，跟朱马的脚一样结实。慢慢吃点东西，喝点茶，然后继续睡你的觉。我们俩是没事的。”

“对不起，我太困了。”

“你和基博寻找大象，跑了一整夜，哪能不困呢。想吃，就再吃些肉吧。”

“不饿了。”

“好吧。饮用水还够三天喝的呢。明天就又有水源了。山里的溪水多着呢。”

“那只大象是要到哪里去？”

“朱马觉得他能摸得透。”

“不会弄得竹篮打水一场空吧。”

“没那么糟糕，戴维。”

“那我就继续睡我的觉了。”戴维说，“不用盖你的外套了。”

没等父亲跟他说声晚安，戴维就睡着了。他中间醒了一次，看见月光照到了脸上，不由想起了大象站在森林里扑扇着大耳朵的情景——由于象牙太重，脑袋都垂下来了。这天夜里回忆起大象，他有一种空落落的感觉，便以为是醒来肚子饿导致的。其实并非如此——这是他在接下来的三天里才发现的。

次日的情况非常糟糕，远没有到中午之前，戴维就发现小孩和大人之间的差别并不仅仅在于缺觉。头三个小时，他的精神头比大人大，自告奋勇地问朱马要那只.303口径的步枪扛，而朱马摇了摇头，脸上一点笑容也没有。朱马一直都是他最好的朋友，曾手把手地教他打猎。他心中暗忖：他昨天还提出让我扛枪呢，今天我的状态比昨天好，却不让我扛了。当时他的精神头固然不错，可是到了十点钟的时候，他就发现今天的状况跟昨天一样糟糕，或者说更糟糕。

他原以为自己追踪大象跟父亲一般棒，就和他以为打猎打得跟父亲一般好，现在看来这种想法太愚蠢了。他知道个中的原因并非仅仅因为他们是成年人。他们可是职业猎手呀！他现在终于明白了朱马不苟言笑的原因。两个大人对大象的一举一动都了如指掌，遇见情况，两人无须说话，只要打个手势便可以心领神会。碰到难以判断的现象，父亲总是听朱马的。看见前边有一条小溪，他们留住脚步给水壶灌水。父亲说：“别多灌，够今天喝的就行了，戴维。”当他们跨越了坑洼不平的原野，爬山向森林进发时，大象的足印朝右一拐，拐上了一条古老的象径。他看见父亲和朱马在商量。当他走过去时，朱马回首望了望他们刚才走过的路，然后又眺望了一眼远方干涸的地区那一座座像孤岛一样的石头山，似乎在根据远方天地交接之处三座碧绿的山峰目测此处的方位。

“朱马现在知道大象要到哪里去了。”父亲解释说，“他以前就认为自己是心中有数的，可后来大象一拐弯，跑到了这里来。”父亲边说边回头望了一眼他们花了一天的时间才穿越的那片原野，“接下来的路就相当顺了，只是仍需要爬爬山。”

他们一行翻山越岭，直至天黑，然后找了块干燥的地方扎营。就在眼看太阳就要落山的时候，有一小群鸡鹑横穿小径，戴维急忙取过弹弓打杀了两只。鸡鹑走上古老的象径时，一副闲庭信步的样子，只只都肥嘟嘟的。其中的一只背部中矢，扑扇着翅膀，一跌一撞的，另一只跑上前施救，戴维又装上一粒石子，一拉弹弓，射出去的石子击中了第二只鸡鹑的肋骨。他跑过去捡猎物，惊得其他的鸡鹑呼地四散逃窜。朱马回头看看，这次罕见地露出了笑容。戴维将两只中矢的鸡鹑捡起，见它们都肥肥的，羽毛平整，拿在手里暖乎乎的。然后，他把鸡鹑的头在猎刀的柄上摔打了几下，结果了它们的性命。

扎营过夜时，父亲说道：“这么肥的鸡鹑以前从没见过。好样的，你一次就打中了两只。”

朱马将两只鸡鹑串在一根棍子上，架在一小堆炭火上烤。父亲往烧瓶的瓶盖里倒了些威士忌，加了点水，一边喝，一边和戴维斜靠在那儿观望朱马忙活。鸡鹑烤好后，朱马将胸肉和心分发给了父子俩，自己吃鸡鹑的脖子、脊背和腿。

“你的贡献可真是不小，戴维。”父亲说，“现在，咱们的干粮充足得多了。”

“距离大象还有多远？”戴维问。

“已经非常近了。”父亲说，“关键要看月亮升起时它是否继续前行。今夜的月亮出来要比昨夜晚一个小时，比你发现它的那天夜里晚两个小时。”

“朱马怎么那么有信心，觉得自己知道它要到哪里去？”

“就在离此不远的地方，朱马曾经开枪打伤了它，猎杀了它的‘卫兵’。”

“什么时候？”

“据他说，那是五年前的事了。他的说法也不一定准确。他说你当时还是个‘托托’(1)呢。”

“这头象成了光杆司令啦？”

“他说是的。他再没见过它，只是从别人口中听说过它。”

“他说这头象有多大？”

“光象牙都差不多有两百磅吧，比我所见过的象都要大。他说只有一头比这还大，也是出没于这一带。”

“我该睡觉了，”戴维说，“希望明天精力能充沛些。”

“你今天表现得很出色，”父亲说，“我为你感到非常自豪。朱马也跟我一样。”

夜间月亮升起后，戴维一觉醒来，不由胡思乱想起来，觉得两个大人也许很欣赏他眼明手快地射杀了两只鸟禽，在别的方面不会为他感到自豪的。另外，是他那天夜里发现了这头象，并一路追踪，看见两只象牙都还在，然后返回找到两个大人，带他们寻了过来。这一点，恐怕也会叫他们感到自豪的。可是，危险的追踪一旦开始，他就派不上用场了，还可能会坏了他们的事，就跟那天夜里他靠近大象，差点没让基博搅了局一样。最初在时间还充裕时，他们却没有打发他回去，此时一定会为此而自恨自怨了。这头象有两根象牙，每一根重达二百磅。正是因为象牙超常的大，才使得这头大象遭到追杀。此时他们三个要猎杀这头象，也是为了这两根巨牙。

戴维有信心，认为他们一定能如愿以偿。这一天，他咬牙坚持了下来。中午时分，行进的速度拖垮了他，但他仍继续紧追不舍。这种坚韧不拔的精神恐怕也会叫大人为他而感到自豪的。不过，他毕竟没有做出实际的贡献，没有他这个累赘，大人们会轻松得多呢。在白天，他曾经三番五次产生悔意，觉得自己不该把有关大象的线索说出来，记得下午的时候他还希望自己压根就没有看见这头象。此刻在月光下醒来，他又觉得以前的想法并非自己的真意。

次日早晨，他们跟着大象的足印走上了一条古老的象径——那象径穿过森林，已被大象踩得硬硬的。看上去，就好像火山的熔岩一冷却，该地区长出又高又密的林子，就有大象在这条小径上走了。

朱马信心十足，他们行进的速度很快。朱马和父亲显得极为笃定，行走在象径上一副轻轻松松的样子。穿过时明时暗的密林时，朱马甚至还把他的.303口径的猎枪交给了戴维扛。后来遇见几堆还冒着热气的大象粪便和一些圆圆的、扁平的足印（这些都是从小径左侧密林里出来的一群象留下的），他们便迷失了那头巨牙象的踪迹。朱马极为恼火，一把将那支.303口径的猎枪从戴维手里拿了过去。到了下午，他们才找到象群，悄悄地挨近，从树干间的缝隙望得见大象灰色的身躯，看见它们扑扇着大耳朵，长鼻子一卷一伸，听见咔嚓咔嚓树枝被折断以及树木被象鼻子卷倒的声音，还听见大象肚子里传出的咕噜咕噜的声音和象粪落地的噼啪声。

最后，他们终于发现了那头老公象的踪迹——老公象的足印拐了个弯，转到了一条比较狭窄的象径上。朱马瞧瞧戴维的父亲，咧嘴一笑，露出了一口大黄牙。父亲点了点头。他们俩的样子，就好像有什么不可告人的秘密似的，那天夜里戴维在营地找到他俩，他们就是这副表情。

没过多久，谜底就揭开了。秘密就藏在右侧的森林里——老公象的足印便是通向那里的。原来是一个大象的头骨，高度达到戴维的胸前，因日晒雨淋已发白。头骨的前额上有一处深深的凹陷，鼻梁两旁是两个发白的、空空的眼窝，原来的象牙已被凿走，留下的是两个带有凿痕的空窟窿。

朱马指了指他们追踪的那头大象曾经站过的地方——那头大象曾伫立在头骨前，低头看着它。那头大象曾用鼻子将头骨从原地移开了一点，移到了此处，头骨旁留有它的长牙尖触地的痕印。他还让戴维看白骨额头凹陷处的一个弹孔，以及耳朵根密布的四个弹孔。他冲戴维笑笑，又冲戴维的父亲笑笑，从口袋里掏出一颗.303口径的子弹，将弹头塞进头骨前额的弹孔里，刚好塞得下。

“朱马就是在这儿打伤那头大公象的。”父亲说，“这头骨是它的‘卫兵’的。那也是一头大公象，其实就是它的朋友。它冲过来，朱马一枪撂倒了它，又在耳朵根补几枪要了它的命。”

朱马指给他们看了看满地的碎骨，描述了那头大公象是怎样徘徊于碎骨场。戴维父子对这一发现颇为高兴。

“你看这两个朋友在一起有多长时间了？”戴维问父亲。

“这我就一点不知道了。”父亲说，“你问朱马吧。”

“你还是问他吧。”

父亲和朱马交谈了几句。朱马瞧瞧戴维，哈哈地笑了。

“他说它们在一起的时间之长大概四五倍于你的年龄。”父亲对戴维说，“其实他也不清楚，也不关心这个。”

戴维心想：“我关心这个。我在月光下看到它时，它孤苦伶仃的。而我有基博做伴，基博也有我相陪。它又不伤害任何人，而我们却追踪它，来到它凭吊亡友的地方，非置它于死地不可。要怪都怪我，是我出卖了它。”

朱马找到了那头大象的踪迹，对父亲做了个手势，他们一行又出发了。

戴维暗忖：“我父亲又没必要靠猎象糊口。要是当初我没看见这头象，把它告诉大人，朱马是找不到它的。他曾碰运气发现了它，打伤了它，杀害了它的朋友。我和基博发现它后，千不该万不该，不该告诉大人，而应该为它保密，把秘密永远埋藏在心里，就让两个大人喝他们的酒，醉他们的吧。那时的朱马醉得不省人事，叫都叫不醒呢。今后不管有什么事都要藏在心里，再也不讲出去了。杀了大象卖掉象牙，朱马又会醉生梦死，要不然就再给自己娶个老婆。我真傻，当初为什么就没有帮帮这头大象呢？当初，第二天不跟着来就好了。那也不行，因为那样无法拖住他们。朱马照样还会来的。悔不该把大象的踪迹告诉了他们。千不该万不该，不该告诉他们。以此为戒，以后有事情绝不告诉他人。不管再发生什么事情，决不讲出去。”

父亲等着他赶上来后，轻声细语地对他说：“那只象在这儿休息过。现在，它走路不像以前走得那么快了。咱们随时都可以追上它。”

“猎什么象，猎个狗屎！”戴维小声嘟哝了一句。

“你说什么？”父亲问他。

“猎什么象，猎个狗屎！”戴维又低声重复了一遍。

“你小心点，可别把事情搞砸了。”父亲冲他说道，然后又狠狠瞪了他一眼。

“总算把事情摊开了。”戴维心想，“他可不笨，这下子了解我的心思了，以后再也不会信任我了。这样倒好，我才不稀罕让他信任呢。反正以后有事情我决不告诉他，也不告诉任何人，再怎么也不告诉他们。我发誓：绝不告诉任何人！”

这天上午，他们追到了远处的山坡上。那只象不再似以前那般匆匆赶路了，而是漫无目的地游荡，时不时停下来吃上点东西。戴维知道他们正一点点接近它。

他竭力想回忆回忆自己以前对大象的感受，觉得自己对它并无感情可言。对此，他必须铭记在心。他只是太累了，由此推想到了老年的不易，继而产生了伤感。正是由于自己年幼体弱，他才能体会到衰弱暮年的惨景。

想到基博，他倍感孤独，再想想是朱马枪杀了那只大象的朋友，便有兔死狐悲之感，对朱马恨恨不已，仿佛大象和他有手足之情。那天在月光下看到那只象，紧紧地跟着它，到了空地时距离大象仅有咫尺之遥，巨大的象牙能看得清清楚楚，他知道那幅情景对自己产生了深远的影响。可是，他所不知道的是那样美好的情景再也不会出现了。父亲和朱马要杀死那头象，而自己却无法阻止。是他出卖了大象，竟然跑回营地把大象的踪迹告诉了大人。他心想，要是我和基博长了象牙，他们也会杀我们的。不过，他知道这仅仅是不着边的胡想而已。

那只象可能要去寻找它出生的地方，而大人们就是要在那儿杀死它，使这件事有个圆满的收场。本来，他们是想在杀死它朋友的地方就地要它的命。真是一场闹剧。杀死大象，这才会叫他们称心如意。这两个杀象的凶手实在可恶！

此时，他们追到了遮天蔽日的密林的边上，大象就在前方不远的地方，戴维都可以闻到它身上的气味了。只听见大象折树枝弄出咔嚓咔嚓的响动。父亲把手搭在戴维的肩上，让他朝后退，等在密林的外边，然后从衣袋里取出个布袋，掏出一大把灰扬到空中。灰从空中飘落时，微微朝着他们这个方向落下。父亲冲着朱马点点头，弓腰跟随他进了密林深处。戴维望着他们的背影——那两人的臀部时隐时现，悄无声息，听不见任何响动。

戴维纹丝不动，静听大象吃东西发出的声音。就像那天夜里月光下摸到它跟前，看见了它漂亮的巨牙时一样，他可以闻到它那浓烈的体味。等了一会，那声音消失了，气味也闻不到了。突然，那支.303口径的猎枪响了，声音尖利、刺耳。接着，父亲的那支.450口径的猎枪也响了，响了两声，震天动地的。随后，枪声噼里啪啦响成了一片，像炒豆一样。他一头钻进了林子，见朱马一副惶恐的样子，额头上鲜血如注，流得满脸都是。父亲脸色煞白，怒不可遏。

“它冲过来，把朱马撞倒了。”父亲说，“朱马击中了它的头部。”

“你击中了它的哪个部位？”

“我没管哪个部位，哪儿好打就打哪儿。”父亲说，“快顺着血迹朝前追。”

只见到处都是大象的血。有一股血喷得有戴维的头那么高，染红了树干、树叶和藤蔓；还有一股比这一股要低多了，是黑红色的，散发出大象胃里的酸臭味。

“它的内脏中了枪弹。”父亲说，“它肯定倒下去了，或者动不了了——但愿如此。”他在后面补充了一句。

他们找到大象，见它果然动不了了。伤痛和绝望交织在一起，使得它寸步难移。它从觅食的地方穿过茂密的林子，又走过一片稀疏的林带，挣扎着来到了这里。戴维和父亲是循着血迹斑斑的大象的足印找来的。当时大象钻进了一片稠密的林子，戴维看见它站在那里，灰色的庞大身躯靠在树干上。从后边看，只能看见它的臀部。父亲朝前摸去，戴维紧随其后。父子俩走到大象的身边，觉得它大得就像艘轮船。它的腰部鲜血泉涌而出，顺着两侧哗哗地朝下流淌。父亲举枪射击，大象把头连同那两根巨大的象牙缓慢而沉重地转过来，用眼睛望着他们。当父亲的第二声枪响时，大象摇晃了几下，像是一棵被伐倒的大树一样，轰隆朝着他们倒了下来，然而尚未断气。原先它只是动弹不得，现在肩胛骨被打碎，才倒了下来。它一动不动，但眼睛却充满了生气，直直地盯着戴维。它的眼睫毛很长，一双眼睛生机蓬勃——戴维从未见过如此充满生命力的东西。

“用那支.303口径的枪朝它的耳朵眼里打。”父亲说，“快点。”

“要打你自己打吧。”戴维说。

这时，朱马满脸是血地一瘸一拐走了过来，额头上的皮掉下来遮在左眼上方，鼻梁骨都露了出来，一只耳朵伤得不轻。他一声不响地从戴维手中拿过枪来，将枪口一伸，几乎塞进了大象的耳朵眼里，怒气冲冲地把枪栓一拉一推，连开了两枪。第一声枪响时，大象的眼睛还睁得大大的，随后便开始变得呆滞，鲜血从它的耳朵里奔涌而出，形成两条鲜红的溪流，顺着满是皱纹的灰色象皮潺潺流淌。这些血的颜色与别的血是不一样的。戴维心想，这幅情景我必须记住。他记住是记住了，但仅仅记住是解决不了问题的。大象原来的那种雍容的气质、尊贵的神态以及威风凛凛的容貌已不复存在，转眼间它变成了一大堆皱巴巴的皮肉。

“啊，总算结束了，戴维。有你一份功劳呢。”父亲说，“应该生堆火，让我给朱马包扎包扎伤口。到这儿来，你这个满身是血的矮胖子(2)。先不要急着摆弄那象牙。”

朱马笑嘻嘻地走了过来，手里拎着象尾巴，上面没有毛，光秃秃的。两人开了个下流玩笑。接着，父亲说起了斯瓦希里语，语速很快：“此处离水源地有多远？还要走多远才能找到人把这两根象牙运出去？怎么样，你这个狗日的饭桶？伤在哪里了？”

听了朱马的回答后，父亲对戴维说：“你和我一起去把丢在那儿的背包取回来。朱马留在这儿捡柴生火。医药箱在我的包里放着呢。咱们赶天黑之前回来。朱马的伤不是抓伤，不会感染的。走吧。”

傍晚时分，戴维坐在火堆旁望着脸上被缝了几针、断了几根肋骨的朱马，不由浮想联翩：“大象试图撞死他，是不是认出了他就是杀害它朋友的凶手？”他希望情况是这样。如今，大象成了他心目中的英雄，就像他长久以来视父亲为英雄一样。他心想：“它如此年迈，又是那样疲倦，竟然还能拼死一搏，让人难以相信。它显然是要置朱马于死地。但它看我的时候，似乎并无害我之意，只是显得很伤心，跟我心里的感受是一样的。就在它的死亡日，它还去看望了自己的老朋友。”

戴维仍记得，大象的眼睛一旦失去了生气，它所有雍容高贵的气质便烟消云散了。他和父亲取背包归来时，尽管傍晚时分空气凉爽，大象却已开始肿胀。那只大象已不复存在，成了一具死尸，有着灰色的皱巴巴的皮，全身浮肿，他们为之而起杀机的两根巨大的象牙上满是褐色和黄色的斑点。他见象牙上沾了血，已经凝固，便用指甲抠了一些下来，就像抠掉信封上的火漆一样，将其放入衬衣口袋里。除了从大象那儿获取了有关什么叫孤独的知识以外，再就是这点血块了。

那天夜里在火堆旁，在拔出象牙之后，父亲想和他说会儿话。

“这头象是有人命在身的，戴维。”父亲说道，“据朱马说，没人清楚它到底杀死过多少人。”

“是那些人先要杀它的，对不对？”

“当然喽，”父亲说，“有那么两根象牙，谁不眼红。”

“那怎么能说它是个杀人犯呢？”

“随你怎么想吧。”父亲说，“很遗憾，你对那头象竟有如此糊涂的想法。”

“真希望它把朱马也杀死才好呢。”戴维说。

“我觉得这话说得有点太过分了。”父亲说，“要知道，朱马可是你的朋友呀。”

“已经不是了。”

“你可不能对他说这话。”

“他自己心里是清楚的。”

“我觉得你错怪了他。”父亲说。

父子两人的对话到此也就结束了。

后来，他们费尽千辛万苦，总算把象牙安安全全运了回去。两根象牙靠在枝条和泥巴筑成的房屋墙壁上，尖挨着尖。那象牙简直太高了，太粗了，叫人即便用手摸着都不敢相信这是真的。在两个尖相挨的地方，两根象牙都各有弯弯的弧度，没人能够得着那打弯处的顶部，连戴维的父亲也力所不及。朱马和他们父子俩成了英雄，基博成了英雄的狗，那几个抬象牙的人也成了英雄——那几个抬夫喝了酒有些醉意，还执意要喝，非得喝个酩酊大醉不可。

就在这时，只听父亲说道：“你愿意和解吗，戴维？”

“好吧。”戴维应了一声，心里却想到他反正已决定以后再不把自己的想法往外讲了。

“这叫我高兴，”(3)亲说，“这样事情就简单得多，好办得多了。”

父子两人坐在无花果树荫下的长者席上喝着啤酒，那两根象牙靠在小屋的墙壁上。啤酒盛在葫芦杯里，由一个年轻姑娘和她的弟弟（英雄的专职侍童）一杯杯端上席。小侍童和英雄的狗基博一道守在身边，席地而坐。就连小英雄戴维的那只小公鸡也身价百倍，被提升为英雄的随身侍从。他们喝着啤酒，听见大鼓声骤起，鼓点越来越急。

————————————————————

(1) 土著语：小不点。

(2) 旧童谣中的蛋状人物，从墙上掉下来被摔碎。

(3) 子两人坐在无花果树荫下的长者席上喝着啤酒，那两根象牙

The Short Happy Life of Francis Macomber

It was now lunch time and they were all sitting under the double green fly of the dining tent pretending that nothing had happened.

“Will you have lime juice or lemon squash?”Macomber asked.

“I'll have a gimlet,”Robert Wilson told him.

“I'll have a gimlet too. I need something,”Macomber's wife said.

“I suppose it's the thing to do,”Macomber agreed.“Tell him to make three gimlets.”

The mess boy had started them already, lifting the bottles out of the canvas cooling bags that sweated wet in the wind that blew through the trees that shaded the tents.

“What had I ought to give them?”Macomber asked.

“A quid would be plenty,”Wilson told him.“You don't want to spoil them.”

“Will the headman distribute it?”

“Absolutely.”

Francis Macomber had, half an hour before, been carried to his tent from the edge of the camp in triumph on the arms and shoulders of the cook, the personal boys, the skinner and the porters. The gun-bearers had taken no part in the demonstration. When the native boys put him down at the door of his tent, he had shaken all their hands, received their congratulations, and then gone into the tent and sat on the bed until his wife came in. She did not speak to him when she came in and he left the tent at once to wash his face and hands in the portable wash basin outside and go over to the dining tent to sit in a comfortable canvas chair in the breeze and the shade.

“You've got your lion,”Robert Wilson said to him,“and a damned fine one too.”

Mrs. Macomber looked at Wilson quickly. She was an extremely handsome and well-kept woman of the beauty and social position which had, five years before, commanded five thousand dollars as the price of endorsing, with photographs, a beauty product which she had never used. She had been married to Francis Macomber for eleven years.

“He is a good lion, isn't he?”Macomber said. His wife looked at him now. She looked at both these men as though she had never seen them before.

One, Wilson, the white hunter, she knew she had never truly seen before. He was about middle height with sandy hair, a stubby mustache, a very red face and extremely cold blue eyes with faint white wrinkles at the corners that grooved merrily when he smiled. He smiled at her now and she looked away from his face at the way his shoulders sloped in the loose tunic he wore with the four big cartridges held in loops where the left breast pocket should have been, at his big brown hands, his old slacks, his very dirty boots and back to his red face again. She noticed where the baked red of his face stopped in a white line that marked the circle left by his Stetson hat that hung now from one of the pegs of the tent pole.

“Well, here's to the lion,”Robert Wilson said. He smiled at her again and, not smiling, she looked curiously at her husband.

Francis Macomber was very tall, very well built if you did not mind that length of bone, dark, his hair cropped like an oarsman, rather thin-lipped, and was considered handsome. He was dressed in the same sort of safari clothes that Wilson wore except that his were new, he was thirty-five years old, kept himself very fit, was good at court games, had a number of big-game fishing records, and had just shown himself, very publicly, to be a coward.

“Here's to the lion,”he said.“I can't ever thank you for what you did.”

Margaret, his wife, looked away from him and back to Wilson.

“Let's not talk about the lion,”she said.

Wilson looked over at her without smiling and now she smiled at him.

“It's been a very strange day,”she said.“Hadn't you ought to put your hat on even under the canvas at noon? You told me that, you know.”

“Might put it on,”said Wilson.

“You know you have a very red face, Mr. Wilson,”she told him and smiled again.

“Drink,”said Wilson.

“I don't think so,”she said.“Francis drinks a great deal, but his face is never red.”

“It's red today,”Macomber tried a joke.

“No,”said Margaret.“It's mine that's red today. But Mr. Wilson's is always red.”

“Must be racial,”said Wilson.“I say, you wouldn't like to drop my beauty as a topic, would you?”

“I've just started on it.”

“Let's chuck it,”said Wilson.

“Conversation is going to be so difficult,”Margaret said.

“Don't be silly, Margot,”her husband said.

“No difficulty,”Wilson said.“Got a damn fine lion.”

Margot looked at them both and they both saw that she was going to cry. Wilson had seen it coming for a long time and he dreaded it. Macomber was past dreading it.

“I wish it hadn't happened. Oh, I wish it hadn't happened,”she said and started for her tent. She made no noise of crying but they could see that her shoulders were shaking under the rose-colored, sun-proofed shirt she wore.

“Women upset,”said Wilson to the tall man.“Amounts to nothing. Strain on the nerves and one thing'n another.”

“No,”said Macomber.“I suppose that I rate that for the rest of my life now.”

“Nonsense. Let's have a spot of the giant killer,”said Wilson.“Forget the whole thing. Nothing to it anyway.”

“We might try,”said Macomber.“I won't forget what you did for me though.”

“Nothing,”said Wilson.“All nonsense.”

So they sat there in the shade where the camp was pitched under some wide-topped acacia trees with a boulder-strewn cliff behind them, and a stretch of grass that ran to the bank of a boulder-filled stream in front with forest beyond it, and drank their just-cool lime drinks and avoided one another's eyes while the boys set the table for lunch. Wilson could tell that the boys all knew about it now and when he saw Macomber's personal boy looking curiously at his master while he was putting dishes on the table he snapped at him in Swahili. The boy turned away with his face blank.

“What were you telling him?”Macomber asked.

“Nothing. Told him to look alive or I'd see he got about fifteen of the best.”“What's that? Lashes?”

“It's quite illegal,”Wilson said.“You're supposed to fine them.”

“Do you still have them whipped?”

“Oh, yes. They could raise a row if they chose to complain. But they don't. They prefer it to the fines.”

“How strange!”said Macomber.

“Not strange, really,”Wilson said.“Which would you rather do? Take a good birching or lose your pay?”

Then he felt embarrassed at asking it and before Macomber could answer he went on,“We all take a beating every day, you know, one way or another.”

This was no better.“Good God,”he thought.“I am a diplomat, aren't I?”

“Yes, we take a beating,”said Macomber, still not looking at him.“I'm awfully sorry about that lion business. It doesn't have to go any further, does it? I mean no one will hear about it, will they?”

“You mean will I tell it at the Mathaiga Club?”Wilson looked at him now coldly. He had not expected this. So he's a bloody four-letter man as well as a bloody coward, he thought. I rather liked him too until today. But how is one to know about an American?

“No,”said Wilson.“I'm a professional hunter. We never talk about our clients. You can be quite easy on that. It's supposed to be bad form to ask us not to talk though.”

He had decided now that to break would be much easier. He would eat, then, by himself and could read a book with his meals. They would eat by themselves. He would see them through the safari on a very formal basis—what was it the French called it? Distinguished consideration—and it would be a damn sight easier than having to go through this emotional trash. He'd insult him and make a good clean break. Then he could read a book with his meals and he'd still be drinking their whisky. That was the phrase for it when a safari went bad. You ran into another white hunter and you asked,“How is everything going?”and he answered,“Oh, I'm still drinking their whisky,”and you knew everything had gone to pot.

“I'm sorry,”Macomber said and looked at him with his American face that would stay adolescent until it became middle-aged, and Wilson noted his crew-cropped hair, fine eyes only faintly shifty, good nose, thin lips and handsome jaw.“I'm sorry I didn't realize that. There are lots of things I don't know.”

So what could he do, Wilson thought. He was all ready to break it off quickly and neatly and here the beggar was apologizing after he had just insulted him. He made one more attempt.“Don't worry about me talking,”he said.“I have a living to make. You know in Africa no woman ever misses her lion and no white man ever bolts.”

“I bolted like a rabbit,”Macomber said.

Now what in hell were you going to do about a man who talked like that, Wilson wondered.

Wilson looked at Macomber with his flat, blue, machine-gunner's eyes and the other smiled back at him. He had a pleasant smile if you did not notice how his eyes showed when he was hurt.

“Maybe I can fix it up on buffalo,”he said.“We're after them next, aren't we?”

“In the morning if you like,”Wilson told him. Perhaps he had been wrong. This was certainly the way to take it. You most certainly could not tell a damned thing about an American. He was all for Macomber again. If you could forget the morning. But, of course, you couldn't. The morning had been about as bad as they come.

“Here comes the Memsahib,”he said. She was walking over from her tent looking refreshed and cheerful and quite lovely. She had a very perfect oval face, so perfect that you expected her to be stupid. But she wasn't stupid, Wilson thought, no, not stupid.

“How is the beautiful red-faced Mr. Wilson? Are you feeling better, Francis, my pearl?”

“Oh, much,”said Macomber.

“I've dropped the whole thing,”she said, sitting down at the table.“What importance is there to whether Francis is any good at killing lions? That's not his trade. That's Mr. Wilson's trade. Mr. Wilson is really very impressive killing anything. You do kill anything, don't you?”

“Oh, anything,”said Wilson.“Simply anything.”They are, he thought, the hardest in the world; the hardest, the cruelest, the most predatory and the most attractive and their men have softened or gone to pieces nervously as they have hardened. Or is it that they pick men they can handle? They can't know that much at the age they marry, he thought. He was grateful that he had gone through his education on American women before now because this was a very attractive one.

“We're going after buff in the morning,”he told her.

“I'm coming,”she said.

“No, you're not.”

“Oh, yes, I am. Mayn't I, Francis?”

“Why not stay in camp?”

“Not for anything,”she said.“I wouldn't miss something like today for anything.”

When she left, Wilson was thinking, when she went off to cry, she seemed a hell of a fine woman. She seemed to understand, to realize, to be hurt for him and for herself and to know how things really stood. She is away for twenty minutes and now she is back, simply enamelled in that American female cruelty. They are the damnedest women. Really the damnedest.

“We'll put on another show for you tomorrow,”Francis Macomber said.

“You're not coming,”Wilson said.

“You're very mistaken,”she told him.“And I want so to see you perform again. You were lovely this morning. That is if blowing things' heads off is lovely.”

“Here's the lunch,”said Wilson.“You're very merry, aren't you?”

“Why not? I didn't come out here to be dull.”

“Well, it hasn't been dull,”Wilson said. He could see the boulders in the river and the high bank beyond with the trees and he remembered the morning.

“Oh, no,”she said.“It's been charming. And tomorrow. You don't know how I look forward to tomorrow.”

“That's eland he's offering you,”Wilson said.

“They're the big cowy things that jump like hares, aren't they?”

“I suppose that describes them,”Wilson said.

“It's very good meat,”Macomber said.

“Did you shoot it, Francis?”she asked.

“Yes.”

“They're not dangerous, are they?”

“Only if they fall on you,”Wilson told her.

“I'm so glad.”

“Why not let up on the bitchery just a little, Margot,”Macomber said, cutting the eland steak and putting some mashed potato, gravy and carrot on the down-turned fork that tined through the piece of meat.

“I suppose I could,”she said,“since you put it so prettily.”

“Tonight we'll have champagne for the lion,”Wilson said.“It's a bit too hot at noon.”

“Oh, the lion,”Margot said.“I'd forgotten the lion!”

So, Robert Wilson thought to himself, she is giving him a ride, isn't she? Or do you suppose that's her idea of putting up a good show? How should a woman act when she discovers her husband is a bloody coward? She's damn cruel but they're all cruel. They govern, of course, and to govern one has to be cruel sometimes. Still, I've seen enough of their damn terrorism.

“Have some more eland,”he said to her politely.

That afternoon, late, Wilson and Macomber went out in the motor car with the native driver and the two gun-bearers. Mrs. Macomber stayed in the camp. It was too hot to go out, she said, and she was going with them in the early morning. As they drove off Wilson saw her standing under the big tree, looking pretty rather than beautiful in her faintly rosy khaki, her dark hair drawn back off her forehead and gathered in a knot low on her neck, her face as fresh, he thought, as though she were in England. She waved to them as the car went off through the swale of high grass and curved around through the trees into the small hills of orchard bush.

In the orchard bush they found a herd of impala, and leaving the car they stalked one old ram with long, wide-spread horns and Macomber killed it with a very creditable shot that knocked the buck down at a good two hundred yards and sent the herd off bounding wildly and leaping over one another's backs in long, leg-drawn-up leaps as unbelievable and as floating as those one makes sometimes in dreams.

“That was a good shot,”Wilson said.“They're a small target.”

“Is it a worth-while head?”Macomber asked.

“It's excellent,”Wilson told him.“You shoot like that and you'll have no trouble.”

“Do you think we'll find buffalo tomorrow?”

“There's a good chance of it. They feed out early in the morning and with luck we may catch them in the open.”

“I'd like to clear away that lion business,”Macomber said.“It's not very pleasant to have your wife see you do something like that.”

I should think it would be even more unpleasant to do it, Wilson thought, wife or no wife, or to talk about it having done it. But he said,“I wouldn't think about that any more. Any one could be upset by his first lion. That's all over.”

But that night after dinner and a whisky and soda by the fire before going to bed, as Francis Macomber lay on his cot with the mosquito bar over him and listened to the night noises it was not all over. It was neither all over nor was it beginning. It was there exactly as it happened with some parts of it indelibly emphasized and he was miserably ashamed at it. But more than shame he felt cold, hollow fear in him. The fear was still there like a cold slimy hollow in all the emptiness where once his confidence had been and it made him feel sick. It was still there with him now.

It had started the night before when he had wakened and heard the lion roaring somewhere up along the river. It was a deep sound and at the end there were sort of coughing grunts that made him seem just outside the tent, and when Francis Macomber woke in the night to hear it he was afraid. He could hear his wife breathing quietly, asleep. There was no one to tell he was afraid, nor to be afraid with him, and, lying alone, he did not know the Somali proverb that says a brave man is always frightened three times by a lion; when he first sees his track, when he first hears him roar and when he first confronts him. Then while they were eating breakfast by lantern light out in the dining tent, before the sun was up, the lion roared again and Francis thought he was just at the edge of camp.

“Sounds like an old-timer,”Robert Wilson said, looking up from his kippers and coffee.“Listen to him cough.”

“Is he very close?”

“A mile or so up the stream.”

“Will we see him?”

“We'll have a look.”

“Does his roaring carry that far? It sounds as though he were right in camp.”

“Carries a hell of a long way,”said Robert Wilson.“It's strange the way it carries. Hope he's a shootable cat. The boys said there was a very big one about here.”

“If I get a shot, where should I hit him,”Macomber asked,“to stop him?”

“In the shoulders,”Wilson said.“In the neck if you can make it. Shoot for bone. Break him down.”

“I hope I can place it properly,”Macomber said.

“You shoot very well,”Wilson told him.“Take your time. Make sure of him. The first one in is the one that counts.”

“What range will it be?”

“Can't tell. Lion has something to say about that. Don't shoot unless it's close enough so you can make sure.”

“At under a hundred yards?”Macomber asked.

Wilson looked at him quickly.

“Hundred's about right. Might have to take him a bit under. Shouldn't chance a shot at much over that. A hundred's a decent range. You can hit him wherever you want at that. Here comes the Memsahib.”

“Good morning,”she said.“Are we going after that lion?”

“As soon as you deal with your breakfast,”Wilson said.“How are you feeling?”

“Marvellous,”she said.“I'm very excited.”

“I'll just go and see that everything is ready.”Wilson went off. As he left the lion roared again.

“Noisy beggar,”Wilson said.“We'll put a stop to that.”

“What's the matter, Francis?”his wife asked him.

“Nothing,”Macomber said.

“Yes, there is,”she said.“What are you upset about?”

“Nothing,”he said.

“Tell me,”she looked at him.“Don't you feel well?”

“It's that damned roaring,”he said.“It's been going on all night, you know.”

“Why didn't you wake me,”she said.“I'd love to have heard it.”

“I've got to kill the damned thing,”Macomber said, miserably.

“Well, that's what you're out here for, isn't it?”

“Yes. But I'm nervous. Hearing the thing roar gets on my nerves.”

“Well then, as Wilson said, kill him and stop his roaring.”

“Yes, darling,”said Francis Macomber.“It sounds easy, doesn't it?”

“You're not afraid, are you?”

“Of course not. But I'm nervous from hearing him roar all night.”

“You'll kill him marvellously,”she said.“I know you will. I'm awfully anxious to see it.”

“Finish your breakfast and we'll be starting.”

“It's not light yet,”she said.“This is a ridiculous hour.”

Just then the lion roared in a deep-chested moaning, suddenly guttural, ascending vibration that seemed to shake the air and ended in a sigh and a heavy, deep-chested grunt.

“He sounds almost here,”Macomber's wife said.

“My God,”said Macomber.“I hate that damned noise.”

“It's very impressive.”

“Impressive. It's frightful.”

Robert Wilson came up then carrying his short, ugly, shockingly big-bored .505 Gibbs and grinning.

“Come on,”he said.“Your gun-bearer has your Springfield and the big gun. Everything's in the car. Have you solids?”

“Yes.”

“I'm ready,”Mrs. Macomber said.

“Must make him stop that racket,”Wilson said.“You get in front. The Memsahib can sit back here with me.”

They climbed into the motor car and, in the gray first daylight, moved off up the river through the trees. Macomber opened the breech of his rifle and saw he had metal-cased bullets, shut the bolt and put the rifle on safety. He saw his hand was trembling. He felt in his pocket for more cartridges and moved his fingers over the cartridges in the loops of his tunic front. He turned back to where Wilson sat in the rear seat of the doorless, box-bodied motor car beside his wife, them both grinning with excitement, and Wilson leaned forward and whispered,

“See the birds dropping. Means the old boy has left his kill.”

On the far bank of the stream Macomber could see, above the trees, vultures circling and plummeting down.

“Chances are he'll come to drink along here,”Wilson whispered.“Before he goes to lay up. Keep an eye out.”

They were driving slowly along the high bank of the stream which here cut deeply to its boulder-filled bed, and they wound in and out through big trees as they drove. Macomber was watching the opposite bank when he felt Wilson take hold of his arm. The car stopped.

“There he is,”he heard the whisper.“Ahead and to the right. Get out and take him. He's a marvellous lion.”

Macomber saw the lion now. He was standing almost broadside, his great head up and turned toward them. The early morning breeze that blew toward them was just stirring his dark mane, and the lion looked huge, silhouetted on the rise of bank in the gray morning light, his shoulders heavy, his barrel of a body bulking smoothly.

“How far is he?”asked Macomber, raising his rifle.

“About seventy-five. Get out and take him.”

“Why not shoot from where I am?”

“You don't shoot them from cars,”he heard Wilson saying in his ear.“Get out. He's not going to stay there all day.”

Macomber stepped out of the curved opening at the side of the front seat, onto the step and down onto the ground. The lion still stood looking majestically and coolly toward this object that his eyes only showed in silhouette, bulking like some super-rhino. There was no man smell carried toward him and he watched the object, moving his great head a little from side to side. Then watching the object, not afraid, but hesitating before going down the bank to drink with such a thing opposite him, he saw a man figure detach itself from it and he turned his heavy head and swung away toward the cover of the trees as he heard a cracking crash and felt the slam of a .30-06 220-grain solid bullet that bit his flank and ripped in sudden hot scalding nausea through his stomach. He trotted, heavy, bigfooted, swinging wounded full-bellied, through the trees toward the tall grass and cover, and the crash came again to go past him ripping the air apart. Then it crashed again and he felt the blow as it hit his lower ribs and ripped on through, blood sudden hot and frothy in his mouth, and he galloped toward the high grass where he could crouch and not be seen and make them bring the crashing thing close enough so he could make a rush and get the man that held it.

Macomber had not thought how the lion felt as he got out of the car. He only knew his hands were shaking and as he walked away from the car it was almost impossible for him to make his legs move. They were stiff in the thighs, but he could feel the muscles fluttering. He raised the rifle, sighted on the junction of the lion's head and shoulders and pulled the trigger. Nothing happened though he pulled until he thought his finger would break. Then he knew he had the safety on and as he lowered the rifle to move the safety over he moved another frozen pace forward, and the lion seeing his silhouette flow clear of the silhouette of the car, turned and started off at a trot, and, as Macomber fired, he heard a whunk that meant that the bullet was home; but the lion kept on going. Macomber shot again and every one saw the bullet throw a spout of dirt beyond the trotting lion. He shot again, remembering to lower his aim, and they all heard the bullet hit, and the lion went into a gallop and was in the tall grass before he had the bolt pushed forward.

Macomber stood there feeling sick at his stomach, his hands that held the Springfield still cocked, shaking, and his wife and Robert Wilson were standing by him. Beside him too were the two gun-bearers chattering in Wakamba.

“I hit him,”Macomber said.“I hit him twice.”

“You gut-shot him and you hit him somewhere forward,”Wilson said without enthusiasm. The gun-bearers looked very grave. They were silent now.

“You may have killed him,”Wilson went on.“We'll have to wait a while before we go in to find out”

“What do you mean?”

“Let him get sick before we follow him up.”

“Oh,”said Macomber.

“He's a hell of a fine lion,”Wilson said cheerfully.“He's gotten into a bad place though.”

“Why is it bad?”

“Can't see him until you're on him.”

“Oh,”said Macomber.

“Come on,”said Wilson.“The Memsahib can stay here in the car. We'll go to have a look at the blood spoor.”

“Stay here, Margot,”Macomber said to his wife. His mouth was very dry and it was hard for him to talk.

“Why?”she asked.

“Wilson says to.”

“We're going to have a look,”Wilson said.“You stay here. You can see even better from here.”

“All right.”

Wilson spoke in Swahili to the driver. He nodded and said,“Yes, Bwana.”

Then they went down the steep bank and across the stream, climbing over and around the boulders and up the other bank, pulling up by some projecting roots, and along it until they found where the lion had been trotting when Macomber first shot. There was dark blood on the short grass that the gun-bearers pointed out with grass stems, and that ran away behind the river bank trees.

“What do we do?”asked Macomber.

“Not much choice,”said Wilson.“We can't bring the car over. Bank's too steep. We'll let him stiffen up a bit and then you and I'll go in and have a look for him.”

“Can't we set the grass on fire?”Macomber asked.

“Too green.”

“Can't we send beaters?”

Wilson looked at him appraisingly.“Of course we can,”he said.“But it's just a touch murderous. You see, we know the lion's wounded. You can drive an unwounded lion—he'll move on ahead of a noise—but a wounded lion's going to charge. You can't see him until you're right on him. He'll make himself perfectly flat in cover you wouldn't think would hide a hare. You can't very well send boys in there to that sort of a show. Somebody bound to get mauled.”

“What about the gun-bearers?”

“Oh, they'll go with us. It's their shauri. You see, they signed on for it. They don't look too happy though, do they?”

“I don't want to go in there,”said Macomber. It was out before he knew he'd said it.

“Neither do I,”said Wilson very cheerily.“Really no choice though.”Then, as an afterthought, he glanced at Macomber and saw suddenly how he was trembling and the pitiful look on his face.

“You don't have to go in, of course,”he said.“That's what I'm hired for, you know. That's why I'm so expensive.”

“You mean you'd go in by yourself? Why not leave him there?”

Robert Wilson, whose entire occupation had been with the lion and the problem he presented, and who had not been thinking about Macomber except to note that he was rather windy, suddenly felt as though he had opened the wrong door in a hotel and seen something shameful.

“What do you mean?”

“Why not just leave him?”

“You mean pretend to ourselves he hasn't been hit?”

“No. Just drop it.”

“It isn't done.”

“Why not?”

“For one thing, he's certain to be suffering. For another, some one else might run onto him.”

“I see.”

“But you don't have to have anything to do with it.”

“I'd like to,”Macomber said.“I'm just scared, you know.”

“I'll go ahead when we go in,”Wilson said,“with Kongoni tracking. You keep behind me and a little to one side. Chances are we'll hear him growl. If we see him we'll both shoot. Don't worry about anything. I'll keep you backed up. As a matter of fact, you know, perhaps you'd better not go. It might be much better. Why don't you go over and join the Memsahib while I just get it over with?”

“No, I want to go.”

“All right,”said Wilson.“But don't go in if you don't want to. This is my shauri now, you know.”

“I want to go,”said Macomber.

They sat under a tree and smoked.

“Want to go back and speak to the Memsahib while we're waiting?”Wilson asked.

“No.”

“I'll just step back and tell her to be patient.”

“Good,”said Macomber. He sat there, sweating under his arms, his mouth dry, his stomach hollow feeling, wanting to find courage to tell Wilson to go on and finish off the lion without him. He could not know that Wilson was furious because he had not noticed the state he was in earlier and sent him back to his wife. While he sat there Wilson came up.“I have your big gun,”he said.“Take it. We've given him time, I think. Come on.”

Macomber took the big gun and Wilson said:

“Keep behind me and about five yards to the right and do exactly as I tell you.”Then he spoke in Swahili to the two gun-bearers who looked the picture of gloom.

“Let's go,”he said.

“Could I have a drink of water?”Macomber asked. Wilson spoke to the older gun-bearer, who wore a canteen on his belt, and the man unbuckled it, unscrewed the top and handed it to Macomber, who took it noticing how heavy it seemed and how hairy and shoddy the felt covering was in his hand. He raised it to drink and looked ahead at the high grass with the flat-topped trees behind it. A breeze was blowing toward them and the grass rippled gently in the wind. He looked at the gun-bearer and he could see the gun-bearer was suffering too with fear.

Thirty-five yards into the grass the big lion lay flattened out along the ground. His ears were back and his only movement was a slight twitching up and down of his long, black-tufted tail. He had turned at bay as soon as he had reached this cover and he was sick with the wound through his full belly, and weakening with the wound through his lungs that brought a thin foamy red to his mouth each time he breathed. His flanks were wet and hot and flies were on the little openings the solid bullets had made in his tawny hide, and his big yellow eyes, narrowed with hate, looked straight ahead, only blinking when the pain came as he breathed, and his claws dug in the soft baked earth. All of him, pain, sickness, hatred and all of his remaining strength, was tightening into an absolute concentration for a rush. He could hear the men talking and he waited, gathering all of himself into this preparation for a charge as soon as the men would come into the grass. As he heard their voices his tail stiffened to twitch up and down, and, as they came into the edge of the grass, he made a coughing grunt and charged.

Kongoni, the old gun-bearer, in the lead watching the blood spoor, Wilson watching the grass for any movement, his big gun ready, the second gun-bearer looking ahead and listening, Macomber close to Wilson, his rifle cocked, they had just moved into the grass when Macomber heard the blood-choked coughing grunt, and saw the swishing rush in the grass. The next thing he knew he was running; running wildly, in panic in the open, running toward the stream.

He heard the ca-ra-wong! of Wilson's big rifle, and again in a second crashing carawong! and turning saw the lion, horrible-looking now, with half his head seeming to be gone, crawling toward Wilson in the edge of the tall grass while the red-faced man worked the bolt on the short ugly rifle and aimed carefully as another blasting carawong! came from the muzzle, and the crawling, heavy, yellow bulk of the lion stiffened and the huge, mutilated head slid forward and Macomber, standing by himself in the clearing where he had run, holding a loaded rifle, while two black men and a white man looked back at him in contempt, knew the lion was dead. He came toward Wilson, his tallness all seeming a naked reproach, and Wilson looked at him and said:

“Want to take pictures?”

“No,”he said.

That was all any one had said until they reached the motor car. Then Wilson had said:

“Hell of a fine lion. Boys will skin him out. We might as well stay here in the shade.”

Macomber's wife had not looked at him nor he at her and he had sat by her in the back seat with Wilson sitting in the front seat. Once he had reached over and taken his wife's hand without looking at her and she had removed her hand from his. Looking across the stream to where the gun-bearers were skinning out the lion he could see that she had been able to see the whole thing. While they sat there his wife had reached forward and put her hand on Wilson's shoulder. He turned and she had leaned forward over the low seat and kissed him on the mouth.

“Oh, I say,”said Wilson, going redder than his natural baked color.

“Mr. Robert Wilson,”she said.“The beautiful red-faced Mr. Robert Wilson.”

Then she sat down beside Macomber again and looked away across the stream to where the lion lay, with uplifted, white-muscled, tendon-marked naked forearms, and white bloating belly, as the black men fleshed away the skin. Finally the gun-bearers brought the skin over, wet and heavy, and climbed in behind with it, rolling it up before they got in, and the motor car started. No one had said anything more until they were back in camp.

That was the story of the lion. Macomber did not know how the lion had felt before he started his rush, nor during it when the unbelievable smash of the .505 with a muzzle velocity of two tons had hit him in the mouth, nor what kept him coming after that, when the second ripping crash had smashed his hind quarters and he had come crawling on toward the crashing, blasting thing that had destroyed him. Wilson knew something about it and only expressed it by saying,“Damned fine lion,”but Macomber did not know how Wilson felt about things either. He did not know how his wife felt except that she was through with him.

His wife had been through with him before but it never lasted. He was very wealthy, and would be much wealthier, and he knew she would not leave him ever now. That was one of the few things that he really knew. He knew about that, about motor cycles—that was earliest—about motor cars, about duck-shooting, about fishing, trout, salmon and big-sea, about sex in books, many books, too many books, about all court games, about dogs, not much about horses, about hanging on to his money, about most of the other things his world dealt in, and about his wife not leaving him. His wife had been a great beauty and she was still a great beauty in Africa, but she was not a great enough beauty any more at home to be able to leave him and better herself and she knew it and he knew it. She had missed the chance to leave him and he knew it. If he had been better with women she would probably have started to worry about him getting another new, beautiful wife; but she knew too much about him to worry about him either. Also, he had always had a great tolerance which seemed the nicest thing about him if it were not the most sinister.

All in all they were known as a comparatively happily married couple, one of those whose disruption is often rumored but never occurs, and as the society columnist put it, they were adding more than a spice of adventure to their much envied and ever-enduring Romance by a Safari in what was known as Darkest Africa until the Martin Johnsons lighted it on so many silver screens where they were pursuing Old Simba the lion, the buffalo, Tembo the elephant and as well collecting specimens for the Museum of Natural History. This same columnist had reported them on the verge at least three times in the past and they had been. But they always made it up. They had a sound basis of union. Margot was too beautiful for Macomber to divorce her and Macomber had too much money for Margot ever to leave him.

It was now about three o'clock in the morning and Francis Macomber, who had been asleep a little while after he had stopped thinking about the lion, wakened and then slept again, woke suddenly, frightened in a dream of the bloody-headed lion standing over him, and listening while his heart pounded, he realized that his wife was not in the other cot in the tent. He lay awake with that knowledge for two hours.

At the end of that time his wife came into the tent, lifted her mosquito bar and crawled cozily into bed.

“Where have you been?”Macomber asked in the darkness.

“Hello,”she said.“Are you awake?”

“Where have you been?”

“I just went out to get a breath of air.”

“You did, like hell.”

“What do you want me to say, darling?”

“Where have you been?”

“Out to get a breath of air.”

“That's a new name for it. You are a bitch.”

“Well, you're a coward.”

“All right,”he said.“What of it?”

“Nothing as far as I'm concerned. But please let's not talk, darling, because I'm very sleepy.”

“You think that I'll take anything.”

“I know you will, sweet.”

“Well, I won't.”

“Please, darling, let's not talk. I'm so very sleepy.”

“There wasn't going to be any of that. You promised there wouldn't be.”

“Well, there is now,”she said sweetly.

“You said if we made this trip that there would be none of that. You promised.”

“Yes, darling. That's the way I meant it to be. But the trip was spoiled yesterday. We don't have to talk about it, do we?”

“You don't wait long when you have an advantage, do you?”

“Please let's not talk. I'm so sleepy, darling.”

“I'm going to talk.”

“Don't mind me then, because I'm going to sleep.”And she did.

At breakfast they were all three at the table before daylight and Francis Macomber found that, of all the many men that he had hated, he hated Robert Wilson the most.

“Sleep well?”Wilson asked in his throaty voice, filling a pipe.

“Did you?”

“Topping,”the white hunter told him.

You bastard, thought MaComber, you insolent bastard.

So she woke him when she came in, Wilson thought, looking at them both with his flat, cold eyes. Well, why doesn't he keep his wife where she belongs? What does he think I am, a bloody plaster saint? Let him keep her where she belongs. It's his own fault.

“Do you think we'll find buffalo?”Margot asked, pushing away a dish of apricots.

“Chance of it,”Wilson said and smiled at her.“Why don't you stay in camp?”

“Not for anything,”she told him.

“Why not order her to stay in camp?”Wilson said to Macomber.

“You order her,”said Macomber coldly.

“Let's not have any ordering, nor,”turning to Macomber,“any silliness, Francis,”Margot said quite pleasantly.

“Are you ready to start?”Macomber asked.

“Any time,”Wilson told him.“Do you want the Memsahib to go?”

“Does it make any difference whether I do or not?”

The hell with it, thought Robert Wilson. The utter complete hell with it. So this is what it's going to be like. Well, this is what it's going to be like, then.

“Makes no difference,”he said.

“You're sure you wouldn't like to stay in camp with her yourself and let me go out and hunt the buffalo?”Macomber asked.

“Can't do that,”said Wilson.“Wouldn't talk rot if I were you.”

“I'm not talking rot. I'm disgusted.”

“Bad word, disgusted.”

“Francis, will you please try to speak sensibly,”his wife said.

“I speak too damned sensibly,”Macomber said.“Did you ever eat such filthy food?”

“Something wrong with the food?”asked Wilson quietly.

“No more than with everything else.”

“I'd pull yourself together, laddybuck,”Wilson said very quietly.“There's a boy waits at table that understands a little English.”

“The hell with him.”

Wilson stood up and puffing on his pipe strolled away, speaking a few words in Swahili to one of the gun-bearers who was standing waiting for him. Macomber and his wife sat on at the table. He was staring at his coffee cup.

“If you make a scene I'll leave you, darling,”Margot said quietly.

“No, you won't.”

“You can try it and see.”

“You won't leave me.”

“No,”she said.“I won't leave you and you'll behave your self.”

“Behave myself? That's a way to talk. Behave myself.”

“Yes. Behave yourself.”

“Why don't you try behaving?”

“I've tried it so long. So very long.”

“I hate that red-faced swine,”Macomber said.“I loathe the sight of him.”

“He's really very nice.”

“Oh, shut up,”Macomber almost shouted. Just then the car came up and stopped in front of the dining tent and the driver and the two gunbearers got out. Wilson walked over and looked at the husband and wife sitting there at the table.

“Going shooting?”he asked.

“Yes,”said Macomber, standing up.“Yes.”

“Better bring a woolly. It will be cool in the car,”Wilson said.

“I'll get my leather jacket,”Margot said.

“The boy has it,”Wilson told her. He climbed into the front with the driver and Francis Macomber and his wife sat, not speaking, in the back seat.

Hope the silly beggar doesn't take a notion to blow the back of my head off, Wilson thought to himself. Women are a nuisance on safari.

The car was grinding down to cross the river at a pebbly ford in the gray daylight and then climbed, angling up the steep bank, where Wilson had ordered a way shovelled out the day before so they could reach the parklike wooded rolling country on the far side.

It was a good morning, Wilson thought. There was a heavy dew and as the wheels went through the grass and low bushes he could smell the odor of the crushed fronds. It was an odor like verbena and he liked this early morning smell of the dew, the crushed bracken and the look of the tree trunks showing black through the early morning mist, as the car made its way through the untracked, parklike country. He had put the two in the back seat out of his mind now and was thinking about buffalo. The buffalo that he was after stayed in the daytime in a thick swamp where it was impossible to get a shot, but in the night they fed out into an open stretch of country and if he could come between them and their swamp with the car, Macomber would have a good chance at them in the open. He did not want to hunt buff with Macomber in thick cover. He did not want to hunt buff or anything else with Macomber at all, but he was a professional hunter and he had hunted with some rare ones in his time. If they got buff today there would only be rhino to come and the poor man would have gone through his dangerous game and things might pick up. He'd have nothing more to do with the woman and Macomber would get over that too. He must have gone through plenty of that before by the look of things. Poor beggar. He must have a way of getting over it. Well, it was the poor sod's own bloody fault.

He, Robert Wilson, carried a double size cot on safari to accommodate any windfalls he might receive. He had hunted for a certain clientele, the international, fast, sporting set, where the women did not feel they were getting their money's worth unless they had shared that cot with the white hunter. He despised them when he was away from them although he liked some of them well enough at the time, but he made his living by them; and their standards were his standards as long as they were hiring him.

They were his standards in all except the shooting. He had his own standards about the killing and they could live up to them or get some one else to hunt them. He knew, too, that they all respected him for this. This Macomber was an odd one though. Damned if he wasn't. Now the wife. Well, the wife. Yes, the wife. Hm, the wife. Well he'd dropped all that. He looked around at them. Macomber sat grim and furious. Margot smiled at him. She looked younger today, more innocent and fresher and not so professionally beautiful. What's in her heart God knows, Wilson thought. She hadn't talked much last night. At that it was a pleasure to see her.

The motor car climbed up a slight rise and went on through the trees and then out into a grassy prairie-like opening and kept in the shelter of the trees along the edge, the driver going slowly and Wilson looking carefully out across the prairie and all along its far side. He stopped the car and studied the opening with his field glasses. Then he motioned to the driver to go on and the car moved slowly along, the driver avoiding warthog holes and driving around the mud castles ants had built. Then, looking across the opening, Wilson suddenly turned and said,

“By God, there they are!”

And looking where he pointed, while the car jumped forward and Wilson spoke in rapid Swahili to the driver, Macomber saw three huge, black animals looking almost cylindrical in their long heaviness, like big black tank cars, moving at a gallop across the far edge of the open prairie. They moved at a stiff-necked, stiff bodied gallop and he could see the upswept wide black horns on their heads as they galloped heads out; the heads not moving.

“They're three old bulls,”Wilson said.“We'll cut them off before they get to the swamp.”

The car was going a wild forty-five miles an hour across the open and as Macomber watched, the buffalo got bigger and bigger until he could see the gray, hairless, scabby look of one huge bull and how his neck was a part of his shoulders and the shiny black of his horns as he galloped a little behind the others that were strung out in that steady plunging gait; and then, the car swaying as though it had just jumped a road, they drew up close and he could see the plunging hugeness of the bull, and the dust in his sparsely haired hide, the wide boss of horn and his outstretched, wide-nostrilled muzzle, and he was raising his rifle when Wilson shouted,“Not from the car, you fool!”and he had no fear, only hatred of Wilson, while the brakes clamped on and the car skidded, plowing sideways to an almost stop and Wilson was out on one side and he on the other, stumbling as his feet hit the still speeding-by of the earth, and then he was shooting at the bull as he moved away, hearing the bullets whunk into him, emptying his rifle at him as he moved steadily away, finally remembering to get his shots forward into the shoulder, and as he fumbled to re-load, he saw the bull was down. Down on his knees, his big head tossing, and seeing the other two still galloping he shot at the leader and hit him. He shot again and missed and he heard the carawonging roar as Wilson shot and saw the leading bull slide forward onto his nose.

“Get that other,”Wilson said.“Now you're shooting!”

But the other bull was moving steadily at the same gallop and he missed, throwing a spout of dirt, and Wilson missed and the dust rose in a cloud and Wilson shouted,“Come on. He's too far!”and grabbed his arm and they were in the car again, Macomber and Wilson hanging on the sides and rocketing swayingly over the uneven ground, drawing up on the steady, plunging, heavy-necked, straight-moving gallop of the bull.

They were behind him and Macomber was filling his rifle, dropping shells onto the ground, jamming it, clearing the jam, then they were almost up with the bull when Wilson yelled“Stop,”and the car skidded so that it almost swung over and Macomber fell forward onto his feet, slammed his bolt forward and fired as far forward as he could aim into the galloping, rounded black back, aimed and shot again, then again, then again, and the bullets, all of them hitting, had no effect on the buffalo that he could see. Then Wilson shot, the roar deafening him, and he could see the bull stagger. Macomber shot again, aiming carefully, and down he came, onto his knees.

“All right,”Wilson said.“Nice work. That's the three.”

Macomber felt a drunken elation.

“How many times did you shoot?”he asked.

“Just three,”Wilson said.“You killed the first bull. The biggest one. I helped you finish the other two. Afraid they might have got into cover.

You had them killed. I was just mopping up a little. You shot damn well.”

“Let's go to the car,”said Macomber.“I want a drink.”

“Got to finish off that buff first,”Wilson told him. The buffalo was on his knees and he jerked his head furiously and bellowed in pig-eyed, roaring rage as they came toward him.

“Watch he doesn't get up,”Wilson said. Then,“Get a little broadside and take him in the neck just behind the ear.”

Macomber aimed carefully at the center of the huge, jerking, rage-driven neck and shot. At the shot the head dropped forward.

“That does it,”said Wilson.“Got the spine. They're a hell of a looking thing, aren't they?”

“Let's get the drink,”said Macomber. In his life he had never felt so good.

In the car Macomber's wife sat very white-faced.“You were marvellous, darling,”she said to Macomber.“What a ride.”

“Was it rough?”Wilson asked.

“It was frightful. I've never been more frightened in my life.”

“Let's all have a drink,”Macomber said.

“By all means,”said Wilson.“Give it to the Memsahib.”She drank the neat whisky from the flask and shuddered a little when she swallowed. She handed the flask to Macomber who handed it to Wilson.

“It was frightfully exciting,”she said.“It's given me a dreadful headache. I didn't know you were allowed to shoot them from cars though.

“No one shot from cars,”said Wilson coldly.

“I mean chase them from cars.”

“Wouldn't ordinarily,”Wilson said.“Seemed sporting enough to me though while we were doing it. Taking more chance driving that way across the plain full of holes and one thing and another than hunting on foot. Buffalo could have charged us each time we shot if he liked. Gave him every chance. Wouldn't mention it to any one though. It's illegal if that's what you mean.”

“It seemed very unfair to me,”Margot said,“chasing those big helpless things in a motor car.”

“Did it?”said Wilson.

“What would happen if they heard about it in Nairobi?”

“I'd lose my licence for one thing. Other unpleasantnesses,”Wilson said, taking a drink from the flask.“I'd be out of business.”

“Really?”

“Yes, really.”

“Well,”said Macomber, and he smiled for the first time all day.“Now she has something on you.”

“You have such a pretty way of putting things, Francis,”Margot Macomber said. Wilson looked at them both. If a four-letter man marries a five-letter woman, he was thinking, what number of letters would their children be? What he said was,“We lost a gun-bearer. Did you notice it?”

“My God, no,”Macomber said.

“Here he comes,”Wilson said.“He's all right. He must have fallen off when we left the first bull.”

Approaching them was the middle-aged gun-bearer, limping along in his knitted cap, khaki tunic, shorts and rubber sandals, gloomy-faced and disgusted looking. As he came up he called out to Wilson in Swahili and they all saw the change in the white hunter's face.

“What does he say?”asked Margot.

“He says the first bull got up and went into the bush,”Wilson said with no expression in his voice.

“Oh,”said Macomber blankly.

“Then it's going to be just like the lion,”said Margot, rull of anticipation.

“It's not going to be a damned bit like the lion,”Wilson told her.“Did you want another drink, Macomber?”

“Thanks, yes,”Macomber said. He expected the feeling he had had about the lion to come back but it did not. For the first time in his life he really felt wholly without fear. Instead of fear he had a feeling of definite elation.

“We'll go and have a look at the second bull,”Wilson said.“I'll tell the driver to put the car in the shade.”

“What are you going to do?”asked Margaret Macomber.

“Take a look at the buff,”Wilson said.

“I'll come.”

“Come along.”

The three of them walked over to where the second buffalo bulked blackly in the open, head forward on the grass, the massive horns swung wide.

“He's a very good head,”Wilson said.“That's dose to a fifty-inch spread.”

Macomber was looking at him with delight.

“He's hateful looking,”said Margot.“Can't we go into the shade?”

“Of course,”Wilson said.“Look,”he said to Macomber, and pointed.“See that patch of bush?”

“Yes.”

“That's where the first bull went in. The gun-bearer said when he fell off the bull was down. He was watching us helling along and the other two buff galloping. When he looked up there was the bull up and looking at him. Gun-bearer ran like hell and the bull went off slowly into that bush.”

“Can we go in after him now?”asked Macomber eagerly.

Wilson looked at him appraisingly. Damned if this isn't a strange one, he thought. Yesterday he's scared sick and today he's a ruddy fire eater.

“No, we'll give him a while.”

“Let's please go into the shade,”Margot said. Her face was white and she looked ill.

They made their way to the car where it stood under a single, wide-spreading tree and all climbed in.

“Chances are he's dead in there,”Wilson remarked.“After a little we'll have a look.”

Macomber felt a wild unreasonable happiness that he had never known before.

“By God, that, was a chase,”he said.“I've never felt any such feeling. Wasn't it marvellous, Margot?”

“I hated it.”

“Why?”

“I hated it,”she said bitterly.“I loathed it.”

“You know I don't think I'd ever be afraid of anything again,”Macomber said to Wilson.“Something happened in me after we first saw the buff and started after him. Like a dam bursting. It was pure excitement.”

“Cleans out your liver,”said Wilson.“Damn funny things happen to people.”

Macomber's face was shining.“You know something did happen to me,”he said.“I feel absolutely different.”

His wife said nothing and eyed him strangely. She was sitting far back in the seat and Macomber was sitting forward talking to Wilson who turned sideways talking over the back of the front seat.

“You know, I'd like to try another lion,”Macomber said.“I'm really not afraid of them now. After all, what can they do to you?”

“That's it,”said Wilson.“Worst one can do is kill you. How does it go? Shakespeare. Damned good. See if I can remember. Oh, damned good. Used to quote it to myself at one time. Let's see.‘By my troth, I care not; a man can die but once; we owe God a death and let it go which way it will, he that dies this year is quit for the next.’Damned fine, eh?”

He was very embarrassed, having brought out this thing he had lived by, but he had seen men come of age before and it always moved him. It was not a matter of their twenty-first birthday.

It had taken a strange chance of hunting, a sudden precipitation into action without opportunity for worrying beforehand, to bring this about with Macomber, but regardless of how it had happened it had most certainly happened. Look at the beggar now, Wilson thought. It's that some of them stay little boys so long, Wilson thought. Sometimes all their lives. Their figures stay boyish when they're fifty. The great American boy-men. Damned strange people. But he liked this Macomber now. Damned strange fellow. Probably meant the end of cuckoldry too. Well, that would be a damned good thing. Damned good thing. Beggar had probably been afraid all his life. Don't know what started it. But over now. Hadn't had time to be afraid with the buff. That and being angry too. Motor car too. Motor cars made it familiar. Be a damn fire eater now. He'd seen it in the war work the same way. More of a change than any loss of virginity. Fear gone like an operation. Something else grew in its place. Main thing a man had. Made him into a man. Women knew it too. No bloody fear.

From the far corner of the seat Margaret Macomber looked at the two of them. There was no change in Wilson. She saw Wilson as she had seen him the day before when she had first realized what his great talent was. But she saw the change in Francis Macomber now.

“Do you have that feeling of happiness about what's going to happen?”Macomber asked, still exploring his new wealth.

“You're not supposed to mention it,”Wilson said, looking in the other's face.“Much more fashionable to say you're scared. Mind you, you'll be scared too, plenty of times.”

“But you have a feeling of happiness about action to come?”

“Yes,”said Wilson.“There's that. Doesn't do to talk too much about all this. Talk the whole thing away. No pleasure in anything if you mouth it up too much.”

“You're both talking rot,”said Margot.“Just because you've chased some helpless animals in a motor car you talk like heroes.”

“Sorry,”said Wilson.“I have been gassing too much.”She's worried about it already, he thought.

“If you don't know what we're talking about why not keep out of it?”Macomber asked his wife.

“You've gotten awfully brave, awfully suddenly,”his wife said contemptuously, but her contempt was not secure. She was very afraid of something.

Macomber laughed, a very natural hearty laugh.“You know I have,”he said.“I really have.”

“Isn't it sort of late?”Margot said bitterly. Because she had done the best she could for many years back and the way they were together now was no one person's fault.

“Not for me,”said Macomber.

Margot said nothing but sat back in the corner of the seat.

“Do you think we've given him time enough?”Macomber asked Wilson cheerfully.

“We might have a look,”Wilson said.“Have you any solids left?”

“The gun-bearer has some.”

Wilson called in Swahili and the older gun-bearer, who was skinning out one of the heads, straightened up, pulled a box of solids out of his pocket and brought them over to Macomber, who filled his magazine and put the remaining shells in his pocket.

“You might as well shoot the Springfield,”Wilson said.“You're used to it. We'll leave the Mannlicher in the car with the Memsahib. Your gun-bearer can carry your heavy gun. I've this damned cannon. Now let me tell you about them.”He had saved this until the last because he did not want to worry Macomber.“When a buff comes he comes with his head high and thrust straight out. The boss of the horns covers any sort of a brain shot. The only shot is straight into the nose. The only other shot is into his chest or, if you're to one side, into the neck or the shoulders. After they've been hit once they take a hell of a lot of killing. Don't try anything fancy. Take the easiest shot there is. They've finished skinning out that head now. Should we get started?”

He called to the gun-bearers, who came up wiping their hands, and the older one got into the back.

“I'll only take Kongoni,”Wilson said.“The other can watch to keep the birds away.”

As the car moved slowly across the open space toward the island of brushy trees that ran in a tongue of foliage along a dry water course that cut the open swale, Macomber felt his heart pounding and his mouth was dry again, but it was excitement, not fear.

“Here's where he went in,”Wilson said. Then to the gun-bearer in Swahili,“Take the blood spoor.”

The car was parallel to the patch of bush. Macomber, Wilson and the gun-bearer got down. Macomber, looking back, saw his wife, with the rifle by her side, looking at him. He waved to her and she did not wave back.

The brush was very thick ahead and the ground was dry. The middle-aged gun-bearer was sweating heavily and Wilson had his hat down over his eyes and his red neck showed just ahead of Macomber. Suddenly the gun-bearer said something in Swahili to Wilson and ran forward.

“He's dead in there,”Wilson said.“Good work,”and he turned to grip Macomber's hand and as they shook hands, grinning at each other, the gun-bearer shouted wildly and they saw him coming out of the bush sideways, fast as a crab, and the bull coming, nose out, mouth tight closed, blood dripping, massive head straight out, coming in a charge, his little pig eyes bloodshot as he looked at them. Wilson, who was ahead, was kneeling shooting, and Macomber, as he fired, unhearing his shot in the roaring of Wilson's gun, saw fragments like slate burst from the huge boss of the horns, and the head jerked, he shot again at the wide nostrils and saw the horns jolt again and fragments fly, and he did not see Wilson now and, aiming carefully, shot again with the buffalo's huge bulk almost on him and his rifle almost level with the on-coming head, nose out, and he could see the little wicked eyes and the head started to lower and he felt a sudden white-hot, blinding flash explode inside his head and that was all he ever felt.

Wilson had ducked to one side to get in a shoulder shot. Macomber had stood solid and shot for the nose, shooting a touch high each time and hitting the heavy horns, splintering and chipping them like hitting a slate roof, and Mrs. Macomber, in the car, had shot at the buffalo with the 6.5 Mannlicher as it seemed about to gore Macomber and had hit her husband about two inches up and a little to one side of the base of his skull.

Francis Macomber lay now, face down, not two yards from where the buffalo lay on his side and his wife knelt over him with Wilson beside her.

“I wouldn't turn him over,”Wilson said.

The woman was crying hysterically.

“I'd get back in the car,”Wilson said.“Where's the rifle?”

She shook her head, her face contorted. The gun-bearer picked up the rifle.

“Leave it as it is,”said Wilson. Then,“Go get Abdulla so that he may witness the manner of the accident.”

He knelt down, took a handkerchief from his pocket, and spread it over Francis Macomber's crew-cropped head where it lay. The blood sank into the dry, loose earth.

Wilson stood up and saw the buffalo on his side, his legs out, his thinly-haired belly crawling with ticks.“Hell of a good bull,”his brain registered automatically.“A good fifty inches, or better. Better.”He called to the driver and told him to spread a blanket over the body and stay by it. Then he walked over to the motor car where the woman sat crying in the corner.

“That was a pretty thing to do,”he said in a toneless voice.“He would have left you too.”

“Stop it,”she said.

“Of course it's an accident,”he said.“I know that.”

“Stop it,”she said.

“Don't worry,”he said.“There will be a certain amount of unpleasantness but I will have some photographs taken that will be very useful at the inquest. There's the testimony of the gun-bearers and the driver too. You're perfectly all right.”

“Stop it,”she said.

“There's a hell of a lot to be done,”he said.“And I'll have to send a truck off to the lake to wireless for a plane to take the three of us into Nairobi. Why didn't you poison him? That's what they do in England.”

“Stop it. Stop it. Stop it,”the woman cried.

Wilson looked at her with his flat blue eyes.

“I'm through now,”he said.“I was a little angry. I'd begun to like your husband.”

“Oh, please stop it,”she said.“Please stop it.”

“That's better,”Wilson said.“Please is much better. Now I'll stop.”

Old Man at the Bridge

An old man with steel rimmed spectacles and very dusty clothes sat by the side of the road. There was a pontoon bridge across the river and carts, trucks, and men, women and children were crossing it. The mule-drawn carts staggered up the steep bank from the bridge with soldiers helping push against the spokes of the wheels. The trucks ground up and away heading out of it all and the peasants plodded along in the ankle deep dust. But the old man sat there without moving. He was too tired to go any farther.

It was my business to cross the bridge, explore the bridgehead beyond and find out to what point the enemy had advanced. I did this and returned over the bridge. There were not so many carts now and very few people on foot, but the old man was still there.

“Where do you come from?”I asked him.

“From San Carlos,”he said, and smiled.

That was his native town and so it gave him pleasure to mention it and he smiled.

“I was taking care of animals,”he explained.

“Oh,”I said, not quite understanding.

“Yes,”he said,“I stayed, you see, taking care of animals. I was the last one to leave the town of San Carlos.”

He did not look like a shepherd nor a herdsman and I looked at his black dusty clothes and his gray dusty face and his steel rimmed spectacles and said,“What animals were they?”

“Various animals,”he said, and shook his head.“I had to leave them.”

I was watching the bridge and the African looking country of the Ebro Delta and wondering how long now it would be before we would see the enemy, and listening all the while for the first noises that would signal that ever mysterious event called contact, and the old man still sat there.

“What animals were they?”I asked.

“There were three animals altogether,”he explained.“There were two goats and a cat and then there were four pairs of pigeons.”

“And you had to leave them?”I asked.

“Yes. Because of the artillery. The captain told me to go because of the artillery.”

“And you have no family?”I asked, watching the far end of the bridge where a few last carts were hurrying down the slope of the bank.

“No,”he said,“only the animals I stated. The cat, of course, will be all right. A cat can look out for itself, but I cannot think what will become of the others.”

“What politics have you?”I asked.

“I am without politics,”he said.“I am seventy-six years old. I have come twelve kilometers now and I think now I can go no further.”

“This is not a good place to stop,”I said.“If you can make it, there are trucks up the road where it forks for Tortosa.”

“I will wait a while,”he said,“and then I will go. Where do the trucks go?”

“Towards Barcelona,”I told him.

“I know no one in that direction,”he said,“but thank you very much. Thank you again very much.”

He looked at me very blankly and tiredly, then said, having to share his worry with some one,“The cat will be all right, I am sure. There is no need to be unquiet about the cat. But the others. Now what do you think about the others?”

“Why they'll probably come through it all right.”

“You think so?”

“Why not,”I said, watching the far bank where now there were no carts.

“But what will they do under the artillery when I was told to leave because of the artillery?”

“Did you leave the dove cage unlocked?”I asked.

“Yes.”

“Then they'll fly.”

“Yes, certainly they'll fly. But the others. It's better not to think about the others,”he said.

“If you are rested I would go,”I urged.“Get up and try to walk now.”

“Thank you,”he said and got to his feet, swayed from side to side and then sat down backwards in the dust.

“I was taking care of animals,”he said dully, but no longer to me.“I was only taking care of animals.”

There was nothing to do about him. It was Easter Sunday and the Fascists were advancing toward the Ebro. It was a gray overcast day with a low ceiling so their planes were not up. That and the fact that cats know how to look after themselves was all the good luck that old man would ever have.

After the Storm

It wasn't about anything, something about making punch, and then we started fighting and I slipped and he had me down kneeling on my chest and choking me with both hands like he was trying to kill me and all the time I was trying to get the knife out of my pocket to cut him loose. Everybody was too drunk to pull him off me. He was choking me and hammering my head on the floor and I got the knife out and opened it up; and I cut the muscle right across his arm and he let go of me. He couldn't have held on if he wanted to. Then he rolled and hung onto that arm and started to cry and I said:

“What the hell you want to choke me for?”

I'd have killed him. I couldn't swallow for a week. He hurt my throat bad.

Well, I went out of there and there were plenty of them with him and some came out after me and I made a turn and was down by the docks and I met a fellow and he said somebody killed a man up the street. I said“Who killed him?”and he said“I don't know who killed him but he's dead all right,”and it was dark and there was water standing in the street and no lights and windows broke and boats all up in the town and trees blown down and everything all blown and I got a skiff and went out and found my boat where I had her inside of Mango Key and she was all right only she was full of water. So I bailed her out and pumped her out and there was a moon but plenty of clouds and still plenty rough and I took it down along; and when it was daylight I was off Eastern Harbor.

Brother, that was some storm. I was the first boat out and you never saw water like that was. It was just as white as a lye barrel and coming from Eastern Harbor to Sou'west Key you couldn't recognize the shore. There was a big channel blown right out through the middle of the beach. Trees and all blown out and a channel cut through and all the water white as chalk and everything on it; branches and whole trees and dead birds, and all floating. Inside the keys were all the pelicans in the world and all kinds of birds flying. They must have gone inside there when they knew it was coming.

I lay at Sou'west Key a day and nobody came after me. I was the first boat out and I seen a spar floating and I knew there must be a wreck and I started out to look for her. I found her. She was a three-masted schooner and I could just see the stumps of her spars out of water. She was in too deep water and I didn't get anything off of her. So I went on looking for something else. I had the start on all of them and I knew I ought to get whatever there was. I went on down over the sand-bars from where I left that three-masted schooner and I didn't find anything and I went on a long way. I was way out toward the quicksands and I didn't find anything so I went on. Then when I was in sight of the Rebecca light I saw all kinds of birds making over something and I headed over for them to see what it was and there was a cloud of birds all right.

I could see something looked like a spar up out of the water and when I got over close the birds all went up in the air and stayed all around me. The water was clear out there and there was a spar of some kind sticking out just above the water and when I come up close to it I saw it was all dark under water like a long shadow and I came right over it and there under water was a liner; just lying there all under water as big as the whole world. I drifted over her in the boat. She lay on her side and the stern was deep down. The port holes were all shut tight and I could see the glass shine in the water and the whole of her; the biggest boat I ever saw in my life laying there and I went along the whole length of her and then I went over and anchored and I had the skiff on the deck forward and I shoved it down into the water and sculled over with the birds all around me.

I had a water glass like we use sponging and my hand shook so I could hardly hold it. All the port holes were shut that you could see going along over her but way down below near the bottom something must have been open because there were pieces of things floating out all the time. You couldn't tell what they were. Just pieces. That's what the birds were after. You never saw so many birds. They were all around me; crazy yelling.

I could see everything sharp and clear. I could see her rounded over and she looked a mile long under the water. She was lying on a clear white bank of sand and the spar was a sort of foremast or some sort of tackle that slanted out of water the way she was laying on her side. Her bow wasn't very far under. I could stand on the letters of her name on her bow and my head was just out of water. But the nearest port hole was twelve feet down. I could just reach it with the grains pole and I tried to break it with that but I couldn't. The glass was too stout. So I sculled back to the boat and got a wrench and lashed it to the end of the grains pole and I couldn't break it. There I was looking down through the glass at that liner with everything in her and I was the first one to her and I couldn't get into her. She must have had five million dollars worth in her.

It made me shaky to think how much she must have in her. Inside the port hole that was closest I could see something but I couldn't make it out through the water glass. I couldn't do any good with the grains pole and I took off my clothes and stood and took a couple of deep breaths and dove over off the stern with the wrench in my hand and swam down. I could hold on for a second to the edge of the port hole and I could see in and there was a woman inside with her hair floating all out. I could see her floating plain and I hit the glass twice with the wrench hard and I heard the noise clink in my ears but it wouldn't break and I had to come up.

I hung onto the dinghy and got my breath and then I climbed in and took a couple of breaths and dove again. I swam down and took hold of the edge of the port hole with my fingers and held it and hit the glass as hard as I could with the wrench. I could see the woman floated in the water through the glass. Her hair was tied once close to her head and it floated all out in the water. I could see the rings on one of her hands. She was right up close to the port hole and I hit the glass twice and I didn't even crack it. When I came up I thought I wouldn't make it to the top before I'd have to breathe.

I went down once more and I cracked the glass, only cracked it, and when I came up my nose was bleeding and I stood on the bow of the liner with my bare feet on the letters of her name and my head just out and rested there and then I swam over to the skiff and pulled up into it and sat there waiting for my head to stop aching and looking down into the water glass, but I bled so I had to wash out the water glass. Then I lay back in the skiff and held my hand under my nose to stop it and I lay there with my head back looking up and there was a million birds above and all around.

When I quit bleeding I took another look through the glass and then I sculled over to the boat to try and find something heavier than the wrench but I couldn't find a thing; not even a sponge hook. I went back and the water was clearer all the time and you could see everything that floated out over that white bank of sand. I looked for sharks but there weren't any. You could have seen a shark a long way away. The water was so clear and the sand white. There was a grapple for an anchor on the skiff and I cut it off and went overboard and down with it. It carried me right down and past the port hole and I grabbed and couldn't hold anything and went on down and down, sliding along the curved side of her. I had to let go of the grapple. I heard it bump once and it seemed like a year before I came up through to the top of the water. The skiff was floated away with the tide and I swam over to her with my nose bleeding in the water while I swam and I was plenty glad there weren't sharks; but I was tired.

My head felt cracked open and I lay in the skiff and rested and then I sculled back. It was getting along in the afternoon. I went down once more with the wrench and it didn't do any good. That wrench was too light. It wasn't any good diving unless you had a big hammer or something heavy enough to do good. Then I lashed the wrench to the grains pole again and I watched through the water glass and pounded on the glass and hammered until the wrench came off and I saw it in the glass, clear and sharp, go sliding down along her and then off and down to the quicksand and go in. Then I couldn't do a thing. The wrench was gone and I'd lost the grapple so I sculled back to the boat. I was too tired to get the skiff aboard and the sun was pretty low. The birds were all pulling out and leaving her and I headed for Sou'west Key towing the skiff and the birds going on ahead of me and behind me. I was plenty tired.

That night it came on to blow and it blew for a week. You couldn't get out to her. They come out from town and told me the fellow I'd had to cut was all right except for his arm and I went back to town and they put me under five hundred dollar bond. It came out all right because some of them, friends of mine, swore he was after me with an ax, but by the time we got back out to her the Greeks had blown her open and cleaned her out. They got the safe out with dynamite. Nobody ever knows how much they got. She carried gold and they got it all. They stripped her clean. I found her and I never got a nickel out of her.

It was a hell of a thing all right. They say she was just outside of Havana harbor when the hurricane hit and she couldn't get in or the owners wouldn't let the captain chance coming in; they say he wanted to try; so she had to go with it and in the dark they were running with it trying to go through the gulf between Rebecca and Tortugas when she struck on the quicksands. Maybe her rudder was carried away. Maybe they weren't even steering. But anyway they couldn't have known they were quicksands and when she struck the captain must have ordered them to open up the ballast tanks so she'd lay solid. But it was quicksand she'd hit and when they opened the tank she went in stern first and then over on her beam ends. There were four hundred and fifty passengers and the crew on board of her and they must all have been aboard of her when I found her. They must have opened the tanks as soon as she struck and the minute she settled on it the quicksands took her down. Then her boilers must have burst and that must have been what made those pieces that came out. It was funny there weren't any sharks though. There wasn't a fish. I could have seen them on that clear white sand.

Plenty of fish now though; jewfish, the biggest kind. The biggest part of her's under the sand now but they live inside of her; the biggest kind of jewfish. Some weigh three to four hundred pounds. Sometime we'll go out and get some. You can see the Rebecca light from where she is. They've got a buoy on her now. She's right at the end of the quicksand right at the edge of the gulf. She only missed going through by about a hundred yards. In the dark in the storm they just missed it; raining the way it was they couldn't have seen the Rebecca. Then they're not used to that sort of thing. The captain of a liner isn't used to scudding that way. They have a course and they tell me they set some sort of a compass and it steers itself. They probably didn't know where they were when they ran with that blow but they come close to making it. Maybe they'd lost the rudder though. Anyway there wasn't another thing for them to hit till they'd get to Mexico once they were in that gulf. Must have been something though when they struck in that rain and wind and he told them to open her tanks. Nobody could have been on deck in that blow and rain. Everybody must have been below. They couldn't have lived on deck. There must have been some scenes inside all right because you know she settled fast. I saw that wrench go into the sand. The captain couldn't have known it was quicksand when she struck unless he knew these waters. He just knew it wasn't rock. He must have seen it all up in the bridge. He must have known what it was about when she settled. I wonder how fast she made it. I wonder if the mate was there with him. Do you think they stayed inside the bridge or do you think they took it outside? They never found any bodies. Not a one. Nobody floating. They float a long way with life belts too. They must have took it inside. Well, the Greeks got it all. Everything. They must have come fast all right. They picked her clean. First there was the birds, then me, then the Greeks, and even the birds got more out of her than I did.

A Clean, Well-Lighted Place

It was late and every one had left the café except an old man who sat in the shadow the leaves of the tree made against the electric light. In the day time the street was dusty, but at night the dew settled the dust and the old man liked to sit late because he was deaf and now at night it was quiet and he felt the difference. The two waiters inside the café knew that the old man was a little drunk, and while he was a good client they knew that if he became too drunk he would leave without paying, so they kept watch on him.

“Last week he tried to commit suicide,”one waiter said.

“Why?”

“He was in despair.”

“What about?”

“Nothing.”

“How do you know it was nothing?”

“He has plenty of money.”

They sat together at a table that was close against the wall near the door of the café and looked at the terrace where the tables were all empty except where the old man sat in the shadow of the leaves of the tree that moved slightly in the wind. A girl and a soldier went by in the street. The street light shone on the brass number on his collar. The girl wore no head covering and hurried beside him.

“The guard will pick him up,”one waiter said.

“What does it matter if he gets what he's after?”

“He had better get off the street now. The guard will get him. They went by five minutes ago.”

The old man sitting in the shadow rapped on his saucer with his glass. The younger waiter went over to him.

“What do you want?”

The old man looked at him.“Another brandy,”he said.

“You'll be drunk,”the waiter said. The old man looked at him. The waiter went away.

“He'll stay all night,”he said to his colleague.“I'm sleepy now. I never get into bed before three o'clock. He should have killed himself last week.”

The waiter took the brandy bottle and another saucer from the counter inside the café and marched out to the old man's table. He put down the saucer and poured the glass full of brandy.

“You should have killed yourself last week,”he said to the deaf man. The old man motioned with his finger.“A little more,”he said. The waiter poured on into the glass so that the brandy slopped over and ran down the stem into the top saucer of the pile.“Thank you,”the old man said. The waiter took the bottle back inside the café. He sat down at the table with his colleague again.

“He's drunk now,”he said.

“He's drunk every night.”

“What did he want to kill himself for?”

“How should I know.”

“How did he do it?”

“He hung himself with a rope.”

“Who cut him down?”

“His niece.”

“Why did they do it?”

“Fear for his soul.”

“How much money has he got?”

“He's got plenty.”

“He must be eighty years old.”

“Anyway I should say he was eighty.”

“I wish he would go home. I never get to bed before three o'clock. What kind of hour is that to go to bed?”

“He stays up because he likes it.”

“He's lonely. I'm not lonely. I have a wife waiting in bed for me.”

“He had a wife once too.”

“A wife would be no good to him now.”

“You can't tell. He might be better with a wife.”

“His niece looks after him. You said she cut him down.”

“I know.”

“I wouldn't want to be that old. An old man is a nasty thing.”

“Not always. This old man is clean. He drinks without spilling. Even now, drunk. Look at him.”

“I don't want to look at him. I wish he would go home. He has no regard for those who must work.”

The old man looked from his glass across the square, then over at the waiters.

“Another brandy,”he said, pointing to his glass. The waiter who was in a hurry came over.

“Finished,”he said, speaking with that omission of syntax stupid people employ when talking to drunken people or foreigners.“No more tonight. Close now.”

“Another,”said the old man.

“No. Finished.”The waiter wiped the edge of the table with a towel and shook his head.

The old man stood up, slowly counted the saucers, took a leather coin purse from his pocket and paid for the drinks, leaving half a peseta tip.

The waiter watched him go down the street, a very old man walking unsteadily but with dignity.

“Why didn't you let him stay and drink?”the unhurried waiter asked. They were putting up the shutters.“It is not half-past two.”

“I want to go home to bed.”

“What is an hour?”

“More to me than to him.”

“An hour is the same.”

“You talk like an old man yourself. He can buy a bottle and drink at home.”

“It's not the same.”

“No, it is not,”agreed the waiter with a wife. He did not wish to be unjust. He was only in a hurry.

“And you? You have no fear of going home before your usual hour?”

“Are you trying to insult me?”

“No, hombre, only to make a joke.”

“No,”the waiter who was in a hurry said, rising from pulling down the metal shutters.“I have confidence. I am all confidence.”

“You have youth, confidence, and a job,”the older waiter said.“You have everything.”

“And what do you lack?”

“Everything but work.”

“You have everything I have.”

“No. I have never had confidence and I am not young.”

“Come on. Stop talking nonsense and lock up.”

“I am of those who like to stay late at the café,”the older waiter said.“With all those who do not want to go to bed. With all those who need a light for the night.”

“I want to go home and into bed.”

“We are of two different kinds,”the older waiter said. He was now dressed to go home.“It is not only a question of youth and confidence although those things are very beautiful. Each night I am reluctant to close up because there may be some one who needs the café.”

“Hombre, there are bodegas open all night long.”

“You do not understand. This is a clean and pleasant café. It is well lighted. The light is very good and also, now, there are shadows of the leaves.”

“Good night,”said the younger waiter.

“Good night,”the other said. Turning off the electric light he continued the conversation with himself. It is the light of course but it is necessary that the place be clean and pleasant. You do not want music. Certainly you do not want music. Nor can you stand before a bar with dignity although that is all that is provided for these hours. What did he fear? It was not fear or dread. It was a nothing that he knew too well. It was all a nothing and a man was nothing too. It was only that and light was all it needed and a certain cleanness and order. Some lived in it and never felt it but he knew it all was nada y pues nada y nada y pues nada. Our nada who art in nada, nada be thy name thy kingdom nada thy will be nada in nada as it is in nada. Give us this nada our daily nada and nada us our nada as we nada our nadas and nada us not into nada but deliver us from nada; pues nada. Hail nothing full of nothing, nothing is with thee. He smiled and stood before a bar with a shining steam pressure coffee machine.

“What's yours?”asked the barman.

“Nada.”

“Otro loco más,”said the barman and turned away.

“A little cup,”said the waiter.

The barman poured it for him.

“The light is very bright and pleasant but the bar is unpolished,”the waiter said.

The barman looked at him but did not answer. It was too late at night for conversation.

“You want another copita?”the barman asked.

“No, thank you,”said the waiter and went out. He disliked bars and bodegas. A clean, well-lighted café was a very different thing. Now, without thinking further, he would go home to his room. He would lie in the bed and finally, with daylight, he would go to sleep. After all, he said to himself, it is probably only insomnia. Many must have it.

The Light of the World

When he saw us come in the door the bartender looked up and then reached over and put the glass covers on the two free-lunch bowls.

“Give me a beer,”I said. He drew it, cut the top off with the spatula and then held the glass in his hand. I put the nickel on the wood and he slid the beer toward me.

“What's yours?”he said to Tom.

“Beer.”

He drew that beer and cut it off and when he saw the money he pushed the beer across to Tom.

“What's the matter?”Tom asked.

The bartender didn't answer him. He just looked over our heads and said,“What's yours?”to a man who'd come in.

“Rye,”the man said. The bartender put out the bottle and glass and a glass of water.

Tom reached over and took the glass off the free-lunch bowl. It was a bowl of pickled pig's feet and there was a wooden thing that worked like a scissors, with two wooden forks at the end to pick them up with.

“No,”said the bartender and put the glass cover back on the bowl. Tom held the wooden scissors fork in his hand.“Put it back,”said the bartender.

“You know where,”said Tom.

The bartender reached a hand forward under the bar, watching us both. I put fifty cents on the wood and he straightened up.

“What was yours?”he said.

“Beer,”I said, and before he drew the beer he uncovered both the bowls.

“Your goddam pig's feet stink,”Tom said, and spit what he had in his mouth on the floor. The bartender didn't say anything. The man who had drunk the rye paid and went out without looking back.

“You stink yourself,”the bartender said.“All you punks stink.”

“He says we're punks,”Tommy said to me.

“Listen,”I said.“Let's get out.”

“You punks clear the hell out of here,”the bartender said.

“I said we were going out,”I said.“It wasn't your idea.”

“We'll be back,”Tommy said.

“No you won't,”the bartender told him.

“Tell him how wrong he is,”Tom turned to me.

“Come on,”I said.

Outside it was good and dark.

“What the hell kind of place is this?”Tommy said.

“I don't know,”I said.“Let's go down to the station.”

We'd come in that town at one end and we were going out the other. It smelled of hides and tan bark and the big piles of sawdust. It was getting dark as we came in, and now that it was dark it was cold and the puddles of water in the road were freezing at the edges.

Down at the station there were five whores waiting for the train to come in, and six white men and four Indians. It was crowded and hot from the stove and full of stale smoke. As we came in nobody was talking and the ticket window was down.

“Shut the door, can't you?”somebody said.

I looked to see who said it. It was one of the white men. He wore stagged trousers and lumbermen's rubbers and a mackinaw shirt like the others, but he had no cap and his face was white and his hands were white and thin.

“Aren't you going to shut it?”

“Sure,”I said, and shut it.

“Thank you,”he said. One of the other men snickered.

“Ever interfere with a cook?”he said to me.

“No.”

“You can interfere with this one,”he looked at the cook.“He likes it.”

The cook looked away from him holding his lips tight together.

“He puts lemon juice on his hands,”the man said.“He wouldn't get them in dishwater for anything. Look how white they are.”

One of the whores laughed out loud. She was the biggest whore I ever saw in my life and the biggest woman. And she had on one of those silk dresses that change colors. There were two other whores that were nearly as big but the big one must have weighed three hundred and fifty pounds. You couldn't believe she was real when you looked at her. All three had those changeable silk dresses. They sat side by side on the bench. They were huge. The other two were just ordinary looking whores, peroxide blondes.

“Look at his hands,”the man said and nodded his head at the cook. The whore laughed again and shook all over.

The cook turned and said to her quickly,“You big disgusting mountain of flesh.”

She just keep on laughing and shaking.

“Oh, my Christ,”she said. She had a nice voice.“Oh, my sweet Christ.”

The two other whores, the big ones, acted very quiet and placid as though they didn't have much sense, but they were big, nearly as big as the biggest one. They'd have both gone well over two hundred and fifty pounds. The other two were dignified.

Of the men, besides the cook and the one who talked, there were two other lumberjacks, one that listened, interested but bashful, and the other that seemed getting ready to say something, and two Swedes. Two Indians were sitting down at the end of the bench and one standing up against the wall.

The man who was getting ready to say something spoke to me very low,“Must be like getting on top of a hay mow.”

I laughed and said it to Tommy.

“I swear to Christ I've never been anywhere like this,”he said.“Look at the three of them.”Then the cook spoke up.

“How old are you boys?”

“I'm ninety-six and he's sixty-nine,”Tommy said.

“Ho! Ho! Ho!”the big whore shook with laughing. She had a really pretty voice. The other whores didn't smile.

“Oh, can't you be decent?”the cook said.“I asked just to be friendly.”

“We're seventeen and nineteen,”I said.

“What's the matter with you?”Tommy turned to me.

“That's all right.”

“You can call me Alice,”the big whore said and then she began to shake again.

“Is that your name?”Tommy asked.

“Sure,”she said.“Alice. Isn't it?”she turned to the man who sat by the cook.

“Alice. That's right.”

“That's the sort of name you'd have,”the cook said.

“It's my real name,”Alice said.

“What's the other girls' names?”Tom asked.

“Hazel and Ethel,”Alice said. Hazel and Ethel smiled. They weren't very bright.

“What's your name?”I said to one of the blondes.

“Frances,”she said.

“Frances what?”

“Frances Wilson. What's it to you?”

“What's yours?”I asked the other one.

“Oh, don't be fresh,”she said.

“He just wants us all to be friends,”the man who talked said.“Don't you want to be friends?”

“No,”the peroxide one said.“Not with you.”

“She's just a spitfire,”the man said.“A regular little spitfire.”

The one blonde looked at the other and shook her head.

“Goddamned mossbacks,”she said.

Alice commenced to laugh again and to shake all over.

“There's nothing funny,”the cook said.“You all laugh but there's nothing funny. You two young lads; where are you bound for?”

“Where are you going yourself?”Tom asked him.

“I want to go to Cadillac,”the cook said.“Have you ever been there? My sister lives there.”

“He's a sister himself,”the man in the stagged trousers said.

“Can't you stop that sort of thing?”the cook asked.“Can't we speak decently?”

“Cadillac is where Steve Ketchel came from and where Ad Wolgast is from,”the shy man said.

“Steve Ketchel,”one of the blondes said in a high voice as though the name had pulled a trigger in her.“His own father shot and killed him. Yes, by Christ, his own father. There aren't any more men like Steve Ketchel.”

“Wasn't his name Stanley Ketchel?”asked the cook.

“Oh, shut up,”said the blonde.“What do you know about Steve? Stanley. He was no Stanley. Steve Ketchel was the finest and most beautiful man that ever lived. I never saw a man as clean and as white and as beautiful as Steve Ketchel. There never was a man like that. He moved just like a tiger and he was the finest, free-est spender that ever lived.”

“Did you know him?”one of the men asked.

“Did I know him? Did I know him? Did I love him? You ask me that? I knew him like you know nobody in the world and I loved him like you love God. He was the greatest, finest, whitest, most beautiful man that ever lived, Steve Ketchel, and his own father shot him down like a dog.”

“Were you out on the coast with him?”

“No. I knew him before that. He was the only man I ever loved.”

Every one was very respectful to the peroxide blonde, who said all this in a high stagey way, but Alice was beginning to shake again. I felt it sitting by her.

“You should have married him,”the cook said.

“I wouldn't hurt his career,”the peroxide blonde said.“I wouldn't be a drawback to him. A wife wasn't what he needed. Oh, my God, what a man he was.”

“That was a fine way to look at it,”the cook said.“Didn't Jack Johnson knock him out though?”

“It was a trick,”Peroxide said.“That big dinge took him by surprise. He'd just knocked Jack Johnson down, the big black bastard. That nigger beat him by a fluke.”

The ticket window went up and the three Indians went over to it.

“Steve knocked him down,”Peroxide said.“He turned to smile at me.”

“I thought you said you weren't on the coast,”some one said.

“I went out just for that fight. Steve turned to smile at me and that black son of a bitch from hell jumped up and hit him by surprise. Steve could lick a hundred like that black bastard.”

“He was a great fighter,”the lumberjack said.

“I hope to God he was,”Peroxide said.“I hope to God they don't have fighters like that now. He was like a god, he was. So white and clean and beautiful and smooth and fast and like a tiger or like lightning.”

“I saw him in the moving pictures of the fight,”Tom said. We were all very moved. Alice was shaking all over and I looked and saw she was crying. The Indians had gone outside on the platform.

“He was more than any husband could ever be,”Peroxide said.“We were married in the eyes of God and I belong to him right now and always will and all of me is his. I don't care about my body. They can take my body. My soul belongs to Steve Ketchel. By God, he was a man.”

Everybody felt terribly. It was sad and embarrassing. Then Alice, who was still shaking, spoke.“You're a dirty liar,”she said in that low voice.“You never laid Steve Ketchel in your life and you know it.”

“How can you say that?”Peroxide said proudly.

“I say it because it's true,”Alice said.“I'm the only one here that ever knew Steve Ketchel and I come from Mancelona and I knew him there and it's true and you know it's true and God can strike me dead if it isn't true.”

“He can strike me too,”Peroxide said.

“This is true, true, true, and you know it. Not just made up and I know exactly what he said to me.”

“What did he say?”Peroxide asked, complacently.

Alice was crying so she could hardly speak from shaking so.“He said‘You're a lovely piece, Alice.’That's exactly what he said.”

“It's a lie,”Peroxide said.

“It's true,”Alice said.“That's truly what he said.”

“It's a lie,”Peroxide said proudly.

“No, it's true, true, true, to Jesus and Mary true.”

“Steve couldn't have said that. It wasn't the way he talked,”Peroxide said happily.

“It's true,”said Alice in her nice voice.“And it doesn't make any difference to me whether you believe it or not.”She wasn't crying any more and she was calm.

“It would be impossible for Steve to have said that,”Peroxide declared.

“He said it,”Alice said and smiled.“And I remember when he said it and I was a lovely piece then exactly as he said, and right now I'm a better piece than you, you dried up old hot-water bottle.”

“You can't insult me,”said Peroxide.“You big mountain of pus. I have my memories.”

“No,”Alice said in that sweet lovely voice,“you haven't got any real memories except having your tubes out and when you started C. and M. Everything else you just read in the papers. I'm clean and you know it and men like me, even though I'm big, and you know it, and I never lie and you know it.”

“Leave me with my memories,”Peroxide said.“With my true, wonderful memories.”

Alice looked at her and then at us and her face lost that hurt look and she smiled and she had about the prettiest face I ever saw. She had a pretty face and a nice smooth skin and a lovely voice and she was nice all right and really friendly. But my God she was big. She was as big as three women. Tom saw me looking at her and he said,“Come on. Let's go.”

“Good-bye,”said Alice. She certainly had a nice voice.

“Good-bye,”I said.

“Which way are you boys going?”asked the cook.

“The other way from you,”Tom told him.

God Rest You Merry, Gentlemen

In those days the distances were all very different, the dirt blew off the hills that now have been cut down, and Kansas City was very like Constantinople. You may not believe this. No one believes this; but it is true. On this afternoon it was snowing and inside an automobile dealer's show window, lighted against the early dark, there was a racing motor car finished entirely in silver with Dans Argent lettered on the hood. This I believed to mean the silver dance or the silver dancer, and, slightly puzzled which it meant but happy in the sight of the car and pleased by my knowledge of a foreign language, I went along the street in the snow. I was walking from the Woolf Brothers' saloon where, on Christmas and Thanksgiving Day, a free turkey dinner was served, toward the city hospital which was on a high hill that overlooked the smoke, the buildings and the streets of the town. In the reception room of the hospital were the two ambulance surgeons Doc Fischer and Doctor Wilcox, sitting, the one before a desk, the other in a chair against the wall.

Doc Fischer was thin, sand-blond, with a thin mouth, amused eyes and gambler's hands. Doctor Wilcox was short, dark and carried an indexed book, The Young Doctor's Friend and Guide, which, being consulted on any given subject, told symptoms and treatment. It was also cross-indexed so that being consulted on symptoms it gave diagnoses. Doc Fischer had suggested that any future editions should be further cross-indexed so that if consulted as to the treatments being given, it would reveal ailments and symptoms.“As an aid to memory,”he said.

Doctor Wilcox was sensitive about this book but could not get along without it. It was bound in limp leather and fitted his coat pocket and he had bought it at the advice of one of his professors who had said,“Wilcox, you have no business being a physician and I have done everything in my power to prevent you from being certified as one. Since you are now a member of this learned profession I advise you, in the name of humanity, to obtain a copy of The Young Doctor's Friend and Guide, and use it, Doctor Wilcox. Learn to use it.”

Doctor Wilcox had said nothing but he had bought the leather-bound guide that same day.

“Well, Horace,”Doc Fischer said as I came in the receiving room which smelt of cigarettes, iodoform, carbolic and an overheated radiator.

“Gentlemen,”I said.

“What news along the rialto?”Doc Fischer asked. He affected a certain extravagance of speech which seemed to me to be of the utmost elegance.

“The free turkey at Woolf's,”I answered.

“You partook?”

“Copiously.”

“Many of the confrères present?”

“All of them. The whole staff.”

“Much Yuletide cheer?”

“Not much.”

“Doctor Wilcox here has partaken slightly,”Doc Fischer said. Doctor Wilcox looked up at him, then at me.

“Want a drink?”he asked.

“No, thanks,”I said.

“That's all right,”Doctor Wilcox said.

“Horace,”Doc Fischer said,“you don't mind me calling you Horace, do you?”

“No.”

“Good old Horace. We've had an extremely interesting case.”

“I'll say,”said Doctor Wilcox.

“You know the lad who was in here yesterday?”

“Which one?”

“The lad who sought eunuch-hood.”

“Yes.”I had been there when he came in. He was a boy about sixteen. He came in with no hat on and was very excited and frightened but determined. He was curly haired and well built and his lips were prominent.

“What's the matter with you, son?”Doctor Wilcox asked him.“I want to be castrated,”the boy said.

“Why?”Doc Fischer asked.

“I've prayed and I've done everything and nothing helps.”

“Helps what?”

“That awful lust.”

“What awful lust?”

“The way I get. The way I can't stop getting. I pray all night about it.”

“Just what happens?”Doc Fischer asked.

The boy told him.“Listen, boy,”Doc Fischer said.“There's nothing wrong with you. That's the way you're supposed to be. There's nothing wrong with that.”

“It is wrong,”said the boy.“It's a sin against purity. It's a sin against our Lord and Saviour.”

“No,”said Doc Fisher.“It's a natural thing. It's the way you are supposed to be and later on you will think you are very fortunate.”

“Oh, you don't understand,”the boy said.

“Listen,”Doc Fischer said and he told the boy certain things.

“No. I won't listen. You can't make me listen.”

“Please listen,”Doc Fischer said.

“You're just a goddamned fool,”Doctor Wilcox said to the boy.

“Then you won't do it?”the boy asked.

“Do what?”

“Castrate me.”

“Listen,”Doc Fischer said.“No one will castrate you. There is nothing wrong with your body. You have a fine body and you must not think about that. If you are religious remember that what you complain of is no sinful state but the means of consummating a sacrament.”

“I can't stop it happening,”the boy said.“I pray all night and I pray in the daytime. It is a sin, a constant sin against purity.”

“Oh, go and—”Doctor Wilcox said.

“When you talk like that I don't hear you,”the boy said with dignity to Doctor Wilcox.“Won't you please do it?”he asked Doc Fischer.

“No,”said Doc Fischer.“I've told you, boy.”

“Get him out of here,”Doctor Wilcox said.

“I'll get out,”the boy said.“Don't touch me. I'll get out.”

That was about five o'clock on the day before.

“So what happened?”I asked.

“So at one o'clock this morning,”Doc Fischer said,“we receive the youth self-mutilated with a razor.”

“Castrated?”

“No,”said Doc Fisher.“He didn't know what castrate meant.”

“He may die,”Doctor Wilcox said.

“Why?”

“Loss of blood.”

“The good physician here. Doctor Wilcox, my colleague, was on call and he was unable to find this emergency listed in his book.”

“The hell with you talking that way,”Doctor Wilcox said.

“I only mean it in the friendliest way, Doctor,”Doc Fischer said, looking at his hands, at his hands that had, with his willingness to oblige and his lack of respect for Federal statutes, made him his trouble.“Horace here will bear me out that I only speak of it in the very friendliest way. It was an amputation the young man performed, Horace.”

“Well, I wish you wouldn't ride me about it,”Doctor Wilcox said.“There isn't any need to ride me.”

“Ride you, Doctor, on the day, the very anniversary, of our Saviour's birth?”

“Our Saviour? Ain't you a Jew?”Doctor Wilcox said.

“So I am. So I am. It always is slipping my mind. I've never given it its proper importance. So good of you to remind me. Your Saviour. That's right. Your Saviour, undoubtedly your Saviour—and the ride for Palm Sunday.”

“You're too damned smart,”Doctor Wilcox said.

“An excellent diagnosis, Doctor. I was always too damned smart. Too damned smart on the coast certainly. Avoid it, Horace. You haven't much tendency but sometimes I see a gleam. But what a diagnosis—and without the book.”

“The hell with you,”Doctor Wilcox said.

“All in good time, Doctor,”Doc Fischer said.“All in good time. If there is such a place I shall certainly visit it. I have even had a very small look into it. No more than a peek, really. I looked away almost at once. And do you know what the young man said, Horace, when the good Doctor here brought him in? He said,‘Oh, I asked you to do it. I asked you so many times to do it.’”

“On Christmas Day, too,”Doctor Wilcox said.

“The significance of the particular day is not important,”Doc Fischer said.

“Maybe not to you,”said Doctor Wilcox.

“You hear him, Horace?”Doc Fischer said.“You hear him? Having discovered my vulnerable point, my achilles tendon so to speak, the doctor pursues his advantage.”

“You're too damned smart,”Doctor Wilcox said.

A Way You'll Never Be

The attack had gone across the field, been held up by machine-gun fire from the sunken road and from the group of farm houses, encountered no resistance in the town, and reached the bank of the river. Coming along the road on a bicycle, getting off to push the machine when the surface of the road became too broken, Nicholas Adams saw what had happened by the position of the dead.

They lay alone or in clumps in the high grass of the field and along the road, their pockets out, and over them were flies and around each body or group of bodies were the scattered papers.

In the grass and the grain, beside the road, and in some places scattered over the road, there was much material: a field kitchen, it must have come over when things were going well; many of the calf-skin-covered haversacks, stick bombs, helmets, rifles, sometimes one butt-up, the bayonet stuck in the dirt, they had dug quite a little at the last; stick bombs, helmets, rifles, in trenching tools, ammunition boxes, star-shell pistols, their shells scattered about, medical kits, gas masks, empty gas-mask cans, a squat, tripodded machine gun in a nest of empty shells, full belts protruding from the boxes, the water-cooling can empty and on its side, the breech block gone, the crew in odd positions, and around them, in the grass, more of the typical papers.

There were mass prayer books, group postcards showing the machine-gun unit standing in ranked and ruddy cheerfulness as in a football picture for a college annual; now they were humped and swollen in the grass; propaganda postcards showing a soldier in Austrian uniform bending a woman backward over a bed; the figures were impressionistically drawn; very attractively depicted and had nothing in common with actual rape in which the woman's skirts are pulled over her head to smother her, one comrade sometimes sitting upon the head. There were many of these inciting cards which had evidently been issued just before the offensive. Now they were scattered with the smutty postcards, photographic; the small photographs of village girls by village photographers, the occasional pictures of children, and the letters, letters, letters. There was always much paper about the dead and the débris of this attack was no exception.

These were new dead and no one had bothered with anything but their pockets. Our own dead, or what he thought of, still, as our own dead, were surprisingly few, Nick noticed. Their coats had been opened too and their pockets were out, and they showed, by their positions, the manner and the skill of the attack. The hot weather had swollen them all alike regardless of nationality.

The town had evidently been defended, at the last, from the line of the sunken road and there had been few or no Austrians to fall back into it. There were only three bodies in the street and they looked to have been killed running. The houses of the town were broken by the shelling and the street had much rubble of plaster and mortar and there were broken beams, broken tiles, and many holes, some of them yellow-edged from the mustard gas. There were many pieces of shell, and shrapnel balls were scattered in the rubble. There was no one in the town at all.

Nick Adams had seen no one since he had left Fornaci, although, riding along the road through the over-foliaged country, he had seen guns hidden under screens of mulberry leaves to the left of the road, noticing them by the heat-waves in the air above the leaves where the sun hit the metal. Now he went on through the town, surprised to find it deserted, and came out on the low road beneath the bank of the river. Leaving the town there was a bare open space where the road slanted down and he could see the placid reach of the river and the low curve of the opposite bank and the whitened, sun-baked mud where the Austrians had dug. It was all very lush and over-green since he had seen it last and becoming historical had made no change in this, the lower river.

The battalion was along the bank to the left. There was a series of holes in the top of the bank with a few men in them. Nick noticed where the machine guns were posted and the signal rockets in their racks. The men in the holes in the side of the bank were sleeping. No one challenged. He went on and as he came around a turn in the mud bank a young second lieutenant with a stubble of beard and red-rimmed, very blood-shot eyes pointed a pistol at him.

“Who are you?”

Nick told him.

“How do I know this?”

Nick showed him the tessera with photograph and identification and the seal of the third army. He took hold of it.

“I will keep this.”

“You will not,”Nick said.“Give me back the card and put your gun away. There. In the holster.”

“How am I to know who you are?”

“The tessera tells you.”

“And if the tessera is false? Give me that card.”

“Don't be a fool,”Nick said cheerfully.“Take me to your company commander.”

“I should send you to battalion headquarters.”

“All right,”said Nick.“Listen, do you know the Captain Paravicini? The tall one with the small mustache who was an architect and speaks English?”

“You know him?”

“A little.”

“What company does he command?”

“The second.”

“He is commanding the battalion.”

“Good,”said Nick. He was relieved to know that Para was all right.“Let us go to the battalion.”

As Nick had left the edge of the town three shrapnel had burst high and to the right over one of the wrecked houses and since then there had been no shelling. But the face of this officer looked like the face of a man during a bombardment. There was the same tightness and the voice did not sound natural. His pistol made Nick nervous.

“Put it away,”he said.“There's the whole river between them and you.”

“If I thought you were a spy I would shoot you now,”the second lieutenant said.

“Come on,”said Nick.“Let us go to the battalion.”This officer made him very nervous.

The Captain Paravicini, acting major, thinner and more English-looking than ever, rose when Nick saluted from behind the table in the dugout that was battalion headquarters.

“Hello,”he said.“I didn't know you. What are you doing in that uniform?”

“They've put me in it.”

“I am very glad to see you, Nicolo.”

“Right. You look well. How was the show?”

“We made a very fine attack. Truly. A very fine attack. I will show you. Look.”

He showed on the map how the attack had gone.

“I came from Fornaci,”Nick said.“I could see how it had been. It was very good.”

“It was extraordinary. Altogether extraordinary. Are you attached to the regiment?”

“No. I am supposed to move around and let them see the uniform.”

“How odd.”

“If they see one American uniform that is supposed to make them believe others are coming.”

“But how will they know it is an American uniform?”“You will tell them.”

“Oh. Yes, I see. I will send a corporal with you to show you about and you will make a tour of the lines.”

“Like a bloody politician,”Nick said.

“You would be much more distinguished in civilian clothes. They are what is really distinguished.”

“With a homburg hat,”said Nick.

“Or with a very furry fedora.”

“I'm supposed to have my pockets full of cigarettes and postal cards and such things,”Nick said.“I should have a musette full of chocolate. These I should distribute with a kind word and a pat on the back. But there weren't any cigarettes and postcards and no chocolate. So they said to circulate around anyway.”

“I'm sure your appearance will be very heartening to the troops.”

“I wish you wouldn't,”Nick said.“I feel badly enough about it as it is. In principle, I would have brought you a bottle of brandy.”

“In principle,”Para said and smiled, for the first time, showing yellowed teeth.“Such a beautiful expression. Would you like some grappa?”

“No, thank you,”Nick said.

“It hasn't any ether in it.”

“I can taste that still,”Nick remembered suddenly and completely.

“You know I never knew you were drunk until you started talking coming back in the camions.”

“I was stinking in every attack,”Nick said.

“I can't do it,”Para said.“I took it in the first show, the very first show, and it only made me very upset and then frightfully thirsty.”

“You don't need it.”

“You're much braver in an attack than I am.”

“No,”Nick said.“I know how I am and I prefer to get stinking. I'm not ashamed of it.”

“I've never seen you drunk.”

“No?”said Nick.“Never? Not when we rode from Mestre to Portogrande that night and I wanted to go to sleep and used the bicycle for a blanket and pulled it up under my chin?”

“That wasn't in the lines.”

“Let's not talk about how I am,”Nick said.“It's a subject I know too much about to want to think about it any more.”

“You might as well stay here a while,”Paravicini said.“You can take a nap if you like. They didn't do much to this in the bombardment. It's too hot to go out yet.”

“I suppose there is no hurry.”

“How are you really?”

“I'm fine. I'm perfectly all right.”

“No. I mean really.”

“I'm all right. I can't sleep without a light of some sort. That's all I have now.”

“I said it should have been trepanned. I'm no doctor but I know that.”

“Well, they thought it was better to have it absorb, and that's what I got. What's the matter? I don't seem crazy to you, do I?”

“You seem in top-hole shape.”

“It's a hell of a nuisance once they've had you certified as nutty,”Nick said.“No one ever has any confidence in you again.”

“I would take a nap, Nicolo,”Paravicini said.“This isn't battalion headquarters as we used to know it. We're just waiting to be pulled out. You oughtn't to go out in the heat now—it's silly. Use that bunk.”

“I might just lie down,”Nick said.

Nick lay on the bunk. He was very disappointed that he felt this way and more disappointed, even, that it was so obvious to Captain Paravicini. This was not as large a dugout as the one where that platoon of the class of 1899, just out at the front, got hysterics during the bombardment before the attack, and Para had had him walk them two at a time outside to show them nothing would happen, he wearing his own chin strap tight across his mouth to keep his lips quiet. Knowing they could not hold it when they took it. Knowing it was all a bloody balls—if he can't stop crying, break his nose to give him something else to think about. I'd shoot one but it's too late now. They'd all be worse. Break his nose. They've put it back to five-twenty. We've only got four minutes more. Break that other silly bugger's nose and kick his silly ass out of here. Do you think they'll go over? If they don't, shoot two and try to scoop the others out some way. Keep behind them, sergeant. It's no use to walk ahead and find there's nothing coming behind you. Bail them out as you go. What a bloody balls. All right. That's right. Then, looking at the watch, in that quiet tone, that valuable quiet tone,“Savoia.”Making it cold, no time to get it, he couldn't find his own after the cave-in, one whole end had caved in; it was that started them; making it cold up that slope the only time he hadn't done it stinking. And after they came back the teleferica house burned, it seemed, and some of the wounded got down four days later and some did not get down, but we went up and we went back and we came down—we always came down. And there was Gaby Delys, oddly enough, with feathers on; you called me baby doll a year ago tadada you said that I was rather nice to know tadada with feathers on, with feathers off, the great Gaby, and my name's Harry Pilcer, too, we used to step out of the far side of the taxis when it got steep going up the hill and he could see that hill every night when he dreamed with Sacré Coeur, blown white, like a soap bubble. Sometimes his girl was there and sometimes she was with some one else and he could not understand that, but those were the nights the river ran so much wider and stiller than it should and outside of Fossalta there was a low house painted yellow with willows all around it and a low stable and there was a canal, and he had been there a thousand times and never seen it, but there it was every night as plain as the hill, only it frightened him. That house meant more than anything and every night he had it. That was what he needed but it frightened him especially when the boat lay there quietly in the willows on the canal, but the banks weren't like this river. It was all lower, as it was at Portogrande, where they had seen them come wallowing across the flooded ground holding the rifles high until they fell with them in the water. Who ordered that one? If it didn't get so damned mixed up he could follow it all right. That was why he noticed everything in such detail to keep it all straight so he would know just where he was, but suddenly it confused without reason as now, he lying in a bunk at battalion headquarters, with Para commanding a battalion and he in a bloody American uniform. He sat up and looked around; they all watching him. Para was gone out. He lay down again.

The Paris part came earlier and he was not frightened of it except when she had gone off with some one else and the fear that they might take the same driver twice. That was what frightened about that. Never about the front. He never dreamed about the front now any more but what frightened him so that he could not get rid of it was that long yellow house and the different width of the river. Now he was back here at the river, he had gone through that same town, and there was no house. Nor was the river that way. Then where did he go each night and what was the peril, and why would he wake, soaking wet, more frightened than he had ever been in a bombardment, because of a house and a long stable and a canal?

He sat up; swung his legs carefully down; they stiffened any time they were out straight for long; returned the stares of the adjutant, the signallers and the two runners by the door and put on his cloth-covered trench helmet.

“I regret the absence of the chocolate, the postal cards and cigarettes,”he said.“I am, however, wearing the uniform.”

“The major is coming back at once,”the adjutant said. In that army an adjutant is not a commissioned officer.

“The uniform is not very correct,”Nick told them.“But it gives you the idea. There will be several millions of Americans here shortly.”

“Do you think they will send Americans down here?”asked the adjutant.

“Oh, absolutely. Americans twice as large as myself, healthy, with clean hearts, sleep at night, never been wounded, never been blown up, never had their heads caved in, never been scared, don't drink, faithful to the girls they left behind them, many of them never had crabs, wonderful chaps. You'll see.”

“Are you an Italian?”asked the adjutant.

“No, American. Look at the uniform. Spagnolini made it but it's not quite correct.”

“A North or South American?”

“North,”said Nick. He felt it coming on now. He would quiet down.

“But you speak Italian.”

“Why not? Do you mind if I speak Italian? Haven't I a right to speak Italian?”

“You have Italian medals.”

“Just the ribbons and the papers. The medals come later. Or you give them to people to keep and the people go away; or they are lost with your baggage. You can purchase others in Milan. It is the papers that are of importance. You must not feel badly about them. You will have some yourself if you stay at the front long enough.”

“I am a veteran of the Eritrea campaign,”said the adjutant stiffly.“I fought in Tripoli.”

“It's quite something to have met you,”Nick put out his hand.“Those must have been trying days. I noticed the ribbons. Were you, by any chance, on the Carso?”

“I have just been called up for this war. My class was too old.”

“At one time I was under the age limit,”Nick said.“But now I am reformed out of the war.”

“But why are you here now?”

“I am demonstrating the American uniform,”Nick said.“Don't you think it is very significant? It is a little tight in the collar but soon you will see untold millions wearing this uniform swarming like locusts. The grasshopper, you know, what we call the grasshopper in America, is really a locust. The true grasshopper is small and green and comparatively feeble. You must not, however, make a confusion with the seven-year locust or cicada which emits a peculiar sustained sound which at the moment I cannot recall. I try to recall it but I cannot. I can almost hear it and then it is quite gone. You will pardon me if I break off our conversation?”

“See if you can find the major,”the adjutant said to one of the two runners.“I can see you have been wounded,”he said to Nick.

“In various places,”Nick said.“If you are interested in scars I can show you some very interesting ones but I would rather talk about grasshoppers. What we call grasshoppers that is; and what are, really, locusts. These insects at one time played a very important part in my life. It might interest you and you can look at the uniform while I am talking.”

The adjutant made a motion with his hand to the second runner who went out.

“Fix your eyes on the uniform. Spagnolini made it, you know. You might as well look, too,”Nick said to the signallers.“I really have no rank. We're under the American consul. It's perfectly all right for you to look. You can stare, if you like. I will tell you about the American locust. We always preferred one that we called the medium-brown. They last the best in the water and fish prefer them. The larger ones that fly making a noise somewhat similar to that produced by a rattlesnake rattling his rattlers, a very dry sound, have vivid colored wings, some are bright red, others yellow barred with black, but their wings go to pieces in the water and they make a very blowsy bait, while the medium-brown is a plump, compact, succulent hopper that I can recommend as far as one may well recommend something you gentlemen will probably never encounter. But I must insist that you will never gather a sufficient supply of these insects for a day's fishing by pursuing them with your hands or trying to hit them with a bat. That is sheer nonsense and a useless waste of time. I repeat, gentlemen, that you will get nowhere at it. The correct procedure, and one which should be taught all young officers at every small-arms course if I had anything to say about it, and who knows but what I will have, is the employment of a seine or net made of common mosquito netting. Two officers holding this length of netting at alternate ends, or let us say one at each end, stoop, hold the bottom extremity of the net in one hand and the top extremity in the other and run into the wind. The hoppers, flying with the wind, fly against the length of netting and are imprisoned in its folds. It is no trick at all to catch a very great quantity indeed, and no officer, in my opinion, should be without a length of mosquito netting suitable for the improvisation of one of these grasshopper seines. I hope I have made myself clear, gentlemen. Are there any questions? If there is anything in the course you do not understand please ask questions. Speak up. None? Then I would like to close on this note. In the words of that great soldier and gentleman, Sir Henry Wilson: Gentlemen, either you must govern or you must be governed. Let me repeat it. Gentlemen, there is one thing I would like to have you remember. One thing I would like you to take with you as you leave this room. Gentlemen, either you must govern—or you must be governed. That is all, gentlemen. Good-day.”

He removed his cloth-covered helmet, put it on again and, stooping, went out the low entrance of the dugout. Para, accompanied by the two runners, was coming down the line of the sunken road. It was very hot in the sun and Nick removed the helmet.

“There ought to be a system for wetting these things,”he said.“I shall wet this one in the river.”He started up the bank.

“Nicolo,”Paravicini called.“Nicolo. Where are you going?”

“I don't really have to go.”Nick came down the slope, holding the helmet in his hands.“They're a damned nuisance wet or dry. Do you wear yours all the time?”

“All the time,”said Para.“It's making me bald. Come inside.”

Inside Para told him to sit down.

“You know they're absolutely no damned good,”Nick said.“I remember when they were a comfort when we first had them, but I've seen them full of brains too many times.”

“Nicolo,”Para said.“I think you should go back. I think it would be better if you didn't come up to the line until you had those supplies. There's nothing here for you to do. If you move around, even with something worth giving away, the men will group and that invites shelling. I won't have it.”

“I know it's silly,”Nick said.“It wasn't my idea. I heard the brigade was here so I thought I would see you or some one else I knew. I could have gone to Zenzon or to San Dona. I'd like to go to San Dona to see the bridge again.”

“I won't have you circulating around to no purpose,”Captain Paravicini said.

“All right,”said Nick. He felt it coming on again.

“You understand?”

“Of course,”said Nick. He was trying to hold it in.

“Anything of that sort should be done at night.”

“Naturally,”said Nick. He knew he could not stop it now.

“You see, I am commanding the battalion,”Para said.

“And why shouldn't you be?”Nick said. Here it came.“You can read and write, can't you?”

“Yes,”said Para gently.

“The trouble is you have a damned small battalion to command. As soon as it gets to strength again they'll give you back your company. Why don't they bury the dead? I've seen them now. I don't care about seeing them again. They can bury them any time as far as I'm concerned and it would be much better for you. You'll all get bloody sick.”

“Where did you leave your bicycle?”

“Inside the last house.”

“Do you think it will be all right?”

“Don't worry,”Nick said.“I'll go in a little while.”

“Lie down a little while, Nicolo.”

“All right.”

He shut his eyes, and in place of the man with the beard who looked at him over the sights of the rifle, quite calmly before squeezing off, the white flash and clublike impact, on his knees, hot-sweet choking, coughing it onto the rock while they went past him, he saw a long, yellow house with a low stable and the river much wider than it was and stiller.“Christ,”he said,“I might as well go.”

He stood up.

“I'm going, Para,”he said.“I'll ride back now in the afternoon. If any supplies have come I'll bring them down tonight. If not I'll come at night when I have something to bring.”

“It is still hot to ride,”Captain Paravicini said.

“You don't need to worry,”Nick said.“I'm all right now for quite a while. I had one then but it was easy. They're getting much better. I can tell when I'm going to have one because I talk so much.”

“I'll send a runner with you.”

“I'd rather you didn't. I know the way.”

“You'll be back soon?”

“Absolutely.”

“Let me send—”

“No,”said Nick.“As a mark of confidence.”

“Well, ciao then.”

“Ciao,”said Nick. He started back along the sunken road toward where he had left the bicycle. In the afternoon the road would be shady once he had passed the canal. Beyond that there were trees on both sides that had not been shelled at all. It was on that stretch that, marching, they had once passed the Terza Savoia cavalry regiment riding in the snow with their lances. The horses' breath made plumes in the cold air. No, that was somewhere else. Where was that?

“I'd better get to that damned bicycle,”Nick said to himself.“I don't want to lose the way to Fornaci.”

A Day's Wait

He came into the room to shut the windows while we were still in bed and I saw he looked ill. He was shivering, his face was white, and he walked slowly as though it ached to move.

“What's the matter, Schatz?”

“I've got a headache.”

“You better go back to bed.”

“No. I'm all right.”

“You go to bed. I'll see you when I'm dressed.”

But when I came downstairs he was dressed, sitting by the fire, looking a very sick and miserable boy of nine years. When I put my hand on his forehead I knew he had a fever.

“You go up to bed,”I said,“you're sick.”

“I'm all right,”he said.

When the doctor came he took the boy's temperature.

“What is it?”I asked him.

“One hundred and two.”

Downstairs, the doctor left three different medicines in different colored capsules with instructions for giving them. One was to bring down the fever, another a purgative, the third to overcome an acid condition. The germs of influenza can only exist in an acid condition, he explained. He seemed to know all about influenza and said there was nothing to worry about if the fever did not go above one hundred and four degrees. This was a light epidemic offlu and there was no danger if you avoided pneumonia.

Back in the room I wrote the boy's temperature down and made a note of the time to give the various capsules.

“Do you want me to read to you?”

“All right. If you want to,”said the boy. His face was very white and there were dark areas under his eyes. He lay still in the bed and seemed very detached from what was going on.

I read aloud from Howard Pyle's Book of Pirates; but I could see he was not following what I was reading.

“How do you feel, Schatz?”I asked him.

“Just the same, so far,”he said.

I sat at the foot of the bed and read to myself while I waited for it to be time to give another capsule. It would have been natural for him to go to sleep, but when I looked up he was looking at the foot of the bed, looking very strangely.

“Why don't you try to go to sleep? I'll wake you up for the medicine.”

“I'd rather stay awake.”

After a while he said to me,“You don't have to stay in here with me, Papa, if it bothers you.”

“It doesn't bother me.”

“No, I mean you don't have to stay if it's going to bother you.”

I thought perhaps he was a little lightheaded and after giving him the prescribed capsules at eleven o'clock I went out for a while.

It was a bright, cold day, the ground covered with a sleet that had frozen so that it seemed as if all the bare trees, the bushes, the cut brush and all the grass and the bare ground had been varnished with ice. I took the young Irish setter for a little walk up the road and along a frozen creek, but it was difficult to stand or walk on the glassy surface and the red dog slipped and slithered and I fell twice, hard, once dropping my gun and having it slide away over the ice.

We flushed a covey of quail under a high clay bank with overhanging brush and I killed two as they went out of sight over the top of the bank. Some of the covey lit in trees, but most of them scattered into brush piles and it was necessary to jump on the ice-coated mounds of brush several times before they would flush. Coming out while you were poised unsteadily on the icy, springy brush they made difficult shooting and I killed two, missed five, and started back pleased to have found a covey close to the house and happy there were so many left to find on another day.

At the house they said the boy had refused to let any one come into the room.

“You can't come in,”he said.“You mustn't get what I have.”

I went up to him and found him in exactly the position I had left him, white-faced, but with the tops of his cheeks flushed by the fever, staring still, as he had stared, at the foot of the bed.

I took his temperature.

“What is it?”

“Something like a hundred,”I said. It was one hundred and two and four tenths.

“It was a hundred and two,”he said.

“Who said so?”

“The doctor.”

“Your temperature is all right,”I said.“It's nothing to worry about.”

“I don't worry,”he said,“but I can't keep from thinking.”

“Don't think,”I said.“Just take it easy.”

“I'm taking it easy,”he said and looked straight ahead. He was evidently holding tight onto himself about something.

“Take this with water.”

“Do you think it will do any good?”

“Of course it will.”

I sat down and opened the Pirate book and commenced to read, but I could see he was not following, so I stopped.

“About what time do you think I'm going to die?”he asked.

“What?”

“About how long will it be before I die?”

“You aren't going to die. What's the matter with you?”

“Oh, yes, I am. I heard him say a hundred and two.”

“People don't die with a fever of one hundred and two. That's a silly way to talk.”

“I know they do. At school in France the boys told me you can't live with forty-four degrees. I've got a hundred and two.”

He had been waiting to die all day, ever since nine o'clock in the morning.

“You poor Schatz,”I said.“Poor old Schatz. It's like miles and kilometers. You aren't going to die. That's a different thermometer. On that thermometer thirty-seven is normal. On this kind it's ninety-eight.”

“Are you sure?”

“Absolutely,”I said.“It's like miles and kilometers. You know, like how many kilometers we make when we do seventy miles in the car?”

“Oh,”he said.

But his gaze at the foot of the bed relaxed slowly. The hold over himself relaxed too, finally, and the next day it was very slack and he cried very easily at little things that were of no importance.

A Natural History of the Dead

It has always seemed to me that the war has been omitted as a field for the observations of the naturalist. We have charming and sound accounts of the flora and fauna of Patagonia by the late W. H. Hudson, the Reverend Gilbert White has written most interestingly of the Hoopoe on its occasional and not at all common visits to Selborne, and Bishop Stanley has given us a valuable, although popular, Familiar History of Birds. Can we not hope to furnish the reader with a few rational and interesting facts about the dead? I hope so.

When that persevering traveller, Mungo Park, was at one period of his course fainting in the vast wilderness of an African desert, naked and alone, considering his days as numbered and nothing appearing to remain for him to do but to lie down and die, a small moss-flower of extraordinary beauty caught his eye.“Though the whole plant,”says he,“was no larger than one of my fingers, I could not contemplate the delicate conformation of its roots, leaves and capsules without admiration. Can that Being who planted, watered and brought to perfection, in this obscure part of the world, a thing which appears of so small importance, look with unconcern upon the situation and suffering of creatures formed after his own image? Surely not. Reflections like these would not allow me to despair; I started up and, disregarding both hunger and fatigue, travelled forward, assured that relief was at hand; and I was not disappointed.”

With a disposition to wonder and adore in like manner, as Bishop Stanley says, can any branch of Natural History be studied without increasing that faith, love and hope which we also, every one of us, need in our journey through the wilderness of life? Let us therefore see what inspiration we may derive from the dead.

In war the dead are usually the male of the human species although this does not hold true with animals, and I have frequently seen dead mares among the horses. An interesting aspect of war, too, is that it is only there that the naturalist has an opportunity to observe the dead of mules. In twenty years of observation in civil life I had never seen a dead mule and had begun to entertain doubts as to whether these animals were really mortal. On rare occasions I had seen what I took to be dead mules, but on close approach these always proved to be living creatures who seemed to be dead through their quality of complete repose. But in war these animals succumb in much the same manner as the more common and less hardy horse.

Most of those mules that I saw dead were along mountain roads or lying at the foot of steep declivities whence they had been pushed to rid the road of their encumbrance. They seemed a fitting enough sight in the mountains where one was accustomed to their presence and looked less incongruous there than they did later, at Smyrna, where the Greeks broke the legs of all their baggage animals and pushed them off the quay into the shallow water to drown. The numbers of broken-legged mules and horses drowning in the shallow water called for a Goya to depict them. Although, speaking literally, one can hardly say that they called for a Goya since there has only been one Goya, long dead, and it is extremely doubtful if these animals, were they able to call, would call for pictorial representation of their plight but, more likely, would, if they were articulate, call for some one to alleviate their condition.

Regarding the sex of the dead it is a fact that one becomes so accustomed to the sight of all the dead being men that the sight of a dead woman is quite shocking. I first saw inversion of the usual sex of the dead after the explosion of a munition factory which had been situated in the countryside near Milan, Italy. We drove to the scene of the disaster in trucks along poplar-shaded roads, bordered with ditches containing much minute animal life, which I could not clearly observe because of the great clouds of dust raised by the trucks. Arriving where the munition plant had been, some of us were put to patrolling about those large stocks of munitions which for some reason had not exploded, while others were put at extinguishing a fire which had gotten into the grass of an adjacent field; which task being concluded, we were ordered to search the immediate vicinity and surrounding fields for bodies. We found and carried to an improvised mortuary a good number of these and, I must admit, frankly, the shock it was to find that these dead were women rather than men. In those days women had not yet commenced to wear their hair cut short, as they did later for several years in Europe and America, and the most disturbing thing, perhaps because it was the most unaccustomed, was the presence and, even more disturbing, the occasional absence of this long hair. I remember that after we had searched quite thoroughly for the complete dead we collected fragments. Many of these were detached from a heavy, barbed-wire fence which had surrounded the position of the factory and from the still existent portions of which we picked many of these detached bits which illustrated only too well the tremendous energy of high explosive. Many fragments we found a considerable distance away in the fields, they being carried farther by their own weight.

On our return to Milan I recall one or two of us discussing the occurrence and agreeing that the quality of unreality and the fact that there were no wounded did much to rob the disaster of a horror which might have been much greater. Also the fact that it had been so immediate and that the dead were in consequence still as little unpleasant as possible to carry and deal with made it quite removed from the usual battlefield experience. The pleasant, though dusty, ride through the beautiful Lombard countryside also was a compensation for the unpleasantness of the duty and on our return, while we exchanged impressions, we all agreed that it was indeed fortunate that the fire which broke out just before we arrived had been brought under control as rapidly as it had and before it had attained any of the seemingly huge stocks of unexploded munitions. We agreed too that the picking up of the fragments had been an extraordinary business; it being amazing that the human body should be blown into pieces which exploded along no anatomical lines, but rather divided as capriciously as the fragmentation in the burst of a high explosive shell.

A naturalist, to obtain accuracy of observation, may confine himself in his observations to one limited period and I will take first that following the Austrian offensive of June, 1918, in Italy as one in which the dead were present in their greatest numbers, a withdrawal having been forced and an advance later made to recover the ground lost so that the positions after the battle were the same as before except for the presence of the dead. Until the dead are buried they change somewhat in appearance each day. The color change in Caucasian races is from white to yellow, to yellow-green, to black. If left long enough in the heat the flesh comes to resemble coal-tar, especially where it has been broken or torn, and it has quite a visible tarlike iridescence. The dead grow larger each day until sometimes they become quite too big for their uniforms, filling these until they seem blown tight enough to burst. The individual members may increase in girth to an unbelievable extent and faces fill as taut and globular as balloons. The surprising thing, next to their progressive corpulence, is the amount of paper that is scattered about the dead. Their ultimate position, before there is any question of burial, depends on the location of the pockets in the uniform. In the Austrian army these pockets were in the back of the breeches and the dead, after a short time, all consequently lay on their faces, the two hip pockets pulled out and, scattered around them in the grass, all those papers their pockets had contained. The heat, the flies, the indicative positions of the bodies in the grass, and the amount of paper scattered are the impressions one retains. The smell of a battlefield in hot weather one cannot recall. You can remember that there was such a smell, but nothing ever happens to you to bring it back. It is unlike the smell of a regiment, which may come to you suddenly while riding in the street car and you will look across and see the man who has brought it to you. But the other thing is gone as completely as when you have been in love; you remember things that happened, but the sensation cannot be recalled.

One wonders what that persevering traveller, Mungo Park, would have seen on a battlefield in hot weather to restore his confidence. There were always poppies in the wheat in the end of June and in July, and the mulberry trees were in full leaf and one could see the heat waves rise from the barrels of the guns where the sun struck them through the screens of leaves; the earth was turned a bright yellow at the edge of holes where mustard gas shells had been and the average broken house is finer to see than one that has been shelled, but few travellers would take a good full breath of that early summer air and have any such thoughts as Mungo Park about those formed in His own image.

The first thing that you found about the dead was that, hit badly enough, they died like animals. Some quickly from a little wound you would not think would kill a rabbit. They died from little wounds as rabbits die sometimes from three or four small grains of shot that hardly seem to break the skin. Others would die like cats; a skull broken in and iron in the brain, they lie alive two days like cats that crawl into the coal bin with a bullet in the brain and will not die until you cut their heads off. Maybe cats do not die then, they say they have nine lives, I do not know, but most men die like animals, not men. I'd never seen a natural death, so called, and so I blamed it on the war and like the persevering traveller, Mungo Park, knew that there was something else; that always absent something else, and then I saw one.

The only natural death I've ever seen, outside of loss of blood, which isn't bad, was death from Spanish influenza. In this you drown in mucus, choking, and how you know the patient's dead is: at the end he turns to be a little child again, though with his manly force, and fills the sheets as full as any diaper with one vast, final, yellow cataract that flows and dribbles on after he's gone. So now I want to see the death of any self-called Humanist(1) because a persevering traveller like Mungo Park or me lives on and maybe yet will live to see the actual death of members of this literary sect and watch the noble exits that they make. In my musings as a naturalist it has occurred to me that while decorum is an excellent thing some must be indecorous if the race is to be carried on since the position prescribed for procreation is indecorous, highly indecorous, and it occurred to me that perhaps that is what these people are, or were: the children of decorous cohabitation. But regardless of how they started I hope to see the finish of a few, and speculate how worms will try that long preserved sterility; with their quaint pamphlets gone to bust and into foot-notes all their lust.

While it is, perhaps, legitimate to deal with these self-designated citizens in a natural history of the dead, even though the designation may mean nothing by the time this work is published, yet it is unfair to the other dead, who were not dead in their youth of choice, who owned no magazines, many of whom had doubtless never even read a review, that one has seen in the hot weather with a half-pint of maggots working where their mouths have been. It was not always hot weather for the dead, much of the time it was the rain that washed them clean when they lay in it and made the earth soft when they were buried in it and sometimes then kept on until the earth was mud and washed them out and you had to bury them again. Or in the winter in the mountains you had to put them in the snow and when the snow melted in the spring some one else had to bury them. They had beautiful burying grounds in the mountains, war in the mountains is the most beautiful of all war, and in one of them, at a place called Pocol, they buried a general who was shot through the head by a sniper. This is where those writers are mistaken who write books called Generals Die in Bed, because this general died in a trench dug in snow, high in the mountains, wearing an Alpine hat with an eagle feather in it and a hole in front you couldn't put your little finger in and a hole in back you could put your fist in, if it were a small fist and you wanted to put it there, and much blood in the snow. He was a damned fine general, and so was General von Behr who commanded the Bavarian Alpenkorps troops at the battle of Caporetto and was killed in his staff car by the Italian rearguard as he drove into Udine ahead of his troops, and the titles of all such books should be Generals Usually Die in Bed, if we are to have any sort of accuracy in such things.

In the mountains too, sometimes, the snow fell on the dead outside the dressing station on the side that was protected by the mountain from any shelling. They carried them into a cave that had been dug into the mountainside before the earth froze. It was in this cave that a man whose head was broken as a flower-pot may be broken, although it was all held together by membranes and a skillfully applied bandage now soaked and hardened, with the structure of his brain disturbed by a piece of broken steel in it, lay a day, a night, and a day. The stretcher-bearers asked the doctor to go in and have a look at him. They saw him each time they made a trip and even when they did not look at him they heard him breathing. The doctor's eyes were red and the lids swollen, almost shut from tear gas. He looked at the man twice; once in daylight, once with a flashlight. That too would have made a good etching for Goya, the visit with the flashlight, I mean. After looking at him the second time the doctor believed the stretcher-bearers when they said the soldier was still alive.

“What do you want me to do about it?”he asked.

There was nothing they wanted done. But after a while they asked permission to carry him out and lay him with the badly wounded.

“No. No. No!”said the doctor, who was busy.“What's the matter? Are you afraid of him?”

“We don't like to hear him in there with the dead.”

“Don't listen to him. If you take him out of there you will have to carry him right back in.”

“We wouldn't mind that, Captain Doctor.”

“No,”said the doctor.“No. Didn't you hear me say no?”

“Why don't you give him an overdose of morphine?”asked an artillery officer who was waiting to have a wound in his arm dressed.

“Do you think that is the only use I have for morphine? Would you like me to have to operate without morphine? You have a pistol, go out and shoot him yourself.”

“He's been shot already,”said the officer.“If some of you doctors were shot you'd be different.”

“Thank you very much,”said the doctor waving a forceps in the air.“Thank you a thousand times. What about these eyes?”He pointed the forceps at them.“How would you like these?”

“Tear gas. We call it lucky if it's tear gas.”

“Because you leave the line,”said the doctor.“Because you come running here with your tear gas to be evacuated. You rub onions in your eyes.”

“You are beside yourself. I do not notice your insults. You are crazy.”

The stretcher-bearers came in.

“Captain Doctor,”one of them said.

“Get out of here!”said the doctor.

They went out.

“I will shoot the poor fellow,”the artillery officer said.“I am a humane man. I will not let him suffer.”

“Shoot him then,”said the doctor.“Shoot him. Assume the responsibility. I will make a report. Wounded shot by lieutenant of artillery in first curing post. Shoot him. Go ahead shoot him.”

“You are not a human being.”

“My business is to care for the wounded, not to kill them. That is for gentlemen of the artillery.”

“Why don't you care for him then?”

“I have done so. I have done all that can be done.”

“Why don't you send him down on the cable railway?”

“Who are you to ask me questions? Are you my superior officer? Are you in command of this dressing post? Do me the courtesy to answer.”

The lieutenant of artillery said nothing. The others in the room were all soldiers and there were no other officers present.

“Answer me,”said the doctor holding a needle up in his forceps.“Give me a response.”

“F—yourself,”said the artillery officer.

“So,”said the doctor.“So, you said that. All right. All right. We shall see.”

The lieutenant of artillery stood up and walked toward him.

“F—yourself,”he said.“F—yourself. F—your mother. F—your sister....”

The doctor tossed the saucer full of iodine in his face. As he came toward him, blinded, the lieutenant fumbled for his pistol. The doctor skipped quickly behind him, tripped him and, as he fell to the floor, kicked him several times and picked up the pistol in his rubber gloves. The lieutenant sat on the floor holding his good hand to his eyes.

“I'll kill you!”he said.“I'll kill you as soon as I can see.”

“I am the boss,”said the doctor.“All is forgiven since you know I am the boss. You cannot kill me because I have your pistol. Sergeant! Adjutant! Adjutant!”

“The adjutant is at the cable railway,”said the sergeant.

“Wipe out this officer's eyes with alcohol and water. He has got iodine in them. Bring me the basin to wash my hands. I will take this officer next.”

“You won't touch me.”

“Hold him tight. He is a little delirious.”

One of the stretcher-bearers came in.

“Captain Doctor.”

“What do you want?”

“The man in the dead-house—”

“Get out of here.”

“Is dead, Captain Doctor. I thought you would be glad to know.”

“See, my poor lieutenant? We dispute about nothing. In time of war we dispute about nothing.”

“F—you,”said the lieutenant of artillery. He still could not see.“You've blinded me.”

“It is nothing,”said the doctor.“Your eyes will be all right. It is nothing. A dispute about nothing.”

“Ayee! Ayee! Ayee!”suddenly screamed the lieutenant.“You have blinded me! You have blinded me!”

“Hold him tight,”said the doctor.“He is in much pain. Hold him very tight.”

————————————————————

(1) The reader's indulgence is requested for this mention of an extinct phenomenon. The reference, like all references to fashions, dates the story but it is retained because of its mild historical interest and because its omission would spoil the rhythm.

The Gambler, the Nun, and the Radio

They brought them in around midnight and then, all night long, every one along the corridor heard the Russian.

“Where is he shot?”Mr. Frazer asked the night nurse.

“In the thigh, I think.”

“What about the other one?”

“Oh, he's going to die, I'm afraid.”

“Where is he shot?”

“Twice in the abdomen. They only found one of the bullets.”

They were both beet workers, a Mexican and a Russian, and they were sitting drinking coffee in an all-night restaurant when some one came in the door and started shooting at the Mexican. The Russian crawled under a table and was hit, finally, by a stray shot fired at the Mexican as he lay on the floor with two bullets in his abdomen. That was what the paper said.

The Mexican told the police he had no idea who shot him. He believed it to be an accident.

“An accident that he fired eight shots at you and hit you twice, there?”

“Sí, señor,”said the Mexican, who was named Cayetano Ruiz.

“An accident that he hit me at all, the cabrón,”he said to the interpreter.

“What does he say?”asked the detective sergeant, looking across the bed at the interpreter.

“He says it was an accident.”

“Tell him to tell the truth, that he is going to die,”the detective said.

“Na,”said Cayetano.“But tell him that I feel very sick and would prefer not to talk so much.”

“He says that he is telling the truth,”the interpreter said. Then, speaking confidently, to the detective,“He don't know who shot him. They shot him in the back.”

“Yes,”said the detective.“I understand that, but why did the bullets all go in the front?”

“Maybe he is spinning around,”said the interpreter.

“Listen,”said the detective, shaking his finger almost at Cayetano's nose, which projected, waxen yellow, from his dead-man's face in which his eyes were alive as a hawk's.“I don't give a damn who shot you, but I've got to clear this thing up. Don't you want the man who shot you to be punished? Tell him that,”he said to the interpreter.

“He says to tell who shot you.”

“Mandarlo al carajo,”said Cayetano, who was very tired.

“He says he never saw the fellow at all,”the interpreter said.“I tell you straight they shot him in the back.”

“Ask him who shot the Russian.”

“Poor Russian,”said Cayetano.“He was on the floor with his head enveloped in his arms. He started to give cries when they shoot him and he is giving cries ever since. Poor Russian.”

“He says some fellow that he doesn't know. Maybe the same fellow that shot him.”

“Listen,”the detective said.“This isn't Chicago. You're not a gangster. You don't have to act like a moving picture. It's all right to tell who shot you. Anybody would tell who shot them. That's all right to do. Suppose you don't tell who he is and he shoots somebody else. Suppose he shoots a woman or a child. You can't let him get away with that. You tell him,”he said to Mr. Frazer.“I don't trust that damn interpreter.”

“I am very reliable,”the interpreter said. Cayetano looked at Mr. Frazer.

“Listen, amigo,”said Mr. Frazer.“The policeman says that we are not in Chicago but in Hailey, Montana. You are not a bandit and this has nothing to do with the cinema.”

“I believe him,”said Cayetano softly.“Ya lo creo.”

“One can, with honor, denounce one's assailant. Every one does it here, he says. He says what happens if after shooting you, this man shoots a woman or a child?”

“I am not married,”Cayetano said.

“He says any woman, any child.”

“The man is not crazy,”Cayetano said.

“He says you should denounce him,”Mr. Frazer finished.

“Thank you,”Cayetano said.“You are of the great translators. I speak English, but badly. I understand it all right. How did you break your leg?”

“A fall off a horse.”

“What bad luck. I am very sorry. Does it hurt much?”

“Not now. At first, yes.”

“Listen, amigo,”Cayetano began,“I am very weak. You will pardon me. Also I have much pain; enough pain. It is very possible that I die. Please get this policeman out of here because I am very tired.”He made as though to roll to one side; then held himself still.

“I told him everything exactly as you said and he said to tell you, truly, that he doesn't know who shot him and that he is very weak and wishes you would question him later on,”Mr. Frazer said.

“He'll probably be dead later on.”

“That's quite possible.”

“That's why I want to question him now.”

“Somebody shot him in the back, I tell you,”the interpreter said.

“Oh, for Chrisake,”the detective sergeant said, and put his notebook in his pocket.

Outside in the corridor the detective sergeant stood with the interpreter beside Mr. Frazer's wheeled chair.

“I suppose you think somebody shot him in the back too?”

“Yes,”Frazer said.“Somebody shot him in the back. What's it to you?”

“Don't get sore,”the sergeant said.“I wish I could talk spick.”

“Why don't you learn?”

“You don't have to get sore. I don't get any fun out of asking that spick questions. If I could talk spick it would be different.”

“You don't need to talk Spanish,”the interpreter said.“I am a very reliable interpreter.”

“Oh, for Chrisake,”the sergeant said.“Well, so long. I'll come up and see you.”

“Thanks. I'm always in.”

“I guess you are all right. That was bad luck all right. Plenty bad luck.”

“It's coming along good now since he spliced the bone.”

“Yes, but it's a long time. A long, long time.”

“Don't let anybody shoot you in the back.”

“That's right,”he said.“That's right. Well, I'm glad you're not sore.”

“So long,”said Mr. Frazer.

Mr. Frazer did not see Cayetano again for a long time, but each morning Sister Cecilia brought news of him. He was so uncomplaining she said and he was very bad now. He had peritonitis and they thought he could not live. Poor Cayetano, she said. He had such beautiful hands and such a fine face and he never complains. The odor, now, was really terrific. He would point toward his nose with one finger and smile and shake his head, she said. He felt badly about the odor. It embarrassed him, Sister Cecilia said. Oh, he was such a fine patient. He always smiled. He wouldn't go to confession to Father but he promised to say his prayers, and not a Mexican had been to see him since he had been brought in. The Russian was going out at the end of the week. I could never feel anything about the Russian, Sister Cecilia said. Poor fellow, he suffered too. It was a greased bullet and dirty and the wound infected, but he made so much noise and then I always like the bad ones. That Cayetano, he's a bad one. Oh, he must really be a bad one, a thoroughly bad one, he's so fine and delicately made and he's never done any work with his hands. He's not a beet worker. I know he's not a beet worker. His hands are as smooth and not a callous on them. I know he's a bad one of some sort. I'm going down and pray for him now. Poor Cayetano, he's having a dreadful time and he doesn't make a sound. What did they have to shoot him for? Oh, that poor Cayetano! I'm going right down and pray for him.

She went right down and prayed for him.

In that hospital a radio did not work very well until it was dusk. They said it was because there was so much ore in the ground or something about the mountains, but anyway it did not work well at all until it began to get dark outside; but all night it worked beautifully and when one station stopped you could go farther west and pick up another. The last one that you could get was Seattle, Washington, and due to the difference in time, when they signed off at four o'clock in the morning it was five o'clock in the morning in the hospital; and at six o'clock you could get the morning revellers in Minneapolis. That was on account of the difference in time, too, and Mr. Frazer used to like to think of the morning revellers arriving at the studio and picture how they would look getting off a street-car before daylight in the morning carrying their instruments. Maybe that was wrong and they kept their instruments at the place they revelled, but he always pictured them with their instruments. He had never been in Minneapolis and believed he probably would never go there, but he knew what it looked like that early in the morning.

Out of the window of the hospital you could see a field with tumbleweed coming out of the snow, and a bare clay butte. One morning the doctor wanted to show Mr. Frazer two pheasants that were out there in the snow, and pulling the bed toward the window, the reading light fell off the iron bedstead and hit Mr. Frazer on the head. This does not sound so funny now but it was very funny then. Every one was looking out the window, and the doctor, who was a most excellent doctor, was pointing at the pheasants and pulling the bed toward the window, and then, just as in a comic section, Mr. Frazer was knocked out by the leaded base of the lamp hitting the top of his head. It seemed the antithesis of healing or whatever people were in the hospital for, and every one thought it was very funny, as a joke on Mr. Frazer and on the doctor. Everything is much simpler in a hospital, including the jokes.

From the other window, if the bed was turned, you could see the town, with a little smoke above it, and the Dawson mountains looking like real mountains with the winter snow on them. Those were the two views since the wheeled chair had proved to be premature. It is really best to be in bed if you are in a hospital; since two views, with time to observe them, from a room the temperature of which you control, are much better than any number of views seen for a few minutes from hot, empty rooms that are waiting for some one else, or just abandoned, which you are wheeled in and out of. If you stay long enough in a room the view, whatever it is, acquires a great value and becomes very important and you would not change it, not even by a different angle. Just as, with the radio, there are certain things that you become fond of, and you welcome them and resent the new things. The best tunes they had that winter were“Sing Something Simple,”“Singsong Girl,”and“Little White Lies.”No other tunes were as satisfactory, Mr. Frazer felt.“Betty Co-ed”was a good tune too, but the parody of the words which came unavoidably into Mr. Frazer's mind, grew so steadily and increasingly obscene that there being no one to appreciate it, he finally abandoned it and let the song go back to football.

About nine o'clock in the morning they would start using the X-ray machine, and then the radio, which, by then, was only getting Hailey, became useless. Many people in Hailey who owned radios protested about the hospital's X-ray machine which ruined their morning reception, but there was never any action taken, although many felt it was a shame the hospital could not use their machine at a time when people were not using their radios.

About the time when it became necessary to turn off the radio Sister Cecilia came in.

“How's Cayetano, Sister Cecilia?”Mr. Frazer asked.

“Oh, he's very bad.”

“Is he out of his head?”

“No, but I'm afraid he's going to die.”

“How are you?”

“I'm very worried about him, and do you know that absolutely no one has come to see him? He could die just like a dog for all those Mexicans care. They're really dreadful.”

“Do you want to come up and hear the game this afternoon?”

“Oh, no,”she said.“I'd be too excited. I'll be in the chapel praying.”

“We ought to be able to hear it pretty well,”Mr. Frazer said.“They're playing out on the coast and the difference in time will bring it late enough so we can get it all right.”

“Oh, no. I couldn't do it. The world series nearly finished me. When the Athletics were at bat I was praying right out loud:‘Oh, Lord, direct their batting eyes! Oh, Lord, may he hit one! Oh, Lord, may he hit safely!’Then when they filled the bases in the third game, you remember, it was too much for me.‘Oh, Lord, may he hit it out of the lot! Oh, Lord, may he drive it clean over the fence!’Then you know when the Cardinals would come to bat it was simply dreadful.‘Oh, Lord, may they not see it! Oh, Lord, don't let them even catch a glimpse of it! Oh, Lord, may they fan!’And this game is even worse. It's Notre Dame. Our Lady. No, I'll be in the chapel. For Our Lady. They're playing for Our Lady. I wish you'd write something sometime for Our Lady. You could do it. You know you could do it, Mr. Frazer.”

“I don't know anything about her that I could write. It's mostly been written already,”Mr. Frazer said.“You wouldn't like the way I write. She wouldn't care for it either.”

“You'll write about her sometime,”Sister said.“I know you will. You must write about Our Lady.”

“You'd better come up and hear the game.”

“It would be too much for me. No, I'll be in the chapel doing what I can.”

That afternoon they had been playing about five minutes when a probationer came into the room and said,“Sister Cecilia wants to know how the game is going?”

“Tell her they have a touchdown already.”

In a little while the probationer came into the room again.

“Tell her they're playing them off their feet,”Mr. Frazer said.

A little later he rang the bell for the nurse who was on floor duty.“Would you mind going down to the chapel or sending word down to Sister Cecilia that Notre Dame has them fourteen to nothing at the end of the first quarter and that it's all right. She can stop praying.”

In a few minutes Sister Cecilia came into the room. She was very excited.“What does fourteen to nothing mean? I don't know anything about this game. That's a nice safe lead in baseball. But I don't know anything about football. It may not mean a thing. I'm going right back down to the chapel and pray until it's finished.”

“They have them beaten,”Frazer said.“I promise you. Stay and listen with me.”

“No. No. No. No. No. No. No,”she said.“I'm going right down to the chapel to pray.”

Mr. Frazer sent down word whenever Notre Dame scored, and finally, when it had been dark a long time, the final result.

“How's Sister Cecilia?”

“They're all at chapel,”she said.

The next morning Sister Cecilia came in. She was very pleased and confident.

“I knew they couldn't beat Our Lady,”she said.“They couldn't. Cayetano's better too. He's much better. He's going to have visitors. He can't see them yet, but they are going to come and that will make him feel better and know he's not forgotten by his own people. I went down and saw that O'Brien boy at Police Headquarters and told him that he's got to send some Mexicans up to see poor Cayetano. He's going to send some this afternoon. Then that poor man will feel better. It's wicked the way no one has come to see him.”

That afternoon about five o'clock three Mexicans came into the room.

“Can one?”asked the biggest one, who had very thick lips and was quite fat.

“Why not?”Mr. Frazer answered.“Sit down, gentlemen. Will you take something?”

“Many thanks,”said the big one.

“Thanks,”said the darkest and smallest one.

“Thanks, no,”said the thin one.“It mounts to my head.”He tapped his head.

The nurse brought some glasses.“Please give them the bottle,”Frazer said.“It is from Red Lodge,”he explained.

“That of Red Lodge is the best,”said the big one.“Much better than that of Big Timber.”

“Clearly,”said the smallest one,“and costs more too.”

“In Red Lodge it is of all prices,”said the big one.

“How many tubes has the radio?”asked the one who did not drink.

“Seven.”

“Very beautiful,”he said.“What does it cost?”

“I don't know,”Mr. Frazer said.“It is rented.”

“You gentlemen are friends of Cayetano?”

“No,”said the big one.“We are friends of he who wounded him.”

“We were sent here by the police,”the smallest one said.

“We have a little place,”the big one said.“He and I,”indicating the one who did not drink.“He has a little place too,”indicating the small, dark one.“The police tell us we have to come—so we come.”

“I am very happy you have come.”

“Equally,”said the big one.

“Will you have another little cup?”

“Why not?”said the big one.

“With your permission,”said the smallest one.

“Not me,”said the thin one.“It mounts to my head.”

“It is very good,”said the smallest one.

“Why not try some,”Mr. Frazer asked the thin one.“Let a little mount to your head.”

“Afterwards comes the headache,”said the thin one.

“Could you not send friends of Cayetano to see him?”Frazer asked.

“He has no friends.”

“Every man has friends.”

“This one, no.”

“What does he do?”

“He is a card-player.”

“Is he good?”

“I believe it.”

“From me,”said the smallest one,“he won one hundred and eighty dollars. Now there is no longer one hundred and eighty dollars in the world.”

“From me,”said the thin one,“he won two hundred and eleven dollars. Fix yourself on that figure.”

“I never played with him,”said the fat one.

“He must be very rich,”Mr. Frazer suggested.

“He is poorer than we,”said the little Mexican.“He has no more than the shirt on his back.”

“And that shirt is of little value now,”Mr. Frazer said.“Perforated as it is.”

“Clearly.”

“The one who wounded him was a card-player?”

“No, a beet worker. He has had to leave town.”

“Fix yourself on this,”said the smallest one.“He was the best guitar player ever in this town. The finest.”

“What a shame.”

“I believe it,”said the biggest one.“How he could touch the guitar.”

“There are no good guitar players left?”

“Not the shadow of a guitar player.”

“There is an accordion player who is worth something,”the thin man said.

“There are a few who touch various instruments,”the big one said.“You like music?”

“How would I not?”

“We will come one night with music? You think the sister would allow it? She seems very amiable.”

“I am sure she would permit it when Cayetano is able to hear it.”“Is she a little crazy?”asked the thin one.

“Who?”

“That sister.”

“No,”Mr. Frazer said.“She is a fine woman of great intelligence and sympathy.”

“I distrust all priests, monks, and sisters,”said the thin one.

“He had bad experiences when a boy,”the smallest one said.

“I was acolyte,”the thin one said proudly.“Now I believe in nothing. Neither do I go to mass.”

“Why? Does it mount to your head?”

“No,”said the thin one.“It is alcohol that mounts to my head. Religion is the opium of the poor.”

“I thought marijuana was the opium of the poor,”Frazer said.

“Did you ever smoke opium?”the big one asked.

“No.”

“Nor I,”he said.“It seems it is very bad. One commences and cannot stop. It is a vice.”

“Like religion,”said the thin one.

“This one,”said the smallest Mexican,“is very strong against religion.”

“It is necessary to be very strong against something,”Mr. Frazer said politely.

“I respect those who have faith even though they are ignorant,”the thin one said.

“Good,”said Mr. Frazer.

“What can we bring you?”asked the big Mexican.“Do you lack for anything?”

“I would be glad to buy some beer if there is good beer.”

“We will bring beer.”

“Another copita before you go?”

“It is very good.”

“We are robbing you.”

“I can't take it. It goes to my head. Then I have a bad headache and sick at the stomach.”

“Good-by, gentlemen.”

“Good-by and thanks.”

They went out and there was supper and then the radio, turned to be as quiet as possible and still be heard, and the stations finally signing off in this order: Denver, Salt Lake City, Los Angeles, and Seattle. Mr. Frazer received no picture of Denver from the radio. He could see Denver from the Denver Post, and correct the picture from The Rocky Mountain News. Nor did he ever have any feel of Salt Lake City or Los Angeles from what he heard from those places. All he felt about Salt Lake City was that it was dean, but dull, and there were too many ballrooms mentioned in too many big hotels for him to see Los Angeles. He could not feel it for the ballrooms. But Seattle he came to know very well, the taxicab company with the big white cabs (each cab equipped with radio itself) he rode in every night out to the roadhouse on the Canadian side where he followed the course of parties by the musical selections they phoned for. He lived in Seattle from two o'clock on, each night, hearing the pieces that all the different people asked for, and it was as real as Minneapolis, where the revellers left their beds each morning to make that trip down to the studio. Mr. Frazer grew very fond of Seattle, Washington.

The Mexicans came and brought beer but it was not good beer. Mr. Frazer saw them but he did not feel like talking, and when they went he knew they would not come again. His nerves had become tricky and he disliked seeing people while he was in this condition. His nerves went bad at the end of five weeks, and while he was pleased they lasted that long yet he resented being forced to make the same experiment when he already knew the answer. Mr. Frazer had been through this all before. The only thing which was new to him was the radio. He played it all night long, turned so low he could barely hear it, and he was learning to listen to it without thinking.

Sister Cecilia came into the room about ten o'clock in the morning on that day and brought the mail. She was very handsome, and Mr. Frazer liked to see her and to hear her talk, but the mail, supposedly coming from a different world, was more important. However, there was nothing in the mail of any interest.

“You look so much better,”she said.“You'll be leaving us soon.”

“Yes,”Mr. Frazer said.“You look very happy this morning.”

“Oh, I am. This morning I feel as though I might be a saint.”

Mr. Frazer was a little taken aback at this.

“Yes,”Sister Cecilia went on.“That's what I want to be. A saint. Ever since I was a little girl I've wanted to be a saint. When I was a girl I thought if I renounced the world and went into the convent I would be a saint. That was what I wanted to be and that was what I thought I had to do to be one. I expected I would be a saint. I was absolutely sure I would be one. For just a moment I thought I was one. I was so happy and it seemed so simple and easy. When I awoke in the morning I expected I would be a saint, but I wasn't. I've never become one. I want so to be one. All I want is to be a saint. That is all I've ever wanted. And this morning I feel as though I might be one. Oh, I hope I will get to be one.”

“You'll be one. Everybody gets what they want. That's what they always tell me.”

“I don't know now. When I was a girl it seemed so simple. I knew I would be a saint. Only I believed it took time when I found it did not happen suddenly. Now it seems almost impossible.”

“I'd say you had a good chance.”

“Do you really think so? No, I don't want just to be encouraged. Don't just encourage me. I want to be a saint. I want so to be a saint.”

“Of course you'll be a saint,”Mr. Frazer said.

“No, probably I won't be. But, oh, if I could only be a saint! I'd be perfectly happy.”

“You're three to one to be a saint.”

“No, don't encourage me. But, oh, if I could only be a saint! If I could only be a saint!”

“How's your friend Cayetano?”

“He's going to get well but he's paralyzed. One of the bullets hit the big nerve that goes down through his thigh and that leg is paralyzed. They only found it out when he got well enough so that he could move.”

“Maybe the nerve will regenerate.”

“I'm praying that it will,”Sister Cecilia said.“You ought to see him.”

“I don't feel like seeing anybody.”

“You know you'd like to see him. They could wheel him in here.”

“All right.”

They wheeled him in, thin, his skin transparent, his hair black and needing to be cut, his eyes very laughing, his teeth bad when he smiled.

“Hola, amigo! Qué tal?”

“As you see,”said Mr. Frazer.“And thou?”

“Alive and with the leg paralyzed.”

“Bad,”Mr. Frazer said.“But the nerve can regenerate and be as good as new.”

“So they tell me.”

“What about the pain?”

“Not now. For a while I was crazy with it in the belly. I thought the pain alone would kill me.”

Sister Cecilia was observing them happily.

“She tells me you never made a sound,”Mr. Frazer said.

“So many people in the ward,”the Mexican said deprecatingly.“What class of pain do you have?”

“Big enough. Clearly not as bad as yours. When the nurse goes out I cry an hour, two hours. It rests me. My nerves are bad now.”

“You have the radio. If I had a private room and a radio I would be crying and yelling all night long.”

“I doubt it.”

“Hombre, sí. It's very healthy. But you cannot do it with so many people.”

“At least,”Mr. Frazer said,“the hands are still good. They tell me you make your living with the hands.”

“And the head,”he said, tapping his forehead.“But the head isn't worth as much.”

“Three of your countrymen were here.”

“Sent by the police to see me.”

“They brought some beer.”

“It probably was bad.”

“It was bad.”

“Tonight, sent by the police, they come to serenade me.”He laughed, then tapped his stomach.“I cannot laugh yet. As musicians they are fatal.”

“And the one who shot you?”

“Another fool. I won thirty-eight dollars from him at cards. That is not to kill about.”

“The three told me you win much money.”

“And am poorer than the birds.”

“How?”

“I am a poor idealist. I am the victim of illusions.”He laughed, then grinned and tapped his stomach.“I am a professional gambler but I like to gamble. To really gamble. Little gambling is all crooked. For real gambling you need luck. I have no luck.”

“Never?”

“Never. I am completely without luck. Look, this cabrón who shoots me just now. Can he shoot? No. The first shot he fires into nothing. The second is intercepted by a poor Russian. That would seem to be luck. What happens? He shoots me twice in the belly. He is a lucky man. I have no luck. He could not hit a horse if he were holding the stirrup. All luck.”

“I thought he shot you first and the Russian after.”

“No, the Russian first, me after. The paper was mistaken.”

“Why didn't you shoot him?”

“I never carry a gun. With my luck, if I carried a gun I would be hanged ten times a year. I am a cheap card player, only that.”He stopped, then continued.“When I make a sum of money I gamble and when I gamble I lose. I have passed at dice for three thousand dollars and crapped out for the six. With good dice. More than once.”

“Why continue?”

“If I live long enough the luck will change. I have bad luck now for fifteen years. If I ever get any good luck I will be rich.”He grinned.“I am a good gambler, really I would enjoy being rich.”

“Do you have bad luck with all games?”

“With everything and with women.”He smiled again, showing his bad teeth.

“Truly?”

“Truly.”

“And what is there to do?”

“Continue, slowly, and wait for luck to change.”

“But with women?”

“No gambler has luck with women. He is too concentrated. He works nights. When he should be with the woman. No man who works nights can hold a woman if the woman is worth anything.”

“You are a philosopher.”

“No, hombre. A gambler of the small towns. One small town, then another, another, then a big town, then start over again.”

“Then shot in the belly.”

“The first time,”he said.“That has only happened once.”

“I tire you talking?”Mr. Frazer suggested.

“No,”he said.“I must tire you.”

“And the leg?”

“I have no great use for the leg. I am all right with the leg or not. I will be able to circulate.”

“I wish you luck, truly, and with all my heart,”Mr. Frazer said.

“Equally,”he said.“And that the pain stops.”

“It will not last, certainly. It is passing. It is of no importance.”

“That it passes quickly.”

“Equally.”

That night the Mexicans played the accordion and other instruments in the ward and it was cheerful and the noise of the inhalations and exhalations of the accordion, and of the bells, the traps, and the drum came down the corridor. In that ward there was a rodeo rider who had come out of the chutes on Midnight on a hot dusty afternoon with the big crowd watching, and now, with a broken back, was going to learn to work in leather and to cane chairs when he got well enough to leave the hospital. There was a carpenter who had fallen with a scaffolding and broken both ankles and both wrists. He had lit like a cat but without a cat's resiliency. They could fix him up so that he could work again but it would take a long time. There was a boy from a farm, about sixteen years old, with a broken leg that had been badly set and was to be rebroken. There was Cayetano Ruiz, a small-town gambler with a paralyzed leg. Down the corridor Mr. Frazer could hear them all laughing and merry with the music made by the Mexicans who had been sent by the police. The Mexicans were having a good time. They came in, very excited, to see Mr. Frazer and wanted to know if there was anything he wanted them to play, and they came twice more to play at night of their own accord.

The last time they played Mr. Frazer lay in his room with the door open and listened to the noisy, bad music and could not keep from thinking. When they wanted to know what he wished played, he asked for the Cucaracha, which has the sinister lightness and deftness of so many of the tunes men have gone to die to. They played noisily and with emotion. The tune was better than most of such tunes, to Mr. Frazer's mind, but the effect was all the same.

In spite of this introduction of emotion, Mr. Frazer went on thinking. Usually he avoided thinking all he could, except when he was writing, but now he was thinking about those who were playing and what the little one had said.

Religion is the opium of the people. He believed that, that dyspeptic little joint-keeper. Yes, and music is the opium of the people. Old mount-to-the-head hadn't thought of that. And now economics is the opium of the people; along with patriotism the opium of the people in Italy and Germany. What about sexual intercourse; was that an opium of the people? Of some of the people. Of some of the best of the people. But drink was a sovereign opium of the people, oh, an excellent opium. Although some prefer the radio, another opium of the people, a cheap one he had just been using. Along with these went gambling, an opium of the people if there ever was one, one of the oldest. Ambition was another, an opium of the people, along with a belief in any new form of government. What you wanted was the minimum of government, always less government. Liberty, what we believed in, now the name of a MacFadden publication. We believed in that although they had not found a new name for it yet. But what was the real one? What was the real, the actual, opium of the people? He knew it very well. It was gone just a little way around the corner in that well-lighted part of his mind that was there after two or more drinks in the evening; that he knew was there (it was not really there of course). What was it? He knew very well. What was it? Of course; bread was the opium of the people. Would he remember that and would it make sense in the daylight? Bread is the opium of the people.

“Listen,”Mr. Frazer said to the nurse when she came.“Get that little thin Mexican in here, will you, please?”

“How do you like it?”the Mexican said at the door.

“Very much.”

“It is a historic tune,”the Mexican said.“It is the tune of the real revolution.”

“Listen,”said Mr. Frazer.“Why should the people be operated on without an anaesthetic?”

“I do not understand.”

“Why are not all the opiums of the people good? What do you want to do with the people?”

“They should be rescued from ignorance.”

“Don't talk nonsense. Education is an opium of the people. You ought to know that. You've had a little.”

“You do not believe in education?”

“No,”said Mr. Frazer.“In knowledge, yes.”

“I do not follow you.”

“Many times I do not follow myself with pleasure.”

“You want to hear the Cucaracha another time?”asked the Mexican worriedly.

“Yes,”said Mr. Frazer.“Play the Cucaracha another time. It's better than the radio.”

Revolution, Mr. Frazer thought, is no opium. Revolution is a catharsis; an ecstasy which can only be prolonged by tyranny. The opiums are for before and for after. He was thinking well, a little too well.

They would go now in a little while, he thought, and they would take the Cucaracha with them. Then he would have a little spot of the giant killer and play the radio, you could play the radio so that you could hardly hear it.

Fathers and Sons

There had been a sign to detour in the center of the main street of this town, but cars had obviously gone through, so, believing it was some repair which had been completed, Nicholas Adams drove on through the town along the empty, brick-paved street, stopped by traffic lights that flashed on and off on this traffic-less Sunday, and would be gone next year when the payments on the system were not met; on under the heavy trees of the small town that are a part of your heart if it is your town and you have walked under them, but that are only too heavy, that shut out the sun and that dampen the houses for a stranger; out past the last house and onto the highway that rose and fell straight away ahead with banks of red dirt sliced cleanly away and the second-growth timber on both sides. It was not his country but it was the middle of fall and all of this country was good to drive through and to see. The cotton was picked and in the clearings there were patches of corn, some cut with streaks of red sorghum, and, driving easily, his son asleep on the seat by his side, the day's run made, knowing the town he would reach for the night, Nick noticed which corn fields had soy beans or peas in them, how the thickets and the cut-over land lay, where the cabins and houses were in relation to the fields and the thickets; hunting the country in his mind as he went by; sizing up each clearing as to feed and cover and figuring where you would find a covey and which way they would fly.

In shooting quail you must not get between them and their habitual cover, once the dogs have found them, or when they flush they will come pouring at you, some rising steep, some skimming by your ears, whirring into a size you have never seen them in the air as they pass, the only way being to turn and take them over your shoulder as they go, before they set their wings and angle down into the thicket. Hunting this country for quail as his father had taught him, Nicholas Adams started thinking about his father. When he first thought about him it was always the eyes. The big frame, the quick movements, the wide shoulders, the hooked, hawk nose, the beard that covered the weak chin, you never thought about—it was always the eyes. They were protected in his head by the formation of the brows; set deep as though a special protection had been devised for some very valuable instrument. They saw much farther and much quicker than the human eye sees and they were the great gift his father had. His father saw as a big-horn ram or as an eagle sees, literally.

He would be standing with his father on one shore of the lake, his own eyes were very good then, and his father would say,“They've run up the flag.”Nick could not see the flag or the flag pole.“There,”his father would say,“it's your sister Dorothy. She's got the flag up and she's walking out onto the dock.”

Nick would look across the lake and he could see the long wooded shore-line, the higher timber behind, the point that guarded the bay, the clear hills of the farm and the white of their cottage in the trees but he could not see anyflag pole, or any dock, only the white of the beach and the curve of the shore.

“Can you see the sheep on the hillside toward the point?”

“Yes.”

They were a whitish patch on the gray-green of the hill.

“I can count them,”his father said.

Like all men with a faculty that surpasses human requirements, his father was very nervous. Then, too, he was sentimental, and, like most sentimental people, he was both cruel and abused. Also, he had much bad luck, and it was not all of it his own. He had died in a trap that he had helped only a little to set, and they had all betrayed him in their various ways before he died. All sentimental people are betrayed so many times. Nick could not write about him yet, although he would, later, but the quail country made him remember him as he was when Nick was a boy and he was very grateful to him for two things: fishing and shooting. His father was as sound on those two things as he was unsound on sex, for instance, and Nick was glad that it had been that way; for some one has to give you your first gun or the opportunity to get it and use it, and you have to live where there is game or fish if you are to learn about them, and now, at thirty-eight, he loved to fish and to shoot exactly as much as when he first had gone with his father. It was a passion that had never slackened and he was very grateful to his father for bringing him to know it.

While for the other, that his father was not sound about, all the equipment you will ever have is provided and each man learns all there is for him to know about it without advice; and it makes no difference where you live. He remembered very clearly the only two pieces of information his father had given him about that. Once when they were out shooting together Nick shot a red squirrel out of a hemlock tree. The squirrel fell, wounded, and when Nick picked him up bit the boy clean through the ball of the thumb.

“The dirty little bugger,”Nick said and smacked the squirrel's head against the tree.“Look how he bit me.”

His father looked and said,“Suck it out clean and put some iodine on when you get home.”

“The little bugger,”Nick said.

“Do you know what a bugger is?”his father asked him.

“We call anything a bugger,”Nick said.

“A bugger is a man who has intercourse with animals.”

“Why?”Nick said.

“I don't know,”his father said.“But it is a heinous crime.”

Nick's imagination was both stirred and horrified by this and he thought of various animals but none seemed attractive or practical and that was the sum total of direct sexual knowledge bequeathed him by his father except on one other subject. One morning he read in the paper that Enrico Caruso had been arrested for mashing.

“What is mashing?”

“It is one of the most heinous of crimes,”his father answered. Nick's imagination pictured the great tenor doing something strange, bizarre, and heinous with a potato masher to a beautiful lady who looked like the pictures of Anna Held on the inside of cigar boxes. He resolved, with considerable horror, that when he was old enough he would try mashing at least once.

His father had summed up the whole matter by stating that masturbation produced blindness, insanity, and death, while a man who went with prostitutes would contract hideous venereal diseases and that the thing to do was to keep your hands off of people. On the other hand his father had the finest pair of eyes he had ever seen and Nick had loved him very much and for a long time. Now, knowing how it had all been, even remembering the earliest times before things had gone badly was not good remembering. If he wrote it he could get rid of it. He had gotten rid of many things by writing them. But it was still too early for that. There were still too many people. So he decided to think of something else. There was nothing to do about his father and he had thought it all through many times. The handsome job the undertaker had done on his father's face had not blurred in his mind and all the rest of it was quite clear, including the responsibilities. He had complimented the undertaker. The undertaker had been both proud and smugly pleased. But it was not the undertaker that had given him that last face. The undertaker had only made certain dashingly executed repairs of doubtful artistic merit. The face had been making itself and being made for a long time. It had modelled fast in the last three years. It was a good story but there were still too many people alive for him to write it.

Nick's own education in those earlier matters had been acquired in the hemlock woods behind the Indian camp. This was reached by a trail which ran from the cottage through the woods to the farm and then by a road which wound through the slashings to the camp. Now if he could still feel all of that trail with bare feet. First there was the pine-needle loam through the hemlock woods behind the cottage where the fallen logs crumbled into wood dust and long splintered pieces of wood hung like javelins in the tree that had been struck by lightning. You crossed the creek on a log and if you stepped off there was the black muck of the swamp. You climbed a fence out of the woods and the trail was hard in the sun across the field with cropped grass and sheep sorrel and mullen growing and to the left the quaky bog of the creek bottom where the killdeer plover fed. The spring house was in that creek. Below the barn there was fresh warm manure and the other older manure that was caked dry on top. Then there was another fence and the hard, hot trail from the barn to the house and the hot sandy road that ran down to the woods, crossing the creek, on a bridge this time, where the cat-tails grew that you soaked in kerosene to make jack-lights with for spearing fish at night.

Then the main road went off to the left, skirting the woods and climbing the hill, while you went into the woods on the wide clay and shale road, cool under the trees, and broadened for them to skid out the hemlock bark the Indians cut. The hemlock bark was piled in long rows of stacks, roofed over with more bark, like houses, and the peeled logs lay huge and yellow where the trees had been felled. They left the logs in the woods to rot, they did not even clear away or burn the tops. It was only the bark they wanted for the tannery at Boyne City; hauling it across the lake on the ice in winter, and each year there was less forest and more open, hot, shadeless, weed-grown slashing.

But there was still much forest then, virgin forest where the trees grew high before there were any branches and you walked on the brown, clean, springy-needled ground with no undergrowth and it was cool on the hottest days and they three lay against the trunk of a hemlock wider than two beds are long, with the breeze high in the tops and the cool light that came in patches, and Billy said:

“You want Trudy again?”

“You want to?”

“Un Huh.”

“Come on.”

“No, here.”

“But Billy—”

“I no mind Billy. He my brother.”

Then afterwards they sat, the three of them, listening for a black squirrel that was in the top branches where they could not see him. They were waiting for him to bark again because when he barked he would jerk his tail and Nick would shoot where he saw any movement. His father gave him only three cartridges a day to hunt with and he had a single-barrel twenty-gauge shotgun with a very long barrel.

“Son of a bitch never move,”Billy said.

“You shoot, Nickie. Scare him. We see him jump. Shoot him again,”Trudy said. It was a long speech for her.

“I've only got two shells,”Nick said.

“Son of a bitch,”said Billy.

They sat against the tree and were quiet. Nick was feeling hollow and happy.

“Eddie says he going to come some night sleep in bed with you sister Dorothy.”

“What?”

“He said.”

Trudy nodded.

“That's all he want do,”she said. Eddie was their older half-brother. He was seventeen.

“If Eddie Gilby ever comes at night and even speaks to Dorothy you know what I'd do to him? I'd kill him like this.”Nick cocked the gun and hardly taking aim pulled the trigger, blowing a hole as big as your hand in the head or belly of that half-breed bastard Eddie Gilby.“Like that. I'd kill him like that.”

“He better not come then,”Trudy said. She put her hand in Nick's pocket.

“He better watch out plenty,”said Billy.

“He's big bluff,”Trudy was exploring with her hand in Nick's pocket.“But don't you kill him. You get plenty trouble.”

“I'd kill him like that,”Nick said. Eddie Gilby lay on the ground with all his chest shot away. Nick put his foot on him proudly.

“I'd scalp him,”he said happily.

“No,”said Trudy.“That's dirty.”

“I'd scalp him and send it to his mother.”

“His mother dead,”Trudy said.“Don't you kill him, Nickie. Don't you kill him for me.”

“After I scalped him I'd throw him to the dogs.”

Billy was very depressed.“He better watch out,”he said gloomily.

“They'd tear him to pieces,”Nick said, pleased with the picture. Then, having scalped that half-breed renegade and standing, watching the dogs tear him, his face unchanging, he fell backward against the tree, held tight around the neck, Trudy holding, choking him, and crying,“No kill him! No kill him! No kill him! No. No. No. Nickie. Nickie. Nickie!”

“What's the matter with you?”

“No kill him.”

“I got to kill him.”

“He just a big bluff.”

“All right,”Nickie said.“I won't kill him unless he comes around the house. Let go of me.”

“That's good,”Trudy said.“You want to do anything now? I feel good now.”

“If Billy goes away.”Nick had killed Eddie Gilby, then pardoned him his life, and he was a man now.

“You go, Billy. You hang around all the time. Go on.”

“Son a bitch,”Billy said.“I get tired this. What we come? Hunt or what?”

“You can take the gun. There's one shell.”

“All right. I get a big black one all right.”

“I'll holler,”Nick said.

Then, later, it was a long time after and Billy was still away.

“You think we make a baby?”Trudy folded her brown legs together happily and rubbed against him. Something inside Nick had gone a long way away.

“I don't think so,”he said.

“Make plenty baby what the hell.”

They heard Billy shoot.

“I wonder if he got one.”

“Don't care,”said Trudy.

Billy came through the trees. He had the gun over his shoulder and he held a black squirrel by the front paws.

“Look,”he said.“Bigger than a cat. You all through?”

“Where'd you get him?”

“Over there. Saw him jump first.”

“Got to go home,”Nick said.

“No,”said Trudy.

“I got to get there for supper.”

“All right.”

“Want to hunt tomorrow?”

“All right.”

“You can have the squirrel.”

“All right.”

“Come out after supper?”

“No.”

“How you feel?”

“Good.”

“All right.”

“Give me kiss on the face,”said Trudy.

Now, as he rode along the highway in the car and it was getting dark, Nick was all through thinking about his father. The end of the day never made him think of him. The end of the day had always belonged to Nick alone and he never felt right unless he was alone at it. His father came back to him in the fall of the year, or in the early spring when there had been jacksnipe on the prairie, or when he saw shocks of corn, or when he saw a lake, or if he ever saw a horse and buggy, or when he saw, or heard, wild geese, or in a duck blind; remembering the time an eagle dropped through the whirling snow to strike a canvas-covered decoy, rising, his wings beating, the talons caught in the canvas. His father was with him, suddenly, in deserted orchards and in new-plowed fields, in thickets, on small hills, or when going through dead grass, whenever splitting wood or hauling water, by grist mills, cider mills and dams and always with open fires. The towns he lived in were not towns his father knew. After he was fifteen he had shared nothing with him.

His father had frost in his beard in cold weather and in hot weather he sweated very much. He liked to work in the sun on the farm because he did not have to and he loved manual work, which Nick did not. Nick loved his father but hated the smell of him and once when he had to wear a suit of his father's underwear that had gotten too small for his father it made him feel sick and he took it off and put it under two stones in the creek and said that he had lost it. He had told his father how it was when his father had made him put it on but his father had said it was freshly washed. It had been, too. When Nick had asked him to smell of it his father sniffed at it indignantly and said that it was clean and fresh. When Nick came home from fishing without it and said he lost it he was whipped for lying.

Afterwards he had sat inside the woodshed with the door open, his shotgun loaded and cocked, looking across at his father sitting on the screen porch reading the paper, and thought,“I can blow him to hell. I can kill him.”Finally he felt his anger go out of him and he felt a little sick about it being the gun that his father had given him. Then he had gone to the Indian camp, walking there in the dark, to get rid of the smell. There was only one person in his family that he liked the smell of; one sister. All the others he avoided all contact with. That sense blunted when he started to smoke. It was a good thing. It was good for a bird dog but it did not help a man.

“What was it like, Papa, when you were a little boy and used to hunt with the Indians?”

“I don't know,”Nick was startled. He had not even noticed the boy was awake. He looked at him sitting beside him on the seat. He had felt quite alone but this boy had been with him. He wondered for how long.“We used to go all day to hunt black squirrels,”he said.“My father only gave me three shells a day because he said that would teach me to hunt and it wasn't good for a boy to go banging around. I went with a boy named Billy Gilby and his sister Trudy. We used to go out nearly every day all one summer.”

“Those are funny names for Indians.”

“Yes, aren't they,”Nick said.

“But tell me what they were like.”

“They were Ojibways,”Nick said.“And they were very nice.”

“But what were they like to be with?”

“It's hard to say,”Nick Adams said. Could you say she did first what no one has ever done better and mention plump brown legs, flat belly, hard little breasts, well holding arms, quick searching tongue, the flat eyes, the good taste of mouth, then uncomfortably, tightly, sweetly, moistly, lovely, tightly, achingly, fully, finally, unendingly, never-endingly, never-to-endingly, suddenly ended, the great bird flown like an owl in the twilight, only it was daylight in the woods and hemlock needles stuck against your belly. So that when you go in a place where Indians have lived you smell them gone and all the empty pain killer bottles and the flies that buzz do not kill the sweetgrass smell, the smoke smell and that other like a fresh cased marten skin. Nor any jokes about them nor old squaws take that away. Nor the sick sweet smell they get to have. Nor what they did finally. It wasn't how they ended. They all ended the same. Long time ago good. Now no good.

And about the other. When you have shot one bird flying you have shot all birds flying. They are all different and they fly in different ways but the sensation is the same and the last one is as good as the first. He could thank his father for that.

“You might not like them,”Nick said to the boy.“But I think you would.”

“And my grandfather lived with them too when he was a boy, didn't he?”

“Yes. When I asked him what they were like he said that he had many friends among them.”

“Will I ever live with them?”

“I don't know,”Nick said.“That's up to you.”

“How old will I be when I get a shotgun and can hunt by myself?”

“Twelve years old if I see you are careful.”

“I wish I was twelve now.”

“You will be, soon enough.”

“What was my grandfather like? I can't remember him except that he gave me an air rifle and an American flag when I came over from France that time. What was he like?”

“He's hard to describe. He was a great hunter and fisherman and he had wonderful eyes.”

“Was he greater than you?”

“He was a much better shot and his father was a great wing shot too.”

“I'll bet he wasn't better than you.”

“Oh, yes he was. He shot very quickly and beautifully. I'd rather see him shoot than any man I ever knew. He was always very disappointed in the way I shot.”

“Why do we never go to pray at the tomb of my grandfather?”

“We live in a different pan of the country. It's a long way from here.”

“In France that wouldn't make any difference. In France we'd go. I think I ought to go to pray at the tomb of my grandfather.”

“Sometime we'll go.”

“I hope we won't live somewhere so that I can never go to pray at your tomb when you are dead.”

“We'll have to arrange it.”

“Don't you think we might all be buried at a convenient place? We could all be buried in France. That would be fine.”

“I don't want to be buried in France,”Nick said.

“Well, then, we'll have to get some convenient place in America. Couldn't we all be buried out at the ranch?”

“That's an idea.”

“Then I could stop and pray at the tomb of my grandfather on the way to the ranch.”

“You're awfully practical.”

“Well, I don't feel good never to have even visited the tomb of my grandfather.”

“We'll have to go,”Nick said.“I can see we'll have to go.”

One Trip Across

You know how it is there early in the morning in Havana with the bums still asleep against the walls of the buildings; before even the ice wagons come by with ice for the bars? Well, we came across the square from the dock to the Pearl of San Francisco Café to get coffee and there was only one beggar awake in the square and he was getting a drink out of the fountain. But when we got inside the café and sat down, there were the three of them waiting for us.

We sat down and one of them came over.

“Well,”he said.

“I can't do it,”I told him.“I'd like to do it as a favor. But I told you last night I couldn't.”

“You can name your own price.”

“It isn't that. I can't do it. That's all.”

The two others had come over and they stood there looking sad. They were nice-looking fellows all right and I would have liked to have done them the favor.

“A thousand apiece,”said the one who spoke good English.

“Don't make me feel bad,”I told him.“I tell you true I can't do it.”

“Afterwards, when things are changed, it would mean a good deal to you.”

“I know it. I'm all for you. But I can't do it.”

“Why not?”

“I make my living with the boat. If I lose her I lose my living.”

“With the money you buy another boat.”

“Not in jail.”

They must have thought I just needed to be argued into it because the one kept on.

“You would have three thousand dollars and it could mean a great deal to you later. All this will not last, you know.”

“Listen,”I said.“I don't care who is President here. But I don't carry anything to the States that can talk.”

“You mean we would talk?”one of them who hadn't spoken said. He was angry.

“I said anything that can talk.”

“Do you think we are lenguas largas?”

“No.”

“Do you know what a lengua larga is?”

“Yes. One with a long tongue.”

“Do you know what we do with them?”

“Don't be tough with me,”I said.“You propositioned me. I didn't offer you anything.”

“Shut up, Pancho,”the one who had done the talking before said to the angry one.

“He said we would talk,”Pancho said.

“Listen,”I said.“I told you I didn't carry anything that can talk. Sacked liquor can't talk. Demijohns can't talk. There's other things that can't talk. Men can talk.”

“Can Chinamen talk?”Pancho said, pretty nasty.

“They can talk, but I can't understand them,”I told him.

“So you won't?”

“It's just like I told you last night. I can't.”

“But you won't talk?”Pancho said.

The one thing that he hadn't understood right had made him nasty. I guess it was disappointment, too. I didn't even answer him.

“You're not a lengua larga, are you?”he asked, still nasty.

“I don't think so.”

“What's that? A threat?”

“Listen,”I told him.“Don't be so tough so early in the morning. I'm sure you've cut plenty people's throats. I haven't even had my coffee yet.”

“So you're sure I've cut people's throats?”

“No,”I said.“And I don't give a damn. Can't you do business without getting angry?”

“I am angry now,”he said.“I would like to kill you.”

“Oh, hell,”I told him,“don't talk so much.”

“Come on, Pancho, the first one said. Then, to me,“I am very sorry. I wish you would take us.”

“I'm sorry, too. But I can't.”

The three of them started for the door, and I watched them go. They were good-looking young fellows, wore good clothes; none of them wore hats, and they looked like they had plenty of money. They talked plenty of money, anyway, and they spoke the kind of English Cubans with money speak.

Two of them looked like brothers and the other one, Pancho, was a little taller but the same sort of looking kid. You know, slim, good clothes, and shiny hair. I didn't figure he was as mean as he talked. I figured he was plenty nervous.

As they turned out of the door to the right, I saw a closed car come across the square toward them. The first thing a pane of glass went and the bullet smashed into the row of bottles on the show-case wall to the right. I heard the gun going and, bop, bop, bop, there were bottles smashing all along the wall.

I jumped behind the bar on the left side and could see looking over the edge. The car was stopped and there were two fellows crouched down by it. One had a Thompson gun and the other had a sawed-off automatic shotgun. The one with the Thompson gun was a nigger. The other had a chauffeur's white duster on.

One of the boys was spread out on the sidewalk, face down, just outside the big window that was smashed. The other two were behind one of the Tropical beer ice wagons that was stopped in front of the Cunard bar next door. One of the ice-wagon horses was down in the harness, kicking, and the other was plunging his head off.

One of the boys shot from the rear corner of the wagon and it ricocheted off the sidewalk. The nigger with the tommy gun got his face almost into the street and gave the back of the wagon a burst from underneath and sure enough one came down, falling toward the sidewalk with his head above the curb. He flopped there, putting his hands over his head, and the chauffeur shot at him with the shotgun while the nigger put in a fresh pan, but it was a long shot. You could see the buckshot marks all over the sidewalk like silver splatters.

The other fellow pulled the one who was hit back by the legs to behind the wagon, and I saw the nigger getting his face down on the paving to give them another burst. Then I saw old Pancho come around the corner of the wagon and step into the lee of the horse that was still up. He stepped clear of the horse, his face white as a dirty sheet, and got the chauffeur with the big Luger he had, holding it in both hands to keep it steady. He shot twice over the nigger's head, coming on, and once low.

He hit a tire on the car because I saw dust blowing in a spurt on the street as the air came out, and at ten feet the nigger shot him in the belly with his tommy gun, with what must have been the last shot in it because I saw him throw it down, and old Pancho sat down hard and went over forward. He was trying to come up, still holding onto the Luger, only he couldn't get his head up, when the nigger took the shotgun that was lying against the wheel of the car by the chauffeur and blew the side of his head off. Some nigger.

I took a quick one out of the first bottle I saw open and I couldn't tell you yet what it was. The whole thing made me feel pretty bad. I slipped along behind the bar and out through the kitchen in back and all the way out. I went clean around the outside of the square and never even looked over toward the crowd there was coming fast in front of the café and went in through the gate and out onto the dock and got on board.

The fellow who had her chartered was on board waiting. I told him what had happened.

“Where's Eddy?”this fellow Johnson that had her chartered asked me.

“I never saw him after the shooting started.”

“Do you suppose he was hit?”

“Hell no. I tell you the only shots that came in the café were into the show case. That was when the car was coming behind them. That was when they shot the first fellow right in front of the window. They came at an angle like this—”

“You seem awfully sure about it,”he said.

“I was watching,”I told him.

Then, as I looked up, I saw Eddy coming along the dock looking taller and sloppier than ever. He walked with his joints all slung wrong.

“There he is.”

Eddy looked pretty bad. He never looked too good early in the morning but he looked plenty bad now.

“Where were you?”I asked him.

“On the floor.”

“Did you see it?”Johnson asked him.

“Don't talk about it, Mr. Johnson,”Eddy said to him.“It makes me sick to even think about it.”

“You better have a drink,”Johnson told him. Then he said to me,“Well, are we going out?”

“That's up to you.”

“What sort of a day will it be?”

“Just about like yesterday. Maybe better.”

“Let's get out then.”

“All right, as soon as the bait comes.”

We'd had this bird out three weeks fishing the stream and I hadn't seen any of his money yet except one hundred dollars he gave me to pay the consul and clear and get some grub and put gas in her before we came across. I was furnishing all the tackle and he had her chartered at thirty-five dollars a day. He slept at a hotel and came aboard every morning. Eddy got me the charter so I had to carry him. I was giving him four dollars a day.

“I've got to put gas in her,”I told Johnson.

“All right.”

“I'll need some money for that.”

“How much?”

“It's twenty-eight cents a gallon. I ought to put in forty gallons anyway. That's eleven-twenty.”

He got out fifteen dollars.

“Do you want to put the rest on the beer and the ice?”I asked him.

“That's fine,”he said.“Just put it down against what I owe you.”

I was thinking three weeks was a long time to let him go but if he was good for it what difference was there? He should have paid every week anyway. But I've let them run a month and got the money. It was my fault but I was glad to see it run at first. It was only the last few days he made me nervous but I didn't want to say anything for fear of getting him plugged at me. If he was good for it, the longer he went the better.

“Have a bottle of beer?”he asked me, opening the box.

“No thanks.”

Just then this nigger we had getting bait comes down the dock and I told Eddy to get ready to cast her off.

The nigger came on board with the bait and we cast off and started out of the harbor, the nigger fixing on a couple of mackerel; passing the hook through their mouth, out the gills, slitting the side and then putting the hook through the other side and out, tying the mouth shut on the wire leader and tying the hook good so it couldn't slip and so the bait would troll smooth without spinning.

He's a real black nigger, smart and gloomy, with blue voodoo beads around his neck under his shirt and an old straw hat. What he liked to do on board was sleep and read the papers. But he put on a nice bait and he was fast.

“Can't you put on a bait like that, Captain?”Johnson asked me.

“Yes, sir.”

“Why do you carry a nigger to do it?”

“When the big fish run you'll see,”I told him.

“What's the idea?”

“The nigger can do it faster than I can.”

“Can't Eddy do it?”

“No, sir.”

“It seems an unnecessary expense to me.”He'd been giving the nigger a dollar a day and the nigger had been on a rumba every night. I could see him getting sleepy already.

“He's necessary,”I said.

By then we had passed the smacks with their fish cars anchored in front of Cabañas and the skiffs anchored fishing for mutton fish on the rock bottom by the Morro, and I headed her out where the gulf made a dark line. Eddy put the two big teasers out and the nigger had baits on three rods.

The stream was in nearly to soundings and as we came toward the edge you could see her running nearly purple with regular whirlpools. There was a light east breeze coming up and we put up plenty of flying fish, those big ones that look like the picture of Lindbergh crossing the Atlantic when they sail off.

Those big flying fish are the best sign there is. As far as you could see, there was that faded yellow gulfweed in small patches that means the main stream is well in and there were birds ahead working over a school of little tuna. You could see them jumping; just little ones weighing a couple of pounds apiece.

“Put out any time you want,”I told Johnson.

He put on his belt and his harness and put out the big rod with the Hardy reel with six hundred yards of thirty-six thread. I looked back and his bait was trolling nice, just bouncing along on the swell and the two teasers were diving and jumping. We were going just about the right speed and I headed her into the stream.

“Keep the rod butt in the socket on the chair,”I told him.“Then the rod won't be as heavy. Keep the drag off so you can slack to him when he hits. If one ever hits with the drag on he'll jerk you overboard.”

Every day I'd have to tell him the same thing but I didn't mind that. One out of fifty parties you get know how to fish. Then when they do know, half the time they're goofy and want to use line that isn't strong enough to hold anything big.

“How does the day look?”he asked me.

“It couldn't be better,”I told him. It was a pretty day all right.

I gave the nigger the wheel and told him to work along the edge of the stream to the eastward and went back to where Johnson was sitting watching his bait bouncing along.

“Want me to put out another rod?”I asked him.

“I don't think so,”he said.“I want to hook, fight, and land my fish myself.”

“Good,”I said.“Do you want Eddy to put it out and hand it to you if one strikes so you can hook him?”

“No,”he said.“I prefer to have only one rod out.”

“All right.”

The nigger was still taking her out and I looked and saw he had seen a patch of flying fish burst out ahead and up the stream a little. Looking back, I could see Havana looking fine in the sun and a ship just coming out of the harbor past the Morro.

“I think you're going to have a chance to fight one today, Mr. Johnson,”I told him.

“It's about time,”he said.“How long have we been out?”

“Three weeks today.”

“That's a long time to fish.”

“They're a funny fish,”I told him.“They aren't here until they come. But when they come there's plenty of them. And they've always come. If they don't come now they're never coming. The moon is right. There's a good stream and we're going to have a good breeze.”

“There were some small ones when we first came.”

“Yes,”I said.“Like I told you. The small ones thin out and stop before the big ones come.”

“You party-boat captains always have the same line. Either it's too early or too late or the wind isn't right or the moon is wrong. But you take the money just the same.”

“Well,”I told him,“the hell of it is that it usually is too early or too late and plenty of time the wind is wrong. Then when you get a day that's perfect you're ashore without a party.”

“But you think today's a good day?”

“Well,”I told him,“I've had action enough for me already today. But I'd like to bet you're going to have plenty.”

“I hope so,”he said.

We settled down to troll. Eddy went forward and lay down. I was standing up watching for a tail to show. Every once in a while the nigger would doze off and I was watching him, too. I bet he had some nights.

“Would you mind getting me a bottle of beer, Captain?”Johnson asked me.

“No, sir,”I said, and I dug down in the ice to get him a cold one.

“Won't you have one?”he asked.

“No, sir,”I said.“I'll wait till tonight.”

I opened the bottle and was reaching it toward him when I saw this big brown bugger with a spear on him longer than your arm burst head and shoulders out of the water and smash at that mackerel. He looked as big around as a saw log.

“Slack it to him!”I yelled.

“He hasn't got it,”Johnson said.

“Hold it, then.”

He'd come up from deep down and missed it. I knew he'd turn and come for it again.

“Get ready to turn it loose to him the minute he grabs it.”

Then I saw him coming from behind under water. You could see his fins out wide like purple wings and the purple stripes across the brown. He came on like a submarine and his top fin came out and you could see it slice the water. Then he came right behind the bait and his spear came out too, sort of wagging clean out of water.

“Let it go into his mouth,”I said. Johnson took his hand off the reel spool and it started to whiz and the old marlin turned and went down and I could see the whole length of him shine bright silver as he turned broadside and headed off fast toward shore.

“Put on a little drag,”I said.“Not much.”

He screwed down on the drag.

“Not too much,”I said. I could see the line slant up.“Shut her down hard and sock him,”I said.“You've got to sock him. He's going to jump anyway.”

Johnson screwed the drag down and came back on the rod.

“Sock him,”I told him.“Stick it into him. Hit him half a dozen times.”

He hit him pretty hard a couple of times more, and then the rod bent double and the reel commenced to screech and out he came, boom, in a long straight jump, shining silver in the sun and making a splash like throwing a horse off a cliff.

“Ease up on the drag,”I told him.

“He's gone,”said Johnson.

“The hell he is,”I told him.“Ease up on the drag quick.”

I could see the curve in the line and the next time he jumped he was astern and headed out to sea. Then he came out again and smashed the water white and I could see he was hooked in the side of his mouth. The stripes showed clear on him. He was a fine fish, bright silver now, barred with purple and as big around as a log.

“He's gone,”Johnson said. The line was slack.

“Reel on him,”I said.“He's hooked good. Put her ahead with all the machine!”I yelled to the nigger.

Then once, twice, he came out stiff as a post, the whole length of him jumping straight toward us, throwing the water high each time he landed. The line came taut and I saw he was headed inshore again and I could see he was turning.

“Now he'll make his run,”I said.“If he hooks up I'll chase him. Keep your drag light. There's plenty of line.”

The old marlin headed out to the nor'west like all the big ones go, and brother, did he hook up. He started jumping in those long lopes and every splash would be like a speed boat in a sea. We went after him, keeping him on the quarter once I'd made the turn. I had the wheel and I kept yelling to Johnson to keep his drag light and reel fast. All of a sudden I see his rod jerk and the line go slack. It wouldn't look slack unless you knew about it because of the pull of the belly of the line in the water. But I knew.

“He's gone,”I told him. The fish was still jumping and he went on jumping until he was out of sight. He was a fine fish all right.

“I can still feel him pull,”Johnson said.

“That's the weight of the line.”

“I can hardly reel it. Maybe he's dead.”

“Look at him,”I said.“He's still jumping.”You could see him out a half a mile, still throwing spouts of water.

I felt his drag. He had it screwed down tight. You couldn't pull out any line. It had to break.

“Didn't I tell you to keep your drag light?”

“But he kept taking out line.”

“So what?”

“So I tightened it.”

“Listen,”I told him.“If you don't give them line when they hook up like that they break it. There isn't any line will hold them. When they want it you've got to give it to them. You have to keep a light drag. The market fishermen can't hold them tight when they do that even with a harpoon line. What we have to do is use the boat to chase them so they don't take it all when they make their run. After they make their run they'll sound and you can tighten up the drag and get it back.”

“Then if it hadn't broken I would have caught him?”

“You'd have had a chance.”

“He couldn't have kept that up, could he?”

“He can do plenty of other things. It isn't until after he's made his run that the fight starts.”

“Well, let's catch one,”he said.

“You have to reel that line in first,”I told him.

We'd hooked that fish and lost him without waking Eddy up. Now old Eddy came back astern.

“What's the matter?”he said.

Eddy was a good man on a boat once, before he got to be a rummy, but he isn't any good now. I looked at him standing there tall and hollowcheeked with his mouth loose and that white stuff in the corners of his eyes and his hair all faded in the sun. I knew he woke up dead for a drink.

“You'd better drink a bottle of beer,”I told him. He took one out of the box and drank it.

“Well, Mr. Johnson,”he said,“I guess I better finish my nap. Much obliged for the beer, sir.”Some Eddy. The fish didn't make any difference to him.

Well, we hooked another one around noon and he jumped off. You could see the hook go thirty feet in the air when he threw it.

“What did I do wrong then?”Johnson asked.

“Nothing,”I said.“He just threw it.”

“Mr. Johnson,”said Eddy, who'd waked up to have another bottle of beer—“Mr. Johnson, you're just unlucky. Now maybe you're lucky with women. Mr. Johnson, what do you say we go out tonight?”Then he went back and lay down again.

About four o'clock when we're coming back close in to shore against the stream, it going like a mill race, us with the sun at our backs, the biggest black marlin I ever saw in my life hit Johnson's bait. We'd put out a feather squid and caught four of those little tuna and the nigger put one on his hook for bait. It trolled pretty heavy but it made a big splash in the wake.

Johnson took the harness off the reel so he could put the rod across his knees because his arms got tired holding it in position all the time. Because his hands got tired holding the spool of the reel against the drag of the big bait, he screwed the drag down when I wasn't looking. I never knew he had it down. I didn't like to see him hold the rod that way but I hated to be crabbing at him all the time. Besides, with the drag off, line would go out so there wasn't any danger. But it was a sloppy way to fish.

I was at the wheel and was working the edge of the stream opposite that old cement factory where it makes deep so close in to shore and where it makes a son of eddy where there is always lots of bait. Then I saw a splash like a depth bomb and the sword and eye and open lower jaw and huge purple-black head of a black marlin. The whole top fin was up out of water looking as high as a full-rigged ship, and the whole scythe tall was out as he smashed at that tuna. The bill was as big around as a baseball bat and slanted up, and as he grabbed the bait he sliced the ocean wide open. He was solid purple-black and he had an eye as big as a soup bowl. He was huge. I bet he'd go a thousand pounds.

I yelled to Johnson to let him have line but before I could say a word I saw Johnson rise up in the air off the chair as though he was being derricked, and him holding just for a second onto that rod and the rod bending like a bow, and then the butt caught him in the belly and the whole works went overboard.

He'd screwed the drag tight, and when the fish struck, it lifted Johnson right out of the chair and he couldn't hold it. He'd had the butt under one leg and the rod across his lap. If he'd had the harness on it would have taken him along, too.

I cut out the engine and went back to the stern. He was sitting there holding onto his belly where the rod butt had hit him.

“I guess that's enough for today,”I said.

“What was it?”he said to me.

“Black marlin,”I said.

“How did it happen?”

“You figure it out,”I said.“The reel cost two hundred and fifty dollars. It costs more now. The rod cost me forty-five. There was a little under six hundred yards of thirty-six thread.”

Just then Eddy slaps him on the back.“Mr. Johnson,”he says,“you're just unlucky. You know I never saw that happen before in my life.”

“Shut up, you rummy,”I said to him.

“I tell you, Mr. Johnson,”Eddy said,“that's the rarest occurrence I ever saw in my life.”

“What would I do if I was hooked to a fish like that?”Johnson said.

“That's what you wanted to fight all by yourself,”I told him. I was plenty sore.

“They're too big,”Johnson said.“Why, it would just be punishment.”

“Listen,”I said.“A fish like that would kill you.”

“They catch them.”

“People who know how to fish catch them. But don't think they don't take punishment.”

“I saw a picture of a girl who caught one.”

“Sure,”I said.“Still fishing. He swallowed the bait and they pulled his stomach out and he came to the top and died. I'm talking about trolling them when they're hooked in the mouth.”

“Well,”said Johnson,“they're too big. If it isn't enjoyable, why do it?”

“That's right, Mr. Johnson,”Eddy said.“If it isn't enjoyable, why do it? Listen, Mr. Johnson. You hit the nail on the head there. If it isn't enjoyable—why do it?”

I was still shaky from seeing that fish and feeling plenty sick about the tackle and I couldn't listen to them. I told the nigger to head her for the Morro. I didn't say anything to them and there they sat, Eddy in one of the chairs with a bottle of beer and Johnson with another.

“Captain,”he said to me after a while,“could you make me a highball?”

I made him one without saying anything, and then I made myself a real one. I was thinking to myself that this Johnson had fished fifteen days, finally he hooks into a fish a fisherman would give a year to tie into, he loses him, he loses my heavy tackle, he makes a fool of himself and he sits there perfectly content drinking with a rummy.

When we got in to the dock and the nigger was standing there waiting, I said,“What about tomorrow?”

“I don't think so,”Johnson said.“I'm about fed up with this kind of fishing.”

“You want to pay off the nigger?”

“How much do I owe him?”

“A dollar. You can give him a tip if you want.”

So Johnson gave the nigger a dollar and two Cuban twenty-cent pieces.

“What's this for?”the nigger asks me, showing the coins.

“A tip,”I told him in Spanish.“You're through. He gives you that.”

“Don't come tomorrow?”

“No.”

The nigger gets his ball of twine he used for tying baits and his dark glasses, puts on his straw hat and goes without saying good-bye. He was a nigger that never thought much of any of us.

“When do you want to settle up, Mr. Johnson?”I asked him.

“I'll go to the bank in the morning,”Johnson said.“We can settle up in the afternoon.”

“Do you know how many days there are?”

“Fifteen.”

“No. There's sixteen with today and a day each way makes eighteen. Then there's the rod and reel and the line from today.”

“The tackle's your risk.”

“No, sir. Not when you lose it that way.”

“I've paid every day for the rent of it. It's your risk.”

“No, sir,”I said.“If a fish broke it and it wasn't your fault, that would be something else. You lost that whole outfit by carelessness.”

“The fish pulled it out of my hands.”

“Because you had the drag on and didn't have the rod in the socket.”

“You have no business to charge for that.”

“If you hired a car and ran it off a cliff, don't you think you'd have to pay for it?”

“Not if I was in it,”Johnson said.

“That's pretty good, Mr. Johnson,”Eddy said.“You see it, don't you, Cap? If he was in it he'd be killed. So he wouldn't have to pay. That's a good one.”

I didn't pay any attention to the rummy.“You owe two hundred and ninety five dollars for that rod and reel and line,”I told Johnson.

“Well, it's not right,”he said.“But if that's the way you feel about it why not split the difference?”

“I can't replace it for under three hundred and sixty. I'm not charging you for the line. A fish like that could get all your line and it not be your fault. If there was anyone here but a rummy they'd tell you how square I'm being with you. I know it seems like a lot of money but it was a lot of money when I bought the tackle, too. You can't fish like that without the best tackle you can buy.”

“Mr. Johnson, he says I'm a rummy. Maybe I am. But I tell you he's right. He's right and he's reasonable,”Eddy told him.

“I don't want to make any difficulties,”Johnson said finally.“I'll pay for it, even though I don't see it. That's eighteen days at thirty-five dollars and two ninety-five extra.”

“You gave me a hundred,”I told him.“I'll give you a list of what I spent and I'll deduct what grub there is left. What you bought for provisions going over and back.”

“That's reasonable,”Johnson said.

“Listen, Mr. Johnson,”Eddy said.“If you knew the way they usually charge a stranger you'd know it was more than reasonable. Do you know what it is? It's exceptional. The cap is treating you like you were his own mother.”

“I'll go to the bank tomorrow and come down in the afternoon. Then I'll get the boat day after tomorrow.”

“You can go back with us and save the boat fare.”

“No,”he said.“I'll save time with the boat.”

“Well,”I said.“What about a drink?”

“Fine,”said Johnson.“No hard feelings now, are there?”

“No, sir,”I told him. So the three of us sat there in the stern and drank a highball together.

The next day I worked around her all morning, changing the oil in her base and one thing and another. At noon I went uptown and ate at a Chink place where you get a good meal for forty cents, and then I bought some things to take home to my wife and our three girls. You know, perfume, a couple of fans and two of those high combs. When I finished I stopped in at Donovan's and had a beer and talked with the old man and then walked back to the San Francisco docks, stopping in at three or four places for a beer on the way. I bought Frankie a couple at the Cunard bar and I came on board feeling pretty good. When I came on board I had just forty cents left. Frankie came on board with me, and while we sat and waited for Johnson I drank a couple of cold ones out of the ice box with Frankie.

Eddy hadn't shown up all night or all day but I knew he would be around sooner or later, as soon as his credit ran out. Donovan told me he'd been in there the night before a little while with Johnson, and Eddy had been setting them up on credit. We waited and I began to wonder about Johnson not showing up. I'd left word at the dock for them to tell him to go on board and wait for me but they said he hadn't come. Still, I figured he had been out late and probably didn't get up till around noon. The banks were open until three-thirty. We saw the plane go out, and about five-thirty I was all over feeling good and was getting plenty worried.

At six o'clock I sent Frankie up to the hotel to see if Johnson was there. I still thought he might be out on a time or he might be there at the hotel feeling too bad to get up. I kept waiting and waiting until it was late. But I was getting plenty worried because he owed me eight hundred and twenty-five dollars.

Frankie was gone about a little over half an hour. When I saw him coming he was walking fast and shaking his head.

“He went on the plane,”he said.

All right. There it was. The consulate was closed. I had forty cents, and anyhow the plane was in Miami by now. I couldn't even send a wire. Some Mr. Johnson, all right. It was my fault. I should have known better.

“Well,”I said to Frankie,“we might as well have a cold one. Mr. Johnson bought them.”There were three bottles of Tropical left.

Frankie felt as bad as I did. I don't know how he could but he seemed to. He just kept slapping me on the back and shaking his head.

So there it was. I was broke. I'd lost five hundred and thirty dollars of the charter, and tackle I couldn't replace for three hundred and fifty more. How some of that gang that hangs around the dock would be pleased at that, I thought. It certainly would make some conchs happy. And the day before I turned down three thousand dollars to land three aliens on the Keys. Anywhere, just to get them out of the country.

All right, what was I going to do now? I couldn't bring in a load because you have to have money to buy the booze and besides there's no money in it any more. The town is flooded with it and there's nobody to buy it. But I was damned if I was going home broke and starve a summer in that town. Besides I've got a family. The clearance was paid when we came in. You usually pay the broker in advance and he enters you and clears you. Hell, I didn't even have enough money to put in gas. It was a hell of a note, all right. Some Mr. Johnson.

“I've got to carry something, Frankie,”I said.“I've got to make some money.”

“I'll see,”said Frankie. He hangs around the water front and does odd jobs and is pretty deaf and drinks too much every night. But you never saw a fellow more loyal nor with a better heart. I've known him since I first started to run over there. He used to help me load plenty of times. Then when I got handling stuff and went party-boating and broke out this sword fishing in Cuba I used to see him a lot around the dock and around the café. He seems dumb and he usually smiles instead of talking but that's because he's deaf.

“You carry anything?”Frankie asked.

“Sure,”I said.“I can't choose now.”

“Anything?”

“Sure.”

“I'll see,”Frankie said.“Where will you be?”

“I'll be at the Perla,”I told him.“I have to eat.”

You can get a good meal at the Perla for twenty-five cents. Everything on the menu is a dime except soup, and that is a nickel. I walked as far as there with Frankie, and I went in and he went on. Before he went he shook me by the hand and clapped me on the back again.

“Don't worry,”he said.“Me Frankie much politics. Much business. Much drinking. No money. But big friend. Don't worry.”

“So long, Frankie,”I said.“Don't you worry either, boy.”

I went in the Perla and sat down at a table. They had a new pane of glass in the window that had been shot up and the show case was all fixed up. There were a lot of gallegos drinking at the bar and some eating. One table was playing dominoes already. I had black bean soup and a beef stew with boiled potatoes for fifteen cents. A bottle of Hatuey beer brought it up to a quarter. When I spoke to the waiter about the shooting he wouldn't say anything. They were all plenty scared.

I finished the meal and sat back and smoked a cigarette and worried my head off. Then I saw Frankie coming in the door with someone behind him. Yellow stuff, I thought to myself. So it's yellow stuff.

“This is Mr. Sing,”Frankie said, and he smiled. He'd been pretty fast all right and he knew it.

“How do you do?”said Mr. Sing.

Mr. Sing was about the smoothest-looking thing I'd ever seen. He was a Chink all right, but he talked like an Englishman and he was dressed in a white suit with a silk shirt and black tie and one of those hundred-and-twenty-five-dollar Panama hats.

“You will have some coffee?”he asked me.

“If you do.”

“Thank you,”said Mr. Sing.“We are quite alone here?”

“Except for everybody in the café,”I told him.

“That is all right,”Mr. Sing said.“You have a boat?”

“Thirty-eight feet,”I said.“Hundred horse Kermath.”

“Ah,”said Mr. Sing.“I had imagined it was a lugger.”

“It can carry two hundred and sixty-five cases without being loaded.”

“Would you care to charter it to me?”

“On what terms?”

“You need not go. I will provide a captain and a crew.”

“No,”I said.“I go on her wherever she goes.”

“I see,”said Mr. Sing.“Would you mind leaving us?”he said to Frankie. Frankie looked as interested as ever and smiled at him.

“He's deaf,”I said.“He doesn't understand much English.”

“I see,”said Mr. Sing.“You speak Spanish. Tell him to rejoin us later.”

I motioned to Frankie with my thumb. He got up and went over to the bar.

“You don't speak Spanish?”I said.

“Oh, yes,”said Mr. Sing.“Now what are the circumstances that would—that have made you consider...”

“I'm broke.”

“I see,”said Mr. Sing.“Does the boat owe any money? Can she be libeled?”

“No.”

“Quite so,”Mr. Sing said.“How many of my unfortunate compatriots could your boat accommodate?”

“You mean carry?”

“That's it.”

“How far?”

“A day's voyage.”

“I don't know,”I said.“She can take a dozen if they didn't have any baggage.”

“They would not have baggage.”

“Where do you want to carry them?”

“I'd leave that to you,”Mr. Sing said.

“You mean where to land them?”

“You would embark them for the Tortugas where a schooner would pick them up.”

“Listen,”I said.“There's a lighthouse at the Tortugas on Loggerhead Key with a radio that works both ways.”

“Quite,”said Mr. Sing.“It would certainly be very silly to land them there.”

“Then what?”

“I said you would embark them for there. That is what their passage calls for.”

“Yes,”I said.

“You would land them wherever your best judgment dictated.”

“Will the schooner come to Tortugas to get them?”

“Of course not,”said Mr. Sing.“How silly.”

“How much are they worth a head?”

“Fifty dollars,”said Mr. Sing.

“No.”

“How would seventy-five do?”

“What do you get a head?”

“Oh, that's quite beside the point. You see, there are a great many facets, or shall we say angles, to my issuing the tickets. It doesn't stop there.”

“Yes,”I said.“And what I'm supposed to do doesn't have to be paid for, either. Eh?”

“I see your point absolutely,”said Mr. Sing.“Should we say a hundred dollars apiece?”

“Listen,”I said.“Do you know how long I would go to jail if they pick me up on this?”

“Ten years,”said Mr. Sing.“Ten years at least. But there is no reason to go to jail, my dear Captain. You run only one risk—when you load your passengers. Everything else is left to your discretion.”

“And if they come back on your hands?”

“That's quite simple. I would accuse you to them of having betrayed me. I will make a partial refund and ship them out again. They realize, of course, that it is a difficult voyage.”

“What about me?”

“I suppose I should send some word to the consulate.”

“I see.”

“Twelve hundred dollars, Captain, is not to be despised at present.”

“When would I get the money?”

“Two hundred when you agree and a thousand when you load.”

“If I would go off with the two hundred?”

“I could do nothing, of course,”he smiled.“But I know you wouldn't do such a thing, Captain.”

“Have you got the two hundred with you?”

“Of course.”

“Put it under the plate.”He did.“All right,”I said.“I'll clear in the morning and pull out at dark. Now, where do we load?”

“How would Bacuranao be?”

“All right. Have you got it fixed?”

“Of course.”

“Now, about the loading,”I said.“You show two lights, one above the other, at the point. I'll come in when I see them. You come out in a boat and load from the boat. You come yourself and you bring the money. I won't take one on board until I have it.”

“No,”he said;“one-half when you start to load and the other when you are finished.”

“All right,”I said.“That's reasonable.”

“So everything is understood?”

“I guess so,”I said.“There's no baggage and no arms. No guns, knives, or razors; nothing. I have to know about that.”

“Captain,”said Mr. Sing,“have you no trust in me? Don't you see our interests are identical?”

“You'll make sure?”

“Please do not embarrass me,”he said.“Do you not see how our interests coincide?”

“All right,”I told him.“What time will you be there?”

“Before midnight.”

“All right,”I said.“I guess that's all.”

“How do you want the money?”

“In hundreds is all right.”

He stood up and I watched him go out. Frankie smiled at him as he went. He was a smooth-looking Chink all right. Some Chink.

Frankie came over to the table.“Well?”he said.

“Where did you know Mr. Sing?”

“He ships Chinamen,”Frankie said.“Big business.”

“How long you know him?”

“He's here about two years,”Frankie said.“Another one ship them before him. Somebody kill him.”

“Somebody will kill Mr. Sing, too.”

“Sure,”said Frankie.“Why not? Plenty big business.”

“Some business,”I said.

“Big business,”said Frankie.“Ship Chinamen never come back. Other Chinamen write letters say everything fine.”

“Wonderful,”I said.

“This kind of Chinamen no understand write. Chinamen can write all rich. Eat nothing. Live on rice. Hundred thousand Chinamen here. Only three Chinese women.”

“Why?”

“Government no let.”

“Hell of a situation,”I said.

“You do business him?”

“Maybe.”

“Good business,”said Frankie.“Better than politics. Much money. Plenty big business.”

“Have a bottle of beer,”I told him.

“You not worry any more?”

“Hell no,”I said.“Plenty big business. Much obliged.”

“Good,”said Frankie and patted me on the back.“Make me happier than nothing. All I want is you happy. Chinamen good business, eh?”

“Wonderful.”

“Make me happy,”said Frankie. I saw he was about ready to cry because he was so pleased everything was all right, so I patted him on the back. Some Frankie.

First thing in the morning I got hold of the broker and told him to clear us. He wanted the crew list and I told him nobody.

“You're going to cross alone, Captain?”

“That's right.”

“What's become of your mate?”

“He's on a drunk,”I told him.

“It's very dangerous to go alone.”

“It's only ninety miles,”I said.“Do you think having a rummy on board makes any difference?”

I ran her over to the Standard Oil dock across the harbor and filled up both the tanks. She held nearly two hundred gallons when I had her full. I hated to buy it at twenty-eight cents a gallon but I didn't know where we might go.

Ever since I'd seen the Chink and taken the money I'd been worrying about the business. I don't think I slept all night. I brought her back to the San Francisco dock, and there was Eddy waiting on the dock for me.

“Hello, Harry,”he said to me and waved. I threw him the stern line and he made her fast, and then came aboard; longer, blearier, drunker than ever. I didn't say anything to him.

“What do you think about that fellow Johnson going off like that, Harry?”he asked me.“What do you know about that?”

“Get out of here,”I told him.“You're poison to me.”

“Brother, don't I feel as bad about it as you do?”

“Get off of her,”I told him.

He just settled back in the chair and stretched his legs out.“I hear we're going across today,”he said.“Well, I guess there isn't any use to stay around.”

“You're not going.”

“What's the matter, Harry? There's no sense to get plugged with me.”

“No? Get off her.”

“Oh, take it easy.”

I hit him in the face and he stood up and then climbed up onto the dock.

“I wouldn't do a thing like that to you, Harry,”he said.

“I'm not going to carry you,”I told him.“That's all.”

“Well, what did you have to hit me for?”

“So you'd believe it.”

“What do you want me to do? Stay here and starve?”

“Starve, hell,”I said.“You can get work on the ferry. You can work your way back.”

“You aren't treating me square,”he said.

“Who did you treat square, you rummy?”I told him.“You'd double-cross your own mother.”

That was true, too. But I felt bad about hitting him. You know how you feel when you hit a drunk. But I wouldn't carry him the way things were now, not even if I wanted to.

He started to walk off down the dock looking longer than a day without breakfast. Then he turned and came back.

“How's to let me take a couple of dollars, Harry?”

I gave him a five-dollar bill of the Chink's.

“I always knew you were my pal. Harry, why don't you carry me?”

“You're bad luck.”

“You're just plugged,”he said.“Never mind, old pal. You'll be glad to see me yet.”

Now he had money he went off a good deal faster but I tell you it was poison to see him walk, even. He walked just like his joints were backwards.

I went up to the Perla and met the broker and he gave me the papers and I bought him a drink. Then I had lunch and Frankie came in.

“Fellow gave me this for you,”he said and handed me a rolled-up sort of tube wrapped in paper and tied with a piece of red string. It looked like a photograph when I unwrapped it and I unrolled it thinking it was maybe a picture someone around the dock had taken of the boat.

All right. It was a close-up picture of the head and chest of a dead nigger with his throat cut clear across from ear to ear and then stitched up neat and a card on his chest saying in Spanish:“This is what we do to lenguas largas.”

“Who gave it to you?”I asked Frankie.

He pointed out a Spanish boy that works around the docks who is just about gone with the con. This kid was standing at the lunch counter.

“Ask him to come over.”

The kid came over. He said two young fellows gave it to him about eleven o'clock. They asked him if he knew me and he said yes. Then he gave it to Frankie for me. They gave him a dollar to see that I got it. They were well dressed, he said.

“Politics,”Frankie said.

“Oh, yes,”I said.

“They think you told the police you were meeting those boys here that morning.”

“Oh, yes.”

“Bad politics,”Frankie said.“Good thing you go.”

“Did they leave any message?”I asked the Spanish boy.

“No,”he said.“Just to give you that.”

“I'm going to have to leave now,”I said to Frankie.

“Bad politics,”Frankie said.“Very bad politics.”

I had all the papers in a bunch that the broker had given me and I paid the bill and walked out of that café and across the square and through the gate and I was plenty glad to come through the warehouse and get out on the dock. Those kids had me spooked all right. They were just dumb enough to think I'd tipped somebody off about that other bunch. Those kids were like Pancho. When they were scared they got excited, and when they got excited they wanted to kill somebody.

I got on board and warmed up the engine. Frankie stood on the dock watching. He was smiling that funny deaf smile. I went back to him.

“Listen,”I said.“Don't you get in any trouble about this.”

He couldn't hear me. I had to yell it at him.

“Me good politics,”Frankie said. He cast her off.

I waved to Frankie, who'd thrown the bowline on board, and I headed her out of the slip and dropped down the channel with her. A British freighter was going out and I ran along beside her and passed her. I went out the harbor and past the Morro and put her on the course for Key West; due north. I left the wheel and went forward and coiled up the bowline and then came back and held her on her course, spreading Havana out astern and then dropping it off behind us as we brought the mountains up.

I dropped the Morro out of sight after a while and then the National Hotel and finally I could just see the dome of the Capitol. There wasn't much current compared to the last day we had fished and there was only a light breeze. I saw a couple of smacks headed in toward Havana and they were coming from the westward so I knew the current was light.

I cut the switch and killed the motor. There wasn't any sense in wasting gas. I'd let her drift. When it got dark I could always pick up the light of the Morro or, if she drifted up too far, the lights of Cojimar, and steer in and run along to Bacuranao. I figured the way the current looked she would drift the twelve miles up to Bacuranao by dark and I'd see the lights of Baracóa.

Well, I killed the engine and climbed up forward to have a look around. All there was to see was the two smacks off to the westward headed in, and way back the dome of the Capitol standing up white out of the edge of the sea. There was some gulfweed on the stream and a few birds working, but not many. I sat up there awhile on top of the house and watched, but the only fish I saw were those little brown ones that rise around the gulfweed. Brother, don't let anybody tell you there isn't plenty of water between Havana and Key West. I was just on the edge of it.

After a while I went down into the cockpit again and there was Eddy!

“What's the matter? What's the matter with the engine?”

“She broke down.”

“Why haven't you got the hatch up?”

“Oh, hell!”I said.

Do you know what he'd done? He'd come back again and slipped the forward hatch and gone down into the cabin and gone to sleep. He had two quarts with him. He'd gone into the first bodega he'd seen and bought it and come aboard. When I started out he woke up and went back to sleep again. When I stopped her out in the gulf and she began to roll a little with the swell it woke him up.

“I knew you'd carry me, Harry,”he said.

“Carry you to hell,”I said.“You aren't even on the crew list. I've got a good mind to make you jump overboard now.”

“You're an old joker, Harry,”he said.“Us conchs ought to stick together when we're in trouble.”

“You,”I said,“with your mouth. Who's going to trust your mouth when you're hot?”

“I'm a good man, Harry. You put me to the test and see what a good man I am.”

“Get me the two quarts,”I told him. I was thinking of something else.

He brought them out and I took a drink from the open one and put them forward by the wheel. He stood there and I looked at him. I was sorry for him and for what I knew I'd have to do. Hell, I knew him when he was a good man.

“What's the matter with her, Harry?”

“She's all right.”

“What's the matter, then? What are you looking at me like that for?”

“Brother,”I told him, and I was sorry for him,“you're in plenty of trouble.”

“What do you mean, Harry?”

“I don't know yet,”I said.“I haven't got it all figured out yet.”

We sat there awhile and I didn't feel like talking to him any more. Once I knew it, it was hard to talk to him. Then I went below and got out the pump-gun and the Winchester thirty-thirty that I always had below in the cabin and hung them up in their cases from the top of the house where we hung the rods usually, right over the wheel where I could reach them. I keep them in those full-length clipped sheep's-wool cases soaked in oil. That's the only way you can keep them from rusting on a boat.

I loosened up the pump and worked her a few times, and then filled her up and pumped one into the barrel. I put a shell in the chamber of the Winchester and filled up the magazine. I got out the Smith and Wesson thirty-eight special I had when I was on the police force up in Miami from under the mattress and cleaned and oiled it and filled it up and put it on my belt.

“What's the matter?”Eddy said.“What the hell's the matter?”

“Nothing,”I told him.

“What's all the damn guns for?”

“I always carry them on board,”I said.“To shoot birds that bother the baits or to shoot sharks cruising along the keys.”

“What's the matter, damn it?”said Eddy.“What's the matter?”

“Nothing,”I told him. I sat there with the old thirty-eight flopping against my leg when she rolled, and I looked at him. I thought, there's no sense to do it now. I'm going to need him now.

“We're going to do a little job,”I said.“In at Bacuranao. I'll tell you what to do when it's time.”

I didn't want to tell him too far ahead because he would get to worrying and get so spooked he wouldn't be any use.

“You couldn't have anybody better than me, Harry,”he said.“I'm the man for you. I'm with you on anything.”

I looked at him, tall and bleary and shaky, and I didn't say anything.

“Listen, Harry. Would you give me just one?”he asked me.“I don't want to get the shakes.”

I gave him one and we sat and waited for it to get dark. It was a fine sunset and there was a nice light breeze, and when the sun got pretty well down I started the engine and headed her in slow toward land.

We lay offshore about a mile in the dark. The current had freshened up with the sun down and I noticed it running in. I could see the Morro light way down to the westward and the glow of Havana, and the lights opposite us were Rincón and Baracóa. I headed her up against the current until I was past Bacuranao and nearly to Cojimar. Then I let her drift down. It was plenty dark but I could tell good where we were. I had all the lights out.

“What's it going to be, Harry?”Eddy asked me. He was beginning to be spooked again.

“What do you think?”

“I don't know,”he said.“You've got me worried.”He was pretty close to the shakes and when he came near me he had a breath like a buzzard.

“What time is it?”

“I'll go down and see,”he said. He came back up and said it was half past nine.

“Are you hungry?”I asked him.

“No,”he said.“You know I couldn't eat, Harry.”

“All right,”I told him.“You can have one.”

After he had it I asked him how he felt. He said he felt fine.

“I'm going to give you a couple more in a little while,”I told him.“I know you haven't got any guts unless you've got rum and there isn't much on board. So you'd better go easy.”

“Tell me what's up,”said Eddy.

“Listen,”I said, talking to him in the dark.“We're going in to Bacuranao and pick up twelve Chinks. You take the wheel when I tell you to and do what I tell you to. We'll take the twelve Chinks on board and we'll lock them below forward. Go on forward now and fasten the hatch from the outside.”

He went up and I saw him shadowed against the dark. He came back and he said,“Harry, can I have one of those now?”

“No,”I said.“I want you rum-brave. I don't want you useless.”

“I'm a good man, Harry. You'll see.”

“You're a rummy,”I said.“Listen. One Chink is going to bring those twelve out. He's going to give me some money at the start. When they're all on board he's going to give me some more money. When you see him start to hand me money the second time you put her ahead and hook her up and head her out to sea. Don't you pay any attention to what happens. You keep her going out no matter what happens. Do you understand?”

“Yes.”

“If any Chink starts bursting out of the cabin or coming through the hatch, once we're out and under way, you take that pump-gun and blow them back as fast as they come out. Do you know how to use the pump-gun?”

“No. But you can show me.”

“You'd never remember. Do you know how to use the Winchester?”

“Just pump the lever and shoot it.”

“That's right,”I said.“Only don't shoot any holes in the hull.”

“You'd better give me that other drink,”Eddy said.

“All right. I'll give you a little one.”

I gave him a real one. I knew they wouldn't make him drunk now; not pouring into all that fear. But each one would work for a little while. After he drank this Eddy said, just as though he was happy,“So we're going to run Chinks. Well, by God, I always said I'd run Chinamen if I was ever broke.”

“But you never got broke before, eh?”I said to him. He was funny all right.

I gave him three more drinks to keep him brave before it was half past ten. It was funny watching him and it kept me from thinking about it myself. I hadn't figured on all this wait. I'd planned to leave after dark, run out, just out of the glare, and coast along to Cojimar.

At a little before eleven I saw the two lights show on the point. I waited a little while and then I took her in slow. Bacuranao is a cove where there used to be a big dock for loading sand. There is a little river that comes in when the rains open the bar across the mouth. The northers, in the winter, pile the sand up and close it.

They used to go in with schooners and load guavas from the river and there used to be a town. But the hurricane took it and it is all gone now except one house that some gallegos built out of the shacks the hurricane blew down and that they use for a clubhouse on Sundays when they come out to swim and picnic from Havana. There is one other house where the delegate lives but it is back from the beach.

Each little place like that all down the coast has a government delegate, but I figured the Chink must use his own boat and have him fixed. As we came in I could smell the sea grape and that sweet smell from the brush you get off the land.

“Get up forward,”I said to Eddy.

“You can't hit anything on that side,”he said.“The reef's on the other side as you go in.”You see, he'd been a good man once.

“Watch her,”I said, and I took her in to where I knew they could see us. With no surf they could hear the engine. I didn't want to wait around, not knowing whether they saw us or not, so I flashed the running lights on once, just the green and red, and turned them off. Then I turned her and headed her out and let her lay there, just outside, with the engine just ticking. There was quite a little swell that close in.

“Come on back here,”I said to Eddy and I gave him a real drink.

“Do you cock it first with your thumb?”he whispered to me. He was sitting at the wheel now, and I had reached up and had both the cases open and the butts pulled out about six inches.

“That's right.”

“Oh boy,”he said.

It certainly was wonderful what a drink would do to him and how quick.

We lay there and I could see a light from the delegate's house back through the bush. I saw the two lights on the point go down, and one of them moving off around the point. They must have blown the other one out.

Then, in a little while, coming out of the cove, I see a boat come toward us with a man sculling. I could tell by the way he swung back and forth. I knew he had a big oar. I was pretty pleased. If they were sculling that meant one man.

They came alongside.

“Good evening, Captain,”said Mr. Sing.

“Come astern and put her broadside,”I said to him.

He said something to the man who was sculling but he couldn't scull her backwards, so I took hold of the gunwale and passed her astern. There were eight men in the boat. The six Chinks, Mr. Sing, and the kid sculling. While I was pulling her astern I was waiting for something to hit me on top of the head but nothing did. I straightened up and let Mr. Sing hold onto the stern.

“Let's see what it looks like,”I said.

He handed it to me and I took it up to where Eddy was at the wheel and put on the binnacle light. I looked at it carefully. It looked all right to me and I turned off the light. Eddy was trembling.

“Pour one yourself,”I said. I saw him reach for the bottle and tip it up.

I went back to the stern.

“All right,”I said.“Let six come on board.”

Mr. Sing and the Cuban that sculled were having a job holding their boat from knocking in what little swell there was. I heard Mr. Sing say something in Chink and all the Chinks in the boat started to climb onto the stern.

“One at a time,”I said.

He said something again, and then one after another six Chinks came over the stern. They were all lengths and sizes.

“Show them forward,”I said to Eddy.

“Right this way, gentlemen,”said Eddy. By God, I knew he had taken a big one.

“Lock the cabin,”I said, when they were all in.

“Yes, sir,”said Eddy.

“I will return with the others,”said Mr. Sing.

“O.K.,”I told him.

I pushed them clear and the boy with him started sculling off.

“Listen,”I said to Eddy.“You lay off that bottle. You're brave enough now.”

“O.K., chief,”said Eddy.

“What's the matter with you?”

“This is what I like to do,”said Eddy.“You say you just pull it backward with your thumb?”

“You lousy rummy,”I told him.“Give me a drink out of that.”

“All gone,”said Eddy.“Sorry, chief.”

“Listen. What you have to do now is watch her when he hands me the money and put her ahead.”

“O.K., chief,”said Eddy.

I reached up and took the other bottle and got the corkscrew and drew the cork. I took a good drink and went back to the stem, putting the cork in tight and laying the bottle behind two wicker jugs full of water.

“Here comes Mr. Sing,”I said to Eddy.

“Yes, sir,”said Eddy.

The boat came out sculling toward us.

He brought her astern and I let them do the holding in. Mr. Sing had hold of the roller we had across the stern to slide a big fish on board.

“Let them come aboard,”I said,“one at a time.”

Six more assorted Chinks came on board over the stern.

“Open up and show them forward,”I told Eddy.

“Yes, sir,”said Eddy.

“Lock the cabin.”

“Yes, sir.”

I saw he was at the wheel.

“All right, Mr. Sing,”I said.“Let's see the rest of it.”

He put his hand in his pocket and reached the money out toward me. I reached for it and grabbed his wrist with the money in his hand, and as he came forward on the stern I grabbed his throat with the other hand. I felt her start and then churn ahead as she hooked up and I was plenty busy with Mr. Sing but I could see the Cuban standing in the stem of the boat holding the sculling oar through all the flopping and bouncing Mr. Sing was doing. He was flopping and bouncing worse than any dolphin on a gaff.

I got his arm around behind him and came up on it but I brought it too far because I felt it go. When it went he made a funny little noise and came forward, me holding him throat and all, and bit me on the shoulder. But when I felt the arm go I dropped it. It wasn't any good to him any more and I took him by the throat with both hands, and brother, that Mr. Sing would flop just like a fish, true, his loose arm flailing, but I got him forward onto his knees and had both thumbs well in behind his talk box and I bent the whole thing back until she cracked. Don't think you can't hear it crack, either.

I held him quiet just a second, and then I laid him down across the stem. He lay there, face up, quiet, in his good clothes, with his feet in the cockpit, and I left him.

I picked up the money off the cockpit floor and took it up and put it on the binnacle and counted it. Then I took the wheel and told Eddy to look under the stem for some pieces of iron that I used for anchoring whenever we fished bottom fishing on patches or rocky bottom where you wouldn't want to risk an anchor.

“I can't find anything,”he said. He was scared being down there by Mr. Sing.

“Take the wheel,”I said.“Keep her out.”

There was a certain amount of moving around going on below but I wasn't spooked about them.

I found a couple of pieces of what I wanted—iron from the old coaling dock at Tortugas—and I took some snapper line and made a couple of good big pieces fast to Mr. Sing's ankles. Then when we were about two miles offshore I slid him over. He slid over smooth off the roller. I never even looked in his pockets. I didn't feel like fooling with him.

He'd bled a little on the stern from his nose and his mouth, and I dipped a bucket of water that nearly pulled me overboard the way we were going, and cleaned her off good with a scrub brush from under the stern.

“Slow her down,”I said to Eddy.

“What if he floats up?”Eddy said.

“I dropped him in about seven hundred fathoms,”I said.“He's going down all that way. That's a long way, brother. He won't float till the gas brings him up and all the time he's going with the current and baiting up fish. Hell,”I said,“you don't have to worry about Mr. Sing.”

“What did you have against him?”Eddy asked me.

“Nothing,”I said.“He was the easiest man to do business with I ever met. I thought there must be something wrong all the time.”

“What did you kill him for?”

“To keep from killing twelve other Chinks,”I told him.

“Harry,”he said,“you've got to give me one because I can feel them coming on. It made me sick to see his head all loose like that.”

So I gave him one.

“What about the Chinks?”Eddy said.

“I want to get them out as quick as I can,”I told him.“Before they smell up the cabin.”

“Where are you going to put them?”

“We'll run them right in to the long beach,”I told him.

“Take her in now?”

“Sure,”I said.“Take her in slow.”

We came in slow over the reef and to where I could see the beach shine. There is plenty of water over the reef and inside it's all sandy bottom and slopes right in to shore.

“Get up forward and give me the depth.”

He kept sounding with a grains pole, motioning me on with the pole. He came back and motioned me to stop. I came astern on her.

“You've got about five feet.”

“We've got to anchor,”I said.“If anything happens so we haven't time to get her up, we can cut loose or break her off.”

Eddy paid out rope and when finally she didn't drag he made her fast. She swung stern in.

“It's sandy bottom, you know,”he said.

“How much water have we got at the stern?”

“Not over five feet.”

“You take the rifle,”I said.“And be careful,”

“Let me have one,”he said. He was plenty nervous.

I gave him one and took down the pump-gun. I unlocked the cabin door, opened it, and said:“Come on out.”

Nothing happened.

Then one Chink put his head out and saw Eddy standing there with a rifle and ducked back.

“Come on out. Nobody's going to hurt you,”I said.

Nothing doing. Only lots of talk in Chink.

“Come on out, you!”Eddy said. My God, I knew he'd had the bottle.

“Put that bottle away,”I said to him,“or I'll blow you out of the boat.”

“Come on out,”I said to them,“or I'll shoot in at you.”

I saw one of them looking at the corner of the door and he saw the beach evidently because he begins to chatter.

“Come on,”I said,“or I'll shoot.”

Out they came.

Now I tell you it would take a hell of a mean man to butcher a bunch of Chinks like that and I'll bet there would be plenty of trouble, too, let alone mess.

They came out and they were scared and they didn't have any guns but there were twelve of them. I walked backwards down to the stem holding the pump gun.“Get overboard,”I said.“It's not over your heads.”

Nobody moved.

“Over you go.”

Nobody moved.

“You yellow rat-eating aliens,”Eddy said,“get overboard.”

“Shut your drunken mouth,”I told him.

“No swim,”one Chink said.

“No need swim,”I said.“No deep.”

“Come on, get overboard,”Eddy said.

“Come astern here,”I said.“Take your gun in one hand and your grains pole in the other and show them how deep it is.”

He showed them.

“No need swim?”the one asked me.

“No.”

“True?”

“Yes.”

“Where we?”

“Cuba.”

“You damn crook,”he said and went over the side, hanging on and then letting go. His head went under but he came up and his chin was out of water.“Damn crook,”he said.“Damn crook.”

He was mad and he was plenty brave. He said something in Chink and the others started going into the water off the stern.

“All right,”I said to Eddy.“Get the anchor up.”

As we headed her out, the moon started to come up and you could see the Chinks with just their heads out of water walking ashore, and the shine of the beach and the brush behind.

We got out past the reef and I looked back once and saw the beach and the mountains starting to show up; then I put her on her course for Key West.

“Now you can take a sleep,”I said to Eddy.“No, wait, go below and open up all the ports to get the stink out and bring me the iodine.”

“What's the matter?”he said when he brought it.

“I cut my finger.”

“Do you want me to steer?”

“Get a sleep,”I said.“I'll wake you up.”

He lay down on the built-in bunk in the cockpit, over the gas tank, and in a little while he was asleep.

I held the wheel with my knee and opened up my shirt and saw where Mr. Sing bit me. It was quite a bite and I put iodine on it, and then I sat there steering and wondering whether a bite from a Chinaman was poisonous and listened to her running nice and smooth and the water washing along her and I figured, Hell no, that bite wasn't poisonous. A man like that Mr. Sing probably scrubbed his teeth two or three times a day. Some Mr. Sing. He certainly wasn't much of a business man. Maybe he was. Maybe he just trusted me. I tell you I couldn't figure him.

Well, now it was all simple except for Eddy. Because he's a rummy he'll talk when he gets hot. I sat there steering and I looked at him and I thought, Hell, he's as well off dead as the way he is, and then I'm all clear. When I found he was on board I decided I'd have to do away with him but then when everything had come out so nice I didn't have the heart. But looking at him lying there it certainly was a temptation. But then I thought there's no sense spoiling it by doing something you'd be sorry for afterwards. Then I started to think he wasn't even on the crew list and I'd have a fine to pay for bringing him in and I didn't know how to consider him.

Well, I had plenty of time to think about it and I held her on her course and every once in a while I'd take a drink out of the bottle he'd brought on board. There wasn't much in it, and when I'd finished it, I opened up the only one I had left, and I tell you I felt pretty good steering, and it was a pretty night to cross. It had turned out a good trip all right, finally, even though it had looked plenty bad plenty of times.

When it got daylight Eddy woke up. He said he felt terrible.

“Take the wheel a minute,”I told him.“I want to look around.”

I went back to the stem and threw a little water on her. But she was perfectly clean. I scrubbed the brush over the side. I unloaded the guns and stowed them below. But I still kept the gun on my belt. It was fresh and nice as you want it below, no smell at all. A little water had come in through the starboard port onto one of the bunks was all; so I shut the ports. There wasn't a customhouse officer in the world could smell Chink in her now.

I saw the clearance papers in the net bag hanging up under her framed license where I'd shoved them when I came on board and I took them out to look them over. Then I went up to the cockpit.

“Listen,”I said.“How did you get on the crew list?”

“I met the broker when he was leaving for the consulate and told him I was going.”

“God looks after rummies,”I told him and I took the thirty-eight off and stowed it down below.

I made some coffee down below and then I came up and took the wheel.

“There's coffee below,”I told him.

“Brother, coffee wouldn't do me any good.”You knew you had to be sorry for him. He certainly looked bad.

About nine o'clock we saw the Sand Key light just about dead ahead. We'd seen tankers going up the gulf for quite a while.

“We'll be in now,”I said to him.“I'm going to give you the same four dollars a day just as if Johnson had paid.”

“How much did you get out of last night?”he asked me.

“Only six hundred,”I told him.

I don't know whether he believed me or not.

“Don't I share in it?”

“That's your share,”I told him.“What I just told you, and if you ever open your mouth about last night I'll hear of it and I'll do away with you.”

“You know I'm no squealer, Harry.”

“You're a rummy. But no matter how rum dumb you get, if you ever talk about that, I promise you.”

“I'm a good man,”he said.“You oughtn't to talk to me like that.”

“They can't make it fast enough to keep you a good man,”I told him. But I didn't worry about him any more, because who was going to believe him? Mr. Sing wouldn't make any complaints. The Chinks weren't going to. You know the boy that sculled them out wasn't. Eddy would mouth about it sooner or later, maybe, but who believes a rummy?

Why, who could prove anything? Naturally it would have made plenty more talk when they saw his name on the crew list. That was luck for me, all right. I could have said he fell overboard, but it makes plenty talk. Plenty of luck for Eddy, too. Plenty of luck, all right.

Then we came to the edge of the stream and the water quit being blue and was light and greenish and inside I could see the stakes on the Long Reef and on the Western Dry Rocks and the wireless masts at Key West and the La Concha hotel up high out of all the low houses and plenty smoke from out where they're burning garbage. Sand Key light was plenty close now and you could see the boathouse and the little dock alongside the light and I knew we were only forty minutes away now and I felt good to be getting back and I had a good stake now for the summertime.

“What do you say about a drink, Eddy?”I said to him.

“Ah, Harry,”he said,“I always knew you were my pal.”